<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <monster>
      <name>Aruk Thundercaller Thuunlakalaga</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (goliath)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>67 (9d8+27)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +6, Insight +4, Medicine +4, Perception +4, Survival +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist>cold</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Mountain Born</name>
      <text>Aruk is acclimated to high altitude, including elevations above 20,000 feet.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Powerful Build</name>
      <text>Aruk counts as one size larger when determining his carrying capacity and the weight he can push, drag, or lift.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Aruk makes two attacks with his greataxe or hurls two javelins.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Greataxe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (1d12 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Greataxe|+6|1d12+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Javelin</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 30/120 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Javelin|+6|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Stone's Endurance (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>When Aruk takes damage, it reduces the damage taken by 9 (1d12 + 3).</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>Goliaths inhabit the Spine of the World, where their mettle is tested against orcs, ogres, frost giants, remorhazes, ice trolls, young white dragons, the treacherous mountain terrain, and the cruel indifference of nature.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 169</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Auril (First Form)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>95 (10d8+50)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>24</int>
    <wis>26</wis>
    <cha>28</cha>
    <save>Con +9, Wis +12</save>
    <skill>Deception +13, Insight +12, Intimidation +13, Perception +16</skill>
    <passive>26</passive>
    <languages>all, telepathy 1000 ft.</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>cold, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable>radiant</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, stunned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft., truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Divine Being</name>
      <text>Auril can't be surprised and can't be changed into another form against her will.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Divine Rejuvenation</name>
      <text>When Auril drops to 0 hit points, her body turns to slush and melts away. Auril instantly reappears in her second form, in an unoccupied space within 60 feet of where her first form disappeared. Her initiative count doesn't change.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (2/Day in This Form)</name>
      <text>If Auril fails a saving throw, she can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Auril has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>Auril doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Auril attacks twice with her talons.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Talons</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage plus 3 (1d6) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Talons|+7|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Touch of Frost</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +13 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 13 (3d8) cold damage, and the target can't take reactions until the start of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Touch of Frost|+13|3d8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Chromatic Orb</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +13 to hit, range 90 ft., one creature. 13 (3d8) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Chromatic Orb|+13|3d8</attack>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>Auril can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Auril regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Talons</name>
      <text>Auril attacks once with her talons.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Teleport</name>
      <text>Auril teleports to an unoccupied space she can see within 30 feet of her.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Touch of Frost (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Auril uses Touch of Frost.</text>
      </legendary>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Auril's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 21, +13 to hit with spell attacks). She can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: chromatic orb (cold orb only; see "Actions" below), detect magic, misty step</text>
      <text>2/day each: control weather, detect thoughts, ice storm</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>chromatic orb, detect magic, misty step, control weather, detect thoughts, ice storm</spells>
    <description>Roleplaying Auril
Portraying a deity, even a lesser god such as Auril the Frostmaiden, can be daunting. For roleplaying purposes, the following suggestions might prove helpful:
• So long as she has mortal worshipers, Auril can't truly die (although the characters can rid the world of her for a time). Thus, she has no reason to capitulate to mortals' demands. As the embodiment of winter's cruelty, she is incapable of showing mercy or compassion. Play her as a supremely cold and unfeeling entity.
• Have Auril speak only when necessary. The less she talks, the less risk you have of unintentionally demystifying her in the eyes of your players. Let her actions, not her words, define her.
• Lesser gods in the D&amp;D multiverse are extremely powerful and arrogant, but also fallible and blind to their own flaws. It's appropriate for Auril to act as though she's invincible while underestimating her mortal enemies, even in her current weakened state.
Lair Actions
Auril dwells on Solstice, a frozen island hidden among the titanic icebergs in the Sea of Moving Ice. Few creatures know of this island, let alone how to reach it. See chapter 5 for information about the regional effects that encompass the island.
While she's on the island, the Frostmaiden can take one of the following lair actions on initiative count 20 (losing initiative ties):
• Auril instantly knows the locations and health of all other creatures on the island. She knows how much damage each of these creatures has taken, how many levels of exhaustion they have, and what conditions are affecting them currently.
• Auril instantly teleports to any location on the island. If the space she chooses as her destination is already occupied, Auril appears in the closest unoccupied space to it instead.
• Auril telepathically communicates with any number of creatures at once, provided they're all on the island. This effect lasts until Auril stops concentrating on it (as if concentrating on a spell) or until she leaves the island or uses a different lair action.
Auril's Three Forms
In her current weakened state, Auril can assume three different forms. To destroy her, heroes must reduce each of her forms to 0 hit points one after another. After she's defeated in her third and final form, Auril dies. As long as she has mortal followers who worship her, however, Auril is reborn at full strength during the next winter solstice, with divine power far beyond what is reflected in the stat blocks presented here.
After finishing a long rest, Auril regains any of her forms that were destroyed, provided at least one form survives. When she transitions from one form to another, she loses all the traits and actions of the old form and gains those of the new form.
A stat block is given for each of Auril's three forms. These descriptions do not reflect Auril at full power, but rather Auril as she is encountered in this adventure.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 275</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Auril (Second Form)</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>136 (13d10+65)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>24</int>
    <wis>26</wis>
    <cha>28</cha>
    <save>Con +9, Wis +12</save>
    <skill>Deception +13, Insight +12, Intimidation +13, Perception +16</skill>
    <passive>26</passive>
    <languages>all, telepathy 1000 ft.</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>cold, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable>fire</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, stunned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft., truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Divine Being</name>
      <text>Auril can't be surprised and can't be changed into another form against her will.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Divine Rejuvenation</name>
      <text>When Auril drops to 0 hit points, her body collapses into shards of ice, whereupon Auril instantly reappears in her third form, in an unoccupied space within 60 feet of where her second form was destroyed. Her initiative count doesn't change.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (2/Day in This Form)</name>
      <text>If Auril fails a saving throw, she can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Auril has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>Auril doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Auril attacks twice with her ice morningstar or hurls three ice darts.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Ice Morningstar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage plus 9 (2d8) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Ice Morningstar|+7|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Ice Dart</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage plus 3 (1d6) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Ice Dart|+7|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Cone of Cold (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>Auril causes a magical blast of cold air to erupt from her hand. Each creature in a 60-foot cone must make a DC 21 Constitution saving throw, taking 36 (8d8) cold damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Cone of Cold (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)||8d8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Create Ice Mephit (3/Day)</name>
      <text>Auril breaks off an icicle from her body and hurls it into an unoccupied space she can see within 20 feet of her, where it magically transforms into an ice mephit (see its entry in the Monster Manual). The mephit acts immediately after Auril in the initiative order and obeys her commands.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Ice Stasis (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>Auril magically creates a gem-sized ice crystal that hovers in a space within 5 feet of her. Auril then targets a creature she can see within 60 feet of the crystal. The target must succeed on a DC 21 Charisma saving throw or become trapped in the crystal, which is immovable. If the saving throw succeeds, the crystal shatters and nothing else happens. A creature trapped in the crystal is stunned, has total cover against attacks and other effects outside the crystal, and takes 21 (6d6) cold damage at the start of each of its turns. The creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, freeing itself on a success. The creature is also freed if the crystal is destroyed, which is a Tiny object with AC 18, 9 hit points, and immunity to all damage except fire damage. The freed creature appears in an unoccupied space of its choice within 30 feet of the shattered crystal.</text>
      <attack>Ice Stasis (Recharge 5-6)||6d6</attack>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>Auril can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Auril regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Attack</name>
      <text>Auril makes one weapon attack.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Ice Flurry (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Each creature within 30 feet of Auril takes 5 (2d4) piercing damage from swirling ice, and nonmagical, open flames in that area are extinguished.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Splinter (Costs 3 Actions)</name>
      <text>Auril uses Create Ice Mephit or causes one to ice mephit she can see within 60 feet of her to explode and die. A mephit that dies in this way does not use its Death Burst. Instead, each creature within 10 feet of the exploding mephit must succeed on a DC 21 Dexterity saving throw, taking 13 (3d8) piercing damage on a failed saving throw, and half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      </legendary>
    <description>Roleplaying Auril
Portraying a deity, even a lesser god such as Auril the Frostmaiden, can be daunting. For roleplaying purposes, the following suggestions might prove helpful:
• So long as she has mortal worshipers, Auril can't truly die (although the characters can rid the world of her for a time). Thus, she has no reason to capitulate to mortals' demands. As the embodiment of winter's cruelty, she is incapable of showing mercy or compassion. Play her as a supremely cold and unfeeling entity.
• Have Auril speak only when necessary. The less she talks, the less risk you have of unintentionally demystifying her in the eyes of your players. Let her actions, not her words, define her.
• Lesser gods in the D&amp;D multiverse are extremely powerful and arrogant, but also fallible and blind to their own flaws. It's appropriate for Auril to act as though she's invincible while underestimating her mortal enemies, even in her current weakened state.
Lair Actions
Auril dwells on Solstice, a frozen island hidden among the titanic icebergs in the Sea of Moving Ice. Few creatures know of this island, let alone how to reach it. See chapter 5 for information about the regional effects that encompass the island.
While she's on the island, the Frostmaiden can take one of the following lair actions on initiative count 20 (losing initiative ties):
• Auril instantly knows the locations and health of all other creatures on the island. She knows how much damage each of these creatures has taken, how many levels of exhaustion they have, and what conditions are affecting them currently.
• Auril instantly teleports to any location on the island. If the space she chooses as her destination is already occupied, Auril appears in the closest unoccupied space to it instead.
• Auril telepathically communicates with any number of creatures at once, provided they're all on the island. This effect lasts until Auril stops concentrating on it (as if concentrating on a spell) or until she leaves the island or uses a different lair action.
Auril's Three Forms
In her current weakened state, Auril can assume three different forms. To destroy her, heroes must reduce each of her forms to 0 hit points one after another. After she's defeated in her third and final form, Auril dies. As long as she has mortal followers who worship her, however, Auril is reborn at full strength during the next winter solstice, with divine power far beyond what is reflected in the stat blocks presented here.
After finishing a long rest, Auril regains any of her forms that were destroyed, provided at least one form survives. When she transitions from one form to another, she loses all the traits and actions of the old form and gains those of the new form.
A stat block is given for each of Auril's three forms. These descriptions do not reflect Auril at full power, but rather Auril as she is encountered in this adventure.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 277</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Auril (Third Form)</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>136 (16d6+80)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>1</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>24</int>
    <wis>26</wis>
    <cha>28</cha>
    <save>Con +9, Wis +12</save>
    <skill>Deception +13, Insight +12, Intimidation +13, Perception +16</skill>
    <passive>26</passive>
    <languages>all, telepathy 1,000 ft.</languages>
    <cr>11</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>cold, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable>thunder</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, stunned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 120 ft. (blind beyond this radius), truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Divine Being</name>
      <text>Auril can't be surprised and can't be changed into another form against her will.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Divine Resurrection</name>
      <text>When Auril drops to 0 hit points, her crystalline form shatters and her divine spark vanishes. She is dead until the next winter solstice, when she reappears at full health in a cold, remote location of her choosing.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Frigid Aura</name>
      <text>So long as Auril has at least 1 hit point in this form, each creature within 10 feet of her takes 10 cold damage at the start of each of her turns.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (1/Day in This Form)</name>
      <text>If Auril fails a saving throw, she can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Auril has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>Auril doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Auril uses Polar Ray twice.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Polar Ray</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +13 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. 14 (4d6) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Polar Ray|+13|4d6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Blizzard Veil</name>
      <text>Auril creates a magical blizzard in a 30-foot-radius sphere centered on herself. The area within the sphere is heavily obscured, and the sphere moves with Auril. The effect lasts until Auril drops to 0 hit points in this form, until she chooses to end the effect (no action required), or until her concentration is broken (as if concentrating on a spell).</text>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>Auril can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Auril regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Polar Ray</name>
      <text>Auril uses Polar Ray.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Intensify Aura (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Auril's Frigid Aura deals an extra 10 cold damage until the end of her next turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Blinding Gleam (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Auril's form flares with a blue light. Each creature that can see Auril and is within 10 feet of her must succeed on a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw or be blinded by Auril's magical gleam for 1 minute. The blinded creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      </legendary>
    <description>Roleplaying Auril
Portraying a deity, even a lesser god such as Auril the Frostmaiden, can be daunting. For roleplaying purposes, the following suggestions might prove helpful:
• So long as she has mortal worshipers, Auril can't truly die (although the characters can rid the world of her for a time). Thus, she has no reason to capitulate to mortals' demands. As the embodiment of winter's cruelty, she is incapable of showing mercy or compassion. Play her as a supremely cold and unfeeling entity.
• Have Auril speak only when necessary. The less she talks, the less risk you have of unintentionally demystifying her in the eyes of your players. Let her actions, not her words, define her.
• Lesser gods in the D&amp;D multiverse are extremely powerful and arrogant, but also fallible and blind to their own flaws. It's appropriate for Auril to act as though she's invincible while underestimating her mortal enemies, even in her current weakened state.
Lair Actions
Auril dwells on Solstice, a frozen island hidden among the titanic icebergs in the Sea of Moving Ice. Few creatures know of this island, let alone how to reach it. See chapter 5 for information about the regional effects that encompass the island.
While she's on the island, the Frostmaiden can take one of the following lair actions on initiative count 20 (losing initiative ties):
• Auril instantly knows the locations and health of all other creatures on the island. She knows how much damage each of these creatures has taken, how many levels of exhaustion they have, and what conditions are affecting them currently.
• Auril instantly teleports to any location on the island. If the space she chooses as her destination is already occupied, Auril appears in the closest unoccupied space to it instead.
• Auril telepathically communicates with any number of creatures at once, provided they're all on the island. This effect lasts until Auril stops concentrating on it (as if concentrating on a spell) or until she leaves the island or uses a different lair action.
Auril's Three Forms
In her current weakened state, Auril can assume three different forms. To destroy her, heroes must reduce each of her forms to 0 hit points one after another. After she's defeated in her third and final form, Auril dies. As long as she has mortal followers who worship her, however, Auril is reborn at full strength during the next winter solstice, with divine power far beyond what is reflected in the stat blocks presented here.
After finishing a long rest, Auril regains any of her forms that were destroyed, provided at least one form survives. When she transitions from one form to another, she loses all the traits and actions of the old form and gains those of the new form.
A stat block is given for each of Auril's three forms. These descriptions do not reflect Auril at full power, but rather Auril as she is encountered in this adventure.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 278</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Avarice</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (tiefling)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>84 (13d8+26)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>8</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save>Int +6, Wis +3</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, History +6</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Infernal, Orc, Yeti</languages>
    <cr>7</cr>
    <resist>cold, fire</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Icy Doom</name>
      <text>When Avarice dies, her corpse freezes for 9 days, during which time it can't be thawed, harmed by fire, animated, or raised from the dead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Avarice wields a staff of frost with 10 charges (see "Actions" below).</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Fire Bolt (Cantrip)</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +6 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. 11 (2d10) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Fire Bolt (Cantrip)|+6|2d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Staff of Frost</name>
      <text>While holding this staff, Avarice can expend 1 or more of its charges to cast one of the following spells from it (spell save DC 14): cone of cold (5 charges), fog cloud (1 charge), ice storm (4 charges), or wall of ice (4 charges). The staff regains 1d6 + 4 charges daily at dawn. If its last charge is expended, roll a d20; on a 1, the staff turns to water and is destroyed.</text>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Banishing Rebuke (Recharges after a Long Rest)</name>
      <text>When Avarice is damaged by a creature that she can see within 60 feet of her, she can banish that creature to a frigid extradimensional prison for 1 minute. While there, the creature is incapacitated and takes 5 (1d10) cold damage at the start of each of its turns. At the end of each of its turns, the creature can make a DC 14 Charisma saving throw, escaping the prison on a success and reappearing in the space it left or in the nearest unoccupied space if that space is occupied. A creature that dies in the prison is trapped there indefinitely.</text>
      </reaction>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Avarice is a 10th-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 14; +6 to hit with spell attacks). She has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt (see "Actions" below), mage hand, message, minor illusion, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, mage armor, magic missile</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): flaming sphere, knock, scorching ray</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fireball, fly</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): banishment, fire shield</text>
      <text>• 5th level (2 slots): Bigby's hand, Rary's telepathic bond</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, mage hand, message, minor illusion, prestidigitation, detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, flaming sphere, knock, scorching ray, counterspell, fireball, fly, banishment, fire shield, Bigby's hand, Rary's telepathic bond</spells>
    <description>Avarice is a cruel and vindictive tiefling trained in the arcane tradition of evocation. She likes using her magic to destroy things, and her hunger for magic items knows no bounds. Her supreme confidence means that she never backs down from a challenge, even when the odds are clearly stacked against her. Seeing other wizards as a threat, paranoia rules her life.
Avarice has been a member of the Arcane Brotherhood for almost two years. She fantasizes about rising to fame and prominence in record time and hopes that plundering the lost Netherese city of Ythryn will turn her fantasies into reality.
The tiefling has the secret support of the archdevil Levistus, having traded her soul years ago for her first taste of magical power. Levistus speaks to her in dreams and guides her path. Shortly after Avarice arrived in Ten-Towns, Levistus urged her to seek out the Black Sword. Avarice didn't know who or what the Black Sword was until she was approached by cultists of Levistus bearing swordlike shards of chardalyn worn as pendants around their necks. These self-styled Knights of the Black Sword offered her sanctuary in the keep of Caer-Dineval, where they are based. Although she doesn't trust the cultists, they treat her with more respect than anyone else does, and the keep is a safer location than most other places in Ten-Towns.
Companions. Avarice has a pair of loyal Gargoyle named Gargle and Gurgle who serve her as bodyguards and scouts. Avarice uses her Rary's telepathic bond spell to stay in telepathic contact with her gargoyles before sending them off on any mission. Avarice also has the support of the Knights of the Black Sword, if she needs to call on their talents.
Familiar. Avarice's familiar throughout the adventure is a squawking raven named Skelm. It uses the raven stat block in the Monster Manual but is a fiend instead of a beast.
Spellbook. Avarice's spellbook has white leather covers and vellum pages. The tiefling's personal sigil is burned into the front cover. The book contains the spells Avarice has prepared plus the following additional spells: burning hands, cone of cold, find familiar, ice storm, lightning bolt, rope trick, thunderwave, tongues, wall of fire, and wall of force.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 269</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Awakened White Moose</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>11 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>68 (8d10+24)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Druidic</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Charge</name>
      <text>If the moose moves at least 20 feet straight toward a target and then hits it with an antlers attack on the same turn, the target takes an extra 9 (2d8) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 14 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sure-Footed</name>
      <text>The moose has advantage on Strength and Dexterity saving throws made against effects that would knock it prone.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The moose makes two attacks: one with its antlers and one with its hooves.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Antlers</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d8 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Antlers|+6|2d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hooves</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (2d4 + 4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Hooves|+6|2d4+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>A white moose is attacking loggers in the forest near Lonelywood. The town's logging industry is essential to the growth and survival of Ten-Towns, and Speaker Nimsy Huddle has assured the other speakers that Lonelywood's "moose problem" will be dealt with in short order. Hunters have been dispatched to kill the moose, but it has eluded them so far. From what the hunters have seen, their prey is smarter than the average moose, and its white hide makes it hard to spot in the snow. What they don't know is that the moose is using a magic mirror as a scrying device to show it where its enemies are.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 82</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Battlehammer Dwarf</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>13 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>16 (3d8+3)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Nature +4, Perception +5, Stealth +6, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Hearing and Sight</name>
      <text>The dwarf has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing or sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
      <text>The dwarf has advantage on saving throws against poison and resistance against poison damage.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The dwarf makes two melee attacks or two ranged attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Handaxe</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 3 (1d6 + 0) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Handaxe|+2|1d6+0</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Light Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, ranged 80/320 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Light Crossbow|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 107</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Bjornhild Solvigsdottir</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>102 (12d8+48)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +7, Intimidation +5, Survival +3</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Yeti</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Auril's Blessing (3/Day)</name>
      <text>When Bjornhild hits a creature with a weapon attack, the attack deals an extra 11 (2d10) cold damage.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Bjornhild makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Greataxe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (1d12 + 4) slashing damage, plus 11 (2d10) cold damage if Bjornhild uses Auril's Blessing.</text>
      <attack>Greataxe|+7|1d12+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage, or 8 (1d8 + 4) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack, plus 11 (2d10) cold damage if Bjornhild uses Auril's Blessing.</text>
      <attack>Spear|+7|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>It's unusual for a woman to lead a Reghed tribe, but Bjornhild is a most extraordinary woman. The fearless wife of the late King Korold, she fought alongside him in many battles. After a frost giant's mammoth companion slew Korold, the formidable Bjornhild took his place.
Bjornhild worships the Frostmaiden and is so ruthless that her enemies believe she has actual ice flowing through her veins. She has no living children that she knows of, but with Auril's blessing, she won't need any heirs to preserve her legacy. Bjornhild intends to live forever by demonstrating her unwavering faith in the Frostmaiden and becoming the Chosen of Auril.
As if she weren't fearsome enough, Bjornhild has a pet saber-toothed tiger named Grava.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 306</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Brain in a Jar</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>11 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>55 (10d6+20)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 10 ft.</speed>
    <str>1</str>
    <dex>3</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>19</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Int +6, Cha +4</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>the languages it knew in life</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, paralyzed, poisoned, prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 120 ft. (blind beyond this radius); see also "detect sentience" below</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Detect Sentience</name>
      <text>The brain can sense the presence and location of any creature within 300 feet of it that has an Intelligence of 3 or higher, regardless of interposing barriers, unless the creature is protected by a mind blank spell.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The brain has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magic effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The brain doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Chill Touch (Cantrip)</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +6 to hit, range 120 ft., one creature. 13 (3d8) necrotic damage, and the target can't regain hit points until the start of the brain's next turn. If the target is undead, it also has disadvantage on attack rolls against the brain until the end of the brain's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Chill Touch (Cantrip)|+6|3d8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Mind Blast (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The brain magically emits psychic energy in a 60-foot cone. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 14 Intelligence saving throw or take 17 (3d8 + 4) psychic damage and be stunned for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <attack>Mind Blast (Recharge 5-6)||3d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting (Psionics)</name>
      <text>The brain's innate spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no components:</text>
      <text>At will: chill touch (see "Actions" below), detect thoughts, mage hand, zone of truth</text>
      <text>3/day each: charm person, hold person</text>
      <text>1/day each: compulsion, hold monster, sleep (3rd-level version), Tasha's hideous laughter</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>chill touch, detect thoughts, mage hand, zone of truth, charm person, hold person, compulsion, hold monster, sleep, Tasha's hideous laughter</spells>
    <description>Through an eldritch ritual combining alchemy, necromancy, and grim surgical precision, the brain of a mortal being (willing or unwilling) is encased in a glass jar filled with preserving fluids and the liquefied goop of their body's flesh. The transformation renders the brain immortal and imbues it with psionic power, so that it can spend eternity plotting and executing its desires.
A brain in a jar can speak without vocal cords, psionically projecting its disembodied voice outward for all to hear. It enjoys conversation so much that it is prone to talking for hours on end, sometimes to itself if there are no others with whom it can speak. It also likes to think out loud and reflect on the events and decisions that led to its great transformation.
Being divorced from one's body can tax the mind, and the longer a brain in a jar exists, the more likely some form of insanity will take hold of it. A brain in a jar is particularly susceptible to dementia, schizophrenia, and paranoia.
Immortal Vessels. The brain floats in a jar of solution, pulsating as it reacts to its surroundings. Some brains have been known to thump against the walls of their containers when excited or vexed. A jar's metal casing might be rusty but serviceable, or an elegantly wrought masterwork, depending on its creator. A brain in a jar weighs roughly 125 pounds.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 278</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Chardalyn Berserker</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>fiend</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>90 (12d8+36)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Survival +4</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Chardalyn Madness</name>
      <text>The berserker must roll a d6 at the start of each of its turns. On a 1, the berserker does nothing on its turn except speak to a nonexistent, evil master whom it has pledged to serve.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Reckless</name>
      <text>At the start of its turn, the berserker can gain advantage on all melee weapon attack rolls during that turn, but attack rolls against it have advantage until the start of its next turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The berserker attacks three times with a melee weapon.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Chardalyn Flail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) bludgeoning damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 13 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Chardalyn Flail|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Chardalyn Javelin</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 30/120 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 13 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Chardalyn Javelin|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Chardalyn berserkers are Reghed nomads who wield weapons made of chardalyn, specifically ones suffused with demonic magic (see the sidebar on Chardalyn). This exposure has transformed them into fiends. They shed their heavier protective clothing and embrace the frigid cold, allowing frostbite to ravage the exposed parts of their bodies, with only their faith in the Frostmaiden keeping them alive.
Chardalyn Weapons. A chardalyn berserker wields one or more weapons made wholly or partly out of chardalyn that has been tainted by demonic magic. Battleaxes, flails, javelins, and spears are favored weapons, though other weapons are possible.
A character who claims one or more of these weapons can be corrupted by them. Each day at dawn, roll a d6 for each such weapon in the character's possession. On a roll of 1, the character must succeed on a DC 13 Charisma saving throw or become an evil NPC under the DM's control, unless the character is evil already. This alignment change can be undone by any magic that ends a curse, but after ten days, it can be reversed only by a wish spell or divine intervention.
A creature wounded by one of these chardalyn weapons can feel a sudden sickness creep over them, but it passes quickly.
Chardalyn Madness. Prolonged contact with the demonic magic imprinted on the chardalyn has afflicted the berserker with a form of madness, causing the berserker to believe that its weapons are conduits through which it can speak to a demon lord or other dark power, as well as channel its rage. If the berserker's madness is cured using magic that removes the effects of madness, the berserker loses its Chardalyn Madness trait but retains its chaotic evil alignment and other qualities. Further exposure to the demonic magic causes the berserker's madness to return, however.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 280</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Chardalyn Dragon</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>147 (14d12+56)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 90 ft.</speed>
    <str>24</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>19</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save>Str +11, Con +8</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>the languages known by its creator</languages>
    <cr>11</cr>
    <resist>radiant; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>cold, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The dragon is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The dragon has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The dragon deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The dragon doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep, and it gains no benefit from finishing a short or long rest.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The dragon uses its Malevolent Presence. It then makes three attacks: two with its claws and one with its tail. If the dragon isn't flying, it can also make one attack with its wings.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 14 (2d6 + 7) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+11|2d6+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 18 (2d10 + 7) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Tail|+11|2d10+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Wings</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 12 (2d4 + 7) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Wings|+11|2d4+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Malevolent Presence</name>
      <text>Any creature with an Intelligence of 4 or more that is within 30 feet of the dragon must succeed on a DC 16 Wisdom saving throw or be charmed by it for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. If a creature's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the creature is immune to the dragon's Malevolent Presence for the next 24 hours. A creature charmed in this way fixates on another creature or object that the dragon mentally chooses and must, on each of its turns, move as close as it can to that target and use its action to make a melee attack against it. If the dragon doesn't choose a target, the charmed creature can act normally on its turn.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Radiant Breath (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The dragon exhales a ray of radiant energy in a 120-foot line that is 5 feet wide. Each creature in that line must make a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw, taking 31 (7d8) radiant damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Radiant Breath (Recharge 5-6)||7d8</attack>
      </action>
    <description>This construct is fashioned from pieces of chardalyn (see the sidebar on Chardalyn) that have been assembled in the form of a dragon. The only parts of the dragon not forged from chardalyn are its wing flaps, which are made of an oily film as tough as rubber, and its heart, which is an orb of pulsating, radiant energy. Demonic magic suffusing the chardalyn imbues the construct with malevolence, allowing it to enjoy the terror it causes. This effect extends outward from it, corrupting other creatures who get too close to the dragon. Those affected by the dragon's presence turn their efforts to helping the dragon inflict suffering on others.
A chardalyn dragon serves the tyrannical will of its evil creator—a tireless drive devotion that exceeds its own instinct of self-preservation. Thus, the dragon will destroy itself in pursuit of its master's desires if necessary. The dragon likes to tear foes apart, as well as knock down doors and other structures. Against enemies it can't reach, it fires a beam of destructive radiance from its grill-like maw.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 281</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Chimeric Baboon</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>3 (1d6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>8</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>4</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>The baboon has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the baboon's allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +1 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 1 (1d4 - 1) piercing damage, plus an extra 3 (1d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+1|1d4-1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 246</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Chimeric Cat</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>2 (1d4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>3</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +3, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft., tremorsense 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>The cat has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +0 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 1 slashing damage.</text>
      </action>
    <description>The chimeric cat has antennae that grant it blindsight and tremorsense out to a range of 60 feet
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 246</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Chimeric Fox</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>2 (1d4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., burrow 5 ft.</speed>
    <str>2</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +3, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Hearing</name>
      <text>The fox has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Chimeric Creation</name>
      <text>The fox has fur that changes color to match its surroundings, giving it advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 1 piercing damage.</text>
      </action>
    <description>The white arctic foxes of Icewind Dale live in burrows and are acclimated to cold weather. They prowl the outskirts of Ten-Towns and nearby forests for food, hunting hares or stealing fish. These timid creatures avoid contact with humanoids, but they are sometimes used as mounts by chwingas.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 246</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Chimeric Hare</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>1 (1d4-1)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., burrow 5 ft., fly 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>1</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>9</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>4</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +2, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Escape</name>
      <text>The hare can take the Dash, Disengage, or Hide action as a bonus action on each of its turns.</text>
      </trait>
    <description>Snowshoe hares are gentle herbivores that live in burrows throughout Icewind Dale. They have shorter ears than other hares and are acclimated to cold weather. Chimeric hares have feathered wings.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 246</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Chimeric Rat</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>1 (1d4-1)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>2</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>9</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>4</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +3, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft., tremorsense 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>The rat has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Chimeric Creation</name>
      <text>The rat has gills, iridescent scales, and the ability to breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +0 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 1 piercing damage.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 246</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Chimeric Weasel</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>1 (1d4-1)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>3</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>8</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +3, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Hearing and Smell</name>
      <text>The weasel has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing or smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Chimeric Creation</name>
      <text>The weasel has glowing eyes that emit bright light out in a 20-foot radius and dim light for an additional 20 feet.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 1 piercing damage.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 246</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Chwinga</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>5 (2d4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., climb 20 ft., swim 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>1</str>
    <dex>20</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +7, Perception +7, Stealth +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The chwinga doesn't require air, food, or drink. When it dies, it turns into a handful of flower petals, a cloud of pollen, a stone statuette resembling its former self, a tiny sphere of smooth stone, or a puddle of fresh water (your choice).</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Evasion</name>
      <text>When the chwinga is subjected to an effect that allows it to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, it instead takes no damage if it succeeds on the saving throw, and only half damage if it fails.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Magical Gift (1/Day)</name>
      <text>The chwinga targets a humanoid it can see within 5 feet of it. The target gains a supernatural charm of the DM's choice. See chapter 7 of the Dungeon Masters Guide for more information on supernatural charms.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Natural Shelter</name>
      <text>The chwinga magically takes shelter inside a rock, a living plant, or a natural source of fresh water in its space. The chwinga can't be targeted by any attack, spell, or other effect while inside this shelter, and the shelter doesn't impair the chwinga's blindsight. The chwinga can use it's action to emerge from a shelter. If its shelter is destroyed, the chwinga is forced out and appears in the shelter's space, but is otherwise unharmed.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The chwinga's innate spellcasting ability is Wisdom. It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material or verbal components:</text>
      <text>At will: druidcraft, guidance, pass without trace, resistance</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>druidcraft, guidance, pass without trace, resistance</spells>
    <description>
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 282</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Coldlight Walker</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>82 (11d8+33)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>8</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save>Int +2, Wis +3</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>cold</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, exhaustion, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Blinding Light</name>
      <text>The walker sheds bright light in a 20-foot radius and dim light for an additional 20 feet. As a bonus action, the walker can target one creature in its bright light that it can see and force it to succeed on a DC 14 Constitution saving throw or be blinded until the start of the walker's next turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Icy Doom</name>
      <text>Any creature killed by the walker freezes for 9 days, during which time it can't be thawed, harmed by fire, animated, or raised from the dead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The walker doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The walker makes two attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (2d8 + 2) bludgeoning damage plus 14 (4d6) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+5|2d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Cold Ray</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +3 to hit, range 60 ft., one target. 25 (4d10 + 3) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Cold Ray|+3|4d10+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Some humanoids who died from extreme cold but whose spirits languish in the mortal world become coldlight walkers, burning with frigid fury at the meaninglessness of life. Their frostbitten corpses emit a spectral light so intense that mortal eyes can barely stand to look at them. They typically wear the clothing in which they died.
God-Spawned Horrors. Gods that personify winter create coldlight walkers as embodiments of winter's wrath. These hateful spirits that were denied passage to the afterlife are preserved in their current forms to remind the living how fragile life can be.
When a coldlight walker dies, its light goes out, leaving behind a frozen, inanimate corpse that can never be raised from the dead.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 284</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Demos Magen</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>16 (chain mail)</ac>
    <hp>51 (6d8+24)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fiery End</name>
      <text>If the magen dies, its body disintegrates in a harmless burst of fire and smoke, leaving behind anything it was wearing or carrying.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The magen has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The magen doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The magen makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Greatsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (2d6 + 2) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Greatsword|+4|2d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Light Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Light Crossbow|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Demos magen wear armor, wield weapons, and typically serve as guards.
Magen are magical, humanlike beings created by a wizard spell (see the create magen spell in appendix D) or by other arcane methods.
Though magen look like humanoids with green skin, they are constructs. When one is wounded, its blood is seen to have the color and consistency of mercury. They exist purely through magical means. When one is killed, its body disappears in a burst of harmless fire and a cloud of smoke that quickly dissipates.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 300</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Dzaan</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>49 (9d8+9)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Int +5, Wis +3</save>
    <skill>Arcana +5, Deception +4, History +5</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Giant, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Shocking Grasp (Cantrip)</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature (the attack roll has advantage if the target is wearing armor made of metal). 9 (2d8) lightning damage, and the target can't take reactions until the start of his next turn.</text>
      <attack>Shocking Grasp (Cantrip)|+5|2d8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Acid Splash (Cantrip)</name>
      <text>Dzaan hurls a bubble of acid at one creature he can see within 60 feet of it, or at two such creatures that are within 5 feet of each other. A target must succeed on a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw or take 7 (2d6) acid damage.</text>
      <attack>Acid Splash (Cantrip)||2d6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Magic Missile (1st-Level Spell; Requires a Spell Slot)</name>
      <text>Dzaan creates three darts of magical force. Each dart unerringly strikes one creature Dzaan can see within 120 feet of it, dealing 3 (1d4 + 1) force damage. If Dzaan casts this spell using a 2nd-level spell slot, he creates one more dart.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Dzaan is a 9th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). He has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): acid splash*, light, minor illusion, shocking grasp*</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, disguise self, magic missile*</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): invisibility, levitate, phantasmal force</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): fireball, sending, slow</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): arcane eye, confusion</text>
      <text>• 5th level (1 slots): animate objects</text>
      <text>*See "Actions" below.</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>acid splash, light, minor illusion, shocking grasp, detect magic, disguise self, magic missile, invisibility, levitate, phantasmal force, fireball, sending, slow, arcane eye, confusion, animate objects</spells>
    <description>Dzaan was a Red Wizard of Thay who studied the arcane tradition of illusion. The leaders of the Arcane Brotherhood welcomed him with open arms, eager to count a Red Wizard among their ranks. Dzaan might have become a force to reckon with in the brotherhood had his quest for power not led him to Icewind Dale, where he was killed by the people of Easthaven after making a few too many enemies.
Dzaan's Demise. Dzaan's trouble started after he broke away from his fellow wizards and hired adventurers to scour Icewind Dale for Netherese ruins. One group of them uncovered a buried tower in the tundra (see "Lost Spire of Netheril"), and Dzaan went out of his way to eliminate anyone who knew of it, including the adventurers who found it and several Ten-Towners with whom they had spoken. After turning the tower into his secret base, Dzaan visited Easthaven to gather supplies. Although he took the precaution of adopting a magical disguise, members of the local militia recognized Dzaan by the way he walked and spoke. They captured him, gagged him, confiscated his spellbook, and condemned him to death.
The characters have no opportunity to speak with Dzaan. They first encounter him in Easthaven, tied to a stake and engulfed in flames (see "Toil and Trouble"). The Ten-Towners enjoy the execution while it lasts. After warming themselves by the fire, they leave Dzaan's ashes to be scattered by the wind.
Dzaan's Simulacrum. Unbeknownst to his executioners, Dzaan had used a spell scroll of simulacrum to create a copy of himself. This simulacrum dwells in the sunken Netherese spire, waiting for its creator to return.
The simulacrum, which looks and acts like Dzaan, has half of Dzaan's hit points and can't regain expended spell slots. It has wasted its 3rd-level spell slots trying to reach Dzaan with sending spells, to no avail, and has expended other spell slots to help it survive the perils of the spire. It uses its remaining spell slots sparingly.
The sunken Netherese tower contains a special room that can transform the simulacrum into a real person—or any magical illusion into the real thing, for that matter. If this change occurs, the simulacrum effectively becomes a Dzaan, authentic in every way. Dzaan's stat block and abilities change as follows:
• He has spell slots appropriate for a 9th-level wizard (four 1st-level spell slots, three 2nd- through 4th-level spell slots, and one 5th-level spell slot), but he lacks a spellbook and therefore can't change his list of prepared spells.
• If he finishes a long rest, he has the following additional spell slots, which allow him to cast the indicated spells: 3rd level (3 slots): fireball, sending, slow 4th level (3 slots): arcane eye, confusion 5th level (1 slot): animate objects
• His hit point maximum becomes 49 (9d8 + 9), and his challenge rating becomes 2 (450 XP). His challenge rating becomes 4 (1,100 XP) if he finishes a long rest and regains his expended spells.
Companion. Because they're so despised throughout Faerûn, Red Wizards often adopt disguises and rarely travel abroad without an escort. They generally favor undead servants and bodyguards, since they find that undead tend to be more obedient than the living. Dzaan's bodyguard is a Thayan wight named Krintaas. When Dzaan returned to Easthaven, he ordered his companion to stay with the simulacrum and watch over it and the buried Netherese spire.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 270</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Dzaan's Simulacrum</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>24 (9d8+9)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Int +5, Wis +3</save>
    <skill>Arcana +5, Deception +4, History +5</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Giant, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Shocking Grasp (Cantrip)</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature (the attack roll has advantage if the target is wearing armor made of metal). 9 (2d8) lightning damage, and the target can't take reactions until the start of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Shocking Grasp (Cantrip)|+5|2d8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Acid Splash (Cantrip)</name>
      <text>The simulacrum hurls a bubble of acid at one creature it can see within 60 feet of it, or at two such creatures that are within 5 feet of each other. A target must succeed on a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw or take 7 (2d6) acid damage.</text>
      <attack>Acid Splash (Cantrip)||2d6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Magic Missile (1st-Level Spell; Requires a Spell Slot)</name>
      <text>The simulacrum creates three darts of magical force. Each dart unerringly strikes one creature the simulacrum can see within 120 feet of it, dealing 3 (1d4 + 1) force damage. If the simulacrum casts this spell using a 2nd-level spell slot, it creates one more dart.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The simulacrum is a 9th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). It has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): acid splash*, light, minor illusion, shocking grasp*</text>
      <text>• 1st level (2 slots): detect magic, disguise self, magic missile*</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (2 slots): invisibility, levitate, phantasmal force</text>
      <text>*See "Actions" below.</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>2, 2</slots>
    <spells>acid splash, light, minor illusion, shocking grasp, detect magic, disguise self, magic missile, invisibility, levitate, phantasmal force</spells>
    <description>Unbeknownst to his executioners, Dzaan had used a spell scroll of simulacrum to create a copy of himself. This simulacrum dwells in the sunken Netherese spire, waiting for its creator to return.
The simulacrum, which looks and acts like Dzaan, has half of Dzaan's hit points and can't regain expended spell slots. It has wasted its 3rd-level spell slots trying to reach Dzaan with sending spells, to no avail, and has expended other spell slots to help it survive the perils of the spire. It uses its remaining spell slots sparingly.
The sunken Netherese tower contains a special room that can transform the simulacrum into a real person—or any magical illusion into the real thing, for that matter. If this change occurs, the simulacrum effectively becomes a clone of Dzaan, authentic in every way.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 270</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>F'yorl</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (breastplate)</ac>
    <hp>9 (13d8+13)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>19</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save>Int +7, Wis +6, Cha +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +7, Deception +6, Insight +6, Perception +6, Persuasion +6, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Deep Speech, Undercommon, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>7</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>F'yorl has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Tentacles</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 15 (2d10 + 4) psychic damage. If the target is Medium or smaller, it is grappled (escape DC 15) and must succeed on a DC 15 Intelligence saving throw or be stunned until this grapple ends.</text>
      <attack>Tentacles|+7|2d10+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Extract Brain</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one incapacitated humanoid grappled by F'yorl. The target takes 55 (10d10) piercing damage. If this damage reduces the target to 0 hit points, F'yorl kills the target by extracting and devouring its brain.</text>
      <attack>Extract Brain|+7|10d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Mind Blast (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>F'yorl magically emits psychic energy in a 60-foot cone. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 15 Intelligence saving throw or take 22 (4d8 + 4) psychic damage and be stunned for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <attack>Mind Blast (Recharge 5-6)||4d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting (Psionics)</name>
      <text>F'yorl's innate spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 15). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no components:</text>
      <text>At will: detect thoughts, levitate</text>
      <text>1/day each: dominate monster, plane shift (self only)</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>detect thoughts, levitate, dominate monster, plane shift</spells>
    <description>
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 183</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Fox</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>2 (1d4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., burrow 5 ft.</speed>
    <str>2</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +3, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Hearing</name>
      <text>The fox has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 1 piercing damage.</text>
      </action>
    <description>The white arctic foxes of Icewind Dale live in burrows and are acclimated to cold weather. They prowl the outskirts of Ten-Towns and nearby forests for food, hunting hares or stealing fish. These timid creatures avoid contact with humanoids, but they are sometimes used as mounts by Chwinga.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 288</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Frost Druid</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>67 (9d8+27)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., burrow 5 ft., climb 30 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save>Int +3, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Nature +3, Perception +6, Survival +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Common, Druidic</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist>cold</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60ft. (beast form only)</senses>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The druid makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Ice Sickle (Humanoid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d4 + 1) slashing damage plus 5 (2d4) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Ice Sickle (Humanoid Form Only)|+4|1d4+1</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Maul (Beast Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d4 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Maul (Beast Form Only)|+4|1d4+1</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Change Shape</name>
      <text>The druid magically polymorphs into a beast form—fox, mountain goat, owl, or wolf—or back into its humanoid form. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying is absorbed or borne by the beast form (the druid's choice). It reverts to its humanoid form when it dies. The druid's statistics are the same in each form, except where noted in this stat block.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting (Humanoid Form Only)</name>
      <text>The druid is a 9th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 14; +6 to hit with spell attacks). It has the following druid spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): druidcraft, guidance, resistance</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): animal friendship, fog cloud, speak with animals</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): animal messenger, moonbeam, pass without trace</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): conjure animals, sleet storm, wind wall</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): hallucinatory terrain, ice storm</text>
      <text>• 5th level (1 slots): awaken</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>druidcraft, guidance, resistance, animal friendship, fog cloud, speak with animals, animal messenger, moonbeam, pass without trace, conjure animals, sleet storm, wind wall, hallucinatory terrain, ice storm, awaken</spells>
    <description>Frost druids are solitary defenders of nature and the natural enemies of civilization in the North. They seek to preserve the arctic wilderness by destroying outsiders who cross their path. Each patrols its territory in the guise of an arctic fox, a mountain goat, a snowy owl, or a wolf, reverting to human form only when it attacks. Clever ambushers, they use hallucinatory terrain spells to create illusory snowdrifts under which they can hide, or to obscure pools covered by thin ice through which others might fall.
Awakened Companions. A frost druid is often accompanied by one or more beasts, shrubs, or evergreen trees that it has made sentient using the awaken spell. These druids favor polar bears and reindeer (use the elk stat block in the Monster Manual) as companions, and such creatures typically share the druid's disposition.
Ice Sickle. A frost druid can carve a sickle out of ice, requiring a total of 24 hours for the work. Bitter cold courses through this weapon while it's in the druid's hands. If the druid dies, the ice sickle melts away. The weapon is otherwise identical to a normal sickle.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 288</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Frost Giant Skeleton</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (armor scraps)</ac>
    <hp>102 (12d12+24)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>8</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages>understands Giant but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>cold, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable>bludgeoning</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The skeleton doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The skeleton makes two greataxe attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Greataxe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 25 (3d12 + 6) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Greataxe|+9|3d12+6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Freezing Stare</name>
      <text>The skeleton targets one creature it can see within 60 feet of it. The target must succeed on a DC 13 Constitution saving throw or take 35 (10d6) cold damage and be paralyzed until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Freezing Stare||10d6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Necromancers can transform the inanimate bones of long-dead frost giants into malevolent juggernauts that love to harm the living.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 288</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Galvan Magen</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>14</ac>
    <hp>68 (8d8+32)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>lightning, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fiery End</name>
      <text>If the magen dies, its body disintegrates in a harmless burst of fire and smoke, leaving behind anything it was wearing or carrying.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The magen has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The magen doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The magen makes two Shocking Touch attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shocking Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target (the magen has advantage on the attack roll if the target is wearing armor made of metal). 7 (1d6 + 4) lightning damage.</text>
      <attack>Shocking Touch|+6|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Static Discharge (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The magen discharges a lightning bolt in a 60-foot line that is 5 feet wide. Each creature in that line must make a DC 14 Dexterity saving throw (with disadvantage if the creature is wearing armor made of metal), taking 22 (4d10) lightning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Static Discharge (Recharge 5-6)||4d10</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Galvan magen can fly. They also store static electricity, which they discharge as lightning bolts.
Magen are magical, humanlike beings created by a wizard spell (see the create magen spell in appendix D) or by other arcane methods.
Though magen look like humanoids with green skin, they are constructs. When one is wounded, its blood is seen to have the color and consistency of mercury. They exist purely through magical means. When one is killed, its body disappears in a burst of harmless fire and a cloud of smoke that quickly dissipates.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 301</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Giant Walrus</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>9</ac>
    <hp>85 (9d12+27)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>22</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>4</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>The walrus can hold its breath for 30 minutes.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The walrus makes two attacks: one with its body flop and one with its tusks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Body Flop</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 15 (2d8 + 6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Body Flop|+8|2d8+6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Tusks</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 16 (3d6 + 6) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Tusks|+8|3d6+6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Giant walruses are enormous, ill-tempered creatures as big as elephants. A typical adult specimen weighs at least 12,000 pounds.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 312</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Gnoll Vampire</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead (shapechanger)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>93 (11d8+44)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save>Dex +7, Con +7</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Gnoll</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist>necrotic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>The vampire has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Rampage</name>
      <text>When it reduces a creature to 0 hit points with a melee attack on its turn, the vampire can take a bonus action to move up to half its speed and make a bite attack.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Regeneration</name>
      <text>The vampire regains 10 hit points at the start of its turn if it has at least 1 hit point and isn't in sunlight or running water. If the vampire takes radiant damage or damage from holy water, this trait doesn't function at the start of the vampire's next turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>If the vampire isn't in sunlight, it can use its action to polymorph into a Large hyena or a Medium cloud of mist, or back into its true form.</text>
      <text>While in hyena form, the vampire can't speak, and its walking speed is 50 feet. Its statistics, other than its size and speed, are unchanged. Anything it is wearing transforms with it, but nothing it is carrying does. It reverts to its true form if it dies.</text>
      <text>While in mist form, the vampire can't take any actions, speak, or manipulate objects. it is weightless, has a flying speed of 20 feet, can hover, and can enter a hostile creature's space and stop there. In addition, if air can pass through a space, the mist can do so without squeezing, and it can't pass through water. It has advantage on Strength, Dexterity, and Constitution saving throws, and it is immune to all nonmagical damage, except the damage it takes from sunlight.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The vampire doesn't require air.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Vampire Weaknesses</name>
      <text>The vampire has the following flaws:</text>
      <text>Enraged by Celestial. If it hears words of Celestial spoken, the vampire must try to attack the source of those spoken words on its next turn. If these words come from multiple sources and from opposite directions, the vampire is restrained. Otherwise, it moves to attack what it perceives to be the closest source.</text>
      <text>Repulsed by Perfume. The vampire has disadvantage on melee attack rolls made against any creature wearing perfume or carrying an open container of it.</text>
      <text>Stake to the Heart. If a piercing weapon made of wood is driven into the vampire's heart while the vampire is incapacitated in its resting place, the vampire is paralyzed until the stake is removed.</text>
      <text>Sunlight Hypersensitivity. The vampire takes 20 radiant damage when it starts its turn in sunlight. While in sunlight, it has disadvantage on attack rolls and ability checks.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack (Vampire Form Only)</name>
      <text>The vampire makes two attacks: one with its bite and one with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite (Hyena or Vampire Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 12 (2d6 + 5) piercing damage plus 9 (2d8) necrotic damage. The target's hit point maximum is reduced by an amount equal to the necrotic damage taken, and the vampire regains hit points equal to that amount. The reduction lasts until the target finishes a long rest. the target dies if its hit point maximum is reduced to 0.</text>
      <attack>Bite (Hyena or Vampire Form Only)|+8|2d6+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws (Vampire Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (2d4 + 5) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws (Vampire Form Only)|+8|2d4+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Frightful Cackle (Hyena or Vampire Form Only)</name>
      <text>The vampire emits a bone-chilling cackle. Each creature of the vampire's choice that is within 120 feet of the vampire and can hear its cackle must succeed on a DC 15 Wisdom saving throw or become frightened for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. If a creature's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the creature is immune to the vampire's Frightful Cackle for the next 24 hours.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Sickening Gaze (Hyena or Vampire Form Only)</name>
      <text>The vampire targets one humanoid it can see within 30 feet of it. If the target can see the vampire, the target must succeed on a DC 15 Constitution saving throw against this magic or be poisoned for 24 hours. A creature whose saving throw is successful is immune to this vampire's Sickening Gaze for 24 hours.</text>
      </action>
    <description>When a gnoll's ravenous hunger is so great that it craves flesh and blood even after death, it can rise as a vampire to continue its feeding frenzy.
A gnoll vampire is a savage predator that feeds on the blood of the living. It cackles maniacally when it catches the scent of its prey and quickly moves in for the kill, tearing away flesh with its claws, gorging on meat and blood, and leaving nothing behind but bones, gristle, and the victim's blood-spattered belongings.
Gnoll vampires are indiscriminate feeders that prefer the flesh and blood of humanoids, including other gnolls. Their noses can't stand the scent of perfumes, and their ears can't abide words spoken aloud in Celestial. They don't cast reflections in mirrors unless they want to.
Unlike normal vampires, gnoll vampires don't have coffins where they rest, and they have no such places to return to when their corporeal bodies are destroyed. They are undeterred by running water, and they can enter residences without invitation. When a gnoll vampire needs to travel quickly, it adopts the form of a giant, emaciated hyena. When it wants to catch its prey by surprise, it takes the form of a cloud of mist. After it feeds on a victim's blood, its mist form takes on a crimson hue for an hour or so before its colorlessness returns.
Tekeli-Li and the Caves of Hunger. 
------
Tekeli-li was a Gnoll Fang of Yeenoghu, a powerful gnoll whose pack invaded Icewind Dale more than a century ago. When the gnolls' wanton slaughter of reindeer herds threatened the survival of the Reghed tribes, the tribes banded together against the gnolls and routed them in the autumn of 1333 DR. Tekeli-li and his surviving kin fled across the tundra with the Reghed tribes in pursuit.
The wounded gnolls found an icy cleft on the edge of the Reghed Glacier and hid there for the winter. To keep their leader alive, the other gnolls allowed Tekeli-li to eat them one by one, yet his hunger would not abate. Auril came upon the starving, half-frozen creature and flung Tekeli-li into an icy tomb deep within the glacier. In doing so, the Frostmaiden sought to preserve what the gnoll had become—the embodiment of winter's remorseless consumption.
Tekeli-li exists today as a gnoll vampire that hasn't fed in decades. Adventurers who use the "Rime of the Frostmaiden" to create a passage through the glacier unknowingly release the starving gnoll vampire from its icy sepulcher. For more information about Tekeli-li's lair, the Caves of Hunger, see chapter 6.
------
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 290</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Gnome Ceremorph</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>16 (breastplate)</ac>
    <hp>58 (13d6+13)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>6</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>19</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save>Int +7, Wis +6, Cha +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +7, Deception +6, Insight +6, Perception +6, Persuasion +6, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Deep Speech, Gnomish, telepathy 120 ft., Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The ceremorph has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Tentacles</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 15 (2d10 + 4) psychic damage. If the target is Medium or smaller, it is grappled (escape DC 9) and must succeed on a DC 15 Intelligence saving throw or be stunned until this grapple ends.</text>
      <attack>Tentacles|+7|2d10+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Extract Brain</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one incapacitated humanoid grappled by the ceremorph. 55 (10d10) piercing damage. If this damage reduces the target to 0 hit points, the ceremorph kills the target by extracting and devouring its brain.</text>
      <attack>Extract Brain|+7|10d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Laser Pistol</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 40/120 ft., one target. 12 (3d6 + 2) radiant damage.</text>
      <attack>Laser Pistol|+5|3d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Mind Blast (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The ceremorph magically emits psychic energy in a 60-foot cone. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 15 Intelligence saving throw or take 22 (4d8 + 4) psychic damage and be stunned for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <attack>Mind Blast (Recharge 5-6)||4d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting (Psionics)</name>
      <text>The ceremorph's innate spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 15). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no components:</text>
      <text>At will: detect thoughts, levitate</text>
      <text>1/day each: dominate monster, plane shift (self only)</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>detect thoughts, levitate, dominate monster, plane shift</spells>
    <description>Mind flayers, which are described in the Monster Manual, are created through ceremorphosis, a process that begins with the implantation of an illithid tadpole in the brain of a humanoid host. After about seven days in its new home, the tadpole transforms its host into a mind flayer. The new creation typically retains no memory of its previous existence.
For reasons unknown, ceremorphosis can go awry when an illithid tadpole is implanted in the brain of a gnome. This deviation might be due to the quasi-magical nature of gnomes, or simply a facet of how their minds work. When the process is warped only slightly, the mind flayer remains gnome-sized and is called a gnome ceremorph. It retains its knowledge of the Gnomish language while becoming able to speak Deep Speech and Undercommon. It retains fragmented memories of its previous life and previous alignment, not to mention a propensity for invention.
Laser Pistol. A gnome ceremorph often carries a home-built device that functions as a laser pistol (see "Firearms" in the Dungeon Master's Guide). This weapon is powered by an energy cell, which enables the weapon to fire 50 shots. After its last shot is expended, the device becomes inoperable. The energy cell can't be removed without destroying the weapon.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 303</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Gnome Squidling</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>8</ac>
    <hp>10 (3d6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 15 ft.</speed>
    <str>4</str>
    <dex>7</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>4</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands Deep Speech and Gnomish but can't speak, telepathy 60 ft.</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The squidling has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Tentacles</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +0 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 5 (2d4) psychic damage. If the target is Medium or smaller, it is grappled (escape DC 7) and must succeed on a DC 7 Intelligence saving throw or be stunned until this grapple ends.</text>
      <attack>Tentacles|+0|2d4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Extract Brain</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +0 to hit, reach 5 ft., one incapacitated creature grappled by the squidling. 27 (5d10) piercing damage. If this damage reduces the target to 0 hit points, the squidling kills the target by extracting and devouring its brain.</text>
      <attack>Extract Brain|+0|5d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Mind Tickle (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The squidling magically emits psychic energy in a 30-foot cone. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 7 Intelligence saving throw or take 2 (1d4) psychic damage and be stunned until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Mind Tickle (Recharge 5-6)||1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting (Psionics)</name>
      <text>The squidling's innate spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 7). It can innately cast levitate at will, requiring no components.</text>
      <text>At will: levitate</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>levitate</spells>
    <description>Mind flayers, which are described in the Monster Manual, are created through ceremorphosis, a process that begins with the implantation of an illithid tadpole in the brain of a humanoid host. After about seven days in its new home, the tadpole transforms its host into a mind flayer. The new creation typically retains no memory of its previous existence.
When the process of turning a gnome into a mind flayer goes horribly awry, the result is a gnome squidling—a deformed mind flayer with weak, spindly limbs and oversized tentacles. It relies on levitation to keep its body aloft and uses its tentacles like legs, to propel it along whatever surface it's floating above. Most mind flayers destroy squidlings on sight, so it's rare to see one or more of these creatures.
Squidlings eat brains for sustenance, just like other mind flayers do, and they don't care where the brains come from.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 303</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Goliath Warrior</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (goliath)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>67 (9d8+27)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +6, Perception +4, Survival +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist>cold</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Mountain Born</name>
      <text>The goliath is acclimated to high altitude, including elevations above 20,000 feet.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Powerful Build</name>
      <text>The goliath counts as one size larger when determining its carrying capacity and the weight it can push, drag, or lift.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The goliath makes two attacks with its greataxe or hurls two javelins.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Greataxe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (1d12 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Greataxe|+6|1d12+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Javelin</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 30/120 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Javelin|+6|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Stone's Endurance (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>When the goliath takes damage, it reduces the damage taken by 9 (1d12 + 3).</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>Goliaths inhabit the Spine of the World, where their mettle is tested against orcs, ogres, frost giants, remorhazes, ice trolls, young white dragons, the treacherous mountain terrain, and the cruel indifference of nature.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 292</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Goliath Werebear</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (goliath, shapechanger)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Good</alignment>
    <ac>10 (in humanoid form, 12 (natural armor) in bear or hybrid form)</ac>
    <hp>161 (19d8+76)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +8, Perception +8, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>18</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant (can't speak in bear form)</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist>cold</resist>
    <immune>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't silvered</immune>
    <vulnerable>fire</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>The werebear has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Mountain Born</name>
      <text>The werebear is acclimated to high altitude, including elevations above 20,000 feet.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Powerful Build (Humanoid Form Only)</name>
      <text>The werebear counts as one size larger when determining its carrying capacity and the weight it can push, drag, or lift.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>The werebear can use its action to polymorph into a Large bear-humanoid hybrid or into a Large polar bear, or back into its goliath form. Its statistics, other than its size and AC, are the same in each form. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying isn't transformed. It reverts to its true form if it dies.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The werebear makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite (Bear or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 16 (2d10 + 5) piercing damage. If the target is a humanoid, it must succeed on a DC 15 Constitution saving throw or be cursed with werebear lycanthropy, as described in the Monster Manual.</text>
      <attack>Bite (Bear or Hybrid Form Only)|+8|2d10+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw (Bear or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 14 (2d8 + 5) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw (Bear or Hybrid Form Only)|+8|2d8+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Greataxe (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (1d12 + 5) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Greataxe (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)|+8|1d12+5</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Stone's Endurance (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>When the werebear takes damage, it reduces the damage taken by 10 (1d12 + 4).</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>Goliath legends speak of a creature that prowls the far reaches of Icewind Dale, known as Oyaminartok the Winter Walker. She can take the form of either a polar bear or a hulking, bipedal shape obscured by wind and blowing snow. Elders invoke her name to keep young goliaths from wandering too far from home before they're ready. Adult goliaths sometimes encounter this legendary individual in their travels to the far-flung corners of the dale. If they flee like cowards, Oyaminartok laughs and lets them go to wander in obscurity. If they challenge Oyaminartok to a fight, the Winter Walker smiles and tests their mettle. Those who impress her with their fighting skills are bitten and become goliath werebears themselves—goliaths who carry Oyaminartok's curse of lycanthropy. Contrary to myth, Oyaminartok is not a monster but a force of good in the region, and she passes her curse only to goliaths whose hearts are pure.
Oyaminartok and others of her kind try to help creatures they come across, for the weather and the geography of Icewind Dale can be brutal. They know the safest routes across the tundra, and they can help guide travelers through the Sea of Moving Ice and across its ever-shifting ice floes. These polar werebears attack evil in the wilderness, but they steer clear of camps and settlements. Fire is Oyaminartok's bane, and thus she and her kind are wary around hearths and open flames.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 293</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Grandolpha Muzgardt</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>9</ac>
    <hp>59 (7d8+28)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Duergar Resilience</name>
      <text>Grandolpha has advantage on saving throws against poison, spells, and illusions, as well as to resist being charmed or paralyzed.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, Grandolpha has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Poison Spray (Cantrip)</name>
      <text>Grandolpha extends her hand toward a creature she can see within 10 feet of her and projects a puff of noxious gas from her palm. The creature must succeed on a DC 13 Constitution saving throw or take 13 (2d12) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Poison Spray (Cantrip)||2d12</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting (Psionics)</name>
      <text>Grandolpha's innate spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 13). She can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: druidcraft, mending, poison spray (see "Actions" below)</text>
      <text>3/day each: detect magic, enlarge/reduce (self only), faerie fire, invisibility (self only), polymorph, stoneskin (self only)</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>druidcraft, mending, poison spray, detect magic, enlarge/reduce, faerie fire, invisibility, polymorph, stoneskin</spells>
    <description>Grandolpha Muzgardt, the grand dame of the Muzgardt duergar clan, has recently arrived at the fortress after being invited here by Xardorok. The Muzgardts are based in Gracklstugh, a duergar city in the Underdark. They mass-produce and distribute a filthy duergar ale made from mushrooms. Xardorok has been eager to take a fourth wife and has had his eye on Grandolpha Muzgardt for many years. He asked Grandolpha to his fortress to give her a gift—a pseudodragon made of chardalyn (a pseudo-pseudodragon, if you will)—and make her an offer she can't refuse. Once he conquers Icewind Dale, he wants the Muzgardts to control the ale trade throughout his sunless surface kingdom.
Grandolpha, for her part, is too canny and jaded to fall for Xardorok's blunt attempt at seduction. She has begun plotting with disenfranchised advisors and warriors in his ranks to overthrow him when the moment is right. Ironically, despite his paranoia, Xardorok is too blinded by his admiration for Grandolpha to foresee her treachery.
Before entering combat, Grandolpha casts stoneskin on herself. Once her guards come to her rescue, she withdraws from combat and uses her faerie fire spell to make enemies easier for her guards to hit. The chardalyn pseudodragon defends Grandolpha to the death.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 176</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Gunvald Halraggson</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>13 (hide armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>76 (9d8+36)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +8, Intimidation +6, Survival +3</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Indomitable (3/Day)</name>
      <text>Gunvald can reroll a saving throw he fails. He must use the new roll.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Menacing Blows (1/Turn)</name>
      <text>Gunvald deals an extra 6 (1d12) damage when he hits a target with a weapon attack. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 14 Wisdom saving throw or be frightened until the start of Gunvald's next turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Second Wind (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Gunvald can regain 15 hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Gunvald makes three melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Battleaxe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (1d8 + 5) slashing damage, or 10 (1d10 + 5) slashing damage when used with two hands, plus 6 (1d12) slashing damage if Gunvald uses Menacing Blows.</text>
      <attack>Battleaxe|+8|1d8+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Javelin</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. 8 (1d6 + 5) piercing damage, plus 6 (1d12) piercing damage if Gunvald uses Menacing Blows.</text>
      <attack>Javelin|+8|1d6+5</attack>
      </action>
    <description>The thirty-year-old Bear King cuts an impressive figure and is renowned for his size and strength. He tries to be honorable, but he is often merciless and doesn't change his mind easily. He has trouble relating to Ten-Towners, so he avoids them. His perspective on townsfolk might change if they helped him destroy the chardalyn berserkers who have turned against their own.
Gunvald has had three wives in six years, each of whom died while she was pregnant. His advisors fear that the gods have cursed Gunvald and the entire tribe. In truth, the king's doting shaman, Ulkora, lusts for him and surreptitiously poisoned his wives. In time, Ulkora hopes Gunvald will turn his loving eye toward her and allow her to bear his true heir. If Gunvald were to learn the truth, he would put Ulkora to death.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 305</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Hare</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>1 (1d4-1)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., burrow 5 ft.</speed>
    <str>1</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>9</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>4</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +2, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Escape</name>
      <text>The hare can take the Dash, Disengage, or Hide action as a bonus action on each of its turns.</text>
      </trait>
    <description>Snowshoe hares are gentle herbivores that live in burrows throughout Icewind Dale. They have shorter ears than other hares and are acclimated to cold weather.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 294</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Headless Iron Golem</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>20 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>150 (10d10+50)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>24</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire, poison, psychic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't adamantine</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fire Absorption</name>
      <text>Whenever the golem is subjected to fire damage, it takes no damage and instead regains a number of hit points equal to the fire damage dealt.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The golem is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The golem has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Weapons</name>
      <text>The golem's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Headless</name>
      <text>It is blinded and deafened, giving it disadvantage on all its attack rolls, and it can't use its Poison Breath.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The golem makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 20 (3d8 + 7) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+13|3d8+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Sword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 23 (3d10 + 7) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Sword|+13|3d10+7</attack>
      </action>
    <description>The mightiest of the golems, the iron golem is a massive, towering giant wrought of heavy metal. An iron golem's shape can be worked into any form, though most are fashioned to look like giant suits of armor. Its fist can destroy creatures with a single blow, and its clanging steps shake the earth beneath its feet. Iron golems wield enormous blades to extend their reach, and all can belch clouds of deadly poison.
An iron golem's body is smelted with rare tinctures and admixtures. Though other golems bear weaknesses inherent in their materials or the power of the elemental spirit bound within them, iron golems were designed to be nearly invulnerable. Their iron bodies imprison the spirits that drive them, and are susceptible only to weapons imbued with magic or the strength of adamantine.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 244</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Hengar Aesnvaard</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Good</alignment>
    <ac>16 (studded leather armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>112 (15d8+45)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Str +7, Dex +5, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +10, Intimidation +5, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Brave</name>
      <text>Hengar has advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Brute</name>
      <text>A melee weapon deals one extra die of its damage when Hengar hits with it (included in the attack).</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Hengar makes three melee attacks or two ranged attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft. and range 20/60 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) piercing damage, or 13 (2d8 + 4) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Spear|+7|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shield Bash</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 9 (2d4 + 4) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Medium or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 15 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Shield Bash|+7|2d4+4</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Hengar adds 3 to his AC against one melee attack that would hit him. To do so, Hengar must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>Human champion of the Reghed Tribe of the Elk.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 215</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Hypnos Magen</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>34 (4d8+16)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak, telepathy 30 ft.</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fiery End</name>
      <text>If the magen dies, its body disintegrates in a harmless burst of fire and smoke, leaving behind anything it was wearing or carrying.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The magen has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The magen doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Psychic Lash</name>
      <text>The magen's eyes glow silver as it targets one creature that it can see within 60 feet of it. The target must succeed on a DC 12 Wisdom saving throw or take 11 (2d10) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Psychic Lash||2d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Suggestion</name>
      <text>The magen casts the suggestion spell (save DC 12), requiring no material components. The target must be a creature that the magen can communicate with telepathically. If it succeeds on its saving throw, the target is immune to this magen's suggestion spell for the next 24 hours. The magen's spellcasting ability is Intelligence.</text>
      </action>
    <description>Hypnos magen are telepathic and use their power of suggestion to control others. Their creators use them to force enemies to withdraw or surrender.
A hypnos magen carries no weapons, relying entirely on its psychic abilities to manipulate and harm other creatures.
Magen are magical, humanlike beings created by a wizard spell (see the create magen spell in appendix D) or by other arcane methods.
Though magen look like humanoids with green skin, they are constructs. When one is wounded, its blood is seen to have the color and consistency of mercury. They exist purely through magical means. When one is killed, its body disappears in a burst of harmless fire and a cloud of smoke that quickly dissipates.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 301</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Ice Piercer</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>22 (3d8+9)</hp>
    <speed>walk 5 ft., climb 5 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>7</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>8</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>cold</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 30 ft., darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>False Appearance</name>
      <text>While the ice piercer remains motionless on the ceiling, it is indistinguishable from a normal stalactite.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Spider Climb</name>
      <text>The ice piercer can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without needing to make an ability check.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Drop</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, one creature directly underneath the ice piercer. 10 (3d6) piercing damage plus 10 (3d6) cold damage. Miss: The ice piercer takes half the normal falling damage for the distance fallen.</text>
      <attack>Drop|+3|3d6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Auril the Frostmaiden has transformed icicles into creatures that resemble piercers.
Clinging to the ceilings of caverns and large subterranean passages, piercers blend in perfectly with natural rock, dropping in silence to impale unsuspecting foes on the ground below.
A piercer is the larval form of a roper, and the two creatures often attack in tandem. A rock-like shell encases a piercer's body, giving it the look and texture of a stalactite. That shell protects a soft, slug-like upper body that lets the piercer move across cavern walls and ceilings to position itself for prey. With its eye and mouth closed, the piercer is difficult to distinguish from ordinary rock formations.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 226</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Ice Troll</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>115 (10d10+60)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>22</con>
    <int>7</int>
    <wis>9</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Giant</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>cold</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Cold Aura</name>
      <text>While it's alive, the troll generates an aura of bitter cold that fills the area within 10 feet of it. At the start of the troll's turn, all nonmagical flames in the aura are extinguished. Any creature that starts its turn within 10 feet of the troll takes 10 (3d6) cold damage.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>The ice troll has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Regeneration</name>
      <text>The ice troll regains 10 hit points at the start of its turn. If the troll takes acid or fire damage, this trait doesn't function at the start of the troll's next turn. The ice troll dies only if it starts its turn with 0 hit points and doesn't regenerate.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The troll makes three attacks: one with its bite and two with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage plus 9 (2d8) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+7|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) slashing damage plus 9 (2d8) cold damage. If the target takes any of the cold damage, the target must succeed on a DC 15 Constitution saving throw or have disadvantage on its attack rolls until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+7|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Ice trolls have all the meanness and hunger of common trolls. Their hearts radiate extreme cold, to the detriment of other nearby creatures.
Ice Troll Hearts. An ice troll's heart remains cold even after the troll's destruction. As long as the troll can't regenerate, its heart can be safely removed from its remains, handled, and kept. An ice troll's heart, once removed, becomes a harmless Tiny object with AC 13, 4 hit points, and immunity to all damage except fire damage. For the next 24 hours, the heart has the following magical properties:
• A creature that eats the heart gains the ability to regenerate for the next 24 hours, regaining 5 hit points at the start of each of its turns. If the creature takes acid or fire damage, this trait doesn't function at the start of its next turn. The creature dies only if it starts its turn with 0 hit points and doesn't regenerate.
• If buried in the ground under a foot or more of earth, the heart melts away and summons a blizzard like that created by the control weather spell. It takes 10 minutes for the heart to melt and the blizzard to form. The blizzard lasts for 8 hours.
• A hag or similar creature can perform a ritual that turns the heart into a magical talisman that acts like a patch of brown mold (see "Brown Mold" in the Dungeon Master's Guide). This effect lasts until the heart is destroyed.
• A creature proficient with alchemist's supplies can squeeze enough residual fluid out of the heart to mix with other alchemical ingredients, creating one Potion of Cold Resistance. It takes 1 hour to create this potion.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 295</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Icewind Kobold</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (kobold)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>14 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>9 (2d6+2)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>7</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>8</int>
    <wis>8</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save>Dex +4, Con +3</save>
    <skill>Perception +1, Stealth +4, Survival +1</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>The kobold has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the kobold's allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, the kobold has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Javelin</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +0 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 30/120 ft., one target. 1 (1d6 - 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Javelin|+0|1d6-2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Kobolds can be found anywhere dragons are known to dwell, and those that live in the mountains and hills of Icewind Dale are among the hardiest of their kind. Drawn to the north by a desire to find and serve white dragons, these kobolds adapted as best they can to the hostile climate. Their sensitive eyes appreciate sunless days and long, dark nights. They use wooden javelins as tools to test the snow ahead of them.
Kobolds native to Icewind Dale frequently wander into Ten-Towns to escape the dreadful cold, hoping to trade what few skills they have for some warm soup and shelter. The people of Ten-Towns, accustomed to the presence of strange outlanders, allow these kobolds to dwell among them for the most part. When the kobolds don't feel safe, they acquire heavy winter clothing and disguise themselves as humans by standing on one another's shoulders. Three kobolds in cold weather gear can pass themselves off as a clumsy human with a successful group Charisma (Deception) check, the DC of which equals the onlooker's Wisdom (Insight) check result.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 296</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Icewind Kobold Zombie</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>9 (scraps of hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>19 (3d6+9)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>8</str>
    <dex>6</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>6</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save>Wis +0</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>8</passive>
    <languages>understands Common and Draconic but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Undead Fortitude</name>
      <text>If damage reduces the zombie to 0 hit points, it must make a Constitution saving throw with a DC of 5 + the damage taken, unless the damage is radiant or from a critical hit. On a success, the zombie drops to 1 hit point instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The zombie doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Javelin</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +1 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d6 - 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Javelin|+1|1d6-1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>The necromancer Vellynne Harpell has Icewind kobold guides in her employ, including a pair that died and were turned into zombies using animate dead spells. The cold climate helps to preserve their dead flesh.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 297</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Isarr Kronenstrom</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>117 (18d8+36)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +6, Intimidation +6, Perception +5, Stealth +6, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Blood Frenzy</name>
      <text>Isarr has advantage on melee attack rolls against any creature that doesn't have all its hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Indomitable (3/Day)</name>
      <text>Isarr can reroll a saving throw he fails. He must use the new roll.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Hearing and Smell</name>
      <text>Isarr has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing or smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Isarr makes three melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Sickle</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage, plus 13 (2d12) piercing damage if the target has no allies it can see within 10 feet of it.</text>
      <attack>Sickle|+6|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Heavy Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 100/400 ft., one target. 8 (1d10 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Heavy Crossbow|+6|1d10+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>The Wolf Tribe has been without a king or queen for years. Its most powerful chieftain, Isarr Kronenstrom, is a psychotic brute who worships Malar the Beast Lord. He hunts Ten-Towners for sport, bathes in their blood, and strikes fear into the hearts of his enemies. Several members of Isarr's clan have deserted him or been killed off, but the few that remain are fiercely loyal. They believe, incorrectly, that he's the Chosen of Malar.
Although Isarr calls himself the Wolf King, few others in the Wolf Tribe support him in that claim, but the other Wolf clan chieftains are too weak and disorganized to challenge him.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 307</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Jarund Elkhardt</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>14 (hide armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>104 (16d8+32)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Con +5, Wis +5</save>
    <skill>Athletics +7, Intimidation +7, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Brute</name>
      <text>A melee weapon deals one extra die of its damage when Jarund hits with it (included in the attack).</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Jarund makes three melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Warhammer</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage, or 15 (2d10 + 4) bludgeoning damage when used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Warhammer|+7|2d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shield</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 11 (2d6 + 4) bludgeoning damage, and Jarund pushes the target 5 feet away from him if it's Large or smaller. Jarund then enters the space vacated by the target. If the target is pushed to within 5 feet of a creature friendly to Jarund, that creature can make an attack against the target as a reaction.</text>
      <attack>Shield|+7|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Javelin</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 30/120 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Javelin|+7|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>The Elk King is Jarund Elkhardt, a terse yet thoughtful giant of a man who is nearly fifty years old—ancient by tribal standards. He has led the Elk Tribe for over half his life, and age has made him cautious. He has seen other kings and queens rise and fall, has made war with friends and peace with his enemies, and has led warriors he knew as babes to their deaths in battle. The strain of his long years of rule is etched on his weather-worn face.
Jarund's late son, Jarund Twice-Born, was killed almost a decade ago while trying to bring down a cave bear, leaving Jarund without an heir. He has failed to produce another child with his wife, Wynneth, and his mistress, Froya, so the future of his royal line remains uncertain.
Auril's unyielding winter concerns Jarund deeply, and he often turns to his shaman, Mjenir, for guidance. The king respects the shaman's understanding of gods and spirits, and the fact that both men have lost their sons serves to strengthen the bond between them. Mjenir believes that the only way to break Auril's spell is to slay the goddess in her home, but Jarund believes that his warriors aren't strong enough to accomplish that task alone.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 305</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Kadroth</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (tiefling)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>33 (6d8+6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +4, Persuasion +4, Religion +2</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist>fire</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dark Devotion</name>
      <text>The fanatic has advantage on saving throws against being charmed or frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The fanatic makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one creature. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The fanatic is a 4th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 11, +3 to hit with spell attacks). The fanatic has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): command, inflict wounds, shield of faith</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): hold person, spiritual weapon</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3</slots>
    <spells>light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy, command, inflict wounds, shield of faith, hold person, spiritual weapon</spells>
    <description>From this usurped office, he coordinates all cult activities in Ten-Towns. It's a role he carved out for himself by asserting that he's tight with Levistus. He rules the roost by sheer force of personality, though it chafes him that Hethyl Arkorran has more respect and influence within the cult. Kadroth doesn't involve Avarice in cult affairs because he fears her spellcasting ability and her connection to the Arcane Brotherhood. She could take over the cult anytime she wanted, and Kadroth doesn't want to give her any reason to do so.
For all his political machinations, Kadroth is a visionary who has so far made the cult stronger through his actions and decisions. He spends hours behind his desk, staring into the burning fireplace and drawing inspiration from its crackling flames. The slightest disturbance upsets him.
Kadroth appreciates the wisdom of maintaining the illusion that Speaker Crannoc Siever is still in charge, if only to keep Caer-Dineval's townsfolk from becoming restless. Thus, when necessary, Kadroth has the town speaker brought to his office to sign official documents.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 42</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Kingsport</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>5 (1d8+1)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>6</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>4</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 30 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>Kingsport can hold its breath for 20 minutes.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Beak</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d4 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Beak|+3|1d4+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Scrivenscry is an arcanaloth who always refers to itself in the third person. It has a fondness for black licorice, strips of which it keeps in the pockets of its robe. The fiend is attended by Kingsport, a blind, albino giant penguin under the effect of an awaken spell.
Scrivenscry's anxious penguin servant, Kingsport, was promised a life of enlightenment. The truth is that Kingsport was turned into Scrivenscry's lackey, who lives in fear of his cruel, unpredictable master. The blind giant penguin hopes to be free of the arcanaloth one day.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 243</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Knight of the Black Sword</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any Non-Good Alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>33 (6d8+6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +4, Persuasion +4, Religion +2</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dark Devotion</name>
      <text>The fanatic has advantage on saving throws against being charmed or frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Icy Doom</name>
      <text>When the cultist dies, its corpse freezes for 9 days, during which time it can't be thawed, harmed by fire, animated, or raised from the dead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The fanatic makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one creature. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The fanatic is a 4th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 11, +3 to hit with spell attacks). The fanatic has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): command, inflict wounds, shield of faith</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): hold person, spiritual weapon</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3</slots>
    <spells>light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy, command, inflict wounds, shield of faith, hold person, spiritual weapon</spells>
    <description>Fanatics are often part of a cult's leadership, using their charisma and dogma to influence and prey on those of weak will. Most are interested in personal power above all else.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 259</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Knucklehead Trout</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>7 (2d6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>6</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>8</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Water Breathing</name>
      <text>The trout can breathe only underwater.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Tail|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>The tasty and tenacious knucklehead trout can't easily be caught in nets. Moreover, using a line to reel in such a strong fish is a significant undertaking. Incautious fishers who get pulled into freezing water can quickly die, particularly if they're weighed down by heavy furs and cloaks.
A male knucklehead trout can weigh 70 pounds or more. The females tend to be smaller, weighing about 50 pounds. Both are prized for their ivory-like bones.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 295</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Kobold Vampire Spawn</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14</ac>
    <hp>39 (6d6+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>8</int>
    <wis>8</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save>Dex +6, Wis +1</save>
    <skill>Perception +1, Stealth +6</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist>necrotic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>The vampire has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the vampire's allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Regeneration</name>
      <text>The vampire regains 10 hit points at the start of its turn if it has at least 1 hit point and isn't in sunlight or running water. If the vampire takes radiant damage or damage from holy water, this trait doesn't function at the start of its next turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The vampire doesn't require air.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Vampire Weaknesses</name>
      <text>The vampire has the following flaws:</text>
      <text>Forbiddance. The vampire can't enter a residence without an invitation from one of the occupants.</text>
      <text>Harmed by Running Water. The vampire takes 20 acid damage when it starts its turn in running water.</text>
      <text>Stake to the Heart. The vampire is destroyed if a piercing weapon made of wood is driven into its heart while it is incapacitated in its resting place.</text>
      <text>Sunlight Hypersensitivity. The vampire takes 20 radiant damage when it starts its turn in sunlight. While in sunlight, it has disadvantage on attack rolls and ability checks.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 6 (1d4 + 4) piercing damage plus 5 (2d4) necrotic damage. The target's hit point maximum is reduced by an amount equal to the necrotic damage taken, and the vampire regains hit points equal to that amount. The reduction lasts until the target finishes a long rest. The target dies if its hit point maximum is reduced to 0.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+6|1d4+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>The gnoll vampire Tekeli-li has a small number of kobold vampire spawn minions to keep it company in the Caves of Hunger (see chapter 6). The vampiric kobolds are terrified of the gnoll vampire and can't understand its commands, so they give Tekeli-li a wide berth. These ravenous undead kobolds thirst for blood and tend to swarm one foe at a time.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 297</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Living Bigby's Hand</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>20 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>52 (5d10+25)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>26</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save>Dex +2, Wis +2</save>
    <skill>Perception +2, Stealth +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The living spell has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The living spell doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Force Fist</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +10 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 26 (4d8 + 8) force damage. If the target is a Large or smaller creature, the living spell can move it up to 5 feet and move with it, without provoking opportunity attacks.</text>
      <attack>Force Fist|+10|4d8+8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Grasping Hand</name>
      <text>The living spell attempts to grab a Huge or smaller creature within 5 feet of it. The target must succeed on a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw or be grappled (escape DC 15). Until the grapple ends, the target takes 15 (2d6 + 8) bludgeoning damage at the start of each of its turns. The living spell can grapple only one creature at a time and can't use Force Fist until the grapple ends.</text>
      <attack>Grasping Hand||2d6+8</attack>
      </action>
    <description>A living Bigby's hand is a Large, hovering hand of shimmering, translucent force. It often serves as a guardian, attacking creatures that cross its path while remaining loyal to its caster.
Areas of wild magic and sites that have been ravaged by powerful eldritch forces can give rise to spell effects that become living beings. These so-called living spells haunt the places where they were created, subsisting on ambient magical energy.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 298</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Living Blade of Disaster</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>67 (9d6+36)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>19</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, deafened, exhaustion, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, restrained, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The living spell has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unfettered</name>
      <text>The living spell can move through any barrier, even a wall of magical force.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The living spell doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Force Blade</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 26 (4d12) force damage, unless the living spell rolled an 18 or higher on the d20 for the attack, in which case the attack is a critical hit that deals 78 (12d12) force damage instead.</text>
      <attack>Force Blade|+6|4d12</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Preemptive Strike</name>
      <text>The living spell makes a melee attack against a creature that starts its turn within 5 feet of the living spell.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>A living blade of disaster is a blade of disaster spell (see appendix D) with a wicked will of its own. It looks like a floating, black planar rift in the shape of a sword. Like a demon, it craves destruction.
Areas of wild magic and sites that have been ravaged by powerful eldritch forces can give rise to spell effects that become living beings. These so-called living spells haunt the places where they were created, subsisting on ambient magical energy.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 299</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Living Demiplane</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>31 (7d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>1</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, restrained, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dimensional Form</name>
      <text>The living spell can enter another creature's space and vice versa, and it can move through a space as narrow as 1 inch wide without squeezing. The living spell can't detach from a solid surface, such as a wall, ceiling, or floor. If it has no surface to attach to, the living spell is destroyed (see "Planar Destruction" below).</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Extradimensional Chamber</name>
      <text>When the living spell enters another creature's space (or vice versa) for the first time on a turn, the other creature must succeed on a DC 10 Dexterity saving throw or be pulled into the living spell's extradimensional space, an unfurnished stone chamber 30 feet in every dimension. A creature too big to fit in this space succeeds on the saving throw automatically. Creatures in the chamber never run out of breathable air. Magic that enables transit between planes, such as plane shift, can be used to escape the chamber, which has no exits otherwise. Creatures trapped inside the extradimensional chamber can't see, target, or deal damage to the living spell; however, they can damage the room around them. Each 5-foot-square section of ceiling, wall, and floor in the chamber has AC 17, 50 hit points, immunity to poison and psychic damage, and immunity to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage that is nonmagical. If any section is reduced to 0 hit points, the living spell and its chamber are destroyed (see "Planar Destruction" below).</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The living spell has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Planar Destruction</name>
      <text>The living spell is destroyed when it or a 5-foot-square section of its extradimensional chamber is reduced to 0 hit points, or when the living spell has no surface to attach to. When the living spell is destroyed, the contents of its extradimensional chamber are expelled, appearing as close to the living spell's previous location as possible. Each expelled creature appears in a randomly determined unoccupied space, along with whatever it is wearing or carrying.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The living spell doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <description>A living demiplane is a demiplane spell that has become vaguely self-aware. It is a shadowy rectangle, 5 feet wide and 10 feet high, which creeps along flat, solid surfaces and groans softly when it moves.
When a living demiplane encounters a creature small enough to fit through its doorway, it tries to pull that creature into itself, then deposits the victim in an extradimensional chamber.
Areas of wild magic and sites that have been ravaged by powerful eldritch forces can give rise to spell effects that become living beings. These so-called living spells haunt the places where they were created, subsisting on ambient magical energy.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 299</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Lonelywood Banshee</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>58 (13d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>1</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save>Wis +2, Cha +5</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Elvish</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist>acid, fire, lightning, thunder; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>cold, necrotic, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Detect Life</name>
      <text>The banshee can magically sense the presence of creatures up to 5 miles away that aren't undead or constructs. She knows the general direction they're in but not their exact locations.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Incorporeal Movement</name>
      <text>The banshee can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. She takes 5 (1d10) force damage if she ends her turn inside an object.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Spectral Longbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +4 to hit, range 150/600 ft., one target. 12 (3d6 + 2) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Spectral Longbow|+4|3d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Horrifying Visage</name>
      <text>Each non-undead creature within 60 feet of the banshee that can see her must succeed on a DC 13 Wisdom saving throw or be frightened for 1 minute. A frightened target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, with disadvantage if the banshee is within line of sight, ending the effect on itself on a success. If a target's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the target is immune to the banshee's Horrifying Visage for the next 24 hours.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Wail (1/Day)</name>
      <text>The banshee releases a mournful wail, provided that she isn't in sunlight. This wail has no effect on constructs and undead. All other creatures within 30 feet of her that can hear her must make a DC 13 Constitution saving throw. On a failure, a creature drops to 0 hit points. On a success, a creature takes 10 (3d6) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Wail (1/Day)||3d6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>This banshee is the spectral remnant of a female elf warrior who was banished for a selfish, evil act. It wields a spectral longbow that shoots phantom arrows. There is only one banshee haunting the forest. If it's destroyed, it re-forms after 24 hours in a random location in the forest, damned to its eternal exile.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 81</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Mjenir</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Medicine +4, Nature +3, Perception +4, Survival +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Druidic plus any two languages</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Quarterstaff</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit (+4 to hit with shillelagh), reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage, 4 (1d8) bludgeoning damage if wielded with two hands, or 6 (1d8 + 2) bludgeoning damage with shillelagh.</text>
      <attack>Quarterstaff|+2|1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Mjenir is a 4th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 12, +4 to hit with spell attacks). He has the following druid spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): druidcraft, produce flame, shillelagh</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): entangle, longstrider, speak with animals, thunderwave</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): animal messenger, barkskin</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3</slots>
    <spells>druidcraft, produce flame, shillelagh, entangle, longstrider, speak with animals, thunderwave, animal messenger, barkskin</spells>
    <description>With grand events having been set in motion, those sensitive to prophecy have begun to experience dreams and visions. One such person is Mjenir, a fifty-year-old shaman of the Reghed Elk Tribe, who received a vision about the characters' journey to the Reghed Glacier.
Druids dwell in forests and other secluded wilderness locations, where they protect the natural world from monsters and the encroachment of civilization. Some are tribal shamans who heal the sick, pray to animal spirits, and provide spiritual guidance.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 215</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Mountain Goat</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>13 (2d8+4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Charge</name>
      <text>If the goat moves at least 20 feet straight toward a target and then hits it with a ram attack on the same turn, the target takes an extra 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 12 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sure-Footed</name>
      <text>The goat has advantage on Strength and Dexterity saving throws made against effects that would knock it prone.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Ram</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Ram|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Mountain goats are found throughout the Spine of the World and on the slopes of Kelvin's Cairn, their thick fur and layers of body fat protecting them from the extreme cold. They are expert climbers, able to leap and bound up sheer slopes.
Mountain goats are territorial but easily placated with offerings of food. Their stubbornness makes them difficult to domesticate.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 304</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Nass Lantomir's Ghost</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>45 (10d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>7</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Draconic, Orc</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist>acid, fire, lightning, thunder; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>cold, necrotic, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Ethereal Sight</name>
      <text>The ghost can see 60 feet into the Ethereal Plane when it is on the Material Plane, and vice versa.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Incorporeal Movement</name>
      <text>The ghost can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. It takes 5 (1d10) force damage if it ends its turn inside an object.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Withering Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 17 (4d6 + 3) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Withering Touch|+6|4d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Etherealness</name>
      <text>The ghost enters the Ethereal Plane from the Material Plane, or vice versa. It is visible on the Material Plane while it is in the Border Ethereal, and vice versa, yet it can't affect or be affected by anything on the other plane.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Horrifying Visage</name>
      <text>Each non-undead creature within 60 feet of the ghost that can see it must succeed on a DC 14 Wisdom saving throw or be frightened for 1 minute. If the save fails by 5 or more, the target also ages 1d4 x 10 years. A frightened target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the frightened condition on itself on a success. If the target's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the target is immune to this ghost's Horrifying Visage for the next 24 hours. The aging effect can be reversed by a greater restoration spell, but only if it is cast within 24 hours.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Possession (Recharge 6)</name>
      <text>One humanoid that the ghost can see within 5 feet of it must succeed on a DC 14 Charisma saving throw or be possessed by the ghost; the ghost then disappears, and the target is incapacitated and loses control of its body. The ghost now controls the body but doesn't deprive the target of awareness. The ghost can't be targeted by any attack, spell, or other effect, except ones that turn undead, and it retains its alignment, Intelligence, Wisdom, Charisma, and immunity to being charmed and frightened. It otherwise uses the possessed target's statistics, but doesn't gain access to the target's knowledge, class features, or proficiencies. The possession lasts until the body drops to 0 hit points, the ghost ends it as a bonus action, or the ghost is turned or forced out by an effect like the dispel evil and good spell. When the possession ends, the ghost reappears in an unoccupied space within 5 feet of the body. The target is immune to this ghost's Possession for 24 hours after succeeding on the saving throw or after the possession ends.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The ghost is a 6th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 14). The ghost has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): mage hand, message, prestidigitation, ray of frost</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, thunderwave</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): </text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3</slots>
    <spells>mage hand, message, prestidigitation, ray of frost, detect magic, thunderwave, counterspell</spells>
    <description>Nass Lantomir was an apprentice of Zelenn the White, one of five archmages who oversee the Arcane Brotherhood. Nass and Zelenn's relationship started off well, but in recent years it has become painfully obvious to Zelenn that Nass has been slow to master the arcane tradition of divination. Zelenn's suggestion that Nass leave the Hosttower of the Arcane and gain experience abroad left Nass feeling unwanted. After much thought, however, Nass came around to the idea. She could put her magic to the test and carve out a name for herself.
As she was preparing to leave the Hosttower, Nass overheard her master talking to another wizard about a covert expedition to Icewind Dale being undertaken to seek out long-lost magic from a bygone empire. Rather than carry out her original plan, Nass followed her fellow wizards to Icewind Dale. She caught up to them in Bryn Shander and made her presence known, claiming she was sent by her master to aid the expedition with her divinations. Egos and frayed nerves caused the group to split up shortly thereafter, with each wizard determined to succeed alone.
One night while the others slept, Nass stole a Professor Skant (see appendix D) from one of her fellow wizards, Vellynne Harpell. Two of Vellynne's kobold companions witnessed the theft, and Nass killed them with Melf's acid arrow spells before fleeing with the orb.
Nass fled Ten-Towns and headed toward the Sea of Moving Ice, hoping to find a tome called The Codicil of White, a book of magic and lore composed by servants of Auril the Frostmaiden. The Arcane Brotherhood believes that this book tells how to reach a lost city of magic entombed in the ice. Before she could obtain the book, Nass perished. She now exists as a ghost, unable to rest until she finds the book. Characters who come upon Nass's frozen remains also find her spellbook and the orb she stole from Vellynne.
Familiar. Nass's magical familiar, a white arctic weasel acclimated to cold weather named Zelennor, watches over the wizard's frozen remains. It uses the weasel stat block in the Monster Manual but is a fey instead of a beast. If Zelennor is reduced to 0 hit points, Nass's ghost is unable to cast the find familiar spell in order to get it back.
Spellcasting. As a ghost, Nass can cast the spells she prepared prior to her death—except that the ghost can't cast spells that require material components, which limits its options. Its list of prepared spells shows only those spells it can cast. Although it has no 2nd-level spells available, the ghost can use its 2nd-level spell slots to cast upgraded versions of the thunderwave spell.
Spellbook. The wooden covers of Nass's spellbook are bound in nothic hide, and silver clasps hold the book shut. Nass's personal sigil is inscribed on the spine, which also bears the title Lantomir's Traveling Libram. The tome contains the following spells: clairvoyance, cloud of daggers, counterspell, detect magic, detect thoughts, find familiar, Melf's acid arrow, Tenser's floating disk, and thunderwave.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 272</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Prisoner 237</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>32 (5d8+10)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Arcana +5, Deception +4, Persuasion +4</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Infernal, Orc</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Shocking Grasp (Cantrip)</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +5 to hit (with advantage on the attack if the target is wearing armor made of metal), reach 5 ft., one creature. 9 (2d8) lightning damage, and the target can't take reactions until the start of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Shocking Grasp (Cantrip)|+5|2d8</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Prisoner 237 is a 5th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 13; +5 to hit with spell attacks). He has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light*, message*, prestidigitation, shocking grasp (see "Actions" below)</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): mage armor*, shield, sleep</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): arcane lock*, detect thoughts*, suggestion*</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (2 slots): counterspell, lightning bolt*</text>
      <text>*Prisoner 237 needs material components to cast these spells.</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>light, message, prestidigitation, shocking grasp, mage armor, shield, sleep, arcane lock, detect thoughts, suggestion, counterspell, lightning bolt</spells>
    <description>Vaelish Gant, Prisoner 237 within the walls of Revel's End, is a member of the Arcane Brotherhood who first engaged in criminal activity by insinuating himself into the trade network of Ten-Towns. He hoped that his work would help the Arcane Brotherhood gain control of the region. A few years ago, shortly after his arrival in Ten-Towns, Gant established a protection racket in Bryn Shander and tried to turn the town against its speaker, Duvessa Shane, with the goal of supplanting her. He also tried to destabilize the economy of Ten-Towns. A party of adventurers thwarted his criminal ventures by capturing him.
Rather than put Gant to death for his crimes in Icewind Dale, the Council of Speakers in Ten-Towns made a deal with representatives of the Lords' Alliance to have Gant serve a life sentence in Revel's End, so as not to incur the Arcane Brotherhood's wrath. The Council of Speakers did this not realizing that Gant's scheme wasn't sanctioned by the Arcane Brotherhood but rather hatched by Gant himself, who intended to impress his superiors by pulling it off.
For a long time, Gant held out hope that the Arcane Brotherhood would apply pressure to secure his release, and that the Lords' Alliance would acquiesce to the brotherhood's demands rather than risk an all-out attack on Revel's End. But by now, Gant has been incarcerated long enough to reasonably conclude that no such rescue is forthcoming. His failed scheme was an embarrassment to the Arcane Brotherhood, which has clearly forsaken him.
Vaelish Gant is a mage who specializes in the arcane tradition of abjuration. Pompous and conniving, he never doubts that he's the smartest person in the room, and he makes sure everyone around him knows how he feels.
Gant has neither a spellbook nor material components for spellcasting, and he can't avail himself of his magic while locked in his cell due to the antimagic field that encompasses it.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 160</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Reghed Chieftain</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>16 (hide armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>112 (15d8+45)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Str +7, Dex +5, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +10, Intimidation +5, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Brave</name>
      <text>The chieftain has advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Brute</name>
      <text>A melee weapon deals one extra die of its damage when the chieftain hits with it (included in the attack).</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The chieftain makes three melee attacks or two ranged attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft. and range 20/60 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) piercing damage, or 13 (2d8 + 4) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Spear|+7|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shield Bash</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 9 (2d4 + 4) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Medium or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 15 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Shield Bash|+7|2d4+4</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>The chieftain adds 3 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, the chieftain must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>Reghed Nomads. Reghed nomads are the children of the Reghed Glacier, as suggested by their name. They are people of the wild, as revealed by their tribal names—the Elk, the Tiger, the Wolf, the Bear. They are the tribes of Icewind Dale, proud and strong, bound to ancient traditions that have kept them alive through countless harsh winters. The Reghed wear heavy furs as well as gloves, boots, and masks made of animal hide, to protect themselves from the bitter cold.
Although they originally descended from humans who were predominantly blue-eyed and fair-haired, the Reghed tribes have assimilated other folk, adding new blood to their dwindling ranks. There used to be more than four Reghed tribes, but the others have all disbanded over the past century, with many of their former members settling in Ten-Towns and abandoning their traditional ways.
The Reghed tribes rely on a nomadic lifestyle to survive, as they follow herds of reindeer along the route of the animals' annual migration. When they make camp, the tribesfolk live in large, round tents made of deerskin and supported by wooden shafts.
Reghed tribe camps are scattered throughout Icewind Dale. None of them appear on maps because they don't stay in one place for long.
Each Reghed tribe is made up of smaller clans, each with its own chieftain (the most powerful of whom often carries the title of king or queen). A clan might set up its camp for a tenday or two, then dismantle it and go back on the move, allowing the clan to stay close to a migrating herd of reindeer as it travels across the tundra.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 152</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Reghed Great Warrior</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>16 (hide armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>112 (15d8+45)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Str +7, Dex +5, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +10, Intimidation +5, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Brave</name>
      <text>The great warrior has advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Brute</name>
      <text>A melee weapon deals one extra die of its damage when the great warrior hits with it (included in the attack).</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The great warrior makes three melee attacks or two ranged attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft. and range 20/60 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) piercing damage, or 13 (2d8 + 4) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Spear|+7|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shield Bash</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 9 (2d4 + 4) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Medium or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 15 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Shield Bash|+7|2d4+4</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>The great warrior adds 3 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, the great warrior must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>Reghed Nomads. Reghed nomads are the children of the Reghed Glacier, as suggested by their name. They are people of the wild, as revealed by their tribal names—the Elk, the Tiger, the Wolf, the Bear. They are the tribes of Icewind Dale, proud and strong, bound to ancient traditions that have kept them alive through countless harsh winters. The Reghed wear heavy furs as well as gloves, boots, and masks made of animal hide, to protect themselves from the bitter cold.
Although they originally descended from humans who were predominantly blue-eyed and fair-haired, the Reghed tribes have assimilated other folk, adding new blood to their dwindling ranks. There used to be more than four Reghed tribes, but the others have all disbanded over the past century, with many of their former members settling in Ten-Towns and abandoning their traditional ways.
The Reghed tribes rely on a nomadic lifestyle to survive, as they follow herds of reindeer along the route of the animals' annual migration. When they make camp, the tribesfolk live in large, round tents made of deerskin and supported by wooden shafts.
Reghed tribe camps are scattered throughout Icewind Dale. None of them appear on maps because they don't stay in one place for long.
Each Reghed tribe is made up of smaller clans, each with its own chieftain (the most powerful of whom often carries the title of king or queen). A clan might set up its camp for a tenday or two, then dismantle it and go back on the move, allowing the clan to stay close to a migrating herd of reindeer as it travels across the tundra.
This great warrior is often the chieftain's spouse, sibling, offspring, or childhood friend—someone the chieftain trusts.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 152</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Reghed Shaman</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Medicine +4, Nature +3, Perception +4, Survival +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common, Druidic</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Quarterstaff</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit (+4 to hit with shillelagh), reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage, 4 (1d8) bludgeoning damage if wielded with two hands, or 6 (1d8 + 2) bludgeoning damage with shillelagh.</text>
      <attack>Quarterstaff|+2|1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The druid is a 4th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 12, +4 to hit with spell attacks). It has the following druid spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): druidcraft, produce flame, shillelagh</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): entangle, longstrider, speak with animals, thunderwave</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): animal messenger, barkskin</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3</slots>
    <spells>druidcraft, produce flame, shillelagh, entangle, longstrider, speak with animals, thunderwave, animal messenger, barkskin</spells>
    <description>In public, the shaman dons a wooden mask carved in the likeness of a bear, an elk, a tiger, or a wolf, as befits the tribe.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 152</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Reghed Warrior</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>11 (2d8+2)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>8</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Survival +4</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>The warrior has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the warrior's allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) piercing damage, or 5 (1d8 + 1) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Spear|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Tribal warriors live beyond civilization, most often subsisting on fishing and hunting. Each tribe acts in accordance with the wishes of its chief, who is the greatest or oldest warrior of the tribe or a tribe member blessed by the gods.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 152</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Reindeer</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>13 (2d10+2)</hp>
    <speed>walk 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Charge</name>
      <text>If the reindeer moves at least 20 feet straight toward a target and then hits it with a ram attack on the same turn, the target takes an extra 7 (2d6) damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 13 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Ram</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Ram|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hooves</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one prone creature. 8 (2d4 + 3) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Hooves|+5|2d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 107</description>
    <environment>grassland, forest, hill</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Seal</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>9 (2d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>The seal can hold its breath for 15 minutes.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>The seal has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 1 piercing damage.</text>
      </action>
    <description>The seals native to the Sea of Moving Ice often beach themselves on ice floes and rocky shores. They are acclimated to the cold weather and feed primarily on small fish, squid, and clams. Seal pups have yellowish-white fur, which turns silvery gray as they enter adulthood.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 308</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sephek Kaltro</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>75 (10d8+30)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +5, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>cold</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Cold Regeneration</name>
      <text>If the temperature around him is 0 degrees Fahrenheit or lower, Sephek regains 5 hit points at the start of his turn. If he takes fire damage, this trait doesn't function at the start of Sephek's next turn. Sephek dies only if he starts his turn with 0 hit points and doesn't regenerate.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Sephek attacks twice with a weapon.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Ice Longsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) slashing damage, or 8 (1d10 + 3) slashing damage if Sephek uses the weapon with two hands, plus 5 (2d4) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Ice Longsword|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Ice Dagger</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage plus 5 (2d4) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Ice Dagger|+5|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Sephek can innately cast misty step up to three times per day, requiring no components. His innate spellcasting ability is Charisma.</text>
      <text>At will: misty step</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>misty step</spells>
    <description>Sephek Kaltro is a well-built man in his thirties. He has an olive complexion, dark hair pulled back in a ponytail, and no facial or body hair. He is dressed in a stylish vest with matching pants and boots, similar in style to those worn by mariners of the southern Sword Coast, but wears no armor or cold weather clothing and doesn't appear to be armed. His most striking feature is his eyes, which are as blue as a frozen lake.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 23</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Snow Golem</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>8</ac>
    <hp>39 (6d8+12)</hp>
    <speed>walk 10 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>6</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>6</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>8</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>cold, poison; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</immune>
    <vulnerable>fire</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Cold Absorption</name>
      <text>Whenever the golem is subjected to cold damage, it takes no damage and instead regains a number of hit points equal to the cold damage dealt.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The golem is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Melt</name>
      <text>While in an area of extreme heat, the golem loses 1d6 hit points at the start of each of its turns.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The golem doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The golem makes three melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) bludgeoning damage plus 7 (2d6) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Snowball</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +0 to hit, range 60 ft., one target. 9 (2d6 + 2) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Snowball|+0|2d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>A snow golem is a mass of snow brought to life through magic. Nonmagical weapons pass through its snowy form without dealing any appreciable damage to it, though heat is its doom.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 308</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Snowy Owlbear</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>59 (7d10+21)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Sight and Smell</name>
      <text>The snowy owlbear has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight or smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The snowy owlbear makes two attacks: one with its beak and one with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Beak</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 10 (1d10 + 5) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Beak|+7|1d10+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 14 (2d8 + 5) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+7|2d8+5</attack>
      </action>
    <description>A snowy owlbear combines the physical features of a snowy owl and a polar bear. When not asleep or hibernating, it galumphs across the icy tundra in search of food.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 309</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Spellix Romwod</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (gnome)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>14 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>33 (6d6+12)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>6</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>9</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Arcana +4, Deception +5, History +4</skill>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Elvish, Gnomish, Goblin</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Gnome Cunning</name>
      <text>Spellix has advantage on all Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saving throws against magic.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Shocking Grasp (Cantrip)</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +5 to hit (with advantage on the attack roll if the target is wearing armor made of metal), reach 5 ft., one creature. 4 (1d8) lightning damage, and the target can't take reactions until the start of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Shocking Grasp (Cantrip)|+5|1d8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Fire Bolt (Cantrip)</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +5 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. 5 (1d10) fire damage. A flammable object hit by this spell ignites if it isn't being worn or carried.</text>
      <attack>Fire Bolt (Cantrip)|+5|1d10</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Spellix's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). He can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: fire bolt*, mage hand, shocking grasp*</text>
      <text>3/day: silent image</text>
      <text>1/day each: chromatic orb, crown of madness, shield</text>
      <text>*See "Actions" below.</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>fire bolt, mage hand, shocking grasp, silent image, chromatic orb, crown of madness, shield</spells>
    <description>
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 144</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sperm Whale</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>189 (14d20+42)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., swim 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>26</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Echolocation</name>
      <text>The whale can't use its blindsight while deafened.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>The whale can hold its breath for 90 minutes.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Hearing</name>
      <text>The whale has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The whale makes two attacks: one with its bite and one with its tail.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 21 (3d8 + 8) piercing damage. If the target is a Large or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 14 Dexterity saving throw or be swallowed by the whale. A swallowed creature has total cover against attacks and other effects outside the whale, and it takes 3 (1d6) acid damage at the start of each of the whale's turns. If the whale takes 30 damage or more on a single turn from a creature inside it, the whale must succeed on a DC 16 Constitution saving throw at the end of that turn or regurgitate all swallowed creatures, which fall prone in a space within 10 feet of the whale. If the whale dies, a swallowed creature can escape from the corpse by using 20 feet of movement, exiting prone.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+11|3d8+8</attack>
      <attack>Bite||1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. 18 (3d6 + 8) bludgeoning damage, or 37 (6d6 + 16) bludgeoning damage if the target is an object.</text>
      <attack>Tail|+11|3d6+8</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Sperm whales are toothed aquatic mammals that can grow to be up to 70 feet long. Their natural predators include whalers and fellow leviathans, such as dragon turtles and krakens.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 309</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Spitting Mimic</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity (shapechanger)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>85 (10d10+30)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>21</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Stealth +7</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>acid</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>The mimic can use its action to polymorph into an object or back into its true, amorphous form. Its statistics are the same in each form. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying isn't transformed. It reverts to its true form if it dies.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Adhesive (Object Form Only)</name>
      <text>The mimic adheres to anything that touches it. A Huge or smaller creature adhered to the mimic is also grappled by it (escape DC 16). Ability checks made to escape this grapple have disadvantage.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>False Appearance (Object Form Only)</name>
      <text>While the mimic remains motionless, it is indistinguishable from an ordinary object.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Grappler</name>
      <text>The mimic has advantage on attack rolls against any creature grappled by it.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The mimic has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The mimic attacks three times: twice with its pseudopods and once with its bite.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Pseudopods</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 10 (1d10 + 5) bludgeoning damage. If the mimic is in object form, the target is subjected to its Adhesive trait.</text>
      <attack>Pseudopods|+8|1d10+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 10 (1d10 + 5) piercing damage plus 7 (2d6) acid damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+8|1d10+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spit Acid (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The mimic spits acid at one creature it can see within 30 feet of it. The target must make a DC 14 Dexterity saving throw, taking 32 (9d6 + 1) acid damage on failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Spit Acid (Recharge 5-6)||9d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Mimics are shape-shifting monsters described in theMonster Manual. The variant presented here is a particularly large and voracious specimen—the result of Netherese experiments on ordinary mimics—that spits acid.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 302</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Telepathic Pentacle</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>172 (15d12+75)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>The Telepathic Pentacle can hold its breath for 1 hour.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Multiple Heads</name>
      <text>The Telepathic Pentacle has five heads. While it has more than one head, the Telepathic Pentacle has advantage on saving throws against being blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, stunned, and knocked unconscious.</text>
      <text>Whenever the Telepathic Pentacle takes 25 or more damage in a single turn, one of its heads dies. If all its heads die, the Telepathic Pentacle dies.</text>
      <text>At the end of its turn, it grows two heads for each of its heads that died since its last turn, unless it has taken fire damage since its last turn. The Telepathic Pentacle regains 10 hit points for each head regrown in this way.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Reactive Heads</name>
      <text>For each head the Telepathic Pentacle has beyond one, it gets an extra reaction that can be used only for opportunity attacks.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Wakeful</name>
      <text>While the Telepathic Pentacle sleeps, at least one of its heads is awake.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The Telepathic Pentacle makes as many bite attacks as it has heads.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 10 (1d10 + 5) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+8|1d10+5</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Months before Ythryn's fall, a circle of mages known as the Telepathic Pentacle tried to fuse their minds together to become a conjoined telepathic force. The procedure went terribly wrong, and their bodies and minds melded into a single monstrosity. Iriolarthas imprisoned the thing in this empty well so that its latent telepathic powers could be tapped by the city's elite. A short obituary is engraved around the lip of the well in Draconic: "Herein lie the immortal remains of the Telepathic Pentacle. Sit, meditate, and learn."
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 244</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Tomb Tapper</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>207 (18d12+90)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., burrow 10 ft.</speed>
    <str>22</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>understands Common and Undercommon but doesn't speak, telepathy 60 ft.</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <resist>lightning</resist>
    <immune>cold, fire</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 240 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Petrified Death</name>
      <text>A tomb tapper reduced to 0 hit points turns into a lifeless stone statue. Anything it's wearing or carrying is not transformed.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sense Magic</name>
      <text>The tomb tapper senses magic within 30 feet of it and can use an action to pinpoint the location of any creature, object, or area in that range that bears magic. This sense penetrates barriers but is blocked by a thin sheet of lead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Tunneler</name>
      <text>The tomb tapper can burrow through solid rock at half its burrowing speed and leaves a 10-foot-wide, 20-foot-tall tunnel in its wake.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The tomb tapper doesn't require air or sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The tomb tapper makes two melee attacks with its sledgehammer or with its claws. If it hits the same creature with both claws, it can pull that creature within 5 feet of its mouth and make a bite attack against it.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 22 (3d10 + 6) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+10|3d10+6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 16 (3d6 + 6) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+10|3d6+6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Sledgehammer</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 15 ft. or range 30/120 ft., one target. 27 (6d6 + 6) bludgeoning or force damage (tomb tapper's choice). If thrown, the hammer returns to the tomb tapper at the end of its turn, landing at the tomb tapper's feet if it doesn't have a hand free to catch the weapon.</text>
      <attack>Sledgehammer|+10|6d6+6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Seekers of Magic. Tomb tappers received their colloquial name from their habit of burrowing into the depths to plunder tombs, temples, and caves in search of magic items, which they bear off. They usually try to seize magic from beings that they encounter.
Magic is sacred to tomb tappers. They don't use any magic items they acquire, instead choosing to protect and venerate such items. Tappers spend their long lives in the search for the source of all magic, which they believe to be hidden deep in the Underdark. They are in awe of earth elementals, believing that they come directly from this source, and are reluctant to attack them.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 310</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Tribal Warrior Spore Servants</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>plant</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>11 (2d8+2)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>6</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, frightened, paralyzed</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 30 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <action>
        <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) piercing damage, or 5 (1d8 + 1) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Spear|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 52</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Vellynne Harpell</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>13 (bracers of defense)</ac>
    <hp>67 (9d8+27)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>18</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save>Int +6, Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, History +6</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Dwarvish, Elvish, Orc</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Vellynne wears bracers of defense and carries a wand of magic missiles (see "Actions" below).</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Vampiric Touch (3rd-Level Spell; Requires a Spell Slot)</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 10 (3d6) necrotic damage, and Vellynne regains hit points equal to half the necrotic damage dealt. If Vellynne casts this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the necrotic damage increases by 1d6 for each slot level above 3rd.</text>
      <attack>Vampiric Touch (3rd-Level Spell; Requires a Spell Slot)|+6|3d6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Chill Touch (Cantrip)</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +6 to hit, range 120 ft., one creature. 9 (2d8) necrotic damage, and the target can't regain hit points until the start of Vellynne's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Chill Touch (Cantrip)|+6|2d8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Wand of Magic Missiles</name>
      <text>While holding this wand, Vellynne can expend 1 or more of its 7 charges to cast the magic missile spell from it. She can expend 1 charge to cast the 1st-level version of the spell. She can increase the spell slot level by one for each additional charge she expends. The wand regains 1d6 + 1 expended charges daily at dawn. If the wand's last charge is expended, roll a d20; on a 1, the wand crumbles into ashes and is destroyed.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Vellynne is an 8th-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks). She has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): chill touch (see "Actions" below), light, mage hand, message, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): comprehend languages, detect magic, ray of sickness, Tasha's hideous laughter</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): darkvision, hold person, ray of enfeeblement</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): animate dead, Leomund's tiny hut, vampiric touch (see "Actions" below)</text>
      <text>• 4th level (2 slots): arcane eye, blight</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>chill touch, light, mage hand, message, prestidigitation, comprehend languages, detect magic, ray of sickness, Tasha's hideous laughter, darkvision, hold person, ray of enfeeblement, animate dead, Leomund's tiny hut, vampiric touch, arcane eye, blight</spells>
    <description>Vellynne Harpell is a member of the prestigious Harpell family, based in the town of Longsaddle. Cold and dispassionate, she took to magic only a decade ago in her late forties and is skilled in the arcane tradition of necromancy. She has a lifelong struggle—a nervous disorder that manifests as trembling. It can affect her balance and her stride, but she has learned to cast her spells unimpeded by it.
Despite her firm grasp of the dark arts, she would not have been admitted into the Arcane Brotherhood without her family connections—a fact that sticks in her craw.
Vellynne brought a family heirloom with her to Icewind Dale: a professor orb (see appendix D) that she refers to by its proper name, Professor Skant. This orb has knowledge about Netheril that could be important if Vellynne locates the lost Netherese city buried under the Reghed Glacier. The orb was recently stolen by Nass Lantomir, one of Vellynne's rivals in the Arcane Brotherhood. Vellynne intends to get it back before resuming her quest to find Ythryn.
Companions. Since arriving in Icewind Dale, Vellynne has secured the services of six Icewind Kobold that act as her valets and guides. Two of them were killed by a Melf's acid arrow spell (cast by Vellynne's rival, Nass Lantomir), but Vellynne animated their corpses, turning them into zombies.
If she is wounded, Vellynne can cast vampiric touch and use the spell to regain hit points at the kobolds' expense.
Familiar. Vellynne's familiar is a snowy owl, which the wizard uses as a scout. It uses the owl stat block in the Monster Manual but is a celestial instead of a beast.
Spellbook. Vellynne's spellbook has black leather covers around pages of ragged parchment, all wrapped in a crimson sash. The necromancer's personal sigil is written in goat's blood on the title page. The tome contains the spells Vellynne has prepared plus the following additional spells: bestow curse, blindness/deafness, false life, find familiar, magic weapon, polymorph, protection from evil and good, remove curse, shield, and Tenser's floating disk.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 273</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Verbeeg Longstrider</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>14 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>119 (14d10+42)</hp>
    <speed>walk 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Dex +5, Con +6, Wis +5</save>
    <skill>Animal handling +5, Athletics +7, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Simple Weapon Wielder</name>
      <text>A simple weapon deals one extra die of its damage when the verbeeg hits with it (included in the attack).</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The verbeeg makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 14 (3d6 + 4) piercing damage, or 17 (3d8 + 4) piercing damage if used to make a ranged attack or used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Spear|+7|3d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Sling</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. 9 (3d4 + 2) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 15 Constitution saving throw or be stunned until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Sling|+5|3d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The verbeeg's innate spellcasting ability is Wisdom. It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no components:</text>
      <text>1/day each: animal messenger, fog cloud, freedom of movement, pass without trace, silence, water walk</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>animal messenger, fog cloud, freedom of movement, pass without trace, silence, water walk</spells>
    <description>Longstriders
Some verbeeg worship gods of nature and help defend the natural world. These even-tempered verbeeg are called longstriders and are blessed with innate spellcasting abilities.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 311</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Verbeeg Marauder</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (hide armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>85 (10d10+30)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save>Dex +2, Con +5</save>
    <skill>Animal handling +2, Athletics +6, Stealth +2</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Simple Weapon Wielder</name>
      <text>A simple weapon deals one extra die of its damage when the verbeeg hits with it (included in the attack).</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The verbeeg makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 14 (3d6 + 4) piercing damage, or 17 (3d8 + 4) piercing damage if used to make a ranged attack or used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Spear|+6|3d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Marauders
Verbeeg conduct themselves like brigands, robbing people they come across in the wild. If food is scarce, they kill those same people and eat them. They prefer to dwell in forlorn places, often sharing territory with hill giants and ogres. It's not unusual to find a gang of hill giants and ogres led by a verbeeg, since verbeeg are much smarter than their brutish cousins. Verbeeg also enjoy the company of mammalian beasts and allow bears, wolves, worgs, and other predators to lair with them. They catch and keep horses, mules, sheep, goats, and cattle for food and trade.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 311</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Walrus</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>9</ac>
    <hp>22 (3d10+6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>4</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>The walrus can hold its breath for 10 minutes.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Tusks</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (2d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Tusks|+4|2d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Walruses are bulky marine mammals that favor arctic climates and communicate by grunting and roaring. A typical adult specimen weighs at least 2,000 pounds. Humans hunt them for their meat, fat, skin, bones, and tusks.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 312</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Xardorok Sunblight</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (chain mail)</ac>
    <hp>93 (11d8+44)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Wis +4, Cha +7</save>
    <skill>Arcana +4, Deception +7, Intimidation +7</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Duergar Resilience</name>
      <text>Xardorok has advantage on saving throws against poison, spells, and illusions, as well as to resist being charmed or paralyzed.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, Xardorok has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Xardorok attacks twice with a weapon or casts eldritch blast twice.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spiked Gauntlet</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage, or 8 (2d4 + 3) piercing damage while Xardorok is enlarged.</text>
      <attack>Spiked Gauntlet|+6|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Eldritch Blast (Cantrip)</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +7 to hit, range 120 ft., one creature. 9 (1d10 + 4) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Eldritch Blast (Cantrip)|+7|1d10+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Enlarge (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>For 1 minute, Xardorok magically increases in size, along with anything he is wearing or carrying. While enlarged, Xardorok is Large, doubles his damage dice on Strength-based weapon attacks (included in his attacks), and makes Strength checks and Strength saving throws with advantage. If Xardorok lacks the room to become Large, he attains the maximum size possible in the space available.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Invisibility (Recharge 4-6)</name>
      <text>Xardorok magically turns invisible until he attacks, he casts a spell, he uses his Enlarge, or his concentration is broken (as if concentrating on a spell). Any equipment Xardorok wears or carries is invisible with him.</text>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Hellish Rebuke (2/Day)</name>
      <text>When Xardorok is damaged by a creature within 60 feet of him that he can see, the creature that damaged him is engulfed in hellish flames and must make a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw, taking 16 (3d10) fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      </reaction>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Xardorok's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 15, +7 to hit with spell attacks). He can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: eldritch blast (see "Actions" below), mage hand</text>
      <text>1/day each: hold person, suggestion</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>eldritch blast, mage hand, hold person, suggestion</spells>
    <description>Xardorok Sunblight leads the Sunblight clan of duergar which, until recently, dwelled in the subterranean depths beneath the Spine of the World. In the guise of Deep Duerra, the duergar god of conquest, the archdevil Asmodeus visited Xardorok and urged him to conquer Icewind Dale, beginning with Ten-Towns.
Dark Obsession. Xardorok is obsessed with chardalyn and can't stand the thought of anyone else possessing it. He must have all the chardalyn that Icewind Dale has to offer and is using his ample supply to forge a dragon, which he plans to unleash upon Ten-Towns. See the sidebar for more information about chardalyn.
Father of Nine. Xardorok has been married three times and has sired nine children. He killed his first wife, Thizrun, for plotting to assassinate him. His second wife, Yrraska, was killed in a tunnel collapse along with two of their daughters. His third wife, Marral, was killed during a raid against a mind flayer enclave, along with another daughter and three sons. Xardorok killed his eldest son, Ulthoon, son of Thizrun, for plotting to overthrow him. His surviving offspring are two sons given to him by Marral, named Durth and Nildar.
Clad in Chardalyn. Xardorok wears the following nonmagical items fashioned from chardalyn: a nine-spired crown (two intact spires representing his two surviving sons, and seven partially broken-off spires representing his seven dead children), a suit of chain mail, and a spiked gauntlet.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 287</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Yeti Tyke</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>11 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>9 (2d6+2)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., climb 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>8</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages>understands Yeti but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>cold</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>The yeti has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Snow Camouflage</name>
      <text>The yeti has advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks made to hide in snowy terrain.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) slashing damage plus 2 (1d4) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Yeti tykes are as volatile and mean as their parents, their fearsomeness diminished only by their size. Standing 3 feet tall on average, they like to bully creatures of their height or smaller. But they are easily intimidated by bigger and stronger creatures. A cowed yeti tyke can be controlled, at least for a while, but raising one to be anything other than a savage, flesh-eating predator is incredibly difficult (though not impossible).
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 313</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Young Griffon (Medium)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>32 (5d6+15)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 80 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Sight</name>
      <text>The griffon has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The griffon makes two attacks: one with its beak and one with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Beak</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Beak|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (2d4 + 1) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+3|2d4+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>A griffon is a ferocious avian carnivore with the muscular body of a lion and the head, forelegs, and wings of an eagle.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 163</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Young Griffon (Small)</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>13 (2d6+6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 80 ft.</speed>
    <str>8</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Sight</name>
      <text>The griffon has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The griffon makes two attacks: one with its beak and one with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Beak</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +1 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Beak|+1|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +1 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+1|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>A griffon is a ferocious avian carnivore with the muscular body of a lion and the head, forelegs, and wings of an eagle.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 163</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Young Griffon (Tiny)</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>5 (1d4+3)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>2</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Sight</name>
      <text>The griffon has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The griffon makes two attacks: one with its beak and one with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Beak</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +0 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 1 piercing damage.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +0 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 1 slashing damage.</text>
      </action>
    <description>A griffon is a ferocious avian carnivore with the muscular body of a lion and the head, forelegs, and wings of an eagle.
Source: Icewind Dale: Rime of the Frostmaiden p. 163</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  </compendium>
