<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Monk</name>
    <hd>8</hd>
    <proficiency>Strength, Dexterity, Acrobatics, Athletics, History, Insight, Religion, Stealth</proficiency>
    <numSkills>2</numSkills>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Starting Monk</name>
        <text>As a 1st-level Monk, you begin play with 8+your Constitution modifier hit points.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>You are proficient with the following items, in addition to any proficiencies provided by your race or background.</text>
        <text>• Armor: none</text>
        <text>• Weapons: simple, shortswords</text>
        <text>• Tools: any one type of artisan's tools or any one {@item musical instrument|PHB} of your choice</text>
        <text>• Skills: Choose 2 from Acrobatics, Athletics, History, Insight, Religion, Stealth</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>You begin play with the following equipment, in addition to any equipment provided by your background.</text>
        <text>• (a) a shortsword or (b) any simple weapon</text>
        <text>• (a) a dungeoneer's pack or (b) an explorer's pack</text>
        <text>• 10 dart</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Alternatively, you may start with 5d4 gp and choose your own equipment.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Multiclass Monk</name>
        <text>To multiclass as a Monk, you must meet the following prerequisites:</text>
        <text>• Wisdom 13</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>You gain the following proficiencies:</text>
        <text>• Armor: none</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>• Tools: none</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <armor>none</armor>
    <weapons>simple, shortswords</weapons>
    <tools>any one type of artisan's tools or any one {@item musical instrument|PHB} of your choice</tools>
    <wealth>5d4</wealth>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Unarmored Defense</name>
        <text>Beginning at 1st level, while you are wearing no armor and not wielding a shield, your AC equals 10 + your Dexterity modifier + your Wisdom modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Martial Arts</name>
        <text>Your practice of martial arts gives you mastery of combat styles that use unarmed strikes and monk weapons, which are shortswords and any simple melee weapons that don't have the two-handed or heavy property.</text>
        <text>You gain the following benefits while you are unarmed or wielding only monk weapons and you aren't wearing armor or wielding a shield.</text>
        <text>• You can use Dexterity instead of Strength for the attack and damage rolls of your unarmed strikes and monk weapons.</text>
        <text>• You can roll a d4 in place of the normal damage of your unarmed strike or monk weapon. This die changes as you gain monk levels, as shown in the Martial Arts column of the Monk table.</text>
        <text>• When you use the Attack action with an unarmed strike or a monk weapon on your turn, you can make one unarmed strike as a bonus action. For example, if you take the Attack action and attack with a quarterstaff, you can also make an unarmed strike as a bonus action, assuming you haven't already taken a bonus action this turn.</text>
        <text>Certain monasteries use specialized forms of the monk weapons. For example, you might use a club that is two lengths of wood connected by a short chain (called a nunchaku) or a sickle with a shorter, straighter blade (called a kama).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Monk Weapons</name>
        <text>1st-level monk feature (enhances Martial Arts)</text>
        <text>You can use this feature to define your monk weapons, rather than using the definition in Martial Arts.</text>
        <text>You practice your martial arts with specially chosen weapons, which become monk weapons for you. You can choose a number of weapons to be your monk weapons equal to 5 + your Wisdom modifier (minimum of five weapons). The chosen weapons must each meet the following criteria:</text>
        <text>• The weapon must be a simple or martial weapon.</text>
        <text>• You must be proficient with the weapon.</text>
        <text>• The weapon must lack these properties: heavy, special, or two-handed.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 6</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature>
          <name>Ki</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, your training allows you to harness the mystic energy of ki. Your access to this energy is represented by a number of ki points. Your monk level determines the number of points you have, as shown in the Ki Points column of the Monk table.</text>
        <text>You can spend these points to fuel various ki features. You start knowing three such features: Flurry of Blows, Patient Defense, and Step of the Wind. You learn more ki features as you gain levels in this class.</text>
        <text>When you spend a ki point, it is unavailable until you finish a short or long rest, at the end of which you draw all of your expended ki back into yourself. You must spend at least 30 minutes of the rest meditating to regain your ki points.</text>
        <text>Some of your ki features require your target to make a saving throw to resist the feature's effects. The saving throw DC is calculated as follows:</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Flurry of Blows:</text>
        <text>   Immediately after you take the Attack action on your turn, you can spend 1 ki point to make two unarmed strikes as a bonus action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Patient Defense:</text>
        <text>   You can spend 1 ki point to take the Dodge action as a bonus action on your turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Step of the Wind:</text>
        <text>   You can spend 1 ki point to take the Disengage or Dash action as a bonus action on your turn, and your jump distance is doubled for the turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature>
          <name>Ki-Fueled Strike</name>
        <text>2nd-level monk feature (enhances Ki)</text>
        <text>If you spend 1 ki or more as part of your action on your turn, you can then immediately make one unarmed strike as a bonus action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 6</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature>
          <name>Ki Features</name>
        <text>2nd-level monk feature (enhances Ki)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ki feature at 2nd level, you get access to the following features.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Distant Eye:</text>
        <text>   When you make a ranged weapon attack, you can spend 1 ki point to prevent attacking at long range from imposing disadvantage on your attack rolls until the end of the current turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Quickened Healing:</text>
        <text>   As an action, you can spend 2 ki points and roll a Martial Arts die. You regain a number of hit points equal to the number rolled.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 6</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature>
          <name>Unarmored Movement</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, your speed increases by 10 feet while you are not wearing armor or wielding a shield. This bonus increases when you reach certain monk levels, as shown in the Monk table.</text>
        <text>At 9th level, you gain the ability to move along vertical surfaces and across liquids on your turn without falling during the move.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature>
          <name>Deflect Missiles</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you can use your reaction to deflect or catch the missile when you are hit by a ranged weapon attack. When you do so, the damage you take from the attack is reduced by 1d10 + your Dexterity modifier + your monk level.</text>
        <text>If you reduce the damage to 0, you can catch the missile if it is small enough for you to hold in one hand and you have at least one hand free. If you catch a missile in this way, you can spend 1 ki point to make a ranged attack (range 20/60 feet) with the weapon or piece of ammunition you just caught, as part of the same reaction. You make this attack with proficiency, regardless of your weapon proficiencies, and the missile counts as a monk weapon for the attack.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature>
          <name>Monastic Tradition</name>
        <text>When you reach 3rd level, you commit yourself to a monastic tradition, chosen from the list of available traditions. Your tradition grants you features at 3rd level and again at 6th, 11th, and 17th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monastic Tradition: Way of Shadow</name>
        <text>Monks of the Way of Shadow follow a tradition that values stealth and subterfuge. These monks might be called ninjas or shadowdancers, and they serve as spies and assassins. Sometimes the members of a ninja monastery are family members, forming a clan sworn to secrecy about their arts and missions. Other monasteries are more like thieves' guilds, hiring out their services to nobles, rich merchants, or anyone else who can pay their fees. Regardless of their methods, the heads of these monasteries expect the unquestioning obedience of their students.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 80</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of Shadow: Shadow Arts</name>
        <text>You can use your ki to duplicate the effects of certain spells. As an action, you can spend 2 ki points to cast darkness, darkvision, pass without trace, or silence, without providing material components. Additionally, you gain the minor illusion cantrip if you don't already know it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 80</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monastic Tradition: Way of the Open Hand</name>
        <text>Monks of the Way of the Open Hand are the ultimate masters of martial arts combat, whether armed or unarmed. They learn techniques to push and trip their opponents, manipulate ki to heal damage to their bodies, and practice advanced meditation that can protect them from harm.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 79</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Open Hand: Open Hand Technique</name>
        <text>You can manipulate your enemy's ki when you harness your own. Whenever you hit a creature with one of the attacks granted by your Flurry of Blows, you can impose one of the following effects on that target.</text>
        <text>• It must succeed on a Dexterity saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
        <text>• It must make a Strength saving throw. If it fails, you can push it up to 15 feet away from you.</text>
        <text>• It can't take reactions until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 79</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monastic Tradition: Way of the Four Elements</name>
        <text>You follow a monastic tradition that teaches you to harness the elements. When you focus your ki, you can align yourself with the forces of creation and bend the four elements to your will, using them as an extension of your body. Some members of this tradition dedicate themselves to a single element, but others weave the elements together.</text>
        <text>Many monks of this tradition tattoo their bodies with representations of their ki powers, commonly imagined as coiling dragons, but also as phoenixes, fish, plants, mountains, and cresting waves.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 80</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Four Elements: Disciple of the Elements</name>
        <text>You learn magical disciplines that harness the power of the four elements. A discipline requires you to spend ki points each time you use it.</text>
        <text>You know the Elemental Attunement discipline and one other elemental discipline of your choice. You learn one additional elemental discipline of your choice at 6th, 11th, and 17th level.</text>
        <text>Whenever you learn a new elemental discipline, you can also replace one elemental discipline that you already know with a different discipline.</text>
        <name>Way of the Four Elements: Casting Elemental Spells</name>
        <text>   Some elemental disciplines allow you to cast spells. See chapter 10 of the Player's Handbook for the general rules of spellcasting. To cast one of these spells, you use its casting time and other rules, but you don't need to provide material components for it.</text>
        <text>   Once you reach 5th level in this class, you can spend additional ki points to increase the level of an elemental discipline spell that you cast, provided that the spell has an enhanced effect at a higher level, as burning hands does. The spell's level increases by 1 for each additional ki point you spend. For example, if you are a 5th-level monk and use Sweeping Cinder Strike to cast burning hands, you can spend 3 ki points to cast it as a 2nd-level spell (the discipline's base cost of 2 ki points plus 1).</text>
        <text>   The maximum number of ki points you can spend to cast a spell in this way (including its base ki point cost and any additional ki points you spend to increase its level) is determined by your monk level, as shown in the Spells and Ki Points table. At 5th level, you may spend up to 3 ki points; this increases to 4 ki points at 9th level, 5 at 13th level, and 6 at 17th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Spells and Ki Points</text>
        <text>Monk Levels | Maximum Ki Points for a Spell</text>
        <text>5th-8th | 3</text>
        <text>9th-12th | 4</text>
        <text>13th-16th | 5</text>
        <text>17th-20th | 6</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 80</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Four Elements: Elemental Disciplines</name>
        <text>The elemental disciplines are presented in alphabetical order. If a discipline requires a level, you must be the level in this class to learn the discipline.</text>
        <name>Way of the Four Elements: Breath of Winter (17th Level Required)</name>
        <name>Way of the Four Elements: Clench of the North Wind (6th Level Required)</name>
        <name>Way of the Four Elements: Eternal Mountain Defense (17th Level Required)</name>
        <name>Way of the Four Elements: Flames of the Phoenix (11th Level Required)</name>
        <name>Way of the Four Elements: Gong of the Summit (6th Level Required)</name>
        <name>Way of the Four Elements: Mist Stance (11th Level Required)</name>
        <name>Way of the Four Elements: Ride the Wind (11th Level Required)</name>
        <name>Way of the Four Elements: River of Hungry Flame (17th Level Required)</name>
        <name>Way of the Four Elements: Wave of Rolling Earth (17th Level Required)</name>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 80</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monastic Tradition: Way of the Long Death</name>
        <text>Monks of the Way of the Long Death are obsessed with the meaning and mechanics of dying. They capture creatures and prepare elaborate experiments to capture, record, and understand the moments of their demise. They use this knowledge to guide their understanding of martial arts, yielding a deadly fighting style.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 130</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Long Death: Touch of Death</name>
        <text>Starting when you choose this tradition at 3rd level, your study of death allows you to extract vitality from another creature as it nears its demise. When you reduce a creature within 5 feet of you to 0 hit points, you gain temporary hit points equal to your Wisdom modifier + your monk level (minimum of 1 temporary hit point).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 130</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monastic Tradition: Way of the Sun Soul</name>
        <text>Monks of the Way of the Sun Soul learn to channel their own life energy into searing bolts of light. They teach that meditation can unlock the ability to unleash the indomitable light shed by the soul of every living creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 131</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Radiant Sun Bolt</name>
        <text>Starting when you choose this tradition at 3rd level, you can hurl searing bolts of magical radiance.</text>
        <text>You gain a ranged spell attack that you can use with the Attack action. The attack has a range of 30 feet. You are proficient with it, and you add your Dexterity modifier to its attack and damage rolls. Its damage is radiant, and its damage die is a d4. This die changes as you gain monk levels—to a d6 at 5th level, a d8 at 11th level, and a d10 at 17th level.</text>
        <text>When you use the Attack action on your turn to use this special attack, you can spend 1 ki point to make two additional attacks with it as a bonus action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 131</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monastic Tradition: Way of the Sun Soul</name>
        <text>Monks of the Way of the Sun Soul learn to channel their life energy into searing bolts of light. They teach that meditation can unlock the ability to unleash the indomitable light shed by the soul of every living creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 131</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Radiant Sun Bolt</name>
        <text>Starting when you choose this tradition at 3rd level, you can hurl searing bolts of magical radiance.</text>
        <text>You gain a new attack option that you can use with the Attack action. This special attack is a ranged spell attack with a range of 30 feet. You are proficient with it, and you add your Dexterity modifier to its attack and damage rolls. Its damage is radiant, and its damage die is a d4. This die changes as you gain monk levels, as shown in the Martial Arts column of the Monk table.</text>
        <text>When you take the Attack action on your turn and use this special attack as part of it, you can spend 1 ki point to make the special attack twice as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>When you gain the Extra Attack feature, this special attack can be used for any of the attacks you make as part of the Attack action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 131</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei (UA): Way of the Kensei</name>
        <text>Monks of the Way of Kensei train relentlessly with their weapons, to the point that the weapon becomes like an extension of the body. A kensei sees a weapon in much the same way a painter regards a brush or a writer sees parchment, ink, and quill. A sword or bow is a tool used to express the beauty and elegance of the martial arts. That such mastery makes a kensei a peerless warrior and is but a side effect of intense devotion, practice, and study.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Monk p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei (UA): Path of the Kensei</name>
        <text>When you choose this tradition at 3rd level, you learn to extend your knowledge of the martial arts beyond the standard array of monk weapons.</text>
        <text>You gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• You gain proficiency with three martial weapons of your choice. A martial weapon is considered a kensei weapon for you if you're proficient with it.</text>
        <text>• Whenever you wield a kensei weapon, you choose whether to use Dexterity or Strength for the attack and damage rolls of the weapon, and you choose whether to use your Martial Arts damage die in place of the weapon's damage die.</text>
        <text>• When you take the Attack action on your turn and hit a target with a kensei weapon, you can use a bonus action to pummel the target, dealing an additional 1d4 bludgeoning damage to that target and to any other target you hit with the weapon as part of the Attack.</text>
        <text>• If you make an unarmed strike as part of the Attack action on your turn and are holding a kensei weapon, you can use that weapon to defend yourself. You gain a +2 bonus to AC until the start of your next turn while you are not incapacitated and the weapon is in your hand.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Monk p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei v2 (UA): Way of the Kensei v2</name>
        <text>Monks of the Way of Kensei train relentlessly with their weapons, to the point that the weapon becomes like an extension of the body. A kensei sees a weapon in much the same way a painter regards a brush or a writer sees parchment, ink, and quill. A sword or bow is a tool used to express the beauty and elegance of the martial arts. That such mastery makes a kensei a peerless warrior is but a side effect of intense devotion, practice, and study.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei v2 (UA): Path of the Kensei</name>
        <text>When you choose this tradition at 3rd level, you learn to extend your knowledge of the martial arts beyond the standard array of monk weapons.</text>
        <text>You gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• Choose two types of weapons to be your kensei weapons: one melee weapon and one ranged weapon. Each of these weapons can be any simple or martial weapon that lacks the heavy and special properties. The longbow is also a valid choice. You gain proficiency with these weapons if you don't already have it. Weapons of the chosen types are monk weapons for you. Many of this tradition's features work only with your kensei weapons. When you reach 6th, 11th, and 17th level in this class, you can choose another type of weapon—melee or ranged—to be a kensei weapon for you, following the criteria above.</text>
        <text>• If you make an unarmed strike as part of the Attack action on your turn and are holding a kensei weapon, you can use it to defend yourself if it is a melee weapon. You gain a +2 bonus to AC until the start of your next turn, while the weapon is in your hand and you aren't incapacitated.</text>
        <text>• You can use a bonus action on your turn to make your ranged attacks with a kensei weapon more deadly. When you do so, any target you hit with a ranged attack using a kensei weapon takes an extra 1d4 damage of the weapon's type. You retain this benefit until the end of the current turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of Tranquility (UA): Way of Tranquility</name>
        <text>Monks of the Way of Tranquility see violence as a last resort. They use diplomacy, mercy, and understanding to resolve conflicts. If pushed, though, they are capable warriors who can bring an end to the unjust or cruel folk who refuse to listen to reason. When adventuring, these monks make excellent diplomats. They are also skilled in the healing arts, and can preserve their allies in the face of daunting foes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Monk p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of Tranquility (UA): Healing Hands</name>
        <text>Your mystical touch can heal wounds. Starting at 3rd level, you have a pool of magical healing power that replenishes when you take a long rest. With that pool, you can restore a total number of hit points equal to your monk level x 10.</text>
        <text>As an action, you can touch a creature and draw power from the pool to restore a number of hit points to that creature, up to the maximum amount remaining in the pool.</text>
        <text>Instead of healing the creature, you can expend 5 hit points from your pool of healing to cure the target of one disease or neutralize one poison affecting it. You can cure multiple diseases and neutralize multiple poisons with a single use of Healing Hands, expending hit points separately for each one.</text>
        <text>When you use your Flurry of Blows, you can replace one of the unarmed strikes with a use of this feature.</text>
        <text>This feature has no effect on undead and constructs.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Monk p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of Tranquility (UA): Path of Tranquility</name>
        <text>When you choose this tradition at 3rd level, you can become an island of calm in even the most chaotic of situations. With this feature, you can cast the sanctuary spell on yourself, no material component required, and it lasts up to 8 hours. Its saving throw DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Wisdom modifier. A creature that succeeds on the save is immune to this effect for 1 hour.</text>
        <text>Once you cast the spell in this way, you can't do so again for 1 minute.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Monk p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Drunken Master (UA): Way of the Drunken Master</name>
        <text>The Way of the Drunken Master teaches its students to move with the jerky, unpredictable movements of a drunkard. A drunken master sways, tottering on unsteady feet, to present what seems like an incompetent combatant but proves frustrating to engage. The drunken master's erratic stumbles conceal a carefully executed dance of blocks, parries, advances, attacks, and retreats. Cunning warriors can see through the drunken master's apparent incompetence to recognize the masterful technique employed.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Drunken Master (UA): Drunken Technique</name>
        <text>When you choose this tradition at 3rd level, you gain proficiency in the Performance skill if you don't already have it; your martial arts technique mixes martial training with the precision of a dancer and the antics of a jester.</text>
        <text>You also learn how to twist and turn quickly as part of your Flurry of Blows. Whenever you use Flurry of Blows, you gain the benefit of the Disengage action, and your walking speed increases by 10 feet until the end of the current turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monastic Tradition: Way of the Drunken Master</name>
        <text>The Way of the Drunken Master teaches its students to move with the jerky, unpredictable movements of a drunkard. A drunken master sways, tottering on unsteady feet, to present what seems like an incompetent combatant who proves frustrating to engage. The drunken master's erratic stumbles conceal a carefully executed dance of blocks, parries, advances, attacks, and retreats.</text>
        <text>A drunken master often enjoys playing the fool to bring gladness to the despondent or to demonstrate humility to the arrogant, but when battle is joined, the drunken master can be a maddening, masterful foe.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 33</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Drunken Master: Bonus Proficiencies</name>
        <text>When you choose this tradition at 3rd level, you gain proficiency in the Performance skill if you don't already have it. Your martial arts technique mixes combat training with the precision of a dancer and the antics of a jester. You also gain proficiency with brewer's supplies if you don't already have it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 33</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Drunken Master: Drunken Technique</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn how to twist and turn quickly as part of your Flurry of Blows. Whenever you use Flurry of Blows, you gain the benefit of the Disengage action, and your walking speed increases by 10 feet until the end of the current turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 33</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monastic Tradition: Way of the Kensei</name>
        <text>Monks of the Way of the Kensei train relentlessly with their weapons, to the point where the weapon becomes an extension of the body. Founded on a mastery of sword fighting, the tradition has expanded to include many different weapons.</text>
        <text>A kensei sees a weapon in much the same way a calligrapher or painter regards a pen or brush. Whatever the weapon, the kensei views it as a tool used to express the beauty and precision of the martial arts. That such mastery makes a kensei a peerless warrior is but a side effect of intense devotion, practice, and study.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 34</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei: Path of the Kensei</name>
        <text>When you choose this tradition at 3rd level, your special martial arts training leads you to master the use of certain weapons. This path also includes instruction in the deft strokes of calligraphy or painting. You gain the following benefits.</text>
        <name>Way of the Kensei: Kensei Weapons</name>
        <text>   Choose two types of weapons to be your kensei weapons: one melee weapon and one ranged weapon. Each of these weapons can be any simple or martial weapon that lacks the heavy and special properties. The longbow is also a valid choice. You gain proficiency with these weapons if you don't already have it. Weapons of the chosen types are monk weapons for you. Many of this tradition's features work only with your kensei weapons. When you reach 6th, 11th, and 17th level in this class, you can choose another type of weapon—either melee or ranged—to be a kensei weapon for you, following the criteria above.</text>
        <name>Way of the Kensei: Agile Parry</name>
        <text>   If you make an unarmed strike as part of the Attack action on your turn and are holding a kensei weapon, you can use it to defend yourself if it is a melee weapon. You gain a +2 bonus to AC until the start of your next turn, while the weapon is in your hand and you aren't incapacitated.</text>
        <name>Way of the Kensei: Kensei's Shot</name>
        <text>   You can use a bonus action on your turn to make your ranged attacks with a kensei weapon more deadly. When you do so, any target you hit with a ranged attack using a kensei weapon takes an extra 1d4 damage of the weapon's type. You retain this benefit until the end of the current turn.</text>
        <name>Way of the Kensei: Way of the Brush</name>
        <text>   You gain proficiency with your choice of calligrapher's supplies or painter's supplies.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 34</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monastic Tradition: Way of the Sun Soul</name>
        <text>Monks of the Way of the Sun Soul learn to channel their own life energy into searing bolts of light. They teach that meditation can unlock the ability to unleash the indomitable light shed by the soul of every living creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 35</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Radiant Sun Bolt</name>
        <text>Starting when you choose this tradition at 3rd level, you can hurl searing bolts of magical radiance.</text>
        <text>You gain a ranged spell attack that you can use with the Attack action. The attack has a range of 30 feet. You are proficient with it, and you add your Dexterity modifier to its attack and damage rolls. Its damage is radiant, and its damage die is a d4. This die changes as you gain monk levels—to a d6 at 5th level, a d8 at 11th level, and a d10 at 17th level.</text>
        <text>When you use the Attack action on your turn to use this special attack, you can spend 1 ki point to make two additional attacks with it as a bonus action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 35</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monastic Tradition: Way of the Sun Soul</name>
        <text>Monks of the Way of the Sun Soul learn to channel their life energy into searing bolts of light. They teach that meditation can unlock the ability to unleash the indomitable light shed by the soul of every living creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 35</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Radiant Sun Bolt</name>
        <text>Starting when you choose this tradition at 3rd level, you can hurl searing bolts of magical radiance.</text>
        <text>You gain a new attack option that you can use with the Attack action. This special attack is a ranged spell attack with a range of 30 feet. You are proficient with it, and you add your Dexterity modifier to its attack and damage rolls. Its damage is radiant, and its damage die is a d4. This die changes as you gain monk levels, as shown in the Martial Arts column of the Monk table.</text>
        <text>When you take the Attack action on your turn and use this special attack as part of it, you can spend 1 ki point to make the special attack twice as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>When you gain the Extra Attack feature, this special attack can be used for any of the attacks you make as part of the Attack action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 35</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monastic Tradition: Way of the Soul Knife (Livestream)</name>
        <text>Transcribed on 2018-10-13. [Square bracketed text] denotes transcriber's annotations.</text>
        <text>Monks of the Way of the Soul Knife are deadly assassins and bounty hunters. They use their psionic talents to manifest psionic blades that tear through their enemies' bodies and psychic auras. Their talents extend beyond combat, as their ability to perceive auras allows them to track down foes and see through their deceptions.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Soul Knife (Livestream): Psychic Slash</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, when you channel ki into your attacks you augment your soul knives to inflict devastating psionic attacks.</text>
        <text>Whenever you hit a creature with one of the attacks granted by your Flurry of Blows and that attack inflicts psychic damage, you can impose one of the following effects on the target:</text>
        <name>Way of the Soul Knife (Livestream): Life Drain</name>
        <text>   You gain temporary hit points equal to half the damage your attack deals.</text>
        <name>Way of the Soul Knife (Livestream): Invoke Terror</name>
        <text>   The target must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or become frightened of you until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <name>Way of the Soul Knife (Livestream): Invoke Wrath</name>
        <text>   The target suffers disadvantage on all attack rolls against targets other than you until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <name>Way of the Soul Knife (Livestream): Astral Slide</name>
        <text>   You teleport the target up to 10 feet to a destination you can see.</text>
        <name>Way of the Soul Knife (Livestream): Synaptic Overload</name>
        <text>   The target gains vulnerability to psychic damage until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Soul Knife (Livestream): Soul Knife</name>
        <text>Starting when you choose this tradition at 3rd level, you can use your psionic energy to manifest blades that disrupt your foes' minds.</text>
        <text>Your unarmed strikes deal your choice of psychic, piercing, slashing, or bludgeoning damage each time you hit.</text>
        <text>In addition, you can use a bonus action to increase the reach of your unarmed strikes by 30 feet until the end of your turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Astral Self (UA): Way of the Astral Self</name>
        <text>Monks of the Way of the Astral Self have an internal struggle with their ki. They see their mystical energy as a representation of their true form, an astral self. This form has the capacity to be a force of good or destruction, with some monasteries training students to either temper their nature or embrace their impulses.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Barbarian And Monk p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Astral Self (UA): Arms of the Astral Self</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, your mastery of your ki allows you to summon a portion of your astral self. On your turn, you can spend 2 ki points as a bonus action to summon the arms of your astral self for 10 minutes. These spectral arms hover near your shoulders. You determine the arms' appearance based on the qualities of your character.</text>
        <text>While your astral arms are summoned, you gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• You can use your Wisdom modifier in place of your Strength modifier when making Strength checks and Strength saving throws.</text>
        <text>• The arms are monk weapons and have a reach of 10 feet. The arms deal radiant or necrotic damage (your choice). When you attack with the arms, you can use your Wisdom modifier instead of your Strength or Dexterity modifier for the attack and damage rolls.</text>
        <text>• Immediately after you use the Attack action with your astral arms on your turn, you can make one extra attack with your astral arms as a bonus action. The number of extra attacks increases when you reach certain levels in this class, increasing to two at 11th level and three at 17th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Barbarian And Monk p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Astral Self (UA): Forms of Your Astral Self</name>
        <text>The astral self is a translucent embodiment of the monk's psyche and soul. As a result, the form of an astral self reflects the mind of the monk who manifests it. Your astral self could be a humanoid knight with a helmeted face and large, muscular arms, or it could be a golden metallic form with thin arms like a modron.</text>
        <text>When choosing this path, consider the quirks that define your monk. Are they obsessed with something? Are you driven by justice or a selfish desire? Any of these motivations could manifest in the form of your astral self.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Barbarian And Monk p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of Mercy (UA): Way of Mercy</name>
        <text>Monks of the Way of Mercy learn to manipulate the life force of others to bring aid to those in need. They are wandering physicians to the poor and hurt. However, to those beyond their help—whether ailing or evil—they bring a swift end as an act of mercy.</text>
        <text>Those who follow the Way of Mercy might be humble members of a religious order, administering to those in greatest need, making grim choices rooted in reality rather than idealism. Some might be gentle-voiced healers, beloved by their communities, while others might be masked bringers of macabre mercies. The walkers of this way usually don simple robes with deep cowls, and they often conceal their faces with masks, presenting themselves as the faceless bringers of life and death. If you wear a mask, choose its appearance, or determine it randomly by rolling on the Merciful Mask table.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Merciful Mask</text>
        <text>d6 | Mask Appearance</text>
        <text>1 | Raven</text>
        <text>2 | Blank and white</text>
        <text>3 | Crying visage</text>
        <text>4 | Laughing visage</text>
        <text>5 | Skull</text>
        <text>6 | Butterfly</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt1 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of Mercy (UA): Hands of Harm</name>
        <text>3rd-level Way of Mercy feature</text>
        <text>You use your ki to inflict wounds. When you hit a creature with an unarmed strike, you can spend 1 ki point to deal extra necrotic damage equal to one roll of your Martial Arts die. If the creature is incapacitated or poisoned, the creature instead takes necrotic damage equal to three rolls of your Martial Arts die instead. You can use this feature only once on each of your turns.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt1 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of Mercy (UA): Hands of Healing</name>
        <text>3rd-level Way of Mercy feature</text>
        <text>Your mystical touch can mend wounds. As an action, you can spend 1 ki point to touch a creature and restore a number of hit points equal to a roll of your Martial Arts die + your Wisdom modifier.</text>
        <text>When you use your Flurry of Blows, you can replace one of the unarmed strikes with a use of this feature without spending its ki cost.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt1 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of Mercy (UA): Implements of Mercy</name>
        <text>3rd-level Way of Mercy feature</text>
        <text>You gain proficiency in the Insight or Medicine skill (your choice), and you gain proficiency with the herbalism kit and the poisoner's kit.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt1 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Ascendant Dragon (UA): Way of the Ascendant Dragon</name>
        <text>Monks who follow the Way of the Ascendant Dragon revere the power and grandeur of dragons. They alter their own ki to resonate with draconic might, channeling it to augment their prowess in battle, soar through the air, and to bolster their allies.</text>
        <text>As a follower of this Monastic Tradition, you decide how you unlocked the power of dragons through your ki. The Ascendant Dragon Origin table offers some possibilities.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Ascendant Dragon Origin</text>
        <text>d6 | Origin</text>
        <text>1 | You honed your abilities by observing a dragon and aligning your ki with their world-altering power.</text>
        <text>2 | A dragon personally took an active role in shaping your inner energy.</text>
        <text>3 | You studied at a monastery that traces its teachings back centuries or more to a single dragon's instruction.</text>
        <text>4 | You spent long stretches meditating in the region of influence of an ancient dragon's lair, absorbing its ambient magic.</text>
        <text>5 | You found a scroll written in Draconic that contained inspiring new techniques.</text>
        <text>6 | After a dream that featured a five-handed dragonborn you awoke with altered ki, reflecting the breaths of dragons.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Ascendant Dragon (UA): Breath of the Dragon</name>
        <text>3rd-level Way of the Ascendant Dragon feature</text>
        <text>You can channel your ki into destructive waves of energy like the dragons you emulate. When you take the Attack action on your turn, you can replace one of the attacks with an exhalation of draconic energy in either a 20-foot cone or a 30foot line that is 5 feet wide (your choice). Choose a damage type: acid, cold, fire, lightning, or poison. Each creature in the area must make a Dexterity saving throw against your ki save DC, taking damage of the chosen type equal to two rolls of your Martial Arts die on a failure, or half as much damage on a success.</text>
        <text>At 11th level, the damage of your breath increases to three rolls of your Martial Arts die.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest. While you have no uses available, you can spend 1 ki point to use this feature again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Ascendant Dragon (UA): Draconic Disciple</name>
        <text>3rd-level Way of the Ascendant Dragon feature</text>
        <text>You can channel your draconic ki to imbue your unarmed strikes with the essence of a dragon's breath and to use your connection with draconic creatures to magnify your presence. You gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• When you damage a target with an unarmed strike, you can change the damage type to acid, cold, fire, lightning, or poison.</text>
        <text>• If you can't already, you learn to speak, read, and write Draconic.</text>
        <text>• If you fail a Charisma (Intimidation) or Charisma (Persuasion) check, you can use your reaction to reroll the check, as you tap into the mighty presence of dragons. Once this feature turns a failure into a success, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 4th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>4th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4">
        <feature>
          <name>Slow Fall</name>
        <text>Beginning at 4th level, you can use your reaction when you fall to reduce any falling damage you take by an amount equal to five times your monk level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
        <feature>
          <name>Extra Attack</name>
        <text>Beginning at 5th level, you can attack twice, instead of once, whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
        <feature>
          <name>Stunning Strike</name>
        <text>Starting at 5th level, you can interfere with the flow of ki in an opponent's body. When you hit another creature with a melee weapon attack, you can spend 1 ki point to attempt a stunning strike. The target must succeed on a Constitution saving throw or be stunned until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature>
          <name>Ki-Empowered Strikes</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, your unarmed strikes count as magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature>
          <name>Monastic Tradition feature</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain one feature granted by your Monastic Tradition.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of Shadow: Shadow Step</name>
        <text>You gain the ability to step from one shadow into another. When you are in dim light or darkness, as a bonus action you can teleport up to 60 feet to an unoccupied space you can see that is also in dim light or darkness. You then have advantage on the first melee attack you make before the end of the turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 80</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Open Hand: Wholeness of Body</name>
        <text>You gain the ability to heal yourself. As an action, you can regain hit points equal to three times your monk level. You must finish a long rest before you can use this feature again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 79</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Four Elements: Extra Elemental Discipline</name>
        <text>You learn one additional elemental discipline of your choice. You should know 2 elemental disciplines, as well as Elemental Attunement.</text>
        <text>Whenever you learn a new elemental discipline, you can also replace one elemental discipline that you already know with a different discipline.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 80</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Long Death: Hour of Reaping</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to unsettle or terrify those around you as an action, for your soul has been touched by the shadow of death. When you take this action, each creature within 30 feet of you that can see you must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or be frightened of you until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 130</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Searing Arc Strike</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to channel your ki into searing waves of energy. Immediately after you take the Attack action on your turn, you can spend 2 ki points to cast the 1st-level spell burning hands as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>You can spend additional ki points to cast burning hands as a higher level spell. Each additional ki point you spend increases the spell's level by 1. The maximum number of ki points (2 plus any additional points) that you can spend on the spell equals half your monk level (round down).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 131</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Searing Arc Strike</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to channel your ki into searing waves of energy. Immediately after you take the Attack action on your turn, you can spend 2 ki points to cast the burning hands spell as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>You can spend additional ki points to cast burning hands as a higher-level spell. Each additional ki point you spend increases the spell's level by 1. The maximum number of ki points (2 plus any additional points) that you can spend on the spell equals half your monk level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 131</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei (UA): One with the Blade</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you extend your ki into the weapons you hold, granting you the following benefits:</text>
        <name>Way of the Kensei (UA): Magic Weapons</name>
        <text>   Your attacks with your kensei weapons count as magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage.</text>
        <name>Way of the Kensei (UA): Precise Strike</name>
        <text>   You can focus your attention on a single target in battle to understand and overcome its defenses. As a bonus action, pick one creature you can see within 30 feet of you. The next weapon attack you make against that creature during the current turn adds double your proficiency bonus to the attack roll, rather than your normal proficiency bonus. Once you use this ability, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Monk p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei v2 (UA): One with the Blade</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you extend your ki into the weapons you hold, granting you the following benefits.</text>
        <name>Way of the Kensei v2 (UA): Magic Kensei Weapons</name>
        <text>   Your attacks with your kensei weapons count as magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage.</text>
        <name>Way of the Kensei v2 (UA): Precise Strike</name>
        <text>   When you hit a target with a kensei weapon, you can spend 1 ki point to cause the weapon to deal extra damage to the target equal to your Martial Arts die. You can use this feature only once on each of your turns.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of Tranquility (UA): Emissary of Peace</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to diffuse violent situations. Whenever you make a Charisma check to calm violent emotions or to counsel peace, you have advantage on the roll. You must make this entreaty in good faith; it doesn't apply if proficiency in the Deception or Intimidation skill applies to your check.</text>
        <text>You also gain proficiency in the Performance or Persuasion skill (choose one).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Monk p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Drunken Master (UA): Tipsy Sway</name>
        <text>At 6th level, your swaying in combat becomes maddeningly unpredictable. As a reaction when an enemy misses you with a melee attack roll, you can cause that attack to hit one creature of your choice, other than the attacker, that you can see within 5 feet of you. Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Drunken Master: Tipsy Sway</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you can move in sudden, swaying ways. You gain the following benefits.</text>
        <name>Way of the Drunken Master: Leap to Your Feet</name>
        <text>   When you're prone, you can stand up by spending 5 feet of movement, rather than half your speed.</text>
        <name>Way of the Drunken Master: Redirect Attack</name>
        <text>   When a creature misses you with a melee attack roll, you can spend 1 ki point as a reaction to cause that attack to hit one creature of your choice, other than the attacker, that you can see within 5 feet of you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 33</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei: One with the Blade</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you extend your ki into your kensei weapons, granting you the following benefits.</text>
        <name>Way of the Kensei: Magic Kensei Weapons</name>
        <text>   Your attacks with your kensei weapons count as magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage.</text>
        <name>Way of the Kensei: Deft Strike</name>
        <text>   When you hit a target with a kensei weapon, you can spend 1 ki point to cause the weapon to deal extra damage to the target equal to your Martial Arts die. You can use this feature only once on each of your turns.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 34</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Searing Arc Strike</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to channel your ki into searing waves of energy. Immediately after you take the Attack action on your turn, you can spend 2 ki points to cast the 1st-level spell burning hands as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>You can spend additional ki points to cast burning hands as a higher level spell. Each additional ki point you spend increases the spell's level by 1. The maximum number of ki points (2 plus any additional points) that you can spend on the spell equals half your monk level (round down).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 35</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Searing Arc Strike</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to channel your ki into searing waves of energy. Immediately after you take the Attack action on your turn, you can spend 2 ki points to cast the burning hands spell as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>You can spend additional ki points to cast burning hands as a higher-level spell. Each additional ki point you spend increases the spell's level by 1. The maximum number of ki points (2 plus any additional points) that you can spend on the spell equals half your monk level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 35</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Soul Knife (Livestream): Aura Sight</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to perceive the auras of other creatures.</text>
        <text>As an action, select a creature that you can see. That creature makes a Wisdom saving throw, though it has no knowledge that you forced it to attempt this saving throw. On a failed save, you learn if the creature shares any aspects of its alignment with you, its current hit points, and its current attitude and intentions toward you or one other creature, object, or location of your choice. In addition, for the next 24 hours or until you use this ability again, you can use an action to determine the creature's distance and direction from you.</text>
        <text>If a creature succeeds on its saving throw against this ability, you cannot use this ability against that creature again until you complete a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Astral Self (UA): Visage of the Astral Self</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you can summon the visage of your astral self. On your turn, you can spend 1 ki point as a bonus action, or as part of summoning your astral arms, to summon this visage for 10 minutes. The spectral visage covers your face like a helmet or mask. You determine its appearance based on the qualities of your character.</text>
        <text>While your visage is summoned, you gain the following benefits.</text>
        <name>Way of the Astral Self (UA): Wisdom of the Spirit</name>
        <text>   You have advantage on Wisdom (Insight) and Charisma (Intimidation) checks.</text>
        <name>Way of the Astral Self (UA): Astral Sight</name>
        <text>   You can see normally in darkness, both magical and nonmagical, to a distance of 120 feet.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Barbarian And Monk p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of Mercy (UA): Noxious Aura</name>
        <text>6th-level Way of Mercy feature</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, you spend 1 ki point to turn your ki into an aura of toxic miasma. The aura extends 5 feet from you in every direction, but not through total cover. It lasts for 1 minute, until you're incapacitated, or you dismiss it (no action required).</text>
        <text>While your aura is active, ranged attacks have disadvantage against you. Any other creature that starts its turn in the aura must succeed on a Constitution saving throw or become poisoned until the end of your next turn and take poison damage equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of 0 damage).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt1 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Ascendant Dragon (UA): Wings Unfurled</name>
        <text>6th-level Way of the Ascendant Dragon feature</text>
        <text>When you use your Step of the Wind, you can unfurl spectral draconic wings from your back that vanish at the end of your turn. While the wings exist, you have a flying speed equal to your walking speed.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest. While you have no uses available, you can spend 1 additional ki point when you activate Step of the Wind to use this feature again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature>
          <name>Evasion</name>
        <text>At 7th level, your instinctive agility lets you dodge out of the way of certain area effects, such as a blue dragon's lightning breath or a fireball spell. When you are subjected to an effect that allows you to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, you instead take no damage if you succeed on the saving throw, and only half damage if you fail.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature>
          <name>Stillness of Mind</name>
        <text>Starting at 7th level, you can use your action to end one effect on yourself that is causing you to be charmed or frightened.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 8th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>8th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
        <feature>
          <name>Unarmored Movement improvement</name>
        <text>At 9th level, you gain the ability to move along vertical surfaces and across liquids on your turn without falling during the move.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature>
          <name>Purity of Body</name>
        <text>At 10th level, your mastery of the ki flowing through you makes you immune to disease and poison.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature>
          <name>Monastic Tradition feature</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain one feature granted by your Monastic Tradition.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of Shadow: Cloak of Shadows</name>
        <text>By 11th level, you have learned to become one with the shadows. When you are in an area of dim light or darkness, you can use your action to become invisible. You remain invisible until you make an attack, cast a spell, or are in an area of bright light.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 80</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Open Hand: Tranquility</name>
        <text>Beginning at 11th level, you can enter a special meditation that surrounds you with an aura of peace. At the end of a long rest, you gain the effect of a sanctuary spell that lasts until the start of your next long rest (the spell can end early as normal). The saving throw DC for the spell equals 8 + your Wisdom modifier + your proficiency bonus.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 79</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Four Elements: Extra Elemental Discipline</name>
        <text>You learn one additional elemental discipline of your choice. You should know 3 elemental disciplines, as well as Elemental Attunement.</text>
        <text>Whenever you learn a new elemental discipline, you can also replace one elemental discipline that you already know with a different discipline.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 80</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Long Death: Mastery of Death</name>
        <text>Beginning at 11th level, you use your familiarity with death to escape its grasp. When you are reduced to 0 hit points, you can expend 1 ki point (no action required) to have 1 hit point instead.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 130</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Searing Sunburst</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to create an orb of light that erupts into a devastating explosion. As an action, you magically create an orb and hurl it at a point you choose within 150 feet, where it erupts into a sphere of radiant light for a brief but deadly instant.</text>
        <text>Each creature in that 20-foot radius sphere must succeed on a Constitution saving throw or take 2d6 radiant damage. A creature doesn't need to make the save if the creature is behind total cover that is opaque.</text>
        <text>You can increase the sphere's damage by spending ki points. Each point you spend, up to a maximum of 3, increases the damage by 2d6.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 131</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Searing Sunburst</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to create an orb of light that erupts into a devastating explosion. As an action, you magically create an orb and hurl it at a point you choose within 150 feet, where it erupts into a sphere of radiant light for a brief but deadly instant.</text>
        <text>Each creature in that 20-foot-radius sphere must succeed on a Constitution saving throw or take 2d6 radiant damage. A creature doesn't need to make the save if the creature is behind total cover that is opaque.</text>
        <text>You can increase the sphere's damage by spending ki points. Each point you spend, to a maximum of 3, increases the damage by 2d6.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 131</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei (UA): Sharpen the Blade</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to augment your weapons with the strength of your ki. As a bonus action, you can expend up to 3 ki points to grant a weapon you touch a bonus to attack and damage rolls while you wield it. The bonus equals the number of ki points you spent. This bonus lasts for 1 minute.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Monk p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei v2 (UA): Sharpen the Blade</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to augment your weapons with the strength of your ki. As a bonus action, you can expend up to 3 ki points to grant one kensei weapon you touch a bonus to attack and damage rolls while you wield it. The bonus equals the number of ki points you spent. This bonus lasts for 1 minute or until you use this feature again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of Tranquility (UA): Douse the Flames of War</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to temporarily extinguish a creature's violent impulses. As an action, you can touch a creature, and it must make a Wisdom saving throw with a DC equal to 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Wisdom modifier. The target automatically succeeds if it's missing any of its hit points. If the target fails the save, it can't attack for 1 minute. During that time, it also can't cast spells that deal damage or that force someone to make a saving throw.</text>
        <text>This effect ends if the target is attacked, takes damage, or is forced to make a saving throw or if the target witnesses any of those things happening to its allies.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Monk p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Drunken Master (UA): Drunkard's Luck</name>
        <text>Starting at 11th level, you always seem to get a lucky bounce at just the right moment to save you from doom. When you make a saving throw, you can spend 1 ki point to give yourself advantage on that roll. You must decide to use this feature before rolling.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Drunken Master: Drunkard's Luck</name>
        <text>Starting at 11th level, you always seem to get a lucky bounce at the right moment. When you make an ability check, an attack roll, or a saving throw and have disadvantage on the roll, you can spend 2 ki points to cancel the disadvantage for that roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 33</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei: Sharpen the Blade</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to augment your weapons further with your ki. As a bonus action, you can expend up to 3 ki points to grant one kensei weapon you touch a bonus to attack and damage rolls when you attack with it. The bonus equals the number of ki points you spent. This bonus lasts for 1 minute or until you use this feature again. This feature has no effect on a magic weapon that already has a bonus to attack and damage rolls.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 34</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Searing Sunburst</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to create an orb of light that erupts into a devastating explosion. As an action, you magically create an orb and hurl it at a point you choose within 150 feet, where it erupts into a sphere of radiant light for a brief but deadly instant.</text>
        <text>Each creature in that 20-foot radius sphere must succeed on a Constitution saving throw or take 2d6 radiant damage. A creature doesn't need to make the save if the creature is behind total cover that is opaque.</text>
        <text>You can increase the sphere's damage by spending ki points. Each point you spend, up to a maximum of 3, increases the damage by 2d6.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 35</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Searing Sunburst</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to create an orb of light that erupts into a devastating explosion. As an action, you magically create an orb and hurl it at a point you choose within 150 feet, where it erupts into a sphere of radiant light for a brief but deadly instant.</text>
        <text>Each creature in that 20-foot-radius sphere must succeed on a Constitution saving throw or take 2d6 radiant damage. A creature doesn't need to make the save if the creature is behind total cover that is opaque.</text>
        <text>You can increase the sphere's damage by spending ki points. Each point you spend, to a maximum of 3, increases the damage by 2d6.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 35</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Soul Knife (Livestream): Spectral Blades</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you can cause your blades to phase through physical objects and defenses.</text>
        <text>Once during your turn, you can choose to forego one unarmed strike in place of forcing a creature within the reach of that attack to make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed saving throw, it takes your unarmed strike's damage, or half that damage if it succeeds.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Astral Self (UA): Awakening of the Astral Self</name>
        <text>Starting at 11th level, you tap into the greater power of your astral self. While you have both your astral arms and visage summoned, you gain the following benefits.</text>
        <name>Way of the Astral Self (UA): Deflect Energy</name>
        <text>   When you take acid, cold, fire, lightning, or force damage, you can use your reaction to deflect it. When you do so, the damage you take is reduced by 1d10 + your Wisdom modifier + your monk level.</text>
        <name>Way of the Astral Self (UA): Empowered Arms</name>
        <text>   Once on each of your turns when you hit a target with your astral arms, you can deal extra damage to the target equal to your Martial Arts die.</text>
        <name>Way of the Astral Self (UA): Word of the Spirit</name>
        <text>   When you speak through your visage, you can direct your words to a creature of your choice that you can see within 30 feet of you, making it so only that creature can hear you. Alternatively, you can amplify your voice so that all creatures within 600 feet can hear you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Barbarian And Monk p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Astral Self (UA): Improved Arms of the Astral Self</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you make two extra attacks instead of one when you attack with your astral arms as a bonus action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Barbarian And Monk p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of Mercy (UA): Healing Technique</name>
        <text>11th-level Way of Mercy feature</text>
        <text>Your skill in manipulating your ki to heal increases. When you restore hit points to a creature using your Hands of Healing, you can also end one disease or a condition from the following list affecting the target: blinded, deafened, paralyzed, or poisoned.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt1 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Ascendant Dragon (UA): Aspect of the Wyrm</name>
        <text>11th-level Way of the Ascendant Dragon feature</text>
        <text>The power of your draconic ki now radiates from you, protecting your allies from harm and punishing any who raise arms against them. As a bonus action, you can create an aura of draconic power that radiates 30 feet from you for 1 minute. Choose acid, cold, fire, lightning, or poison damage, and for the duration, you gain the following effects:</text>
        <text>• You and your allies within your aura gain resistance to the chosen damage type.</text>
        <text>• Waves of destructive energy flow out from you and your allies when any of you are attacked. When you or one of your allies in the aura is hit by an attack made by another creature within the aura, the target that was hit can use their reaction to deal an amount of damage of the chosen type equal to one roll of your Martial Arts die to the attacker.</text>
        <text>Once you use this bonus action, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend 4 ki points to use it again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 12th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>12th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
        <feature>
          <name>Tongue of the Sun and Moon</name>
        <text>Starting at 13th level, you learn to touch the ki of other minds so that you understand all spoken languages. Moreover, any creature that can understand a language can understand what you say.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature>
          <name>Diamond Soul</name>
        <text>Beginning at 14th level, your mastery of ki grants you proficiency in all saving throws.</text>
        <text>Additionally, whenever you make a saving throw and fail, you can spend 1 ki point to reroll it and take the second result.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature>
          <name>Timeless Body</name>
        <text>At 15th level, your ki sustains you so that you suffer none of the frailty of old age, and you can't be aged magically. You can still die of old age, however. In addition, you no longer need food or water.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 16th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>16th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature>
          <name>Monastic Tradition feature</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you gain one feature granted by your Monastic Tradition.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of Shadow: Opportunist</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you can exploit a creature's momentary distraction when it is hit by an attack. Whenever a creature within 5 feet of you is hit by an attack made by a creature other than you, you can use your reaction to make a melee attack against that creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 80</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Open Hand: Quivering Palm</name>
        <text>You gain the ability to set up lethal vibrations in someone's body. When you hit a creature with an unarmed strike, you can spend 3 ki points to start these imperceptible vibrations, which last for a number of days equal to your monk level. The vibrations are harmless unless you use your action to end them. To do so, you and the target must be on the same plane of existence. When you use this action, the creature must make a Constitution saving throw. If it fails, it is reduced to 0 hit points. If it succeeds, it takes 10d10 necrotic damage.</text>
        <text>You can have only one creature under the effect of this feature at a time. You can choose to end the vibrations harmlessly without using an action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 79</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Four Elements: Extra Elemental Discipline</name>
        <text>You learn one additional elemental discipline of your choice. You should know 4 elemental disciplines, as well as Elemental Attunement.</text>
        <text>Whenever you learn a new elemental discipline, you can also replace one elemental discipline that you already know with a different discipline.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 80</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Long Death: Touch of the Long Death</name>
        <text>Starting at 17th level, your touch can channel the energy of death into a creature. As an action, you touch one creature within 5 feet of you, and you expend 1 to 10 ki points. The target must make a Constitution saving throw, and it takes 2d10 necrotic damage per ki point spent on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 130</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Sun Shield</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you become wreathed in a magical, luminous aura. You shed bright light in a 30-foot radius and dim light for an additional 30 feet. You can extinguish or restore the light as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>If a creature hits you with a melee attack while this light shines, you can use your reaction to deal radiant damage to the creature. The radiant damage equals 5 + your Wisdom modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 131</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Sun Shield</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you become wreathed in a luminous, magical aura. You shed bright light in a 30-foot radius and dim light for an additional 30 feet. You can extinguish or restore the light as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>If a creature hits you with a melee attack while this light shines, you can use your reaction to deal radiant damage to the creature. The radiant damage equals 5 + your Wisdom modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 131</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei (UA): Unerring Accuracy</name>
        <text>At 17th level, your mastery of weapons grants you extraordinary accuracy. On each of your turns, you can reroll one weapon attack roll you make that misses.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Monk p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei v2 (UA): Unerring Accuracy</name>
        <text>At 17th level, your mastery of weapons grants you extraordinary accuracy. If you make an attack roll with a monk weapon and miss, you can reroll it. You can use this feature only once on each of your turns.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of Tranquility (UA): Anger of a Gentle Soul</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you gain the ability to visit vengeance on someone who fells others. If you see a creature reduce another creature to 0 hit points, you can use your reaction to grant yourself a bonus to all damage rolls against the aggressor until the end of your next turn. The bonus equals your monk level.</text>
        <text>Once you use this ability, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Monk p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Drunken Master (UA): Intoxicated Frenzy</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you gain the ability to make an overwhelming number of attacks against a group of enemies. When you use your Flurry of Blows, you can make up to three additional attacks with it (up to a total of five attacks), provided that each Flurry of Blows attack targets a different creature this turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Drunken Master: Intoxicated Frenzy</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you gain the ability to make an overwhelming number of attacks against a group of enemies. When you use your Flurry of Blows, you can make up to three additional attacks with it (up to a total of five Flurry of Blows attacks), provided that each Flurry of Blows attack targets a different creature this turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 33</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei: Unerring Accuracy</name>
        <text>At 17th level, your mastery of weapons grants you extraordinary accuracy. If you miss with an attack roll using a monk weapon on your turn, you can reroll it. You can use this feature only once on each of your turns.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 34</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Sun Shield</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you become wreathed in a magical, luminous aura. You shed bright light in a 30-foot radius and dim light for an additional 30 feet. You can extinguish or restore the light as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>If a creature hits you with a melee attack while this light shines, you can use your reaction to deal radiant damage to the creature. The radiant damage equals 5 + your Wisdom modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 35</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Sun Shield</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you become wreathed in a luminous, magical aura. You shed bright light in a 30-foot radius and dim light for an additional 30 feet. You can extinguish or restore the light as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>If a creature hits you with a melee attack while this light shines, you can use your reaction to deal radiant damage to the creature. The radiant damage equals 5 + your Wisdom modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 35</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Soul Knife (Livestream): Psychic Form</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you can transform your physical body into the same psychic energy that comprises your soul knives. As a bonus action, you gain resistance to all types of damage, a fly speed of 30 feet, and the ability to pass through solid objects but not end your movement within them. This benefit lasts for 1 minute. You cannot use it again until you complete a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Astral Self (UA): Complete Astral Self</name>
        <text>Starting at 17th level, your connection to your astral self is complete, allowing you summon it entirely. On your turn, you can spend 10 ki points as a bonus action to summon the arms, visage, and body of your astral self for 10 minutes. This spectral body covers your physical form like a suit of armor, connecting with the arms and visage. You determine its appearance based on the qualities of your character. While your astral self is summoned, you gain the following benefits.</text>
        <name>Way of the Astral Self (UA): Armor of the Spirit</name>
        <text>   You gain a +2 bonus to AC while you aren't incapacitated.</text>
        <name>Way of the Astral Self (UA): Astral Barrage</name>
        <text>   Whenever you use the Extra Attack feature to attack twice, you can instead attack three times using your astral arms.</text>
        <name>Way of the Astral Self (UA): Ki Consumption</name>
        <text>   When a creature within 10 feet of you is reduced to 0 hit points, you can use your reaction to regain ki points equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum 1).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Barbarian And Monk p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Astral Self (UA): Improved Arms of the Astral Self</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you make three extra attacks instead of one when you attack with your astral arms as a bonus action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Barbarian And Monk p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of Mercy (UA): Hand of Mercy</name>
        <text>17th-level Way of Mercy feature</text>
        <text>Your mastery of life energy opens the door to the ultimate respite technique. As an action, you can touch a creature, expend 4 ki points, and force the creature to make a Constitution saving throw (a creature can willingly fail this save). Unless the save succeeds, the creature enters a state of suspended animation for a number of days equal to your monk level or until you end the effect early (no action required). During this time, the creature is paralyzed, has immunity to all damage, and any curse, disease, or poison affecting it is suspended. The creature appears dead to all outward inspection and to spells used to determine the creature's status.</text>
        <text>You can have only one creature under the effect of this feature at a time.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt1 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Ascendant Dragon (UA): Ascendant Aspect</name>
        <text>17th-level Way of the Ascendant Dragon feature</text>
        <text>Your draconic ki reaches its peak. You gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• You gain blindsight out to 30 feet. Within that range, you can effectively see anything that isn't behind total cover, even if you're blinded or in darkness. Moreover, you can see an invisible creature within that range, unless the creature successfully hides from you.</text>
        <text>• When you damage a creature with your Breath of the Dragon, the energy clings to the target. At the start of each of the creature's turns, it takes damage of the type your breath dealt equal to one roll of your Martial Arts die. At the end of its turn, the creature can repeat the save, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
        <text>• When you activate your Aspect of the Wyrm, draconic fury explodes from you. Choose any number of creatures you can see within your aura. Those creatures each take 4d10 acid, cold, fire, lightning, or poison damage (your choice).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature>
          <name>Empty Body</name>
        <text>Beginning at 18th level, you can use your action to spend 4 ki points to become invisible for 1 minute. During that time, you also have resistance to all damage but force damage.</text>
        <text>Additionally, you can spend 8 ki points to cast the astral projection spell, without needing material components. When you do so, you can't take any other creatures with you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 19th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>19th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
        <feature>
          <name>Perfect Self</name>
        <text>At 20th level, when you roll for initiative and have no ki points remaining, you regain 4 ki points.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
