<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Sorcerer</name>
    <hd>6</hd>
    <proficiency>Constitution, Charisma, Arcana, Deception, Insight, Intimidation, Persuasion, Religion</proficiency>
    <numSkills>2</numSkills>
    <spellAbility>Charisma</spellAbility>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Starting Sorcerer</name>
        <text>As a 1st-level Sorcerer, you begin play with 6+your Constitution modifier hit points.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>You are proficient with the following items, in addition to any proficiencies provided by your race or background.</text>
        <text>• Armor: none</text>
        <text>• Weapons: daggers, darts, slings, quarterstaffs, light crossbows</text>
        <text>• Tools: none</text>
        <text>• Skills: Choose 2 from Arcana, Deception, Insight, Intimidation, Persuasion, Religion</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>You begin play with the following equipment, in addition to any equipment provided by your background.</text>
        <text>• (a) a light crossbow and crossbow bolts (20) or (b) any simple weapon</text>
        <text>• (a) a component pouch or (b) an arcane focus</text>
        <text>• (a) a dungeoneer's pack or (b) an explorer's pack</text>
        <text>• Two dagger</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Alternatively, you may start with 3d4 x 10 gp and choose your own equipment.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 99</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Multiclass Sorcerer</name>
        <text>To multiclass as a Sorcerer, you must meet the following prerequisites:</text>
        <text>• Charisma 13</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 99</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <armor>none</armor>
    <weapons>daggers, darts, slings, quarterstaffs, light crossbows</weapons>
    <tools>none</tools>
    <wealth>3d4 x 10</wealth>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <slots>4, 2</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Spellcasting</name>
        <text>An event in your past, or in the life of a parent or ancestor, left an indelible mark on you, infusing you with arcane magic. This font of magic, whatever its origin, fuels your spells. See chapter 10 for the general rules of spellcasting and chapter 11 for the sorcerer spell list.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Cantrips:</text>
        <text>   At 1st level, you know four cantrips of your choice from the sorcerer spell list. You learn an additional sorcerer cantrip of your choice at 4th level and another at 10th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Spell Slots:</text>
        <text>   The Sorcerer table shows how many spell slots you have to cast your sorcerer spells of 1st level and higher. To cast one of these sorcerer spells, you must expend a slot of the spell's level or higher. You regain all expended spell slots when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>   For example, if you know the 1st-level spell burning hands and have a 1st-level and a 2nd-level spell slot available, you can cast burning hands using either slot.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Spells Known of 1st Level and Higher:</text>
        <text>   You know two 1st-level spells of your choice from the sorcerer spell list.</text>
        <text>   You learn an additional sorcerer spell of your choice at each level except 12th, 14th, 16th, 18th, 19th, and 20th. Each of these spells must be of a level for which you have spell slots. For instance, when you reach 3rd level in this class, you can learn one new spell of 1st or 2nd level.</text>
        <text>   Additionally, when you gain a level in this class, you can choose one of the sorcerer spells you know and replace it with another spell from the sorcerer spell list, which also must be of a level for which you have spell slots.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Spellcasting Ability:</text>
        <text>   Charisma is your spellcasting ability for your sorcerer spells, since the power of your magic relies on your ability to project your will into the world. You use your Charisma whenever a spell refers to your spellcasting ability. In addition, you use your Charisma modifier when setting the saving throw DC for a sorcerer spell you cast and when making an attack roll with one.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Spellcasting Focus:</text>
        <text>   You can use an arcane focus as a spellcasting focus for your sorcerer spells.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 99</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Sorcerous Origin</name>
        <text>Choose a sorcerous origin, which describes the source of your innate magical power, from the list of available origins</text>
        <text>Your choice grants you features when you choose it at 1st level and again at 6th, 14th, and 18th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 99</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sorcerous Origin: Draconic Bloodline</name>
        <text>Your innate magic comes from draconic magic that was mingled with your blood or that of your ancestors. Most often, sorcerers with this origin trace their descent back to a mighty sorcerer of ancient times who made a bargain with a dragon or who might even have claimed a dragon parent. Some of these bloodlines are well established in the world, but most are obscure. Any given sorcerer could be the first of a new bloodline, as a result of a pact or some other exceptional circumstance.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 102</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Draconic Bloodline: Draconic Resilience</name>
        <text>As magic flows through your body, it causes physical traits of your dragon ancestors to emerge. At 1st level, your hit point maximum increases by 1 and increases by 1 again whenever you gain a level in this class.</text>
        <text>Additionally, parts of your skin are covered by a thin sheen of dragon-like scales. When you aren't wearing armor, your AC equals 13 + your Dexterity modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 102</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Draconic Bloodline: Dragon Ancestor</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you choose one type of dragon as your ancestor. The damage type associated with each dragon is used by features you gain later.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Draconic Ancestry</text>
        <text>Dragon | Damage Type</text>
        <text>Black | Acid</text>
        <text>Blue | Lightning</text>
        <text>Brass | Fire</text>
        <text>Bronze | Lightning</text>
        <text>Copper | Acid</text>
        <text>Gold | Fire</text>
        <text>Green | Poison</text>
        <text>Red | Fire</text>
        <text>Silver | Cold</text>
        <text>White | Cold</text>
        <text>You can speak, read, and write Draconic. Additionally, whenever you make a Charisma check when interacting with dragons, your proficiency bonus is doubled if it applies to the check.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 102</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sorcerous Origin: Wild Magic</name>
        <text>Your innate magic comes from the wild forces of chaos that underlie the order of creation. You might have endured exposure to some form of raw magic, perhaps through a planar portal leading to Limbo, the Elemental Planes, or the mysterious Far Realm. Perhaps you were blessed by a powerful fey creature or marked by a demon. Or your magic could be a fluke of your birth, with no apparent cause or reason. However it came to be, this chaotic magic churns within you, waiting for any outlet.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 103</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Wild Magic: Tides of Chaos</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, you can manipulate the forces of chance and chaos to gain advantage on one attack roll, ability check, or saving throw. Once you do so, you must finish a long rest before you can use this feature again.</text>
        <text>Any time before you regain the use of this feature, the DM can have you roll on the Wild Magic Surge table immediately after you cast a sorcerer spell of 1st level or higher. You then regain the use of this feature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 103</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Wild Magic: Wild Magic Surge</name>
        <text>Starting when you choose this origin at 1st level, your spellcasting can unleash surges of untamed magic. Immediately after you cast a sorcerer spell of 1st level or higher, the DM can have you roll a d20. If you roll a 1, roll on the Wild Magic Surge table to create a random magical effect. A Wild Magic Surge can happen once per turn.</text>
        <text>If a Wild Magic effect is a spell, it's too wild to be affected by Metamagic. If it normally requires concentration, it doesn't require concentration in this case; the spell lasts for its full duration.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Wild Magic Surge</text>
        <text>d100 | Effect</text>
        <text>01-02 | Roll on this table at the start of each of your turns for the next minute, ignoring this result on subsequent rolls.</text>
        <text>03-04 | For the next minute, you can see any invisible creature if you have line of sight to it.</text>
        <text>05-06 | A modron chosen and controlled by the DM appears in an unoccupied space within 5 feet of you, then disappears 1 minute later.</text>
        <text>07-08 | You cast fireball as a 3rd-level spell centered on yourself.</text>
        <text>09-10 | You cast magic missile as a 5th-level spell.</text>
        <text>11-12 | Roll a d10. Your height changes by a number of inches equal to the roll. If the roll is odd, you shrink. If the roll is even, you grow.</text>
        <text>13-14 | You cast confusion centered on yourself.</text>
        <text>15-16 | For the next minute, you regain 5 hit points at the start of each of your turns.</text>
        <text>17-18 | You grow a long beard made of feathers that remains until you sneeze, at which point the feathers explode out from your face.</text>
        <text>19-20 | You cast grease centered on yourself.</text>
        <text>21-22 | Creatures have disadvantage on saving throws against the next spell you cast in the next minute that involves a saving throw.</text>
        <text>23-24 | Your skin turns a vibrant shade of blue. A remove curse spell can end this effect.</text>
        <text>25-26 | An eye appears on your forehead for the next minute. During that time, you have advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
        <text>27-28 | For the next minute, all your spells with a casting time of 1 action have a casting time of 1 bonus action.</text>
        <text>29-30 | You teleport up to 60 feet to an unoccupied space of your choice that you can see.</text>
        <text>31-32 | You are transported to the Astral Plane until the end of your next turn, after which time you return to the space you previously occupied or the nearest unoccupied space if that space is occupied.</text>
        <text>33-34 | Maximize the damage of the next damaging spell you cast within the next minute.</text>
        <text>35-36 | Roll a d10. Your age changes by a number of years equal to the roll. If the roll is odd, you get younger (minimum 1 year old). If the roll is even, you get older.</text>
        <text>37-38 | 1d6 flumph controlled by the DM appear in unoccupied spaces within 60 feet of you and are frightened of you. They vanish after 1 minute.</text>
        <text>39-40 | You regain 2d10 hit points.</text>
        <text>41-42 | You turn into a potted plant until the start of your next turn. While a plant, you are incapacitated and have vulnerability to all damage. If you drop to 0 hit points, your pot breaks, and your form reverts.</text>
        <text>43-44 | For the next minute, you can teleport up to 20 feet as a bonus action on each of your turns.</text>
        <text>45-46 | You cast levitate on yourself.</text>
        <text>47-48 | A unicorn controlled by the DM appears in a space within 5 feet of you, then disappears 1 minute later.</text>
        <text>49-50 | You can't speak for the next minute. Whenever you try, pink bubbles float out of your mouth.</text>
        <text>51-52 | A spectral shield hovers near you for the next minute, granting you a +2 bonus to AC and immunity to magic missile.</text>
        <text>53-54 | You are immune to being intoxicated by alcohol for the next 5d6 days.</text>
        <text>55-56 | Your hair falls out but grows back within 24 hours.</text>
        <text>57-58 | For the next minute, any flammable object you touch that isn't being worn or carried by another creature bursts into flame.</text>
        <text>59-60 | You regain your lowest-level expended spell slot.</text>
        <text>61-62 | For the next minute, you must shout when you speak.</text>
        <text>63-64 | You cast fog cloud centered on yourself.</text>
        <text>65-66 | Up to three creatures you choose within 30 feet of you take 4d10 lightning damage.</text>
        <text>67-68 | You are frightened by the nearest creature until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text>69-70 | Each creature within 30 feet of you becomes invisible for the next minute. The invisibility ends on a creature when it attacks or casts a spell.</text>
        <text>71-72 | You gain resistance to all damage for the next minute.</text>
        <text>73-74 | A random creature within 60 feet of you becomes poisoned for 1d4 hours.</text>
        <text>75-76 | You glow with bright light in a 30-foot radius for the next minute. Any creature that ends its turn within 5 feet of you is blinded until the end of its next turn.</text>
        <text>77-78 | You cast polymorph on yourself. If you fail the saving throw, you turn into a sheep for the spell's duration.</text>
        <text>79-80 | Illusory butterflies and flower petals flutter in the air within 10 feet of you for the next minute.</text>
        <text>81-82 | You can take one additional action immediately.</text>
        <text>83-84 | Each creature within 30 feet of you takes 1d10 necrotic damage. You regain hit points equal to the sum of the necrotic damage dealt.</text>
        <text>85-86 | You cast mirror image.</text>
        <text>87-88 | You cast fly on a random creature within 60 feet of you.</text>
        <text>89-90 | You become invisible for the next minute. During that time, other creatures can't hear you. The invisibility ends if you attack or cast a spell.</text>
        <text>91-92 | If you die within the next minute, you immediately come back to life as if by the reincarnate spell.</text>
        <text>93-94 | Your size increases by one size category for the next minute.</text>
        <text>95-96 | You and all creatures within 30 feet of you gain vulnerability to piercing damage for the next minute.</text>
        <text>97-98 | You are surrounded by faint, ethereal music for the next minute.</text>
        <text>99-00 | You regain all expended sorcery points.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 103</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul (UA): Favored Soul</name>
        <text>You have been chosen by a deity, and bestowed with a fragment of their divine power. You have been fundamentally changed by the touch of this deity, which awakens powerful magical abilities inside you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 8</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul (UA): Bonus Proficiency</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you gain proficiency in light armor, medium armor, shields, and simple weapons.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 8</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul (UA): Chosen of the Gods</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you choose one of the cleric class's divine domains. You add that domain's spells for 1st-level clerics to your known spells. These spells do not count against the number of spells you can know, and they are considered to be sorcerer spells for you. When you reach 3rd, 5th, 7th, and 9th levels in the sorcerer class, you likewise learn your domain's spells that become available at those levels.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 8</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul v2 (UA): Favored Soul v2</name>
        <text>Sometimes the spark of magic that fuels a sorcerer comes from a divine source that glimmers within the soul. Having such a favored soul, your innate magic might come from a distant but powerful familial connection to a divine being. Perhaps your ancestor was an angel, transformed into a mortal and sent to fight in a god's name. Or your birth might align with an ancient prophecy, marking you as a servant of the gods or a chosen vessel of divine magic.</text>
        <text>Favored souls, with their natural magnetism and strong personalities, are often seen as threats by traditional religious hierarchies. As outsiders who command the power of the gods, these sorcerers can undermine the existing order and claim a direct tie to the divine.</text>
        <text>In some cultures, only those who can claim the power of a favored soul may command religious power. In these lands, ecclesiastical positions are dominated by a few bloodlines and preserved over generations.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul v2 (UA): Divine Magic</name>
        <text>Your link to the divine allows you to learn spells normally associated with the cleric class. When your Spellcasting feature lets you learn a sorcerer cantrip or a sorcerer spell of 1st level or higher, you can choose the new spell from the cleric spell list, in addition to the sorcerer spell list. You must otherwise obey all the restrictions for selecting the spell, and it becomes a sorcerer spell for you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul v2 (UA): Favored by the Gods</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, divine power guards your destiny. If you fail a saving throw or miss with an attack roll, you can roll 2d4 and add it to the total, possibly changing the outcome.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul v2 (UA): Supernatural Resilience</name>
        <text>At 1st level, the blessing of the gods grants you enhanced durability. Your hit point maximum increases by 1, and it increases by 1 again whenever you gain a level in this class.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul v3 (UA): Favored Soul v3</name>
        <text>Sometimes the spark of magic that fuels a sorcerer comes from a divine source that glimmers within the soul. Having such a favored soul, your innate magic might come from a distant but powerful familial connection to a divine being. Perhaps your ancestor was an angel, transformed into a mortal and sent to fight in a god's name. Or your birth might align with an ancient prophecy, marking you as a servant of the gods or a chosen vessel of divine magic.</text>
        <text>Favored souls, with their natural magnetism and strong personalities, are often seen as threats by traditional religious hierarchies. As outsiders who command the power of the gods, these sorcerers can undermine the existing order and claim a direct tie to the divine.</text>
        <text>In some cultures, only those who can claim the power of a favored soul may command religious power. In these lands, ecclesiastical positions are dominated by a few bloodlines and preserved over generations.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul v3 (UA): Divine Magic</name>
        <text>Your link to the divine allows you to learn spells normally associated with the cleric class. When your Spellcasting feature lets you learn a sorcerer cantrip or a sorcerer spell of 1st level or higher, you can choose the new spell from the cleric spell list, in addition to the sorcerer spell list. You must otherwise obey all the restrictions for selecting the spell, and it becomes a sorcerer spell for you.</text>
        <text>You also learn the cure wounds spell, which does not count against your number of sorcerer spells known.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul v3 (UA): Favored by the Gods</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, divine power guards your destiny. If you fail a saving throw or miss with an attack roll, you can roll 2d4 and add it to the total, possibly changing the outcome.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery (UA): Storm Sorcery</name>
        <text>Your innate magic comes from the power of elemental air. Perhaps you were born during a howling gale so powerful that folk still tell stories of it. Your lineage might include the influence of potent air creatures such as vaati or djinni. Whatever the case, the magic of the storm permeates your soul.</text>
        <text>Storm sorcerers are invaluable members of a ship's crew. Their magic allows them to exert control over wind and weather in their immediate area. Their abilities also prove useful in repelling attacks by sahuagin, pirates, and other waterborne threats.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Waterborne Adventures p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery (UA): Stormborn</name>
        <text>The arcane magic you command is infused with elemental air. You can speak, read, and write Primordial. In addition, you gain the following spells at the listed sorcerer level. These spells do not count against the number of sorcerer spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Storm Sorcerer Bonus Spells</text>
        <text>Sorcerer Level | Spells</text>
        <text>1st | Fog cloud, thunderwave</text>
        <text>3rd | Gust of wind, levitate</text>
        <text>5th | Call lightning, sleet storm</text>
        <text>7th | Conjure minor elementals*, ice storm</text>
        <text>9th | Conjure elemental**</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Waterborne Adventures p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery (UA): Tempestuous Magic</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you are attuned to elemental air magic. Whenever you cast a spell other than a cantrip during your turn, whirling gusts of elemental air surround you. You can use a bonus action to fly 10 feet without provoking opportunity attacks.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Waterborne Adventures p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sorcerous Origin: Storm Sorcery</name>
        <text>Your innate magic comes from the power of elemental air. Perhaps you were born during a howling gale so powerful that folk still tell stories of it. Your lineage might include the influence of potent air creatures such as vaati or djinni. Whatever the case, the magic of the storm permeates your soul.</text>
        <text>Storm sorcerers are invaluable members of a ship's crew. Their magic allows them to exert control over wind and weather in their immediate area. Their abilities also prove useful in repelling attacks by sahuagin, pirates, and other waterborne threats.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Tempestuous Magic</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, you can use a bonus action on your turn to cause whirling gusts of elemental air to briefly surround you, immediately before or after you cast a spell of 1st level or higher. Doing so allows you to fly up to 10 feet without provoking opportunity attacks.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Wind Speaker</name>
        <text>The arcane magic you command is infused with elemental air. You can speak, read, and write Primordial. (Knowing this language allows you to understand and be understood by those who speak its dialects: Aquan, Auran, Ignan, and Terran.)</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sorcerous Origin: Storm Sorcery</name>
        <text>Your innate magic comes from the power of elemental air. Many with this power can trace their magic back to a near-death experience caused by the Great Rain, but perhaps you were born during a howling gale so powerful that folk still tell stories of it, or your lineage might include the influence of potent air creatures such as djinn. Whatever the case, the magic of the storm permeates your being.</text>
        <text>Storm sorcerers are invaluable members of a ship's crew. Their magic allows them to exert control over wind and weather in their immediate area. Their abilities also prove useful in repelling attacks by sahuagin, pirates, and other waterborne threats.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Tempestuous Magic</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, you can use a bonus action on your turn to cause whirling gusts of elemental air to briefly surround you, immediately before or after you cast a spell of 1st level or higher. Doing so allows you to fly up to 10 feet without provoking opportunity attacks.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Wind Speaker</name>
        <text>The arcane magic you command is infused with elemental air. You can speak, read, and write Primordial. Knowing this language allows you to understand and be understood by those who speak its dialects: Aquan, Auran, Ignan, and Terran.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Shadow (UA): Shadow</name>
        <text>Your innate magic comes from the Shadowfell. You might trace your lineage to an entity from that place, or perhaps you were exposed to its fell energy and transformed in some fundamental manner.</text>
        <text>The power of shadow magic casts a strange pall over your physical presence. The spark of life that sustains you is muffled, as if it struggles to remain viable against the dark energy that imbues your soul. At your option, you can pick from or roll on the following table to create a unique quirk for your character.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Shadow Sorcerer Quirks</text>
        <text>d6 | Quirk</text>
        <text>1 | You are always icy cold to the touch.</text>
        <text>2 | When you are asleep, you don't appear to breathe (though you must still breathe to survive).</text>
        <text>3 | You don't seem to bleed, even when badly injured.</text>
        <text>4 | Your heart beats once per minute. This even sometimes surprises you.</text>
        <text>5 | You have trouble remembering that living creatures and corpses should be treated differently.</text>
        <text>6 | You blinked. Once. Last week.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Shadow (UA): Eyes of the Dark</name>
        <text>From 1st level, you have darkvision with a range of 60 feet. You can cast darkness by spending 1 sorcery point. You can see through any darkness spell you cast using this ability.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Shadow (UA): Strength of the Grave</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, your existence in a twilight state between life and death makes you difficult to defeat. Whenever damage reduces you to 0 hit points, you can make a Constitution saving throw (DC 5 + the damage taken). On a success, you instead drop to 1 hit point. You cannot use this feature if you are reduced to 0 hit points by radiant damage or by a critical hit.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sorcerous Origin: Phoenix Sorcery (UA)</name>
        <text>Your power draws from the immortal flame that fuels the legendary phoenix. You or your ancestors perhaps rendered a phoenix a great service, or you were born in its presence. Whatever the cause, a shard of the phoenix's power dwells within you.</text>
        <text>That power is a mixed blessing. Like the mythical creature, you can invoke fiery energy and gain the ability to cheat death itself. This power comes at a cost. The fire within you seethes, demanding to be unleashed. You sometimes find yourself absentmindedly feeding fires. You can't bear to allow a fire to sputter out. You feel most comfortable while holding a lit torch or sitting in front of a campfire.</text>
        <text>More importantly, this gift comes with no special protection from fire. You are as vulnerable as any other creature to fiery magic, including your own. Phoenix sorcerers can use their powers to pull themselves back from the brink of death, and all too often their own, rash nature or reliance on destructive magic is what puts them there in the first place.</text>
        <text>Such sorcerers are wanderers by necessity. The volatile nature of their magic makes other folk nervous. If a fire breaks out in town, a phoenix sorcerer had best flee, whether guilty or not. Fire is a dangerous force, and phoenix sorcerers have a reputation (deserved or not) for reckless behavior, confident that the essence of the phoenix can save them.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Phoenix Soul Quirks</text>
        <text>d6 | Phoenix Soul</text>
        <text>1 | You absentmindedly ignite small fires that quickly sputter out.</text>
        <text>2 | You cackle like a fiend when you unleash your fire spells.</text>
        <text>3 | You admire fire, even if it burns your friends.</text>
        <text>4 | You are covered in burns that mark the first time your power manifested.</text>
        <text>5 | You like your food charred.</text>
        <text>6 | You are brave to the point of recklessness.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Phoenix Sorcery (UA): Ignite</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you gain the ability to start fires with a touch. As an action, you can magically ignite a flammable object you touch with your hand—an object such as a torch, a piece of tinder, or the hem of drapes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Phoenix Sorcery (UA): Mantle of Flame</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, you can unleash the phoenix fire that blazes within you.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, you magically wreathe yourself in swirling fire, as your eyes glow like hot coals. For 1 minute, you gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• You shed bright light in a 30-foot radius and dim light for an additional 30 feet.</text>
        <text>• Any creature takes fire damage equal to your Charisma modifier if it hits you with a melee attack from within 5 feet of you or if it touches you.</text>
        <text>• Whenever you roll fire damage on your turn, the roll gains a bonus to equal to your Charisma modifier.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sorcerous Origin: Sea Sorcery (UA)</name>
        <text>The power of water is the strength of flexibility, resilience, and a relentless nature. Water parts to allow a ship to sail over it or a diver to plunge into it, but their passing leaves no mark. Water flowing down a mountain reaches the sea. It might bend and turn across valleys and down hillsides, but it slowly and steadily returns to the waves. Those whose souls are touched by the power of elemental water command a similar power.</text>
        <text>Your heritage ties to powerful creatures of the sea, such as nereids, the lords of the merfolk, and elemental powers. Like a river, you feel the call of the ocean. The call is ever present in your heart, and you are never completely at peace until you are near the sea.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sea Sorcery (UA): Curse of the Sea</name>
        <text>When you choose this origin at 1st level, you learn the secret of infusing your spells with a watery curse.</text>
        <text>When you hit a creature with a cantrip's attack or when a creature fails a saving throw against your cantrip, you can curse the target until the end of your next turn or until you curse a different creature with this feature.</text>
        <text>Once per turn when you cast a spell, you can trigger the curse if that spell deals cold or lightning damage to the cursed target or forces it to move. Doing so subjects the target to the appropriate additional effect below, and then the curse ends if the spell isn't a cantrip (you choose the effect to use if more than one effect applies):</text>
        <name>Sea Sorcery (UA): Cold damage</name>
        <text>   If the affected target takes cold damage from your spell, the target's speed is also reduced by 15 feet until the end of your next turn. If the spell already reduces the target's speed, use whichever reduction is greater.</text>
        <name>Sea Sorcery (UA): Lightning Damage</name>
        <text>   If the affected target takes lightning damage from your spell, the target takes additional lightning damage equal to your Charisma modifier.</text>
        <name>Sea Sorcery (UA): Forced Movement</name>
        <text>   If the target is moved by your spell, increase the distance it is moved by 15 feet.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sea Sorcery (UA): Soul of the Sea</name>
        <text>At 1st level, your tie to the sea grants you the ability to breathe underwater, and you have a swim speed equal to your walking speed.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sorcerous Origin: Stone Sorcery (UA)</name>
        <text>Your magic springs from a mystical link between your soul and the magic of elemental earth. You might trace a distant ancestor to the Plane of Earth, or your family might have earned a mighty boon in return for a service to the dao lords. Whatever your past, the magic of elemental earth is yours to command.</text>
        <text>Your link to earth magic grants you extraordinary resilience, and stone sorcerers have a natural affinity for combat. A steel blade feels like a natural extension of your body, and sorcerers with this origin have a knack for wielding both shields and weapons. In combat your place is amid the fray. You rely on your elemental nature to shield you from harm and your magic and metal weapons to overwhelm your foes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Stone Sorcery (UA): Bonus Proficiencies</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you gain proficiency with shields, simple weapons, and martial weapons.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Stone Sorcery (UA): Stone's Durability</name>
        <text>At 1st level, your connection to stone gives you extra fortitude. Your hit point maximum increases by 1, and it increases by 1 again whenever you gain a level in this class.</text>
        <text>As an action, you can gain a base AC of 13 + your Constitution modifier if you aren't wearing armor, and your skin assumes a stony appearance. This effect lasts until you end it as a bonus action, you are incapacitated, or you don armor other than a shield.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Stone Sorcery (UA): Stone: Metal Magic</name>
        <text>Your affinity for metal gives you the option to learn some non-sorcerer spells that focus on weapon attacks. When your Spellcasting feature lets you learn a sorcerer spell of 1st level or higher, you can select the spell from the following list of spells, in addition to the sorcerer spell list. You must otherwise obey all the restrictions for selecting the spell, and it becomes a sorcerer spell for you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Metal Magic</text>
        <text>Spell Level | Spell</text>
        <text>1st | compelled duel, searing smite, thunderous smite, wrathful smite</text>
        <text>2nd | branding smite, magic weapon</text>
        <text>3rd | blinding smite, elemental weapon</text>
        <text>4th | staggering smite</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sorcerous Origin: Pyromancer (PSK)</name>
        <text>Your innate magic manifests in fire. You are your fire, and your fire is you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Plane Shift: Kaladesh p. 9</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Pyromancer (PSK): Heart of Fire</name>
        <text>At 1st level, whenever you start casting a spell of 1st level or higher that deals fire damage, fiery magic erupts from you. This eruption causes creatures of your choice that you can see within 10 feet of you to take fire damage equal to half your sorcerer level (minimum of 1).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Plane Shift: Kaladesh p. 9</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sorcerous Origin: Divine Soul</name>
        <text>Sometimes the spark of magic that fuels a sorcerer comes from a divine source that glimmers within the soul. Having such a blessed soul is a sign that your innate magic might come from a distant but powerful familial connection to a divine being. Perhaps your ancestor was an angel, transformed into a mortal and sent to fight in a god's name.</text>
        <text>Or your birth might align with an ancient prophecy, marking you as a servant of the gods or a chosen vessel of divine magic.</text>
        <text>A Divine Soul, with a natural magnetism, is seen as a threat by some religious hierarchies. As an outsider who commands sacred power, a Divine Soul can undermine an existing order by claiming a direct tie to the divine.</text>
        <text>In some cultures, only those who can claim the power of a Divine Soul may command religious power. In these lands, ecclesiastical positions are dominated by a few bloodlines and preserved over generations.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Divine Soul: Divine Magic</name>
        <text>Your link to the divine allows you to learn spells from the cleric class. When your Spellcasting feature lets you learn or replace a sorcerer cantrip or a sorcerer spell of 1st level or higher, you can choose the new spell from the cleric spell list or the sorcerer spell list. You must otherwise obey all the restrictions for selecting the spell, and it becomes a sorcerer spell for you.</text>
        <text>In addition, choose an affinity for the source of your divine power: good, evil, law, chaos, or neutrality. You learn an additional spell based on that affinity, as shown below. It is a sorcerer spell for you, but it doesn't count against your number of sorcerer spells known. If you later replace this spell, you must replace it with a spell from the cleric spell list.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Affinity | Spell</text>
        <text>Good | cure wounds</text>
        <text>Evil | inflict wounds</text>
        <text>Law | bless</text>
        <text>Chaos | bane</text>
        <text>Neutrality | protection from evil and good</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Divine Soul: Favored by the Gods</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, divine power guards your destiny. If you fail a saving throw or miss with an attack roll, you can roll 2d4 and add it to the total, possibly changing the outcome. Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sorcerous Origin: Shadow Magic</name>
        <text>You are a creature of shadow, for your innate magic comes from the Shadowfell itself. You might trace your lineage to an entity from that place, or perhaps you were exposed to its fell energy and transformed by it.</text>
        <text>The power of shadow magic casts a strange pall over your physical presence. The spark of life that sustains you is muffled, as if it struggles to remain viable against the dark energy that imbues your soul. At your option, you can pick from or roll on the Shadow Sorcerer Quirks table to create a quirk for your character.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Shadow Sorcerer Quirks</text>
        <text>d6 | Quirk</text>
        <text>1 | You are always icy cold to the touch.</text>
        <text>2 | When you are asleep, you don't appear to breathe (though you must still breathe to survive).</text>
        <text>3 | You barely bleed, even when badly injured.</text>
        <text>4 | Your heart beats once per minute. This event sometimes surprises you.</text>
        <text>5 | You have trouble remembering that living creatures and corpses should be treated differently.</text>
        <text>6 | You blinked. Once. Last week.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Shadow Magic: Eyes of the Dark</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, you have darkvision with a range of 120 feet.</text>
        <text>When you reach 3rd level in this class, you learn the darkness spell, which doesn't count against your number of sorcerer spells known. In addition, you can cast it by spending 2 sorcery points or by expending a spell slot. If you cast it with sorcery points, you can see through the darkness created by the spell.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Shadow Magic: Strength of the Grave</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, your existence in a twilight state between life and death makes you difficult to defeat. When damage reduces you to 0 hit points, you can make a Charisma saving throw (DC 5 + the damage taken). On a success, you instead drop to 1 hit point. You can't use this feature if you are reduced to 0 hit points by radiant damage or by a critical hit.</text>
        <text>After the saving throw succeeds, you can't use this feature again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sorcerous Origin: Storm Sorcery</name>
        <text>Your innate magic comes from the power of elemental air. Perhaps you were born during a howling gale so powerful that folk still tell stories of it. Your lineage might include the influence of potent air creatures such as vaati or djinni. Whatever the case, the magic of the storm permeates your soul.</text>
        <text>Storm sorcerers are invaluable members of a ship's crew. Their magic allows them to exert control over wind and weather in their immediate area. Their abilities also prove useful in repelling attacks by sahuagin, pirates, and other waterborne threats.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Tempestuous Magic</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, you can use a bonus action on your turn to cause whirling gusts of elemental air to briefly surround you, immediately before or after you cast a spell of 1st level or higher. Doing so allows you to fly up to 10 feet without provoking opportunity attacks.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Wind Speaker</name>
        <text>The arcane magic you command is infused with elemental air. You can speak, read, and write Primordial. (Knowing this language allows you to understand and be understood by those who speak its dialects: Aquan, Auran, Ignan, and Terran.)</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sorcerous Origin: Storm Sorcery</name>
        <text>Your innate magic comes from the power of elemental air. Many with this power can trace their magic back to a near-death experience caused by the Great Rain, but perhaps you were born during a howling gale so powerful that folk still tell stories of it, or your lineage might include the influence of potent air creatures such as djinn. Whatever the case, the magic of the storm permeates your being.</text>
        <text>Storm sorcerers are invaluable members of a ship's crew. Their magic allows them to exert control over wind and weather in their immediate area. Their abilities also prove useful in repelling attacks by sahuagin, pirates, and other waterborne threats.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Tempestuous Magic</name>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, you can use a bonus action on your turn to cause whirling gusts of elemental air to briefly surround you, immediately before or after you cast a spell of 1st level or higher. Doing so allows you to fly up to 10 feet without provoking opportunity attacks.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Wind Speaker</name>
        <text>The arcane magic you command is infused with elemental air. You can speak, read, and write Primordial. Knowing this language allows you to understand and be understood by those who speak its dialects: Aquan, Auran, Ignan, and Terran.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sorcerous Origin: Giant Soul (UA)</name>
        <text>The giants once dwelled in a fabled realm known as Ostoria, a paradise for their folk that reflected their mastery of the mortal realm. In time, Ostoria fell, and the giants were scattered and broken. During that mythic era, the giants granted a few chosen individuals among the small folk a shard of their great power. These favored people were caught in the same tragedy that sundered Ostoria. Since that time, they have spread across the many worlds of the multiverse. Now and again, one of their descendants manifests the gifts imparted by the giants, granting them sorcerous magic that allows them to command the elements and gain the might of a giant.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Giant Soul Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Giant Soul (UA): Jotun Resilience</name>
        <text>The resilience of giants flows through your body. At 1st level, your hit point maximum increases by 1, and it increases by 1 again whenever you gain a level in this class.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Giant Soul Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Giant Soul (UA): Mark of the Ordning</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you discover innate magical abilities within yourself that are based on your giant heritage. Select one of the giant types from the Mark of the Ordning table. At 1st and 3rd level, you learn the spells associated with your choice, as shown in the table. These spells count as sorcerer spells for you, but they don't count against your number of sorcerer spells known.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Giant Type | Spells at 1st Level | Spells at 3rd Level</text>
        <text>Cloud Giant | fog cloud, minor illusion | invisibility</text>
        <text>Fire Giant | burning hands, fire bolt | flaming sphere</text>
        <text>Frost Giant | armor of Agathys, ray of frost | hold person</text>
        <text>Hill Giant | heroism, shillelagh | enlarge/reduce</text>
        <text>Stone Giant | entangle, resistance | spike growth</text>
        <text>Storm Giant | shocking grasp, thunderwave | gust of wind</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Giant Soul Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Aberrant Mind (UA): Aberrant Mind</name>
        <text>An alien influence has wrapped its tendrils around you, warping you in both body and mind. Perhaps a psychic splinter lodged in your psyche after you suffered domination by an aboleth. Maybe you were born somewhere tainted by the Far Realm, a planar blot that changed you forever. Or perhaps mind flayers kidnapped you, subjecting you to the nightmarish process of ceremorphosis—but the transformation failed and left you altered.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer And Warlock p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Aberrant Mind (UA): Invasive Thoughts</name>
        <text>1st-level Aberrant Mind feature</text>
        <text>At 1st level, you gain the ability to use a bonus action to magically create a telepathic link with one creature you can see within 30 feet of you. Until the link ends, you can telepathically speak to the target through the link, and if it understands at least one language, it can speak telepathically to you. The link lasts for 10 minutes, and it ends early if you are incapacitated or die, or if you use another bonus action to break the link or to establish this link with a different creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer And Warlock p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Aberrant Mind (UA): Psionic Spells</name>
        <text>1st-level Aberrant Mind feature</text>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, your aberrant nature changes your mind in subtle but profound ways. You learn additional spells when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown on the Psionic Spells table. The spell counts as a sorcerer spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of sorcerer spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Psionic Spells</text>
        <text>Sorcerer Level | Spells</text>
        <text>1st | arms of Hadar, dissonant whispers</text>
        <text>3rd | calm emotions, detect thoughts</text>
        <text>5th | hunger of Hadar, sending</text>
        <text>7th | compulsion, Evard's black tentacles</text>
        <text>9th | modify memory, Rary's telepathic bond</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer And Warlock p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Aberrant Mind (UA): Unique Disturbance</name>
        <text>Regardless of its genesis, the Aberrant Mind origin imparts a sense of eeriness to the character or their surroundings. This can be as subtle as when your sorcerer reads a creature's mind with detect thoughts, anyone in their immediate vicinity experiences a faint but pervasive sense of dread. Or it could be unmistakable, such as sweating a sheen of viscous mucus when you're scared, or your pupils squirming when you're excited. Consider the potentially unspeakable source of your sorcerer's powers, and use that as a guide to weave threads of eeriness throughout your magic.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer And Warlock p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Aberrant Mind (UA): Warped Being</name>
        <text>1st-level Aberrant Mind feature</text>
        <text>Starting at 1st level, your aberrant origin protects you from harm. Your body might have a coating of viscous slime, tough hide, scales, or an invisible psionic barrier (choose the form of protection when you gain this feature). Whatever form the protection takes, your AC equals 13 + your Dexterity modifier while you aren't wearing armor.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer And Warlock p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Clockwork Soul (UA): Clockwork Soul</name>
        <text>A plane of utmost order, Mechanus is a realm overseen by a godlike entity called Primus, whose actions are inscrutable and calculations, vast. You, or someone from your lineage, might have become entangled in one of the machinations of the leader of the modrons. Perhaps you were exposed to an artifact created by Primus, or your ancestor took part in the Great Modron March in some way.</text>
        <text>The power of Mechanus can seem strange and alien to others, but for you it is part of a vast and glorious system that others can't comprehend. At your option, you can pick from or roll on the Manifestations of Mechanus table to create a way your connection to the plane manifests while you are casting a spell.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Manifestations of Mechanus</text>
        <text>d6 | Manifestation</text>
        <text>1 | Large, spectral cogwheels appear hovering behind you.</text>
        <text>2 | The hands of a clock appear in your eyes.</text>
        <text>3 | Your skin glows with a golden, metallic sheen.</text>
        <text>4 | Your features become unnaturally angular, like geometric objects.</text>
        <text>5 | Your spellcasting focus takes the form of a miniature Spawning Stone or other creation of Primus.</text>
        <text>6 | The ringing of a clock can be heard by you and those affected by your magic.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt2 p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Clockwork Soul (UA): Clockwork Magic</name>
        <text>1st-level Clockwork Soul feature</text>
        <text>You learn additional spells when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown on the Clockwork Spells table. Each spell counts as a sorcerer spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of sorcerer spells you know. These spells can't be replaced when you gain a level in this class.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Clockwork Spells</text>
        <text>Sorcerer Level | Spells</text>
        <text>1st | alarm, protection from evil and good</text>
        <text>3rd | find traps, heat metal</text>
        <text>5th | counterspell, glyph of warding</text>
        <text>7th | arcane eye, Otiluke's resilient sphere</text>
        <text>9th | animate objects, wall of force</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt2 p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Clockwork Soul (UA): Restore Balance</name>
        <text>1st-level Clockwork Soul feature</text>
        <text>Your connection to the plane of absolute order allows you to equalize chaotic moments. When a creature you can see within 60 feet of you is about to roll a d20 with advantage or disadvantage, you can use your reaction to prevent the roll from being affected by advantage and disadvantage.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt2 p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psionic Soul (UA): Psionic Soul</name>
        <text>One day a light blazed forth within you—the illumination of psionic power. Your mind now simmers with this power, the full extent of which you won't fully grasp for years to come. You can touch other minds with it and alter the world around you by using it to control the magical energy of the multiverse. Will this power shine from you as a hopeful beacon to others? Or will you be a source of terror to those who feel the stab of your mind and witness the strange manifestations of your might?</text>
        <text>Among githyanki and githzerai, the powers of Psionic Soul sorcerers are revered and marshaled on both sides of the gith war. In Eberron, many kalashtar dream of discovering this origin's abilities within themselves, and in Athas, more sorcerers are born with a Psionic Soul than with any other source of power. In the glades of primeval woods touched by the Feywild, children sometimes awaken to the wonders of psionic power. And in communities that survive Far Realm incursions, some folk are mutated into horrific aberrations, while a lucky few not only remain themselves, but also discover that psionic energy now suffuses their minds.</text>
        <text>As a Psionic Soul sorcerer, you decide how you acquired your powers. Were you born with them, and did they manifest throughout childhood? Or did an extraordinary event later in life leave you shining with psionic awareness? Consult the Psionic Origins table for a possible origin of your power.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Psionic Origins</text>
        <text>d10 | Origin</text>
        <text>1 | You were exposed to the Far Realm's warping influence. You can now use your mind in ways you never thought possible, and you're also convinced that a tendril is growing upon you.</text>
        <text>2 | A psychic wind from the Astral Plane carried psionic energy into your being. When you use your powers now, faint motes of light sparkle around you.</text>
        <text>3 | You or your ancestor were trained by a githzerai monk to unlock the psionic potential within yourself.</text>
        <text>4 | A spirit haunts your mind, lending incredible power to your thoughts. When you sleep, the spirit's memories invade your dreams.</text>
        <text>5 | Deep in a forest touched by the Feywild, you drank from a glimmering stream, and now your mind shines with power. Beasts and fey creatures are often now friendly to you, as if they can sense the light within you.</text>
        <text>6 | Upon recovering from a near-fatal injury, you found yourself with psionic powers. Whenever you use them, your old wound tingles.</text>
        <text>7 | You were implanted with a mind flayer tadpole, but the ceremorphosis never completed. And now the psionic power is yours. When you use it, your flesh shines with a strange mucus.</text>
        <text>8 | As a child, you had an imaginary friend that looked like a flumph or a strange platypuslike creature. One day, it gifted you with psionic powers, which have ended up being not so imaginary.</text>
        <text>9 | Your nightmares whisper the truth to you: your psionic powers are not your own. You draw them from your vestigial twin!</text>
        <text>10 | You grew up near the lair of a sapphire dragon, and now your eyes glow with sapphire light when you use your newfound powers.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psionic Soul (UA): Psionic Talent</name>
        <text>1st-level Psionic Soul feature</text>
        <text>You harbor a wellspring of psionic power within yourself, an energy that ebbs and flows as you channel it in various ways. This power is represented by your Psionic Talent die, the starting size of which is a d6.</text>
        <name>Psionic Soul (UA): Psionic Talent Options</name>
        <text>   You can use your Psionic Talent die in the following ways:</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>   Psionic Discovery.</text>
        <text>• You can unlock the ability to cast a mind-oriented sorcerer spell you don't already know. After meditating for 10 minutes (which can be done during a rest), roll your Psionic Talent die, and choose a sorcerer spell of a level for which you have spell slots and that is in the school of divination or enchantment. You know the chosen spell for a number of hours equal to the number you rolled.</text>
        <text>   Psychic Sorcery.</text>
        <text>• When you cast a spell, you can use your mind to form it, rather than relying on words, gestures, and materials. To do so, roll your Psionic Talent die. The spell then requires no verbal component, and if you rolled the level of the spell or higher, the spell doesn't require somatic or material components either.</text>
        <text>   Telepathic Speech.</text>
        <text>• You can form a telepathic connection between your mind and the mind of another. As a bonus action, choose one creature you can see, and roll your Psionic Talent die. For a number of hours equal to the number you rolled, you and the chosen creature can speak telepathically with each other while the two of you are within a number of miles of each other equal to the number you rolled. To understand each other, you each must speak mentally in a language the other knows. The telepathic connection ends early if you use this ability to form a connection with a different creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <name>Psionic Soul (UA): Changing the Die's Size</name>
        <text>   If you roll the highest number on your Psionic Talent die, it decreases by one die size after the roll. This represents you burning through your psionic energy. For example, if the die is a d6 and you roll a 6, it becomes a d4. If it's a d4 and you roll a 4, it becomes unusable until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>   Conversely, if you roll a 1 on your Psionic Talent die, it increases by one die size after the roll, up to its starting size. This represents you conserving psionic energy for later use. For example, if you roll a 1 on a d4, the die then becomes a d6.</text>
        <text>   Whenever you finish a long rest, your Psionic Talent die resets to its starting size. When you reach certain levels in this class, the starting size of your Psionic Talent die increases: at 5th level (d8), 11th level (d10), and 17th level (d12).</text>
        <name>Psionic Soul (UA): Psi Replenishment</name>
        <text>   As a bonus action, you can calm your mind for a moment and restore your Psionic Talent die to its starting size. You then can't use Psi Replenishment again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Spell Versatility</name>
        <text>1st-level sorcerer feature (enhances Spellcasting)</text>
        <text>Whenever you finish a long rest, you can replace one spell you learned from this Spellcasting feature with another spell from the sorcerer spell list. The new spell must be the same level as the spell you replace.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 10</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <slots>4, 3</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature>
          <name>Font of Magic</name>
        <text>At 2nd level, you tap into a deep wellspring of magic within yourself. This wellspring is represented by sorcery points, which allow you to create a variety of magical effects.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Sorcery Points:</text>
        <text>   You have 2 sorcery points, and you gain one additional point every time you level up, to a maximum of 20 at level 20. You can never have more sorcery points than shown on the table for your level. You regain all spent sorcery points when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 99</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature>
          <name>Font of Magic Options</name>
        <text>2nd-level sorcerer feature (enhances Font of Magic)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Font of Magic feature, you get access to the following ways to spend your sorcery points.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 10</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <slots>4, 4, 2</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature>
          <name>Metamagic</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain the ability to twist your spells to suit your needs. You gain two of the following Metamagic options of your choice. You gain another one at 10th and 17th level.</text>
        <text>You can use only one Metamagic option on a spell when you cast it, unless otherwise noted.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 99</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Metamagic: Careful Spell</name>
        <text>When you cast a spell that forces other creatures to make a saving throw, you can protect some of those creatures from the spell's full force. To do so, you spend 1 sorcery point and choose a number of those creatures up to your Charisma modifier (minimum of one creature). A chosen creature automatically succeeds on its saving throw against the spell.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 102</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Metamagic: Distant Spell</name>
        <text>When you cast a spell that has a range of 5 feet or greater, you can spend 1 sorcery point to double the range of the spell.</text>
        <text>When you cast a spell that has a range of touch, you can spend 1 sorcery point to make the range of the spell 30 feet.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 102</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Metamagic: Empowered Spell</name>
        <text>When you roll damage for a spell, you can spend 1 sorcery point to reroll a number of the damage dice up to your Charisma modifier (minimum of one). You must use the new rolls.</text>
        <text>You can use Empowered Spell even if you have already used a different Metamagic option during the casting of the spell.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 102</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Metamagic: Extended Spell</name>
        <text>When you cast a spell that has a duration of 1 minute or longer, you can spend 1 sorcery point to double its duration, to a maximum duration of 24 hours.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 102</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Metamagic: Heightened Spell</name>
        <text>When you cast a spell that forces a creature to make a saving throw to resist its effects, you can spend 3 sorcery points to give one target of the spell disadvantage on its first saving throw made against the spell.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 102</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Metamagic: Quickened Spell</name>
        <text>When you cast a spell that has a casting time of 1 action, you can spend 2 sorcery points to change the casting time to 1 bonus action for this casting.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 102</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Metamagic: Subtle Spell</name>
        <text>When you cast a spell, you can spend 1 sorcery point to cast it without any somatic or verbal components.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 102</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Metamagic: Twinned Spell</name>
        <text>When you cast a spell that targets only one creature and doesn't have a range of self, you can spend a number of sorcery points equal to the spell's level to target a second creature in range with the same spell (1 sorcery point if the spell is a cantrip).</text>
        <text>To be eligible, a spell must be incapable of targeting more than one creature at the spell's current level. For example, magic missile and scorching ray aren't eligible, but ray of frost and chromatic orb are.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 102</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature>
          <name>Metamagic Options</name>
        <text>3rd-level sorcerer feature (enhances Metamagic)</text>
        <text>When you choose Metamagic options, you have access to the following additional options.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 10</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Metamagic Options: Elemental Spell</name>
        <text>When you cast a spell that deals a type of damage from the following list, you can spend 1 sorcery point to change that damage type to one of the other listed types: acid, cold, fire, lightning, thunder.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 10</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Metamagic Options: Seeking Spell</name>
        <text>When you cast a spell that requires you to make a spell attack roll or that forces a target to make a Dexterity saving throw, you can spend 1 sorcery point to ignore the effects of half- and three-quarters cover against targets of the spell.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 10</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Metamagic Options: Unerring Spell</name>
        <text>If you make an attack roll for a spell and miss, you can spend 2 sorcery points to reroll the attack roll. You must use the result of the second roll.</text>
        <text>You can use Unerring Spell even if you have already used a different Metamagic option during the casting of the spell.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 10</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4">
        <slots>5, 4, 3</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 4th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 99</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>4th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
        <slots>5, 4, 3, 2</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <slots>5, 4, 3, 3</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature>
          <name>Sorcerous Origin feature</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain a feature granted by your Sorcerous Origin.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 99</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Draconic Bloodline: Elemental Affinity</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, when you cast a spell that deals damage of the type associated with your draconic ancestry, you can add your Charisma modifier to one damage roll of that spell. At the same time, you can spend 1 sorcery point to gain resistance to that damage type for 1 hour.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 102</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Wild Magic: Bend Luck</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you have the ability to twist fate using your wild magic. When another creature you can see makes an attack roll, an ability check, or a saving throw, you can use your reaction and spend 2 sorcery points to roll 1d4 and apply the number rolled as a bonus or penalty (your choice) to the creature's roll. You can do so after the creature rolls but before any effects of the roll occur.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 103</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul (UA): Extra Attack</name>
        <text>Beginning at 6th level, you can attack twice, instead of once, whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 8</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul v2 (UA): Blessed Countenance</name>
        <text>At 6th level, your divine essence causes you to undergo a minor physical transformation. Your appearance takes on an otherworldly version of one of the following qualities (your choice): beautiful, youthful, kind, or imposing.</text>
        <text>Whatever your choice, if your proficiency bonus applies to a Charisma check, double that bonus.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul v3 (UA): Empowered Healing</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, the celestial energy coursing through you can empower your healing magic. Whenever you roll dice to determine the number of hit points a sorcerer spell of yours restores, you can spend 1 sorcery point to reroll any number of those dice once.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery (UA): Heart of the Storm</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain resistance to lightning and thunder damage. Whenever you cast a spell other than a cantrip that deals lightning or thunder damage, a stormy aura surrounds you. In addition to the spell's effects, creatures of your choice within 10 feet of you take lightning or thunder damage (choose each time this ability activates) equal to half your sorcerer level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Waterborne Adventures p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery (UA): Storm Guide</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to subtly control the weather around you.</text>
        <text>If it is raining, you can use an action to cause the rain to stop falling in a 20‐foot radius centered on you. You can end this effect as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>If it is windy, you can use a bonus action each round to choose the direction that the wind blows in a 100‐foot radius around you. The wind blows in that direction until the end of your next turn. You have no ability to alter the speed of the wind.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Waterborne Adventures p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Heart of the Storm</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain resistance to lightning and thunder damage. In addition, whenever you cast a spell of 1st level or higher that deals lightning or thunder damage, stormy magic erupts from you. This eruption causes creatures of your choice that you can see within 10 feet of you to take lightning or thunder damage (choose each time this ability activates) equal to half your sorcerer level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Storm Guide</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to subtly control the weather around you.</text>
        <text>If it is raining, you can use an action to cause the rain to stop falling in a 20-foot radius centered on you. You can end this effect as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>If it is windy, you can use a bonus action each round to choose the direction that the wind blows in a 100-foot radius around you. The wind blows in that direction until the end of your next turn. You have no ability to alter the speed of the wind.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Heart of the Storm</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain resistance to lightning and thunder damage. In addition, whenever you start casting a spell of 1st level or higher that deals lightning or thunder damage, stormy magic erupts from you. This eruption causes creatures of your choice that you can see within 10 feet of you to take lightning or thunder damage (choose each time this ability activates) equal to half your sorcerer level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Storm Guide</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to subtly control the weather around you.</text>
        <text>If it is raining, you can use an action to cause the rain to stop falling in a 20-foot-radius sphere centered on you. You can end this effect as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>If it is windy, you can use a bonus action each round to choose the direction that the wind blows in a 100-foot-radius sphere centered on you. The wind blows in that direction until the end of your next turn. This feature doesn't alter the speed of the wind.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Shadow (UA): Hound of Ill Omen</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to call forth a howling creature of darkness to harass your foes. As a bonus action, you can spend 3 sorcery points to summon a hound of ill omen to target one creature you can see. The hound uses a dire wolf's statistics with the following changes:</text>
        <text>• The hound is size Medium.</text>
        <text>• It can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. The hound takes 5 force damage if it ends its turn inside an object.</text>
        <text>• At the start of its turn, the hound automatically knows its target's location. If the target was hidden, it is no longer hidden from the hound.</text>
        <text>The hound appears in an unoccupied space of your choice within 30 feet of the target. Roll initiative for the hound. On its turn, it can move only towards its target by the most direct route, and it can use its action only to attack its target. The hound makes opportunity attack, but only against its target. Additionally, the target has disadvantage on all saving throws against your spells while the hound is within 5 feet of it. The hound disappears if it is reduced to 0 hit points, if its target is reduced to 0 hit points, or after 5 minutes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Phoenix Sorcery (UA): Phoenix Spark</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, the fiery energy within you grows restless and vengeful. In the face of defeat, it surges outward to preserve you in a fiery roar.</text>
        <text>If you are reduced to 0 hit points, you can use your reaction to draw on the spark of the phoenix. You are instead reduced to 1 hit point, and each creature within 10 feet of you takes fire damage equal to half your sorcerer level + your Charisma modifier.</text>
        <text>If you use this feature while under the effects of your Mantle of Flame, this feature instead deals fire damage equal to your sorcerer level + double your Charisma modifier, and your Mantle of Flame immediately ends.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sea Sorcery (UA): Watery Defense</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain resistance to fire damage.</text>
        <text>You also gain the ability to defend yourself by momentarily assuming a watery form. As a reaction when you are hit by an attack and take bludgeoning, piercing, or slashing damage from it, you can reduce that damage by an amount equal to your sorcerer level plus your Charisma score, and then you can move up to 30 feet without provoking opportunity attacks. Once you use this special reaction, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Stone Sorcery (UA): Stone Aegis</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, your command of earth magic grows stronger, allowing you to harness it for your allies' protection.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, you can grant an aegis to one allied creature you can see within 60 feet of you. The aegis is a dim, gray aura of earth magic that protects the target. Any bludgeoning, piercing, or slashing damage the target takes is reduced by 2 + your sorcerer level divided by 4. This effect lasts for 1 minute, until you use it again, or until you are incapacitated.</text>
        <text>In addition, when a creature you can see within 60 feet of you hits the protected target with a melee attack, you can use your reaction to teleport to an unoccupied space you can see within 5 feet of the attacker. You can teleport only if you and the attacker are on the same surface. You can then make one melee weapon attack against the attacker. If that attack hits, it deals an extra 1d10 force damage. This extra damage increases to 2d10 at 11th level and 3d10 at 17th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Pyromancer (PSK): Fire in the Veins</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain resistance to fire damage. In addition, spells you cast ignore resistance to fire damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Plane Shift: Kaladesh p. 9</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Divine Soul: Empowered Healing</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, the divine energy coursing through you can empower healing spells. Whenever you or an ally within 5 feet of you rolls dice to determine the number of hit points a spell restores, you can spend 1 sorcery point to reroll any number of those dice once, provided you aren't incapacitated. You can use this feature only once per turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Shadow Magic: Hound of Ill Omen</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to call forth a howling creature of darkness to harass your foes. As a bonus action, you can spend 3 sorcery points to magically summon a hound of ill omen to target one creature you can see within 120 feet of you. The hound uses the dire wolf's statistics (see the Monster Manual or appendix C in the Player's Handbook), with the following changes:</text>
        <text>• The hound is size Medium, not Large, and it counts as a monstrosity, not a beast.</text>
        <text>• It appears with a number of temporary hit points equal to half your sorcerer level.</text>
        <text>• It can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. The hound takes 5 force damage if it ends its turn inside an object.</text>
        <text>• At the start of its turn, the hound automatically knows its target's location. If the target was hidden, it is no longer hidden from the hound.</text>
        <text>The hound appears in an unoccupied space of your choice within 30 feet of the target. Roll initiative for the hound. On its turn, it can move only toward its target by the most direct route, and it can use its action only to attack its target. The hound can make opportunity attacks, but only against its target. Additionally, while the hound is within 5 feet of the target, the target has disadvantage on saving throws against any spell you cast. The hound disappears if it is reduced to 0 hit points, if its target is reduced to 0 hit points, or after 5 minutes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Heart of the Storm</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain resistance to lightning and thunder damage. In addition, whenever you cast a spell of 1st level or higher that deals lightning or thunder damage, stormy magic erupts from you. This eruption causes creatures of your choice that you can see within 10 feet of you to take lightning or thunder damage (choose each time this ability activates) equal to half your sorcerer level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Storm Guide</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to subtly control the weather around you.</text>
        <text>If it is raining, you can use an action to cause the rain to stop falling in a 20-foot radius centered on you. You can end this effect as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>If it is windy, you can use a bonus action each round to choose the direction that the wind blows in a 100-foot radius around you. The wind blows in that direction until the end of your next turn. You have no ability to alter the speed of the wind.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Heart of the Storm</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain resistance to lightning and thunder damage. In addition, whenever you start casting a spell of 1st level or higher that deals lightning or thunder damage, stormy magic erupts from you. This eruption causes creatures of your choice that you can see within 10 feet of you to take lightning or thunder damage (choose each time this ability activates) equal to half your sorcerer level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Storm Guide</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to subtly control the weather around you.</text>
        <text>If it is raining, you can use an action to cause the rain to stop falling in a 20-foot-radius sphere centered on you. You can end this effect as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>If it is windy, you can use a bonus action each round to choose the direction that the wind blows in a 100-foot-radius sphere centered on you. The wind blows in that direction until the end of your next turn. This feature doesn't alter the speed of the wind.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Giant Soul (UA): Soul of Lost Ostoria</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you gain a benefit whenever you cast one of the spells granted by your Mark of the Ordning Feature.</text>
        <name>Giant Soul (UA): Cloud Giant</name>
        <text>   Immediately after you cast any of your Mark of the Ordning spells, you can magically teleport as a bonus action. You teleport to an unoccupied space you can see that is no farther away than a number of feet equal to 10 + your Constitution modifier.</text>
        <name>Giant Soul (UA): Fire Giant</name>
        <text>   You gain a bonus to the damage rolls of your Mark of the Ordning spells. The bonus equals your Constitution modifier (minimum of +1).</text>
        <name>Giant Soul (UA): Frost Giant</name>
        <text>   Immediately after you cast any of your Mark of the Ordning spells, you gain temporary hit points equal to your Constitution modifier (minimum of 1). But if the spell is armor of Agathys, you instead increase its temporary hit points by an amount equal to your Constitution modifier (minimum of 1).</text>
        <name>Giant Soul (UA): Hill Giant</name>
        <text>   Immediately after you cast any of your Mark of the Ordning spells, you can target up to two creatures within 5 feet of you that you can see. Each target must succeed on a Strength saving throw against your spell save DC or be pushed a number of feet away from you equal to 5 + your Constitution modifier (minimum of +1). A target can choose to fail this save.</text>
        <name>Giant Soul (UA): Stone Giant</name>
        <text>   Immediately after you cast any of your Mark of the Ordning spells, you gain a bonus to AC equal to your Constitution modifier (minimum of +1) until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <name>Giant Soul (UA): Storm Giant</name>
        <text>   Immediately after you cast any of your Mark of the Ordning spells, up to three creatures of your choice that you can see within 30 feet of you take lightning damage equal to your Constitution modifier (minimum of 1).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Giant Soul Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Aberrant Mind (UA): Psionic Sorcery</name>
        <text>6th-level Aberrant Mind feature</text>
        <text>Beginning at 6th level, when you cast any of the spells gained from your Psionic Spells feature, you can cast it by expending a spell slot as normal or by spending a number of sorcery points equal to the spell's level. If you cast the spell using sorcery points, it requires no components.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer And Warlock p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Aberrant Mind (UA): Psychic Defenses</name>
        <text>6th-level Aberrant Mind feature</text>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain resistance to psychic damage, and you have advantage on saving throws against being charmed or frightened.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer And Warlock p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Clockwork Soul (UA): Bulwark of Law</name>
        <text>6th-level Clockwork Soul feature</text>
        <text>You can imbue a creature with a shimmering shield of order. As an action, you can expend 1 to 5 sorcery points to create a magical ward around yourself or another creature you can see within 30 feet of you. The ward lasts until you finish a long rest or until you use this feature again.</text>
        <text>The ward is represented by a number of d8s equal to the number of sorcery points spent to create it. When the warded creature takes damage, it can use its reaction to spend a number of those dice, roll them, and reduce the damage taken by the total of the spent dice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt2 p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psionic Soul (UA): Psychic Strike</name>
        <text>6th-level Psionic Soul feature</text>
        <text>You have learned to channel additional psychic energy into your spells. Immediately after you deal damage to a creature with a sorcerer spell for which you expend a spell slot, you can roll your Psionic Talent die and also deal psychic damage to that creature equal to the number rolled. You can deal this extra damage only once per turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <slots>5, 4, 3, 3, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
        <slots>5, 4, 3, 3, 2</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 8th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 99</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>8th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
        <slots>5, 4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <slots>6, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature>
          <name>Metamagic</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you learn an additional metamagic option.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 99</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <slots>6, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12">
        <slots>6, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 12th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 99</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>12th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
        <slots>6, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <slots>6, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature>
          <name>Sorcerous Origin feature</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you gain a feature granted by your Sorcerous Origin.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 99</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Draconic Bloodline: Dragon Wings</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you gain the ability to sprout a pair of dragon wings from your back, gaining a flying speed equal to your current speed. You can create these wings as a bonus action on your turn. They last until you dismiss them as a bonus action on your turn.</text>
        <text>You can't manifest your wings while wearing armor unless the armor is made to accommodate them, and clothing not made to accommodate your wings might be destroyed when you manifest them.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 102</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Wild Magic: Controlled Chaos</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you gain a modicum of control over the surges of your wild magic. Whenever you roll on the Wild Magic Surge table, you can roll twice and use either number.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 103</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul (UA): Divine Wings</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you gain the ability to sprout a pair of wings from your back (feathered or bat-like, your choice), gaining a flying speed equal to your current walking speed. You can create these wings as a bonus action on your turn. They last until you dismiss them as a bonus action on your turn.</text>
        <text>You can't manifest your wings while wearing armor unless the armor is made to accommodate them, and clothing not made to accommodate your wings might be destroyed when you manifest them.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 8</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul v2 (UA): Divine Purity</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you become immune to disease, poison damage, and the poisoned condition.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul v3 (UA): Angelic Form</name>
        <text>At 14th level, your divine essence causes you to undergo a minor physical transformation. Your appearance takes on an otherworldly version of one of the following qualities (your choice): beautiful, youthful, kind, or imposing.</text>
        <text>In addition, as a bonus action, you can manifest a pair of spectral wings from your back. The wings last until you're incapacitated or you dismiss them as a bonus action. While the wings are present, you have a flying speed of 30 feet.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery (UA): Storm's Fury</name>
        <text>At 14th level, the storm energy you channel through your magic seethes within your soul. When you are hit by a melee attack, you can use your reaction to deal lightning damage to the attacker equal to your sorcerer level. The attacker must also make a Strength saving throw, with a DC equal to 8 + your Charisma bonus + your proficiency bonus. On a failed save, the attacker is pushed in a straight line 20 feet away from you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Waterborne Adventures p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Storm's Fury</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, when you are hit by a melee attack, you can use your reaction to deal lightning damage to the attacker. The damage equals your sorcerer level. The attacker must also make a Strength saving throw against your sorcerer spell save DC. On a failed save, the attacker is pushed in a straight line up to 20 feet away from you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Storm's Fury</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, when you are hit by a melee attack, you can use your reaction to deal lightning damage to the attacker. The damage equals your sorcerer level. The attacker must also make a Strength saving throw against your sorcerer spell save DC. On a failed save, the attacker is pushed in a straight line up to 20 feet away from you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Shadow (UA): Shadow Walk</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you gain the ability to step from one shadow into another. When you are in dim light or darkness, as a bonus action, you can teleport up to 120 feet to an unoccupied space you can see that is also in dim light or darkness.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Phoenix Sorcery (UA): Nourishing Fire</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, your fire spells soothe and restore you. When you expend a spell slot to cast a spell that includes a fire damage roll, you regain hit points equal to the slot's level + your Charisma modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sea Sorcery (UA): Shifting Form</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, you gain the ability to enter a liquid state while moving.</text>
        <text>When you move on your turn, you take only half damage from opportunity attacks, and you can move through any enemy's space but can't willingly end your move there.</text>
        <text>On your turn, you can move through any space that is at least 3 inches in diameter and do so without squeezing. When you stop moving, the regular squeezing rules apply if you're in a space one size smaller than you. You can't willingly stop in a space smaller than that, and if you're forced to do so, you immediately flow to the nearest space that can fit you, back along the path of your movement.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Stone Sorcery (UA): Stone's Edge</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, your mastery of earth magic allows you to add the force of elemental earth to your spells. When you cast a spell that deals damage, choose one creature damaged by that spell on the round you cast it. That creature takes extra force damage equal to half your sorcerer level. This feature can be used only once per casting of a spell.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Pyromancer (PSK): Pyromancer's Fury</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, when you are hit by a melee attack, you can use your reaction to deal fire damage to the attacker. The damage equals your sorcerer level, and ignores resistance to fire damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Plane Shift: Kaladesh p. 9</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Divine Soul: Otherworldly Wings</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, you can use a bonus action to manifest a pair of spectral wings from your back. While the wings are present, you have a flying speed of 30 feet. The wings last until you're incapacitated, you die, or you dismiss them as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>The affinity you chose for your Divine Magic feature determines the appearance of the spectral wings: eagle wings for good or law, bat wings for evil or chaos, and dragonfly wings for neutrality.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Shadow Magic: Shadow Walk</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you gain the ability to step from one shadow into another. When you are in dim light or darkness, as a bonus action, you can magically teleport up to 120 feet to an unoccupied space you can see that is also in dim light or darkness.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Storm's Fury</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, when you are hit by a melee attack, you can use your reaction to deal lightning damage to the attacker. The damage equals your sorcerer level. The attacker must also make a Strength saving throw against your sorcerer spell save DC. On a failed save, the attacker is pushed in a straight line up to 20 feet away from you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Storm's Fury</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, when you are hit by a melee attack, you can use your reaction to deal lightning damage to the attacker. The damage equals your sorcerer level. The attacker must also make a Strength saving throw against your sorcerer spell save DC. On a failed save, the attacker is pushed in a straight line up to 20 feet away from you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Giant Soul (UA): Rage of Fallen Ostoria</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, you gain the ability to channel the souls of your ancestors into your physical form. When you start casting a sorcerer spell on your turn and expend a spell slot, you can increase your size by one category—from Medium to Large, for example.</text>
        <text>This increase lasts for 1 minute. It ends early if you die or are incapacitated. Until it ends, you enjoy the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• Your current hit points and your hit point maximum both increase by 1 per sorcerer level.</text>
        <text>• Your reach increases by 5 feet.</text>
        <text>• Your walking speed increases by 5 feet.</text>
        <text>• You have advantage on Strength checks and Strength saving throws.</text>
        <text>• You gain a bonus to the damage rolls of your melee weapon attacks; the bonus equals your Constitution modifier (minimum of +1).</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Giant Soul Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Aberrant Mind (UA): Revelation in Flesh</name>
        <text>14th-level Aberrant Mind feature</text>
        <text>Beginning at 14th level, you can unleash the aberrant truth hidden within your flesh. As a bonus action, you can spend 1 or more sorcery points to magically transform your body for 1 minute. For each sorcery point you spend, you can gain one of the following benefits of your choice, the effects of which last until the transformation ends:</text>
        <text>• You gain a swimming speed equal to your walking speed and the ability to breathe water. Gills grow from your neck or fan out from behind your ears, your fingers become webbed, or you grow lashing cilia that extend through your clothing.</text>
        <text>• You gain a flying speed equal to your walking speed and can hover. As you fly, your skin glistens with mucus.</text>
        <text>• Your body, along with any equipment you are wearing or carrying, becomes slimy and pliable. You can move through any space as narrow as 1 inch without squeezing, and you can spend 5 feet of movement to escape from nonmagical restraints or being grappled.</text>
        <text>• Your eyes turn black or become writhing sensory tendrils. You are aware of the location of any hidden or invisible creature within 60 feet of you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer And Warlock p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Clockwork Soul (UA): Trance of Order</name>
        <text>14th-level Clockwork Soul feature</text>
        <text>You gain the ability to enter a state of clockwork consciousness as a bonus action. For the next minute, attack rolls against you can't benefit from advantage, and whenever you make an attack roll, an ability check, or a saving throw, you can treat a d20 roll of 9 or lower as a 10.</text>
        <text>Once you use this action, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest or until you expend 5 sorcery points to use it again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt2 p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psionic Soul (UA): Mind Over Body</name>
        <text>14th-level Psionic Soul feature</text>
        <text>You can now use the psi that flows through you to give your body extraordinary abilities. As a bonus action, you can roll your Psionic Talent die and spend 1 or more sorcery points to magically transform yourself for a number of hours equal to the number rolled. Until the transformation ends, you gain one of the following benefits of your choice for each sorcery point you spent, choosing a different benefit for each point:</text>
        <text>• You can see any invisible creature within 60 feet of you, provided it isn't behind total cover.</text>
        <text>• You gain a flying speed equal to your walking speed, and you can hover.</text>
        <text>• You gain a swimming speed equal to twice your walking speed, and you can breathe underwater.</text>
        <text>• Your body, along with any equipment you are wearing or carrying, becomes pliable. You can move through any space as narrow as 1 inch without squeezing, and you can spend 5 feet of movement to escape from nonmagical restraints or being grappled.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <slots>6, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16">
        <slots>6, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 16th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 99</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>16th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <slots>6, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature>
          <name>Metamagic</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you learn an additional metamagic option.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 99</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <slots>6, 4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature>
          <name>Sorcerous Origin feature</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you gain a feature granted by your Sorcerous Origin.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 99</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Draconic Bloodline: Draconic Presence</name>
        <text>Beginning at 18th level, you can channel the dread presence of your dragon ancestor, causing those around you to become awestruck or frightened. As an action, you can spend 5 sorcery points to draw on this power and exude an aura of awe or fear (your choice) to a distance of 60 feet. For 1 minute or until you lose your concentration (as if you were casting a concentration spell), each hostile creature that starts its turn in this aura must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or be charmed (if you chose awe) or frightened (if you chose fear) until the aura ends. A creature that succeeds on this saving throw is immune to your aura for 24 hours.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 102</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Wild Magic: Spell Bombardment</name>
        <text>Beginning at 18th level, the harmful energy of your spells intensifies. When you roll damage for a spell and roll the highest number possible on any of the dice, choose one of those dice, roll it again and add that roll to the damage. You can use the feature only once per turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 103</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul (UA): Power of the Chosen</name>
        <text>Starting at 18th level, when you cast one of the spells you learned from your Chosen of the Gods class feature, you regain hit points equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of +1) + the spell's level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 8</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul v2 (UA): Unearthly Recovery</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you gain the ability to overcome grievous injuries. As a bonus action when you have less than half of your hit points remaining, you can regain a number of hit points equal to half your hit point maximum.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul v3 (UA): Unearthly Recovery</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you gain the ability to overcome grievous injuries. As a bonus action when you have less than half of your hit points remaining, you can regain a number of hit points equal to half your hit point maximum.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery (UA): Wind Soul</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you gain a flying speed of 60 feet and immunity to lightning and thunder damage. As an action, you can reduce your flying speed to 30 feet for one hour and choose a number of creatures within 30 feet of you equal to 3 + your Charisma modifier. The chosen creatures gain a flying speed of 30 feet for 1 hour.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Waterborne Adventures p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Wind Soul</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you gain a flying speed of 60 feet and immunity to lightning and thunder damage.</text>
        <text>As an action, you can reduce your flying speed to 30 feet for one hour and choose a number of creatures within 30 feet of you equal to 3 + your Charisma modifier. The chosen creatures gain a flying speed of 30 feet for 1 hour.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Wind Soul</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you gain immunity to lightning and thunder damage.</text>
        <text>You also gain a magical flying speed of 60 feet. As an action, you can reduce your flying speed to 30 feet for 1 hour and choose a number of creatures within 30 feet of you equal to 3 + your Charisma modifier. The chosen creatures gain a magical flying speed of 30 feet for 1 hour. Once you reduce your flying speed in this way, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 137</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Shadow (UA): Shadow Form</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you can spend 3 sorcery points to transform yourself into a shadow form as a bonus action. In this form, you have resistance to all damage except force damage, and you can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. You take 5 force damage if you end your turn inside an object. You remain in this form for 1 minute.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Phoenix Sorcery (UA): Form of the Phoenix</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you finally master the spark of fire that dances within you. While under the effect of your Mantle of Flame feature, you gain additional benefits:</text>
        <text>• You have a flying speed of 40 feet and can hover.</text>
        <text>• You have resistance to all damage.</text>
        <text>• If you use your Phoenix Spark, that feature deals an extra 20 fire damage to each creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sea Sorcery (UA): Water Soul</name>
        <text>Starting at 18th level, your being is altered by the power of the sea. You gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• You no longer need to eat, drink, or sleep.</text>
        <text>• A critical hit against you becomes a normal hit.</text>
        <text>• You have resistance to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Stone Sorcery (UA): Earth Master's Aegis</name>
        <text>Beginning at 18th level, when you use your Stone Aegis to protect an ally, you can choose up to three creatures to gain its benefits.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Pyromancer (PSK): Fiery Soul</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you gain immunity to fire damage. In addition, any spell or effect you create ignores resistance to fire damage and treats immunity to fire damage as resistance to fire damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Plane Shift: Kaladesh p. 9</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Divine Soul: Unearthly Recovery</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you gain the ability to overcome grievous injuries. As a bonus action when you have fewer than half of your hit points remaining, you can regain a number of hit points equal to half your hit point maximum.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Shadow Magic: Umbral Form</name>
        <text>Starting at 18th level, you can spend 6 sorcery points as a bonus action to magically transform yourself into a shadowy form. In this form, you have resistance to all damage except force and radiant damage, and you can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. You take 5 force damage if you end your turn inside an object.</text>
        <text>You remain in this form for 1 minute. It ends early if you are incapacitated, if you die, or if you dismiss it as a bonus action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 50</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Wind Soul</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you gain a flying speed of 60 feet and immunity to lightning and thunder damage.</text>
        <text>As an action, you can reduce your flying speed to 30 feet for one hour and choose a number of creatures within 30 feet of you equal to 3 + your Charisma modifier. The chosen creatures gain a flying speed of 30 feet for 1 hour.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Storm Sorcery: Wind Soul</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you gain immunity to lightning and thunder damage.</text>
        <text>You also gain a magical flying speed of 60 feet. As an action, you can reduce your flying speed to 30 feet for 1 hour and choose a number of creatures within 30 feet of you equal to 3 + your Charisma modifier. The chosen creatures gain a magical flying speed of 30 feet for 1 hour. Once you reduce your flying speed in this way, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 51</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Giant Soul (UA): Blessing of the All Father</name>
        <text>At 18th level, your Constitution score increases by 2, up to a maximum of 22.</text>
        <text>In addition, you can now use Rage of Fallen Ostoria twice between rests, but no more than once on a turn. If you use that feature while under its effects, its increases to your size, hit points, reach, and walking speed are cumulative.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Giant Soul Sorcerer p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Aberrant Mind (UA): Warp Reality</name>
        <text>18th-level Aberrant Mind feature</text>
        <text>At 18th level, you become the focal point of a reality-warping anomaly. As an action, you can magically radiate a transparent, 20-foot-radius aura for 1 minute. This might take the form of a sphere of rippling psychic energy, a fluctuating amoebic gel, an extrusion of ephemeral parasites, or some other manifestation. Other creatures treat the aura as difficult terrain, and when they start their turn in it, they take 2d10 psychic damage. When you activate this feature, you can choose any number of creatures you can see to be unaffected by the aura.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, you can end the aura early. If you do so, you and any number of creatures you choose within the aura are teleported to a location you can see within 1 mile of you. Each creature must appear within 20 feet of you and in an unoccupied space. An unwilling creature that succeeds on a Charisma saving throw against your spell save DC is not teleported. Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Sorcerer And Warlock p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Clockwork Soul (UA): Clockwork Cavalcade</name>
        <text>18th-level Clockwork Soul feature</text>
        <text>You summon spirits of order to restore balance around you. As an action, you summon the spirits in a 30-foot cube originating from you. The spirits look like modrons or other constructs of your choice. The spirits are intangible and invulnerable, work fast and efficiently, and create the following effects within the cube before vanishing:</text>
        <text>• The spirits restore up to 100 hit points, divided as you choose among any number of creatures of your choice in the cube.</text>
        <text>• Any damaged objects entirely in the cube are repaired.</text>
        <text>• Every spell of 6th level or lower ends on creatures and objects of your choice in the cube.</text>
        <text>Once you use this action, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest or until you expend 7 sorcery points to use it again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt2 p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psionic Soul (UA): Psychic Aura</name>
        <text>18th-level Psionic Soul feature</text>
        <text>If your Psionic Talent die is available, you can unleash your psionic power in a crackling aura of psychic energy; as a bonus action, you can magically radiate this transparent, 30-foot-radius aura for 1 minute or until you're incapacitated or lose the use of your Psionic Talent die.</text>
        <text>Whenever a creature starts its turn in the aura or moves into it for the first time on a turn, you can roll your Psionic Talent die and deal psychic damage to the creature, equaling the number rolled plus your Charisma modifier. If the creature takes any of this damage, its speed is halved until the start of its next turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19">
        <slots>6, 4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 19th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 99</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>19th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
        <slots>6, 4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 2, 2, 1, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
        <feature>
          <name>Sorcerous Restoration</name>
        <text>At 20th level, you regain 4 expended sorcery points whenever you finish a short rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 99</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
