<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Fighter</name>
    <hd>10</hd>
    <proficiency>Strength, Constitution, Acrobatics, Animal Handling, Athletics, History, Insight, Intimidation, Perception, Survival</proficiency>
    <numSkills>2</numSkills>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Starting Fighter</name>
        <text>As a 1st-level Fighter, you begin play with 10+your Constitution modifier hit points.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>You are proficient with the following items, in addition to any proficiencies provided by your race or background.</text>
        <text>• Armor: light, medium, heavy, shields</text>
        <text>• Weapons: simple, martial</text>
        <text>• Tools: none</text>
        <text>• Skills: Choose 2 from Acrobatics, Animal Handling, Athletics, History, Insight, Intimidation, Perception, Survival</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>You begin play with the following equipment, in addition to any equipment provided by your background.</text>
        <text>• (a) chain mail or (b) leather armor, longbow, and arrows (20)</text>
        <text>• (a) a martial weapon and a shield or (b) two martial weapons</text>
        <text>• (a) a light crossbow and crossbow bolts (20) or (b) two handaxe</text>
        <text>• (a) a dungeoneer's pack or (b) an explorer's pack</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Alternatively, you may start with 5d4 x 10 gp and choose your own equipment.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 70</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Multiclass Fighter</name>
        <text>To multiclass as a Fighter, you must meet the following prerequisites:</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>• Strength 13</text>
        <text>• Dexterity 13</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>You gain the following proficiencies:</text>
        <text>• Armor: light, medium, shields</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>• Tools: none</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 70</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <armor>light, medium, heavy, shields</armor>
    <weapons>simple, martial</weapons>
    <tools>none</tools>
    <wealth>5d4 x 10</wealth>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Fighting Style</name>
        <text>You adopt a particular style of fighting as your specialty. Choose one of the following options. You can't take the same Fighting Style option more than once, even if you get to choose again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Archery</name>
        <text>You gain a +2 bonus to attack rolls you make with ranged weapons.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Close Quarters Shooter</name>
        <text>When making a ranged attack while you are within 5 feet of a hostile creature, you do not have disadvantage on the attack roll. Your ranged attacks ignore half cover and three-quarters cover against targets within 30 feet of you. You have a +1 bonus to attack rolls on ranged attacks.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Defense</name>
        <text>While you are wearing armor, you gain a +1 bonus to AC.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Dueling</name>
        <text>When you are wielding a melee weapon in one hand and no other weapons, you gain a +2 bonus to damage rolls with that weapon.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Great Weapon Fighting</name>
        <text>When you roll a 1 or 2 on a damage die for an attack you make with a melee weapon that you are wielding with two hands, you can reroll the die and must use the new roll, even if the new roll is a 1 or a 2. The weapon must have the two-handed or versatile property for you to gain this benefit.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Mariner</name>
        <text>As long as you are not wearing heavy armor or using a shield, you have a swimming speed and a climbing speed equal to your normal speed, and you gain a +1 bonus to AC.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Waterborne Adventures p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Protection</name>
        <text>When a creature you can see attacks a target other than you that is within 5 feet of you, you can use your reaction to impose disadvantage on the attack roll. You must be wielding a shield.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Tunnel Fighter</name>
        <text>As a bonus action, you can enter a defensive stance that lasts until the start of your next turn. While in your defensive stance, you can make opportunity attacks without using your reaction, and you can use your reaction to make a melee attack against a creature that moves more than 5 feet while within your reach.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Two-Weapon Fighting</name>
        <text>When you engage in two-weapon fighting, you can add your ability modifier to the damage of the second attack.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Superior Technique</name>
        <text>You learn one maneuver of your choice from among those available to the Battle Master archetype. If a maneuver you use requires your target to make a saving throw to resist the maneuver's effects, the saving throw DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Strength or Dexterity modifier (your choice).</text>
        <text>You gain one superiority die, which is a d6 (this die is added to any superiority dice you have from another source). This die is used to fuel your maneuvers. A superiority die is expended when you use it. You regain your expended superiority dice when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Blind Fighting</name>
        <text>Being unable to see a creature doesn't impose disadvantage on your attack rolls against it, provided the creature isn't hidden from you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 12</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Interception</name>
        <text>When a creature you can see hits a target that is within 5 feet of you with an attack, you can use your reaction to reduce the damage the target takes by 1d10 + your proficiency bonus (to a minimum of 0 damage). You must be wielding a shield or a simple or martial weapon to use this reaction.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 12</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Thrown Weapon Fighting</name>
        <text>You can draw a weapon that has the thrown property as part of the attack you make with the weapon.</text>
        <text>In addition, when you hit with a ranged attack using a thrown weapon, you gain a +1 bonus to the damage roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 13</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Unarmed Fighting</name>
        <text>Your unarmed strikes can deal bludgeoning damage equal to 1d6 + your Strength modifier. If you strike with two free hands, the d6 becomes a d8.</text>
        <text>When you successfully start a grapple, you can deal 1d4 bludgeoning damage to the grappled creature. Until the grapple ends, you can also deal this damage to the creature whenever you hit it with a melee attack.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 13</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Martial Versatility</name>
        <text>1st-level feature (enhances Fighting Style)</text>
        <text>Whenever you gain a level in this class, you can replace a fighting style you know with another style available to your class. This change represents a shift of focus in your martial training and practice, causing you to lose the benefits of one style and gain the benefits of another style.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 12</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Second Wind</name>
        <text>You have a limited well of stamina that you can draw on to protect yourself from harm. On your turn, you can use a bonus action to regain hit points equal to 1d10 + your fighter level.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you must finish a short or long rest before you can use it again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Maneuver Versatility</name>
        <text>1st-level feature (enhances Maneuvers)</text>
        <text>If you know any maneuvers from the fighter's Battle Master archetype, you can replace one maneuver you know with a different maneuver whenever you finish a long rest. This change reflects your physical and mental preparation for the day ahead.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature>
          <name>Action Surge</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can push yourself beyond your normal limits for a moment. On your turn, you can take one additional action.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you must finish a short or long rest before you can use it again. Starting at 17th level, you can use it twice before a rest, but only once on the same turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature>
          <name>Martial Archetype</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you choose an archetype from the list available that you strive to emulate in your combat styles and techniques. The archetype you choose grants you features at 3rd level and again at 7th, 10th, 15th, and 18th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Martial Archetype: Champion</name>
        <text>The archetypal Champion focuses on the development of raw physical power honed to deadly perfection. Those who model themselves on this archetype combine rigorous training with physical excellence to deal devastating blows.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Champion: Improved Critical</name>
        <text>Beginning when you choose this archetype at 3rd level, your weapon attacks score a critical hit on a roll of 19 or 20.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Martial Archetype: Battle Master</name>
        <text>Those who emulate the archetypal Battle Master employ martial techniques passed down through generations. To a Battle Master, combat is an academic field, sometimes including subjects beyond battle such as weaponsmithing and calligraphy. Not every fighter absorbs the lessons of history, theory, and artistry that are reflected in the Battle Master archetype, but those who do are well-rounded fighters of great skill and knowledge.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Battle Master: Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you learn maneuvers that are fueled by special dice called superiority dice.</text>
        <name>Battle Master: Maneuvers</name>
        <text>   You learn three maneuvers of your choice, which are listed under "Maneuvers" below. Many maneuvers enhance an attack in some way. You can use only one maneuver per attack.</text>
        <text>   You learn two additional maneuvers of your choice at 7th, 10th, and 15th level. Each time you learn new maneuvers, you can also replace one maneuver you know with a different one.</text>
        <name>Battle Master: Superiority Dice</name>
        <text>   You have four superiority dice, which are d8s. A superiority die is expended when you use it. You regain all of your expended superiority dice when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>   You gain another superiority die at 7th level and one more at 15th level.</text>
        <name>Battle Master: Saving Throws</name>
        <text>   Some of your maneuvers require your target to make a saving throw to resist the maneuver's effects. The saving throw DC is calculated as follows:</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Battle Master: Maneuver Options</name>
        <text>1st-level feature (enhances Maneuvers)</text>
        <text>If you have access to maneuvers, the following maneuvers are added to the list of options available to you. Maneuvers are available to Battle Masters and to characters who have the Superior Technique fighting style or the Martial Adept feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Battle Master: Maneuvers</name>
        <text>The maneuvers are presented in alphabetical order.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Battle Master: Student of War</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain proficiency with one type of artisan's tools of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier (UA): Cavalier</name>
        <text>The archetypal Cavalier excels at mounted combat. Usually born to nobility and raised in a royal court, a Cavalier is equally at home leading a cavalry charge or exchanging witty repartee at a state dinner.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier (UA): Bonus Proficiencies</name>
        <text>When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you gain proficiency in two of the following skills of your choice: Animal Handling, Insight, Performance, or Persuasion. You can choose to gain one tool proficiency in place of one skill proficiency.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier (UA): Born to the Saddle</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you have advantage on saving throws made to avoid falling off your mount. If you fall off your mount, you always land on your feet if you are capable of taking actions. Mounting or dismounting a creature costs you only 5 feet of movement, rather than half your speed.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier (UA): Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain a set of abilities that are fueled by special dice called superiority dice.</text>
        <name>Cavalier (UA): Superiority Dice</name>
        <text>   You have four superiority dice, which are d8s. A superiority die is expended when you use it. You regain all of your expended superiority dice when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>   You gain another superiority die at 7th level and one more at 15th level.</text>
        <name>Cavalier (UA): Using Superiority Dice</name>
        <text>   You can expend superiority dice to gain a number of different benefits:</text>
        <text>• When you make a check to influence or control a creature you are riding, you can expend one superiority die to add it to the check. You apply this bonus after making the check but before learning if it was successful.</text>
        <text>• When you make a weapon attack against a creature, you can expend one superiority die to add it to the attack roll. You can use this ability before or after making the attack roll, but before any of the effects of the attack are applied.</text>
        <text>• When you make an attack with a lance while mounted, you can expend one superiority die to add it to your damage roll. In addition, the target of the attack must make a Strength saving throw (DC 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Strength modifier) or be knocked prone.</text>
        <text>• If either you or your mount is hit by an attack while you are mounted, you can expend one superiority die as a reaction, adding the number rolled to your or your mount's AC. If the attack still hits, you or your mount take half damage from it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier v2 (UA): Cavalier v2</name>
        <text>The archetypal Cavalier excels at mounted combat. Usually born among the nobility and raised at court, a Cavalier is equally at home leading a cavalry charge or exchanging repartee at a state dinner. Cavaliers also learn how to guard those in their charge from harm, often serving as the protectors of their superiors and of the weak. Drawn to right wrongs or earn prestige, many of these fighters leave their lives of comfort to embark on glorious adventure.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier v2 (UA): Bonus Proficiencies</name>
        <text>When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you gain proficiency in one of the following skills of your choice: Animal Handling, History, Insight, Performance, or Persuasion. Alternatively, you learn one language of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier v2 (UA): Born to the Saddle</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, your mastery as a rider becomes apparent. You have advantage on saving throws made to avoid falling off your mount. If you fall off your mount and descend no more than 10 feet, you can land on your feet if you're not incapacitated.</text>
        <text>Finally, mounting or dismounting a creature costs you only 5 feet of movement, rather than half your speed.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier v2 (UA): Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain a set of combat abilities, referred to as maneuvers, which are fueled by special dice called superiority dice.</text>
        <name>Cavalier v2 (UA): Superiority Dice</name>
        <text>   You have four superiority dice, which are d8s. A superiority die is expended when you use it. You regain all your expended superiority dice when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>   You gain another superiority die at 7th level and one more at 15th level.</text>
        <name>Cavalier v2 (UA): Maneuvers</name>
        <text>   You spend your superiority dice on your maneuvers. You can use more than one maneuver per turn, but no more than one maneuver per attack. You know the maneuvers detailed under "Maneuvers" below.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier v2 (UA): Maneuvers</name>
        <text>The maneuvers are presented in alphabetical order.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Martial Archetype: Eldritch Knight</name>
        <text>The archetypal Eldritch Knight combines the martial mastery common to all fighters with a careful study of magic. Eldritch Knights use magical techniques similar to those practiced by wizards. They focus their study on two of the eight schools of magic—abjuration and evocation. Abjuration spells grant an Eldritch Knight additional protection in battle, and evocation spells deal damage to many foes at once, extending the fighter's reach in combat. These knights learn a comparatively small number of spells, committing them to memory instead of keeping them in a spellbook.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 74</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Eldritch Knight: Spellcasting</name>
        <text>When you reach 3rd level, you augment your martial prowess with the ability to cast spells. See chapter 10 for the general rules of spellcasting and chapter 11 for the wizard spell list.</text>
        <name>Eldritch Knight: Cantrips</name>
        <text>   You learn two cantrips of your choice from the wizard spell list. You learn an additional wizard cantrip of your choice at 10th level.</text>
        <name>Eldritch Knight: Spell Slots</name>
        <text>   The Eldritch Knight Spellcasting table shows how many spell slots you have to cast your wizard spells of 1st level and higher. To cast one of these spells, you must expend a slot of the spell's level or higher. You regain all expended spell slots when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>   For example, if you know the 1st-level spell shield and have a 1st-level and a 2nd-level spell slot available, you can cast shield using either slot.</text>
        <name>Eldritch Knight: Spells Known of 1st-Level and Higher</name>
        <text>   You know three 1st-level wizard spells of your choice, two of which you must choose from the abjuration and evocation spells on the wizard spell list.</text>
        <text>   The Spells Known column of the Eldritch Knight Spellcasting table shows when you learn more wizard spells of 1st level or higher. Each of these spells must be an abjuration or evocation spell of your choice, and must be of a level for which you have spell slots. For instance, when you reach 7th level in this class, you can learn one new spell of 1st or 2nd level.</text>
        <text>   The spells you learn at 8th, 14th, and 20th level can come from any school of magic.</text>
        <text>   Whenever you gain a level in this class, you can replace one of the wizard spells you know with another spell of your choice from the wizard spell list. The new spell must be of a level for which you have spell slots, and it must be an abjuration or evocation spell, unless you're replacing the spell you gained at 3rd, 8th, 14th, or 20th level from any school of magic.</text>
        <name>Eldritch Knight: Spellcasting Ability</name>
        <text>   Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for your wizard spells, since you learn your spells through study and memorization. You use your Intelligence whenever a spell refers to your spellcasting ability. In addition, you use your Intelligence modifier when setting the saving throw DC for a wizard spell you cast and when making an attack roll with one.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 74</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Eldritch Knight: Weapon Bond</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn a ritual that creates a magical bond between yourself and one weapon. You perform the ritual over the course of 1 hour, which can be done during a short rest. The weapon must be within your reach throughout the ritual, at the conclusion of which you touch the weapon and forge the bond.</text>
        <text>Once you have bonded a weapon to yourself, you can't be disarmed of that weapon unless you are incapacitated. If it is on the same plane of existence, you can summon that weapon as a bonus action on your turn, causing it to teleport instantly to your hand.</text>
        <text>You can have up to two bonded weapons, but can summon only one at a time with your bonus action. If you attempt to bond with a third weapon, you must break the bond with one of the other two.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 74</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Hunter (UA): Monster Hunter</name>
        <text>As an archetypal Monster Hunter, you are an expert at defeating supernatural threats. Typically mentored by an older, experienced Monster Hunter, you learn to overcome a variety of unnatural defenses and attacks, including those of undead, lycanthropes, and other creatures of horror.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Hunter (UA): Bonus Proficiencies</name>
        <text>When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you gain proficiency in two of the following skills of your choice: Arcana, History, Insight, Investigation, Nature, or Perception. You can choose to gain proficiency with thieves' tools in place of one skill choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Hunter (UA): Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain a set of abilities that are fueled by special dice called superiority dice.</text>
        <name>Monster Hunter (UA): Superiority Dice</name>
        <text>   You have four superiority dice, which are d8s. A superiority die is expended when you use it. You regain all of your expended superiority dice when you finish a long or short rest. You gain another superiority die at 7th level and one more at 15th level.</text>
        <name>Monster Hunter (UA): Using Superiority Dice</name>
        <text>   You can expend superiority dice to gain a number of different benefits:</text>
        <text>• When you make a weapon attack against a creature, you can expend one superiority die to add it to the attack roll. You can use this ability before or after making the attack roll, but before any of the effects of the attack are applied.</text>
        <text>• When you damage a creature with a weapon attack, you can expend one superiority die to add it to the damage roll. You can use this ability after rolling damage. If the attack causes the target to make a Constitution saving throw to maintain concentration, it has disadvantage on that save.</text>
        <text>• When you make an Intelligence, a Wisdom, or a Charisma saving throw, you can expend one superiority die to add it to the roll. You can use this feature only before you learn if the save succeeded or failed.</text>
        <text>• When you make a Wisdom (Perception) check to detect a hidden creature or object, or a Wisdom (Insight) check to determine if someone is lying to you, you can expend one superiority die to add it to the roll. You can use this feature after seeing the total but before learning if you succeeded or failed.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Hunter (UA): Hunter's Mysticism</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, your study of the supernatural gives you a limited ability to use magic. You can cast detect magic as a ritual. You can cast protection from evil and good, but you cannot cast it again with this feature until you finish a long rest. Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for these spells.</text>
        <text>In addition, you gain the ability to speak one of the following languages of your choice: Abyssal, Celestial, or Infernal.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Martial Archetype: Purple Dragon Knight (Banneret)</name>
        <text>Purple Dragon Knights are warriors who hail from the kingdom of Cormyr. Pledged to protect the crown, they take the fight against evil beyond the kingdom's borders. They are tasked with wandering the land as knights errant, relying on their judgment, bravery, and fidelity to guide them in defeating evildoers.</text>
        <text>A Purple Dragon Knight inspires greatness in others by committing brave deeds in battle. The mere presence of a knight in a hamlet is enough to cause some orcs and bandits to seek easier prey. A lone knight is a skilled warrior, but a knight leading a band of allies can transform even the most poorly equipped militia into a ferocious war band.</text>
        <text>A knight prefers to lead through deeds, not words. As a knight spearheads an attack, the knight's actions can awaken reserves of courage and conviction in allies that they never suspected they had.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 128</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Purple Dragon Knight (Banneret): Rallying Cry</name>
        <text>When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you learn how to inspire your allies to fight on past their injuries.</text>
        <text>When you use your Second Wind feature, you can choose up to three creatures within 60 feet of you that are allied with you. Each one regains hit points equal to your fighter level, provided that the creature can see or hear you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 128</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Purple Dragon Knight (Banneret): Restriction: Knighthood</name>
        <text>Purple Dragon Knights are tied to a specific order of Cormyrean knighthood.</text>
        <text>Banneret serves as the generic name for this archetype if you use it in other campaign settings or to model warlords other than the Purple Dragon Knights.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 128</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Scout</name>
        <text>The archetypal Scout excels at finding safe passage through dangerous regions. Scouts usually favor light armor and ranged weapons, but they are comfortable using heavier gear when faced with intense fighting.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Bonus Proficiencies</name>
        <text>When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you gain proficiency in three of the following skills of your choice: Acrobatics, Athletics, Investigation, Medicine, Nature, Perception, Stealth, or Survival. You can choose to gain proficiency with thieves' tools in place of one skill choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain a set of abilities that are fueled by special dice called superiority dice.</text>
        <name>Scout (UA): Superiority Dice</name>
        <text>   You have four superiority dice, which are d8s. A superiority die is expended when you use it. You regain all of your expended superiority dice when you finish a long or short rest. You gain another superiority die at 7th level and one more at 15th level.</text>
        <name>Scout (UA): Using Superiority Dice</name>
        <text>   You can expend superiority dice to gain a number of different benefits:</text>
        <text>• When you make a check that allows you to apply your proficiency in Athletics, Nature, Perception, Stealth, or Survival, you can expend one superiority die to bolster the check. Add half the number rolled on the superiority die (rounding up) to your check. You apply this bonus after making the check but before learning if it was successful.</text>
        <text>• When you make a weapon attack against a creature, you can expend one superiority die to add it to the attack roll. You can use this ability before or after making the attack roll, but before any of the effects of the attack are applied.</text>
        <text>• If you are hit by an attack while wearing light or medium armor, you can expend one superiority die as a reaction, adding the number rolled to your AC. If the attack still hits, you take half damage from it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Natural Explorer</name>
        <text>You are particularly familiar with one type of natural environment and are adept at traveling and surviving in such regions. Choose one type of favored terrain: arctic, coast, desert, forest, grassland, mountain, swamp, or the Underdark. When you make an Intelligence or Wisdom check related to your favored terrain, your proficiency bonus is doubled if you are using a skill that you're proficient in.</text>
        <text>While traveling for an hour or more in your favored terrain, you gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• Difficult terrain doesn't slow your group's travel.</text>
        <text>• Your group can't become lost except by magical means.</text>
        <text>• Even when you are engaged in another activity while traveling (such as foraging, navigating, or tracking), you remain alert to danger.</text>
        <text>• If you are traveling alone, you can move stealthily at a normal pace.</text>
        <text>• When you forage, you find twice as much food as you normally would.</text>
        <text>• While tracking other creatures, you also learn their exact number, their sizes, and how long ago they passed through the area.</text>
        <text>You choose additional favored terrain types at 7th and 15th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer (UA): Arcane Archer</name>
        <text>An Arcane Archer studies a unique elven method of archery that weaves magic into attacks to produce supernatural effects. Among elves, Arcane Archers are some of their most elite warriors. These archers stand watch over the fringes of elven domains, keeping a keen eye out for trespassers and using magic-infused arrows to defeat monsters and invaders before they can reach elven settlements. Over the centuries, the methods of these elf archers have been learned by members of other races who can also balance arcane aptitude with archery.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer (UA): Arcane Arrow</name>
        <text>When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you learn to channel magic into your attacks with a longbow or shortbow.</text>
        <name>Arcane Archer (UA): Create Magic Arrow</name>
        <text>   As a bonus action on your turn, you can create one magic arrow in your hand. The arrow lasts until the end of the turn or until it hits or misses a target. You can fire the arrow from a shortbow or longbow. The arrow is a magic weapon that deals an additional 2d6 force damage on a hit.</text>
        <text>   You have two uses of this feature, and you regain all expended uses of it when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <name>Arcane Archer (UA): Arcane Shot</name>
        <text>   When you gain this feature, you learn two Arcane Shot options of your choice (see the Arcane Shots section below). Whenever you create a magic arrow with this feature, you can apply the benefits of one of your Arcane Shot options to that arrow.</text>
        <text>   You gain an additional Arcane Shot option of your choice at 7th, 10th, 15th, and 18th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer (UA): Arcane Shots</name>
        <text>The Arcane Arrow feature lets you choose Arcane Shot options at certain levels. The options are presented here in alphabetical order. These are all magical effects.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer (UA): Archer's Lore</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn a few skills relating to the typical duties of an Arcane Archer. You learn to understand magical theory and develop survival skills for wandering the wilds.</text>
        <text>You gain proficiency in two of the following skills of your choice: Arcana, Athletics, Nature, Perception, Stealth, and Survival.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Arcane Archer v2</name>
        <text>An Arcane Archer studies a unique elven method of archery that weaves magic into attacks to produce supernatural effects. Among elves, Arcane Archers are some of their most elite warriors. These archers stand watch over the fringes of elven domains, keeping a keen eye out for trespassers and using magic-infused arrows to defeat monsters and invaders before they can reach elven settlements. Over the centuries, the methods of these elf archers have been learned by members of other races who can also balance arcane aptitude with archery.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Arcane Arrow</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn to unleash special magical effects with some of your shots. When you gain this feature, you learn two Arcane Shot options of your choice (see the "Arcane Shot Options" section below).</text>
        <text>Once per turn when you fire a magic arrow from a shortbow or longbow as part of the Attack action, you can apply one of your Arcane Shot options to that arrow. You decide to use the option when the arrow hits, unless the option doesn't involve an attack roll. You have two uses of this ability, and you regain all expended uses of it when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>You gain an additional Arcane Shot option of your choice when you reach certain levels in this class: 7th, 10th, 15th, and 18th level. Each option also improves when you become an 18th-level fighter.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Arcane Shot</name>
        <text>The Arcane Shot feature lets you choose options for it at certain levels. The options are presented here in alphabetical order. They are all magical effects, and each one is associated with one of the schools of magic.</text>
        <text>If an option requires a saving throw, your Arcane Shot save DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Intelligence modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Archer's Lore</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn magical theory or some of the secrets of nature—typical for practitioners of this elven martial tradition. You gain proficiency in either the Arcana or Nature skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Magic Arrow</name>
        <text>When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you gain the ability to infuse arrows with magic. Whenever you fire a nonmagical arrow from a shortbow or longbow, you can make it a magic arrow, with a +1 bonus to the attack and damage rolls. The magic fades from the arrow immediately after it hits or misses its target.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Knight (UA): Knight</name>
        <text>The Knight is a colossus on the battlefield who can shrug off attacks and protect allies from harm. Knights fight from the saddle when they can, and in combat they are expected to seek out and lock down the mightiest of the enemy's forces. On adventures, they are the armored bulwark that strives to keep the rest of the party safe.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Knight (UA): Born to the Saddle</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, mounting or dismounting a creature costs you only 5 feet of movement, rather than half your speed. In addition, you have advantage on saving throws made to avoid falling off your mount. If you fall off it, you can automatically land on your feet if you aren't incapacitated and you fall less than 10 feet.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Knight (UA): Implacable Mark</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you excel at foiling attacks and protecting your allies by menacing your foes. When you hit a creature with a melee weapon attack, the target is marked by you until the end of your next turn. A creature ignores this effect if the creature can't be frightened.</text>
        <text>The marked target has disadvantage on any attack roll against a creature other than you or someone else who marked it.</text>
        <text>If a target marked by you is within 5 feet of you on its turn and it moves at least 1 foot or makes an attack that suffers disadvantage from this feature, you can make one melee weapon attack against it using your reaction. This attack roll has advantage, and if it hits, the attack's weapon deals extra damage to the target equal to your fighter level.</text>
        <text>You can make this special attack even if you have already expended your reaction this round, but not if you have already used your reaction this turn. You can make this attack three times, and you regain all expended uses of it when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Samurai (UA): Samurai</name>
        <text>The Samurai is a fighter who draws on an implacable fighting spirit to overcome enemies. A Samurai's willpower is nearly unbreakable, and the enemies in a Samurai's path have two choices: yield or die fighting.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Samurai (UA): Fighting Spirit</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, the might of your willpower can shield you and help you strike true. As a bonus action on your turn, you can give yourself two benefits: advantage on all attack rolls and resistance to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage. These benefits last until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature three times. You regain all expended uses of it when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sharpshooter (UA): Sharpshooter</name>
        <text>The Sharpshooter is a master of ranged combat. An excellent sniper and eagle-eyed scout, this fighter is a perilous foe who can defeat an entire war band so long as they are kept at range.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sharpshooter (UA): Steady Aim</name>
        <text>Beginning when you choose this archetype at 3rd level, your aim becomes deadly. As a bonus action on your turn, you can take careful aim at a creature you can see that is within range of a ranged weapon you're wielding. Until the end of this turn, your ranged attacks with that weapon gain two benefits against the target:</text>
        <text>• The attacks ignore half and three-quarters cover.</text>
        <text>• On each hit, the weapon deals additional damage to the target equal to 2 + half your fighter level.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature three times. You regain all expended uses of it when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Martial Archetype: Arcane Archer</name>
        <text>An Arcane Archer studies a unique elven method of archery that weaves magic into attacks to produce supernatural effects. Arcane Archers are some of the most elite warriors among the elves. They stand watch over the fringes of elven domains, keeping a keen eye out for trespassers and using magic-infused arrows to defeat monsters and invaders before they can reach elven settlements. Over the centuries, the methods of these elf archers have been learned by members of other races who can also balance arcane aptitude with archery.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 28</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer: Arcane Archer Lore</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn magical theory or some of the secrets of nature—typical for practitioners of this elven martial tradition. You choose to gain proficiency in either the Arcana or the Nature skill, and you choose to learn either the prestidigitation or the druidcraft cantrip.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 28</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer: Arcane Shot</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn to unleash special magical effects with some of your shots. When you gain this feature, you learn two Arcane Shot options of your choice (see "Arcane Shot Options" below).</text>
        <text>Once per turn when you fire an arrow from a shortbow or longbow as part of the Attack action, you can apply one of your Arcane Shot options to that arrow. You decide to use the option when the arrow hits a creature, unless the option doesn't involve an attack roll. You have two uses of this ability, and you regain all expended uses of it when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>You gain an additional Arcane Shot option of your choice when you reach certain levels in this class: 7th, 10th, 15th, and 18th level. Each option also improves when you become an 18th-level fighter.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 28</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer: Arcane Shot Options</name>
        <text>The Arcane Shot feature lets you choose options for it at certain levels. The options are presented here in alphabetical order. They are all magical effects, and each one is associated with one of the schools of magic.</text>
        <text>If an option requires a saving throw, your Arcane Shot save DC is calculated as follows:</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 28</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Martial Archetype: Cavalier</name>
        <text>The archetypal Cavalier excels at mounted combat. Usually born among the nobility and raised at court, a Cavalier is equally at home leading a cavalry charge or exchanging repartee at a state dinner. Cavaliers also learn how to guard those in their charge from harm, often serving as the protectors of their superiors and of the weak. Compelled to right wrongs or earn prestige, many of these fighters leave their lives of comfort to embark on glorious adventure.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 30</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier: Bonus Proficiency</name>
        <text>When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you gain proficiency in one of the following skills of your choice: Animal Handling, History, Insight, Performance, or Persuasion. Alternatively, you learn one language of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 30</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier: Born to the Saddle</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, your mastery as a rider becomes apparent. You have advantage on saving throws made to avoid falling off your mount. If you fall off your mount and descend no more than 10 feet, you can land on your feet if you're not incapacitated.</text>
        <text>Finally, mounting or dismounting a creature costs you only 5 feet of movement, rather than half your speed.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 30</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier: Unwavering Mark</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you can menace your foes, foiling their attacks and punishing them for harming others. When you hit a creature with a melee weapon attack, you can mark the creature until the end of your next turn. This effect ends early if you are incapacitated or you die, or if someone else marks the creature.</text>
        <text>While it is within 5 feet of you, a creature marked by you has disadvantage on any attack roll that doesn't target you.</text>
        <text>In addition, if a creature marked by you deals damage to anyone other than you, you can make a special melee weapon attack against the marked creature as a bonus action on your next turn. You have advantage on the attack roll, and if it hits, the attack's weapon deals extra damage to the target equal to half your fighter level.</text>
        <text>Regardless of the number of creatures you mark, you can make this special attack a number of times equal to your Strength modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses of it when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 30</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Martial Archetype: Samurai</name>
        <text>The Samurai is a fighter who draws on an implacable fighting spirit to overcome enemies. A Samurai's resolve is nearly unbreakable, and the enemies in a Samurai's path have two choices: yield or die fighting.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 31</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Samurai: Bonus Proficiency</name>
        <text>When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you gain proficiency in one of the following skills of your choice: History, Insight, Performance, or Persuasion. Alternatively, you learn one language of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 31</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Samurai: Fighting Spirit</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, your intensity in battle can shield you and help you strike true. As a bonus action on your turn, you can give yourself advantage on weapon attack rolls until the end of the current turn. When you do so, you also gain 5 temporary hit points. The number of temporary hit points increases when you reach certain levels in this class, increasing to 10 at 10th level and 15 at 15th level.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature three times, and you regain all expended uses of it when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 31</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Brute (UA): Brute</name>
        <text>Brutes are simple warriors who rely on mighty attacks and their own durability to overcome their enemies. Some brutes combine this physical might with tactical cunning. Others just hit things until those things stop hitting back.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Three Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Brute (UA): Brute Force</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you're able to strike with your weapons with especially brutal force. Whenever you hit with a weapon that you're proficient with and deal damage, the weapon's damage increases by an amount based on your level in this class, as shown on the Brute Bonus Damage table.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Brute Bonus Damage</text>
        <text>Fighter Level | Damage Increase</text>
        <text>3rd | 1d4</text>
        <text>10th | 1d6</text>
        <text>16th | 1d8</text>
        <text>20th | 1d10</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Three Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Martial Archetype: Warlord (Livestream)</name>
        <text>Transcribed on 2018-03-28. [Square bracketed text] denotes transcriber's annotations.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Warlord (Livestream): Tactical Focus</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, your tactical acumen allows you to study an area of a battlefield and provide direction to your allies that can tilt a battle in your favor.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action or as part of the attack action, you can select an area on the ground that measures 10 feet on each side. This area is your tactical focus. It remains your tactical focus until you use this ability again or you are unable to take actions.</text>
        <text>When you select an area as your tactical focus, you choose one of your tactics to apply to that area. You gain three tactics at 3rd level. You gain an additional tactic at 7th and 15 level. Each time you complete a long rest, you can swap one of your tactics for a different one.</text>
        <name>Warlord (Livestream): Tactics</name>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Warlord (Livestream): Tactician's Insight</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you can grant your allies useful tactical insights while they are in the area of your tactical focus.</text>
        <text>You gain a number of uses of insight based on your fighter level.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action or as a part of an attack action you grant insight to yourself or allies in your tactical focus. You grant this benefit to yourself and as many allies as you wish in your focus, but you cannot expend more uses than you currently have [or more than the maximum in the table below. A creature can receive more than one Tactician's Insight when you take this action.]</text>
        <text>A creature that gains your insight can use it in two ways. It can regain hit points immediately upon receiving it. Roll 2d10 and the creature regains that many hit points. If the creature would gain hit points that place it above its maximum, it gains the difference as temporary hit points.</text>
        <text>Alternatively, a creature can save the insight to use when it hits with an attack. It increases the attack's damage by 2d10.</text>
        <text>You regain expended uses of Tactician's Insight when you complete a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Tactician's Insight</text>
        <text>Fighter Level | Uses | Maximum | Gambits</text>
        <text>3 | 2 | 1 | 0</text>
        <text>4-6 | 3 | 1 | 0</text>
        <text>7-9 | 7 | 2 | 3</text>
        <text>10-12 | 9 | 2 | 4</text>
        <text>13-15 | 14 | 3 | 5</text>
        <text>16-18 | 16 | 3 | 6</text>
        <text>19-20 | 20 | 4 | 7</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Warlord (Livestream): Advance</name>
        <text>You and your allies can move 10 ft. in your tactical focus for every 5 feet of movement expended there. [Changed during stream to "You and your allies can basically teleport into your focus. Movement on allies turn." Specifically, the movement is not made as a reaction—your allies can use their movement on their turn(s) to move towards the focus, and gain bonuses to speed or other effects (for example, ignoring difficult terrain, or movement does not provoke opportunity attacks) to aid and incentivize this. Additionally, this may replace "Cover That Flank" in future.]</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Warlord (Livestream): Clear the area</name>
        <text>If an ally hits a creature in your tactical focus with an attack, the ally can move that creature 5 ft. in addition to the attack's other effects.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Warlord (Livestream): Cover That Flank</name>
        <text>When a hostile creature that you can see enters your tactical focus, up to three target creatures of your choice that can see the creature can use a reaction to move up to their speed. The targets must end their movement in the tactical focus. A target creature that ends this movement adjacent to the triggering creature regains its reaction.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Warlord (Livestream): Form Shield Wall</name>
        <text>Allies in your tactical focus gain a +2 bonus to AC while they are adjacent to an ally using a shield. [In future, this will likely be changed to benefit only creatures not already wielding a shield, and to affect each creature at most once.]</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Warlord (Livestream): Get Down</name>
        <text>If an allied creature in your tactical focus must make a Dexterity saving throw it can use its reaction to move up to its speed. If this movement takes it out of the range or area of the effect that caused the saving throw, it is no longer subjected to the effect. [In future, this may be changed to instead give advantage on the saving throw, or require the creature to drop prone, or cancel the creature's next move.]</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Warlord (Livestream): Reorder Ranks</name>
        <text>Allies in your tactical focus do not provoke opportunity attacks while they are within 5 feet of an ally. In addition, you and your allies can end movement in an ally's space. That ally immediately moves so that you do not occupy the same space, but it must end that move at least partially occupying your tactical focus. [Noted as requiring cleanup.]</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Paths of the Sublime Way</name>
        <text>Each path of the sublime way features a unique take on combat mastery. Many, but not all, require you to wield certain weapons to use their exploits.</text>
        <text>When you use a martial exploit, you can choose to use one of the special exploits listed under one of the paths you know. You choose the special exploit when you decide to use a martial exploit.</text>
        <text>Some of these abilities require you to roll fewer dice when using a martial exploit. You cannot use an ability that reduces the total dice you roll for the exploit to less than 1. Such an ability is beyond your skill.</text>
        <text>Some of these abilities require a creature to make a saving throw. The DC for such a save is 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Strength modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Martial Archetype: Weapon Master (Livestream)</name>
        <text>Transcribed on 2018-10-13. [Square bracketed text] denotes transcriber's annotations.</text>
        <text>A weapon master follows the fighting techniques of the Sublime way. This martial discipline combines a variety of sources, from arcane and divine magic to the hardened resolve of a master warrior, to produce astounding battlefield effects.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Martial Exploits</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you gain the ability to use your tactical acumen, physical prowess, and sometimes a dash of mystic energy to achieve astounding feats of martial skill.</text>
        <text>You gain the ability to use martial exploits. You gain uses based on your fighter level, as shown on the Martial Exploits table. You regain all expended uses when you complete a long</text>
        <text>You also gain access to one path of the Sublime Way at 3rd level. The Martial Exploits table also shows when you get access to additional paths as you gain fighter levels.</text>
        <text>Whenever you gain a fighter level, you can choose to lose access to one path and replace it with access to a different one.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Martial Exploits</text>
        <text>Level | Path | Uses | Exploit Dice</text>
        <text>3 | 1 | 4 | 2d6</text>
        <text>4 | 2 | 5 | 2d6</text>
        <text>5 | 2 | 5 | 2d6</text>
        <text>6 | 3 | 5 | 2d6</text>
        <text>7 | 3 | 7 | 3d6</text>
        <text>8 | 3 | 7 | 3d6</text>
        <text>9 | 3 | 7 | 3d6</text>
        <text>10 | 4 | 9 | 3d6</text>
        <text>11 | 4 | 9 | 3d6</text>
        <text>12 | 5 | 9 | 3d6</text>
        <text>13 | 5 | 10 | 4d6</text>
        <text>14 | 5 | 10 | 4d6</text>
        <text>15 | 5 | 10 | 4d6</text>
        <text>16 | 5 | 10 | 5d6</text>
        <text>17 | 5 | 10 | 5d6</text>
        <text>18 | 5 | 10 | 5d6</text>
        <text>19 | 5 | 10 | 6d6</text>
        <text>20 | 5 | 10 | 6d6</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Masterful Strike</name>
        <text>When you reach 3rd level, you gain the ability to use a martial exploit to land a telling blow. When you make a weapon attack, you can expend a martial exploit. Roll the dice for your exploit along with your attack. If your attack misses, you can use one or more of the exploit's dice results as a bonus to your attack. If the attack hits, apply any unused dice as a bonus to your weapon damage roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Path of the Shadow Harlequin</name>
        <text>The Shadow Harlequin path is a school of artful sword play and mesmerizing flourishes. Its practitioners attack a foe's mind and body, maneuvering their foes into tactical blunders with cunning feints and sudden, surprising moves.</text>
        <text>Shadow Harlequins typically fight with light, agile weapons, such as rapiers and short swords, but their talents are useful to almost any warrior.</text>
        <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Come Forth to Dance</name>
        <text>   Your weapon moves in a lazy, hypnotic pattern, luring your foe to blunder ahead and walk into your trap.</text>
        <text>   As an action, expend a martial exploit and select a creature that can see you within 15 feet of you. The target must make a Wisdom saving throw. If it fails, it moves up to 15 feet closer to you. You then make a single melee attack against it using your martial exploit with one die fewer.</text>
        <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Cutting Dialogue</name>
        <text>   If this exchange of blows is a dramatic play, let your rejoinder be its final act.</text>
        <text>   As a reaction when a creature makes a melee attack against you, you can expend a martial exploit and make a melee weapon attack against that creature. You can select one of the dice rolled and add it to your AC against the target's attack.</text>
        <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Dramatic Exit</name>
        <text>   Your overly dramatic strike distracts your opponent, allowing you to slip away from their grasp.</text>
        <text>   When you expend a martial exploit when making a melee weapon attack, you can move up to 5 feet, without provoking opportunity attacks, per exploit die rolled after your attack.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Path of the Stone Dragon</name>
        <text>The Stone Dragon path focuses on brutal power and overwhelming toughness. Most of these exploits require you to attack with a two-handed melee weapon or a versatile melee weapon you wield in two hands.</text>
        <text>Warriors of the Stone Dragon are often cruel destroyers. They fight with the subtlety and irresistible force of an avalanche. Their punishing attacks render their enemies immobile, allowing them to then take careful aim for one, final executioner's blow.</text>
        <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Adamantine Bones</name>
        <text>   You focus your mind and grit your teeth, pushing aside pain and drawing on wellsprings of energy that blot out the pain of your wounds.</text>
        <text>   When you expend a martial exploit when attacking with a two-handed melee weapon or a versatile one wielded in two hands, after rolling the dice you can select one or more of them. You gain temporary hit points equal to the total of the dice + your Constitution modifier (minimum of 1).</text>
        <text>   You can also activate this ability as a bonus action. In that case, you roll your martial exploit dice and gain temporary hit points equal to their total + your Constitution modifier.</text>
        <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Colossus Strike</name>
        <text>   You swing your weapon in an upward arc, catching your foe in the chest and sending them flying across the battlefield.</text>
        <text>   When you expend a martial exploit when attacking with a two-handed melee weapon or a versatile one wielded in two hands, after rolling the dice you can select one or more of them and disregard their result. For each die selected, you push the target 5 feet in a straight line along the ground if your attack hits.</text>
        <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Jaws of the Stone Dragon</name>
        <text>   Like a mighty dragon pouncing upon a helpless victim, you take stock of an immobilized foe before landing a crushing strike.</text>
        <text>   When you expend a martial exploit when attacking a target that cannot move or with a speed of 0 with a two-handed melee weapon or a versatile one wielded in two hands, you gain an additional +2 bonus per die used as a bonus to your weapon damage roll.</text>
        <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Mountain's Grasp</name>
        <text>   Your blows land with such force that your enemy is left off balance, unable to escape your brutal assault.</text>
        <text>   When you expend a martial exploit when attacking with a two-handed melee weapon or a versatile one wielded in two hands, after rolling the dice you can select at least two of them and disregard their results. The target must make a Constitution saving throw. If it fails, its speed is reduced to 0 until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Sweeping Bludgeon</name>
        <text>   As you ready to strike your enemy, you sweep your weapon around you in a great arc that builds momentum and forces your enemies to dive to the ground to avoid a crushing blow.</text>
        <text>   When you expend a martial exploit when attacking with a two-handed melee weapon or a versatile one wielded in two hands, after rolling the dice you can select one or more of them and disregard their result. For each die selected, pick a creature within reach of your attack. Each chosen creature must make a Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Slayer (Livestream): Slayer</name>
        <text>A slayer is a fighter who specializes in bringing down the mightiest monsters wth a few, resounding blows. Some slayers target specific types of monsters, such as dwarven giant slayers who patrol the mountain's peaks or human dragon slayers who train to defeat wyrms of all types.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Slayer (Livestream): Martial Exploits</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you gain the ability to use your tactical acumen and physical prowess to achieve astounding feats of martial skill.</text>
        <text>You gain the ability to use martial exploits. You gain uses of martial exploits based on your fighter level, as shown in the Martial Exploits table. You retain all expenses uses when you complete a long rest.</text>
        <text>You can apply the benefits of only one exploit to any given attack. If more than one exploit applies to an attack, you select which one to use. Some exploits require a creature to make a saving throw. The DC for such a save is 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Strength modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Martial Exploits</text>
        <text>Level | Uses</text>
        <text>3 | 3</text>
        <text>4-6 | 5</text>
        <text>7-9 | 7</text>
        <text>11-12 | 9</text>
        <text>13+ | 10</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Slayer (Livestream): Slayer's Exploits</name>
        <text>When you reach 3rd level, you gain several martial exploits that allow you to lay low even the mightiest foe. The ability to use a martial exploit to land a telling blow. You gain the Adamantine Bones, Bell Ringer, and Masterful Strike exploits.</text>
        <name>Slayer (Livestream): Adamantine Bones</name>
        <text>   You focus your mind and grit your teeth, pushing aside pain and drawing on wellsprings of energy that blot out the pain of your wounds.</text>
        <text>   During your turn, you can expend a martial exploit to gain temporary hit points. You gain temporary hit points equal to 5 times your proficiency bonus.</text>
        <name>Slayer (Livestream): Bellringer</name>
        <text>   You take careful aim at your foe's head or other sensitive point, unleashing a brutal attack that knocks the target senseless.</text>
        <text>   You can expend a martial exploit when you hit with a melee weapon attack. The target of the attack must make a Constitution saving throw. If it fails, it is paralyzed. At the end of each of its turns, it can make a Constitution saving throw to end this effect.</text>
        <name>Slayer (Livestream): Masterful Strike</name>
        <text>   You strike with overwhelming strength and accuracy, battering aside your foe's defense to deliver a deadly strike.</text>
        <text>   When you make an attack, you can expend a martial exploit and roll a number of d6s equal to your proficiency bonus.</text>
        <text>   If the attack misses, you learn the target's AC and can use the result of one or more d6s of your choice as a bonus to your attack roll, possibly turning the miss into a hit. Any remaining dice are used as a bonus to your weapon's damage roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Rune Knight (UA): Rune Knight</name>
        <text>You discovered how to enhance your martial prowess using the supernatural power of runes. The ancient practice of rune magic originated with giants. Skiltgravr ("rune cutters") can be found among any type of giants, and you likely learned your methods first or second hand from such a mystical artisan. Whether you found the giant's work carved into a hill or cave, learned of the runes from a traveling sage, or met the giant in person, you studied the giant's craft. In time, you learned how to carve and apply runes to your equipment and how to invoke their magic, ultimately becoming a Rune Knight.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Rune Knight (UA): Bonus Proficiencies</name>
        <text>3rd-level Rune Knight feature</text>
        <text>You gain proficiency with smith's tools, and you learn to speak, read, and write Giant.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Rune Knight (UA): Giant Might</name>
        <text>3rd-level Rune Knight feature</text>
        <text>You can imbue yourself with the might of giants. As a bonus action, you magically gain the following benefits, which last for 1 minute:</text>
        <text>• If you are smaller than Large, you become Large, along with anything you are wearing. If you lack the room to become Large, your size doesn't change.</text>
        <text>• You have advantage on Strength checks and Strength saving throws.</text>
        <text>• Your weapon attacks deal an extra 1d6 damage.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature twice, and you regain all expended uses of it when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Rune Knight (UA): Rune Magic</name>
        <text>3rd-level Rune Knight feature</text>
        <text>You learn how to use runes to enhance your gear. When you gain this feature, you learn how to inscribe two runes of your choice on weapons, armor, or shields (see "Rune Options").</text>
        <text>Whenever you finish a long rest, you can touch a number of objects equal to the number of runes you know, and you inscribe a different rune onto each of the objects. To be eligible, an object must be a weapon, a suit of armor, or a shield.</text>
        <text>Your rune remains on an object until you finish a long rest, and an object can bear only one of your runes.</text>
        <text>Each time you gain a level in this class, you can replace one rune you know with a different one.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Rune Knight (UA): Rune Options</name>
        <text>Here are rune options for the Rune Magic feature. They are all magical effects. If a rune requires a saving throw, your Rune Magic save DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Intelligence modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psychic Warrior (UA): Psychic Warrior</name>
        <text>Awakening to the psionic power within themselves, a Psychic Warrior is a fighter who augments their physical might with psychically infused weapon strikes, telekinetic lashes, and barriers of mental force.</text>
        <text>As a Psychic Warrior, you might have honed your psionic abilities through your own disciplined practice, unlocked it under the tutelage of a master, or developed it at an academy dedicated to wielding the mind's power as both weapon and shield.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psychic Warrior (UA): Psionic Armament</name>
        <text>3rd-level Psychic Warrior feature</text>
        <text>You can channel your psychic power to magically augment your prowess. When you finish a long rest, choose whether to augment your defenses or your strikes. The chosen benefit lasts until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <name>Psychic Warrior (UA): Augmented Defenses</name>
        <text>   When you or a creature you can see within 30 feet of you takes damage, you can use your reaction to roll a d10 and reduce the amount of damage taken by the number rolled. When you reach 10th level in this class, the die changes to a d12.</text>
        <name>Psychic Warrior (UA): Augmented Strikes</name>
        <text>   Once during each of your turns when you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can also deal 1d4 psychic damage to that target. When you reach 10th level in this class, the psychic damage increases to 1d6.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psychic Warrior (UA): Telekinetic Hand</name>
        <text>3rd-level Psychic Warrior feature</text>
        <text>You learn the mage hand cantrip. You can cast it without components, and you can make the spectral hand invisible. Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for this spell.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Martial Archetype: Echo Knight</name>
        <text>A mysterious and feared frontline warrior of the Kryn Dynasty, the Echo Knight has mastered the art of using dunamis to summon the fading shades of unrealized timelines to aid them in battle. Surrounded by echoes of their own might, they charge into the fray as a cycling swarm of shadows and strikes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 183</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Echo Knight: Manifest Echo</name>
        <text>3rd-level Echo Knight feature</text>
        <text>You can use a bonus action to magically manifest an echo of yourself in an unoccupied space you can see within 15 feet of you. This echo is a magical, translucent, gray image of you that lasts until it is destroyed, until you dismiss it as a bonus action, until you manifest another echo, or until you're incapacitated.</text>
        <text>Your echo has AC 14 + your proficiency bonus, 1 hit point, and immunity to all conditions. If it has to make a saving throw, it uses your saving throw bonus for the roll. It is the same size as you, and it occupies its space. On your turn, you can mentally command the echo to move up to 30 feet in any direction (no action required). If your echo is ever more than 30 feet from you at the end of your turn, it is destroyed.</text>
        <text>You can use the echo in the following ways:</text>
        <text>• As a bonus action, you can teleport, magically swapping places with your echo at a cost of 15 feet of your movement, regardless of the distance between the two of you.</text>
        <text>• When you take the Attack action on your turn, any attack you make with that action can originate from your space or the echo's space. You make this choice for each attack.</text>
        <text>• When a creature that you can see within 5 feet of your echo moves at least 5 feet away from it, you can use your reaction to make an opportunity attack against that creature as if you were in the echo's space.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 183</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Echo Knight: Unleash Incarnation</name>
        <text>3rd-level Echo Knight feature</text>
        <text>You can heighten your echo's fury. Whenever you take the Attack action, you can make one additional melee attack from the echo's position.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Constitution modifier (a minimum of once). You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 183</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psi Knight (UA): Psi Knight</name>
        <text>Awake to the psionic power within, a Psi Knight is a fighter who augments their physical might with psi-infused weapon strikes, telekinetic lashes, and barriers of mental force. Many githyanki train to become such knights, as do some of the most disciplined high elves. In the world of Athas, renowned gladiators in the arenas of the Sorcerer-Kings are often Psi Knights, and in Eberron, the psionic kalashtar view membership in this knighthood as a special honor.</text>
        <text>As a Psi Knight, you might have honed your psionic abilities through solo discipline, unlocked it under the tutelage of a master, or refined it at an academy dedicated to wielding the mind's power as both weapon and shield.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psi Knight (UA): Changing the Die's Size</name>
        <text>If you roll the highest number on your Psionic Talent die, it decreases by one die size after the roll. This represents you burning through your psionic energy. For example, if the die is a d6 and you roll a 6, it becomes a d4. If it's a d4 and you roll a 4, it becomes unusable until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>Conversely, if you roll a 1 on your Psionic Talent die, it increases by one die size after the roll, up to its starting size. This represents you conserving psionic energy for later use. For example, if you roll a 1 on a d4, the die then becomes a d6.</text>
        <text>Whenever you finish a long rest, your Psionic Talent die resets to its starting size. When you reach certain levels in this class, the starting size of your Psionic Talent die increases: at 5th level (d8), 11th level (d10), and 17th level (d12).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psi Knight (UA): Psi Replenishment</name>
        <text>As a bonus action, you can calm your mind for a moment and restore your Psionic Talent die to its starting size. You then can't use Psi Replenishment again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psi Knight (UA): Psionic Talent</name>
        <text>3rd-level Psi Knight feature</text>
        <text>You harbor a wellspring of psionic power within yourself, an energy that ebbs and flows as you channel it in various ways. This power is represented by your Psionic Talent die, the starting size of which is a d6.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psi Knight (UA): Psionic Talent Options</name>
        <text>You can use your Psionic Talent die in the following ways:</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>   Protective Field.</text>
        <text>• When you or another creature you can see within 30 feet of you takes damage, you can use your reaction to roll your Psionic Talent die and reduce the damage taken by the number rolled plus your Intelligence modifier (minimum reduction of 1), as you create a momentary shield of telekinetic force.</text>
        <text>   Psi-Powered Leap.</text>
        <text>• When you make a high or long jump, you can roll your Psionic Talent die and extend the distance of the jump, up to a number of feet equal to twice the number rolled plus twice your Intelligence modifier (minimum of 1 extra foot). This extra distance costs you only 1 foot of movement.</text>
        <text>   Telekinetic Strike.</text>
        <text>• You can propel your attacks with telekinetic force. Once on each of your turns, immediately after you deal damage to a target within 30 feet of you with a weapon attack, you can roll your Psionic Talent die and also deal force damage to the target equal to the number rolled.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 4th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>4th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
        <feature>
          <name>Extra Attack</name>
        <text>Beginning at 5th level, you can attack twice, instead of once, whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.</text>
        <text>The number of attacks increases to three when you reach 11th level in this class and to four when you reach 20th level in this class.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 6th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>6th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature>
          <name>Martial Archetype feature</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain a feature granted by your Martial Archetype.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Champion: Remarkable Athlete</name>
        <text>Starting at 7th level, you can add half your proficiency bonus (round up) to any Strength, Dexterity, or Constitution check you make that doesn't already use your proficiency bonus.</text>
        <text>In addition, when you make a running long jump, the distance you can cover increases by a number of feet equal to your Strength modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Battle Master: Additional Maneuvers</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn two additional maneuvers of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Battle Master: Additional Superiority Die</name>
        <text>You gain another superiority die at 7th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Battle Master: Know Your Enemy</name>
        <text>If you spend at least 1 minute observing or interacting with another creature outside combat, you can learn certain information about its capabilities compared to your own. The DM tells you if the creature is your equal, superior, or inferior in regard to two of the following characteristics of your choice:</text>
        <text>• Strength score</text>
        <text>• Dexterity score</text>
        <text>• Constitution score</text>
        <text>• Armor Class</text>
        <text>• Current hit points</text>
        <text>• Total class levels (if any)</text>
        <text>• Fighter class levels (if any)</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier (UA): Ferocious Charger</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain additional benefits when you use superiority dice to increase your damage when you attack with a lance. You can expend up to two superiority dice on the attack, adding both to the damage roll. If you spend two dice, the target has disadvantage on its Strength saving throw to avoid being knocked prone.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier v2 (UA): Ferocious Charger</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain additional benefits when you use your Trip Attack maneuver. You can expend up to two superiority dice on it, adding both dice to the damage roll. When you spend two dice in this way, the target has disadvantage on its Strength saving throw to avoid being knocked prone.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Eldritch Knight: War Magic</name>
        <text>Beginning at 7th level, when you use your action to cast a cantrip, you can make one weapon attack as a bonus action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 74</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Hunter (UA): Monster Slayer</name>
        <text>At 7th level, whenever you expend superiority dice to add to a damage roll, you can expend up to two dice instead of just one, adding both to the roll. Both dice are expended as normal. If the target of your attack is an aberration, a fey, a fiend, or an undead, you deal maximum damage with both dice, instead of rolling them.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Purple Dragon Knight (Banneret): Royal Envoy</name>
        <text>A Purple Dragon Knight serves as an envoy of the Cormyrean crown. Knights of high standing are expected to conduct themselves with grace.</text>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain proficiency in the Persuasion skill. If you are already proficient in it, you gain proficiency in one of the following skills of your choice: Animal Handling, Insight, Intimidation, or Performance.</text>
        <text>Your proficiency bonus is doubled for any ability check you make that uses Persuasion. You receive this benefit regardless of the skill proficiency you gain from this feature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 128</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Additional Superiority Die</name>
        <text>You gain another superiority die at 7th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer (UA): Conjure Arrows</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn a minor but useful magical trick. As an action, you can conjure 20 nonmagical arrows. The arrows appear in your hand or in a container, such as a quiver, on your body. The arrows remain for 10 minutes or until you use this feature again; they then vanish.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer (UA): Extra Arcane Shot</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn an additional Arcane Shot option.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Curving Shot</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn how to direct an errant arrow toward a new target. When you make an attack roll with a magic arrow and miss, you can use a bonus action to reroll the attack roll against a different target within 60 feet of the original target.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Extra Arcane Shot</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn an additional Arcane Shot option.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Knight (UA): Noble Cavalry</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain proficiency in two of the following skills of your choice: Animal Handling, History, Insight, Persuasion, or Religion. Alternatively, you learn one language of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Samurai (UA): Elegant Courtier</name>
        <text>Starting at 7th level, your discipline and attention to detail allow you to excel in social situations that require strict adherence to etiquette. You can add your Wisdom modifier to any Charisma check you make to persuade or please a noble or anyone else of high social station.</text>
        <text>You also gain proficiency in the History, Insight, or Persuasion skill (choose one). Alternatively, you learn one language of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sharpshooter (UA): Careful Eyes</name>
        <text>Starting at 7th level, you excel at picking out hidden enemies and other threats. You can take the Search action as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>You also gain proficiency in the Perception, Investigation, or Survival skill (choose one).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer: Additional Arcane Shot Option</name>
        <text>You gain an additional Arcane Shot option of your choice when you reach 7th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 28</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer: Curving Shot</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn how to direct an errant arrow toward a new target. When you make an attack roll with a magic arrow and miss, you can use a bonus action to reroll the attack roll against a different target within 60 feet of the original target.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 28</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer: Magic Arrow</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain the ability to infuse arrows with magic. Whenever you fire a nonmagical arrow from a shortbow or longbow, you can make it magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage. The magic fades from the arrow immediately after it hits or misses its target.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 28</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier: Warding Maneuver</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn to fend off strikes directed at you, your mount, or other creatures nearby. If you or a creature you can see within 5 feet of you is hit by an attack, you can roll 1d8 as a reaction if you're wielding a melee weapon or a shield. Roll the die, and add the number rolled to the target's AC against that attack. If the attack still hits, the target has resistance against the attack's damage.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Constitution modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses of it when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 30</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Samurai: Elegant Courtier</name>
        <text>Starting at 7th level, your discipline and attention to detail allow you to excel in social situations. Whenever you make a Charisma (Persuasion) check, you gain a bonus to the check equal to your Wisdom modifier.</text>
        <text>Your self-control also causes you to gain proficiency in Wisdom saving throws. If you already have this proficiency, you instead gain proficiency in Intelligence or Charisma saving throws (your choice).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 31</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Brute (UA): Brutish Durability</name>
        <text>Beginning at 7th level, your toughness allows you to shrug off assaults that would devastate others.</text>
        <text>Whenever you make a saving throw, roll 1d6 and add the die to your saving throw total. If applying this bonus to a death saving throw increases the total to 20 or higher, you gain the benefits of rolling a 20 on the d20.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Three Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Warlord (Livestream): Additional Tactic</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn an additional tactic of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Warlord (Livestream): Tactical Gambits</name>
        <text>Starting at 7th level, your tactical cunning allows you to seize the moment in battle.</text>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn two gambits. You learn an additional gambit at 10th and 18th level.</text>
        <text>You use a gambit as an action. You can use your gambits a number of times based on your fighter level.</text>
        <text>Each time you complete a long rest, you regain all expended uses of your gambits and can swap one of your gambits for a different one.</text>
        <name>Warlord (Livestream): Saving Throws</name>
        <text>   A gambit sometimes requires a saving throw. The saving throw DC is calculated as follows:</text>
        <name>Warlord (Livestream): Gambits</name>
        <text>   The gambits are presented in alphabetical order.</text>
        <name>Warlord (Livestream): Aggressive Advance</name>
        <text>   You and your allies howl in rage and glower at your foes, making a display that sends fear into their hearts.</text>
        <text>   Hostile creatures within 60 feet of you that can see you must make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, a creature is frightened of your tactical focus. A creature frightened by this effect can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on a successful save. As part of this gambit, you may take the attack action. [In future, may be changed to require you or an ally to be present within the focus.]</text>
        <name>Warlord (Livestream): Cut Them Down!</name>
        <text>   You direct your allies to strike with perfect timing. Landing blows just as your enemies are of balance to send them tumbling to the ground.</text>
        <text>   Until the end of your next turn, hostile creatures in your tactical focus that you can see must make Strength saves each time they are hit by an attack. On a failed save, they are knocked prone. As part of this gambit, you may take the attack action.</text>
        <name>Warlord (Livestream): Luring Gambit</name>
        <text>   You entangle your weapon with a chosen foe, luring it to duel you as your allies close in for the kill.</text>
        <text>   As part of this gambit, you may take the attack action. If you hit a creature with a weapon attack during your turn, it must make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, your allies are invisible to it until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <name>Warlord (Livestream): Pile On</name>
        <text>   You direct your allies' attacks against a target, each blow building on the next to build a devastating result. Select a creature in your tactical focus that you can see. At the start of your next turn, that creature must make a Constitution saving throw if you or an ally has hit it with an attack since you used this ability. It suffers disadvantage on the saving throw if it has been hit by three or more attacks [in future, this may be changed to "hit by three or more creatures"]. On a failed saving throw, the creature is stunned until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text>   As part of this gambit, you may take the attack action.</text>
        <name>Warlord (Livestream): Pincer Movement</name>
        <text>   With precise timing, you order your allies to charge into the enemy, dealing body checks that leave your foes entangled and helpless.</text>
        <text>   Up to two allies that can see or hear you can use their reactions to move up to their speed. Any creature adjacent to both of your allies or to you and one of the chosen allies at the end of their movement must make a Strength saving throw or become restrained until the end of your next turn. As part of this gambit, you may take the attack action.</text>
        <name>Warlord (Livestream): Vexing Maneuvers</name>
        <text>   With precise movements, you and your allies dash around the foes to leave them confused and unable to pick out their most dangerous targets.</text>
        <text>   Each enemy in your tactical focus that you can see must make an Intelligence saving throw. On a failed save, it cannot leave your tactical focus using its move until the end of your next turn. As part of this gambit you may take the attack action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Way of the Blade</name>
        <text>Starting at 7th level, you blend your martial talent with the softer skills needed to navigate the world. If you are holding a weapon when you make a Strength (Athletics), Dexterity (Acrobatics), or Charisma (Intimidation) check, you gain a bonus to the roll equal to half your proficiency bonus. You use your weapon to assist in your check, such as pole vaulting with a staff, using your sword to aid your balance, or menacing an enemy with your bloodied flail.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Slayer (Livestream): Slayer's Diplomacy</name>
        <text>Starting at 7th level, you blend your martial talent with the softer skills needed to navigate the world. If you are holding a weapon when you make a Charisma (Intimidation) check, you gain a bonus to the roll equal to your proficiency bonus. You use your weapon to assist in your check, such as pole vaulting with your staff, using your sword to aid your balance, or menacing an enemy with a bloodied flail.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Rune Knight (UA): Defensive Runes</name>
        <text>7th-level Rune Knight feature</text>
        <text>You learn to invoke your rune magic to protect your allies. When another creature you can see within 60 feet of you is hit by an attack roll, you can use your reaction to grant a bonus to the creature's AC against that attack. The bonus equals 1 + your Intelligence modifier (minimum of +2).</text>
        <text>In addition, you learn one new rune of your choice from the Rune Magic feature (for a total of three).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psychic Warrior (UA): Strength of Mind</name>
        <text>7th-level Psychic Warrior feature</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, you can telekinetically lash out at a creature you can see within 20 feet of you. The target must make a Strength saving throw against a DC equal to 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Intelligence modifier. On a failed save, the target takes force damage equal to 2d6 plus your Intelligence modifier and is telekinetically moved 15 feet directly toward or away from you (your choice). On a successful save, it takes half as much damage and isn't moved.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Intelligence modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Echo Knight: Echo Avatar</name>
        <text>7th-level Echo Knight feature</text>
        <text>You can temporarily transfer your consciousness to your echo. As an action, you can see through your echo's eyes and hear through its ears. During this time, you are deafened and blinded. You can sustain this effect for up to 10 minutes, and you can end it at any time (requires no action). While your echo is being used in this way, it can be up to 1,000 feet away from you without being destroyed.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 183</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psi Knight (UA): Telekinetic Adept</name>
        <text>7th-level Psi Knight feature</text>
        <text>You have mastered new ways to use your telekinesis:</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>   Psionic Thrust.</text>
        <text>• When you deal damage to a target with the Telekinetic Strike of your Psionic Talent, you can force the target to make a Strength saving throw against a DC equal to 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Intelligence modifier. Unless the save succeeds, you can knock the target prone or move it up to 10 feet in any direction horizontally.</text>
        <text>   Telekinetic Movement.</text>
        <text>• If your Psionic Talent die is available, you can move an object or a creature with your mind. As an action, you target one loose object that is Large or smaller or one willing creature, other than yourself. If you can see the target and it is within 30 feet of you, you can move it up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space you can see. Alternatively, if it is a Tiny object, you can move it to or from your hand. Either way, you can move the target horizontally, vertically, or both. When you take this action, your Psionic Talent die decreases by one die size.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 8th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>8th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
        <feature>
          <name>Indomitable</name>
        <text>Beginning at 9th level, you can reroll a saving throw that you fail. If you do so, you must use the new roll, and you can't use this feature again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature twice between long rests starting at 13th level and three times between long rests starting at 17th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature>
          <name>Martial Archetype feature</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you gain a feature granted by your Martial Archetype.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Champion: Additional Fighting Style</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you can choose a second option from the Fighting Style class feature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Battle Master: Additional Maneuvers</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you learn two additional maneuvers of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Battle Master: Improved Combat Superiority (d10)</name>
        <text>At 10th level, your superiority dice turn into d10s.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier (UA): Improved Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 10th level, your superiority dice turn into d10s. At 18th level, they turn into d12s.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier v2 (UA): Improved Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 10th level, your superiority dice turn into d10s. At 18th level, they turn into d12s.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Eldritch Knight: Eldritch Strike</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you learn how to make your weapon strikes undercut a creature's resistance to your spells. When you hit a creature with a weapon attack, that creature has disadvantage on the next saving throw it makes against a spell you cast before the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 74</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Hunter (UA): Improved Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 10th level, your superiority dice turn into d10s. At 18th level, they turn into d12s.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Purple Dragon Knight (Banneret): Inspiring Surge</name>
        <text>Starting at 10th level, when you use your Action Surge feature, you can choose one creature within 60 feet of you that is allied with you. That creature can make one melee or ranged weapon attack with its reaction, provided that it can see or hear you.</text>
        <text>Starting at 18th level, you can choose two allies within 60 feet of you, rather than one.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 128</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Improved Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 10th level, your superiority dice turn into d10s. At 18th level, they turn into d12s.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer (UA): Extra Arcane Shot</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you learn an additional Arcane Shot option.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Extra Arcane Shot</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you learn an additional Arcane Shot option.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Knight (UA): Hold the Line</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you master the ability to harass and slow your enemies. As a reaction when a creature moves at least 1 foot within 5 feet of you, you can make one melee weapon attack against that creature. If you hit, the attack's weapon deals extra damage to the target equal to half your fighter level, and the target's speed is reduced to 0 until the end of this turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Samurai (UA): Unbreakable Will</name>
        <text>At 10th level, your superior willpower allows you to shrug off mind-assaulting effects. You gain proficiency in Wisdom saving throws. If you already have this proficiency, you gain proficiency in Intelligence or Charisma saving throws (choose one).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sharpshooter (UA): Close-Quarters Shooting</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you learn to handle yourself in close combat. Making a ranged attack roll while within 5 feet of an enemy doesn't impose disadvantage on your roll.</text>
        <text>In addition, if you hit a creature within 5 feet of you with a ranged attack on your turn, that creature can't take reactions until the end of this turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer: Additional Arcane Shot Option</name>
        <text>You gain an additional Arcane Shot option of your choice when you reach 10th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 28</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier: Hold the Line</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you become a master of locking down your enemies. Creatures provoke an opportunity attack from you when they move 5 feet or more while within your reach, and if you hit a creature with an opportunity attack, the target's speed is reduced to 0 until the end of the current turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 30</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Samurai: Tireless Spirit</name>
        <text>Starting at 10th level, when you roll initiative and have no uses of Fighting Spirit remaining, you regain one use.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 31</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Brute (UA): Additional Fighting Style</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you can choose a second option from the Fighting Style feature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Three Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Warlord (Livestream): Additional Gambit</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you learn an additional gambit of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Warlord (Livestream): Lead from the Front</name>
        <text>At 10th level you strike with a cunning insight that allows your allies to make effective follow up attacks.</text>
        <text>If you hit a creature with a weapon attack, it has disadvantage on all saving throws against your gambits until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Superior Fighting Style</name>
        <text>Starting at 10th level, your mastery of your fighting style deepens. You can choose a second option from the Fighting Style feature you gain at 2nd level, or you can choose an improved version of a fighting style you already know as detailed below.</text>
        <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Superior Archery</name>
        <text>   You gain a +3 bonus to attack rolls you make with ranged weapons.</text>
        <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Superior Defense</name>
        <text>   While you are wearing armor, you gain a +1 bonus to AC. You also gain a +1 bonus to all saving throws.</text>
        <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Superior Dueling</name>
        <text>   When you are wielding a melee weapon in one hand and no other weapons, you gain a +4 bonus to damage rolls with that weapon.</text>
        <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Superior Great Weapon Fighting</name>
        <text>   When you roll a 1, 2, or 3 on a damage die for an attack you make with a melee weapon that you are wielding with two hands, you can reroll the die and must use the new roll, even if the new roll is 1, 2, or 3. The weapon must have the two-handed or versatile property for you to gain this benefit.</text>
        <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Superior Protection</name>
        <text>   When a creature you can see attacks a target other than you that is within 5 feet of you, you can use your reaction to impose disadvantage on the attack roll and make an opportunity attack against the attacker. You must be wielding a shield.</text>
        <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Superior Two-Weapon Fighting</name>
        <text>   When you engage in two-weapon fighting, you can add your ability modifier to the damage of the second attack. You gain a +1 bonus to AC while you are wielding a separate melee weapon in each hand.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Slayer (Livestream): Superior Exploits</name>
        <text>Starting at 10th level, your mastery of your exploits allows you to maximize their effectiveness.</text>
        <name>Slayer (Livestream): Improved Adamantine Bones</name>
        <text>   When you use Adamantine Bones, you gain advantage on all saving throws until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <name>Slayer (Livestream): Improved Bell Ringer</name>
        <text>   If a target successfully saves against your Bell Ringer exploit or the attack misses, you can choose to not expend the use of your exploit. If you do so, you cannot use Bell Ringer again until the start of your next turn.</text>
        <name>Slayer (Livestream): Improved Masterful Strike</name>
        <text>   You now roll d8s instead of d6s when using Masterful Strike.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Rune Knight (UA): Great Stature</name>
        <text>10th-level Rune Knight feature</text>
        <text>The magic of your runes permanently alters you. When you gain this feature, roll  3d4. You grow a number of inches in height equal to the roll. Moreover, the extra damage you deal with your Giant Might feature increases to  1d8.</text>
        <text>In addition, you learn one new rune of your choice from your Rune Magic feature (for a total of four).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psychic Warrior (UA): Psionic Armament Improvement</name>
        <text>10th-level Psychic Warrior feature</text>
        <text>When you reach 10th level in this class, your Augmented Defenses dice increases to 1d12, and your Augmented Strikes dice increases to a d6.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psychic Warrior (UA): Telekinetic Bulwark</name>
        <text>10th-level Psychic Warrior feature</text>
        <text>When you take the Attack action, you can forgo one of your attacks to project a bastion of psionic power in a 10-foot radius around yourself. It lasts for 1 minute or until you're incapacitated. For the duration, you and your allies in that area gain the benefits of half cover and have advantage on Strength saving throws.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest or until after you use your Second Wind feature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Echo Knight: Shadow Martyr</name>
        <text>10th-level Echo Knight feature</text>
        <text>You can make your echo throw itself in front of an attack directed at another creature that you can see. Before the attack roll is made, you can use your reaction to teleport the echo to an unoccupied space within 5 feet of the targeted creature. The attack roll that triggered the reaction is instead made against your echo.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 183</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psi Knight (UA): Psi-Enhanced Metabolism</name>
        <text>10th-level Psi Knight feature</text>
        <text>The psionic energy flowing through you has bolstered your mind and body. You have resistance to poison and psychic damage, and you are immune to the poisoned condition.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature>
          <name>Extra Attack (2)</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you can attack three times whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 12th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>12th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
        <feature>
          <name>Indomitable (two uses)</name>
        <text>At 13th level, you can use Indomitable twice between long rests.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 14th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>14th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature>
          <name>Martial Archetype feature</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you gain a feature granted by your Martial Archetype.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Champion: Superior Critical</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, your weapon attacks score a critical hit on a roll of 18-20.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Battle Master: Additional Maneuvers</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you learn two additional maneuvers of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Battle Master: Additional Superiority Die</name>
        <text>You gain another superiority die at 15th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Battle Master: Relentless</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, when you roll initiative and have no superiority dice remaining, you regain 1 superiority die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier (UA): Relentless</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, when you roll initiative and have no superiority dice remaining, you regain 1 superiority die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier v2 (UA): Relentless</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, when you roll initiative and have no superiority dice remaining, you regain one superiority die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Eldritch Knight: Arcane Charge</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you gain the ability to teleport up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space you can see when you use your Action Surge. You can teleport before or after the additional action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 74</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Hunter (UA): Relentless</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, when you roll initiative and have no superiority dice remaining, you regain 1 superiority die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Purple Dragon Knight (Banneret): Bulwark</name>
        <text>Beginning at 15th level, you can extend the benefit of your Indomitable feature to an ally. When you decide to use Indomitable to reroll an Intelligence, a Wisdom, or a Charisma saving throw and you aren't incapacitated, you can choose one ally within 60 feet of you that also failed its saving throw against the same effect. If that creature can see or hear you, it can reroll its saving throw and must use the new roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 128</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Additional Superiority Die</name>
        <text>You gain another superiority die at 15th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Relentless</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, when you roll initiative and have no superiority dice remaining, you regain 1 superiority die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer (UA): Ever-Ready Arrow</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, you can conjure forth a magic-infused arrow more often than before. One minute after expending your last remaining use of Arcane Arrow, you regain one use of it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer (UA): Extra Arcane Shot</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you learn an additional Arcane Shot option.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Ever-Ready Shot</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, your magical archery is ever available to you when you need it most. If you roll initiative and have no uses of Arcane Shot remaining, you regain one use of it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Extra Arcane Shot</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you learn an additional Arcane Shot option.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Knight (UA): Rapid Strike</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, you learn to trade accuracy for swift strikes. If you have advantage on a weapon attack against a target on your turn, you can forgo that advantage to immediately make an additional weapon attack against the same target as a bonus action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Samurai (UA): Rapid Strike</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, you learn to trade accuracy for swift strikes. If you have advantage on a weapon attack against a target on your turn, you can forgo that advantage to immediately make an additional weapon attack against the same target as a bonus action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sharpshooter (UA): Rapid Strike</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, you learn to trade accuracy for swift strikes. If you have advantage on a weapon attack against a target on your turn, you can forgo that advantage to immediately make an additional weapon attack against the same target as a bonus action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer: Additional Arcane Shot Option</name>
        <text>You gain an additional Arcane Shot option of your choice when you reach 15th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 28</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer: Ever-Ready Shot</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, your magical archery is available whenever battle starts. If you roll initiative and have no uses of Arcane Shot remaining, you regain one use of it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 28</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier: Ferocious Charger</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, you can run down your foes, whether you're mounted or not. If you move at least 10 feet in a straight line right before attacking a creature and you hit it with the attack, that target must succeed on a Strength saving throw (DC 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Strength modifier) or be knocked prone. You can use this feature only once on each of your turns.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 30</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Samurai: Rapid Strike</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, you learn to trade accuracy for swift strikes. If you take the Attack action on your turn and have advantage on an attack roll against one of the targets, you can forgo the advantage for that roll to make an additional weapon attack against that target, as part of the same action. You can do so no more than once per turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 31</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Brute (UA): Devastating Critical</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, when you score a critical hit with a weapon attack, you gain a bonus to that weapon's damage roll equal to your level in this class.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Three Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Warlord (Livestream): Additional Tactic</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you learn an additional tactic of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Warlord (Livestream): Tactical Maneuvers</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you can provide leadership that allows your allies to move in perfect harmony.</text>
        <text>In place of moving, you can instead allow up to three allies who can see or hear you to move up to half their speed. The chosen allies must be capable of taking actions in order to move in this manner.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Unknown</name>
        <text>[No content available.]</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Slayer (Livestream): Bloodthirsty Rush</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, you strike with speed and certainty that catches others off guard. When rolling initiative, you add your proficiency bonus to the roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Rune Knight (UA): Rune Magic Mastery</name>
        <text>15th-level Rune Knight feature</text>
        <text>You can invoke each rune you know from your Rune Magic feature twice, rather than once, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>In addition, you learn one new rune of your choice from the Rune Magic feature (for a total of five).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psychic Warrior (UA): Agonizing Strikes</name>
        <text>15th-level Psychic Warrior feature</text>
        <text>Your attacks can channel psychic agony. When you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can also deal 2d10 psychic damage to that target and force it to make a Constitution saving throw against a DC equal to 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Intelligence modifier. Unless the save succeeds, the target falls prone, and it suffers disadvantage on ability checks until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Intelligence modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Echo Knight: Reclaim Potential</name>
        <text>15th-level Echo Knight feature</text>
        <text>You've learned to absorb the fleeting magic of your echo. When an echo of yours is destroyed by taking damage, you can gain a number of temporary hit points equal to 2d6 + your Constitution modifier, provided you don't already have temporary hit points.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Constitution modifier (a minimum of once). You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 183</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psi Knight (UA): Bulwark of Force</name>
        <text>15th-level Psi Knight feature</text>
        <text>You can shield yourself and others with telekinetic force. As a bonus action, you can choose creatures, which can include you, that you can see within 30 feet of you, up to a number of creatures equal to your Intelligence modifier (minimum of one creature). Each of the chosen creatures is protected by half cover for 1 minute or until you're incapacitated. Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest, unless you decrease your Psionic Talent die by one die size to use this feature again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 16th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>16th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature>
          <name>Action Surge (two uses)</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you can use Action Surge twice before a rest, but only once on the same turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature>
          <name>Indomitable (three uses)</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you can use Indomitable three times between long rests.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature>
          <name>Martial Archetype feature</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you gain a feature granted by your Martial Archetype.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Champion: Survivor</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you attain the pinnacle of resilience in battle. At the start of each of your turns, you regain hit points equal to 5 + your Constitution modifier if you have no more than half of your hit points left. You don't gain this benefit if you have 0 hit points.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Battle Master: Improved Combat Superiority (d12)</name>
        <text>At 18th level, your superiority dice turn into d12s.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier (UA): Improved Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 18th level, your superiority dice turn into d12s.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier v2 (UA): Improved Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 18th level, your superiority dice turn into d12s.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Eldritch Knight: Improved War Magic</name>
        <text>Starting at 18th level, when you use your action to cast a spell, you can make one weapon attack as a bonus action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 74</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Hunter (UA): Improved Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 18th level, your superiority dice turn into d12s.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Gothic Heroes p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Purple Dragon Knight (Banneret): Inspiring Surge</name>
        <text>Starting at 18th level, you can choose two allies within 60 feet of you, rather than one.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 128</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Improved Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 18th level, your superiority dice turn into d12s.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer (UA): Deadly Arrow</name>
        <text>At 18th level, your Arcane Arrow's bonus damage increases to 4d6 force damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer (UA): Extra Arcane Shot</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you learn an additional Arcane Shot option.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Extra Arcane Shot</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you learn an additional Arcane Shot option.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Knight (UA): Defender's Blade</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you respond to danger with extraordinary vigilance. You can use your reaction for an opportunity attack even if you have already expended your reaction this round, but not if you have already used your reaction this turn.</text>
        <text>In addition, you gain a +1 bonus to AC while wearing heavy armor.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Samurai (UA): Strength Before Death</name>
        <text>Starting at 18th level, your fighting spirit can delay the grasp of death. If you take damage that would reduce you to 0 hit points, you can delay that damage and immediately take a bonus turn, interrupting the current turn. You don't take the damage until the bonus turn ends. It is possible to do things, such as gaining resistance, that change how much of that damage you take.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sharpshooter (UA): Snap Shot</name>
        <text>Starting at 18th level, you are ever ready to spring into action. If you take the Attack action on your first turn of a combat, you can make one additional ranged weapon attack as part of that action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer: Additional Arcane Shot Option</name>
        <text>You gain an additional Arcane Shot option of your choice when you reach 18th level. Each option also improves when you become an 18th-level fighter.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 28</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier: Vigilant Defender</name>
        <text>Starting at 18th level, you respond to danger with extraordinary vigilance. In combat, you get a special reaction that you can take once on every creature's turn, except your turn. You can use this special reaction only to make an opportunity attack, and you can't use it on the same turn that you take your normal reaction.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 30</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Samurai: Strength before Death</name>
        <text>Starting at 18th level, your fighting spirit can delay the grasp of death. If you take damage that reduces you to 0 hit points and doesn't kill you outright, you can use your reaction to delay falling unconscious, and you can immediately take an extra turn, interrupting the current turn. While you have 0 hit points during that extra turn, taking damage causes death saving throw failures as normal, and three death saving throw failures can still kill you. When the extra turn ends, you fall unconscious if you still have 0 hit points.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 31</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Brute (UA): Survivor</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you attain the pinnacle of resilience in battle. At the start of each of your turns in combat, you regain hit points equal to 5 + your Constitution modifier (minimum of 1 hit point). You don't gain this benefit if you have 0 hit points or if you have more than half of your hit points left.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Three Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Warlord (Livestream): Additional Gambit</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you learn an additional gambit of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Warlord (Livestream): Perfect Coordination</name>
        <text>Starting at 18th level, you gain the ability to unleash a devastating combination of your allies' abilities. As a bonus action, select up to five allies who can see or hear you. They can use their reactions to immediately take actions.</text>
        <text>Once you use this ability, you cannot use it again until you complete a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Weapon Master (Livestream): Unknown</name>
        <text>[No content available.]</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Slayer (Livestream): Overwhelming Momentum</name>
        <text>Starting at 18th level, when you miss a foe with a melee attack, your next attack this turn against that target gains advantage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Livestream</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Rune Knight (UA): Blessing of the All Father</name>
        <text>18th-level Rune Knight feature</text>
        <text>You learn how to share your rune magic with your allies. When you use your Giant Might feature, you can choose one willing creature you can see within 60 feet of you. The chosen creature also gains the benefits of your Giant Might feature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psychic Warrior (UA): Psychic Dreadnaught</name>
        <text>18th-level Psychic Warrior feature</text>
        <text>The power of your mind suffuses your entire being, making you a nigh-unstoppable force on the battlefield. Using your reaction when you take damage, you can give yourself the following benefits for 1 minute or until you're incapacitated:</text>
        <text>• At the start of each of your turns, you regain 10 hit points.</text>
        <text>• Your walking speed increases by 10 feet.</text>
        <text>• If you're prone, you can stand up by spending 5 feet of movement.</text>
        <text>Once you activate this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Echo Knight: Legion of One</name>
        <text>18th-level Echo Knight feature</text>
        <text>You can use a bonus action to create two echoes with your Manifest Echo feature, and these echoes can coexist. If you try to create a third echo, the previous two echoes are destroyed. Anything you can do from one echo's position can be done from the other's instead.</text>
        <text>In addition, when you roll initiative and have no uses of your Unleash Incarnation feature left, you regain one use of that feature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 183</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psi Knight (UA): Telekinetic Master</name>
        <text>18th-level Psi Knight feature</text>
        <text>Your ability to move creatures and objects with your mind is matched by few. If your Psionic Talent die is available, you can cast the telekinesis spell, requiring no components. Your spellcasting ability for the spell is Intelligence. When you cast this spell, your Psionic Talent die decreases by one die size.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 19th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>19th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
        <feature>
          <name>Extra Attack (3)</name>
        <text>At 20th level, you can attack four times whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
