<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Wizard</name>
    <hd>6</hd>
    <proficiency>Intelligence, Wisdom, Arcana, History, Insight, Investigation, Medicine, Religion</proficiency>
    <numSkills>2</numSkills>
    <spellAbility>Intelligence</spellAbility>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Starting Wizard</name>
        <text>As a 1st-level Wizard, you begin play with 6+your Constitution modifier hit points.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>You are proficient with the following items, in addition to any proficiencies provided by your race or background.</text>
        <text>• Armor: none</text>
        <text>• Weapons: daggers, darts, slings, quarterstaffs, light crossbows</text>
        <text>• Tools: none</text>
        <text>• Skills: Choose 2 from Arcana, History, Insight, Investigation, Medicine, Religion</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>You begin play with the following equipment, in addition to any equipment provided by your background.</text>
        <text>• (a) a quarterstaff or (b) a dagger</text>
        <text>• (a) a component pouch or (b) an arcane focus</text>
        <text>• (a) a scholar's pack or (b) an explorer's pack</text>
        <text>• A spellbook</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Alternatively, you may start with 4d4 x 10 gp and choose your own equipment.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 112</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Multiclass Wizard</name>
        <text>To multiclass as a Wizard, you must meet the following prerequisites:</text>
        <text>• Intelligence 13</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 112</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <armor>none</armor>
    <weapons>daggers, darts, slings, quarterstaffs, light crossbows</weapons>
    <tools>none</tools>
    <wealth>4d4 x 10</wealth>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <slots>3, 2</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Arcane Recovery</name>
        <text>You have learned to regain some of your magical energy by studying your spellbook. Once per day when you finish a short rest, you can choose expended spell slots to recover. The spell slots can have a combined level that is equal to or less than half your wizard level (rounded up), and none of the slots can be 6th level or higher.</text>
        <text>For example, if you're a 4th-level wizard, you can recover up to two levels worth of spell slots.</text>
        <text>You can recover either a 2nd-level spell slot or two 1st-level spell slots.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 112</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Spellcasting</name>
        <text>As a student of arcane magic, you have a spellbook containing spells that show the first glimmerings of your true power. See chapter 10 for the general rules of spellcasting and chapter 11 for the wizard spell list.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Cantrips:</text>
        <text>   At 1st level, you know three cantrips of your choice from the wizard spell list. You learn additional wizard cantrips of your choice at higher levels, as shown in the Cantrips Known column of the Wizard table.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Spellbook:</text>
        <text>   At 1st level, you have a spellbook containing six 1st-level wizard spells of your choice. Your spellbook is the repository of the wizard spells you know, except your cantrips, which are fixed in your mind.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Preparing and Casting Spells:</text>
        <text>   The Wizard table shows how many spell slots you have to cast your spells of 1st level and higher. To cast one of these spells, you must expend a slot of the spell's level or higher. You regain all expended spell slots when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>   You prepare the list of wizard spells that are available for you to cast. To do so, choose a number of wizard spells from your spellbook equal to your Intelligence modifier + your wizard level (minimum of one spell). The spells must be of a level for which you have spell slots.</text>
        <text>   For example, if you're a 3rd-level wizard, you have four 1st-level and two 2nd-level spell slots. With an Intelligence of 16, your list of prepared spells can include six spells of 1st or 2nd level, in any combination, chosen from your spellbook. If you prepare the 1st-level spell magic missile, you can cast it using a 1st-level or a 2nd-level slot. Casting the spell doesn't remove it from your list of prepared spells.</text>
        <text>   You can change your list of prepared spells when you finish a long rest. Preparing a new list of wizard spells requires time spent studying your spellbook and memorizing the incantations and gestures you must make to cast the spell: at least 1 minute per spell level for each spell on your list.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Spellcasting Ability:</text>
        <text>   Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for your wizard spells, since you learn your wizard spells through dedicated study and memorization. You use your Intelligence whenever a spell refers to your spellcasting ability. In addition, you use your Intelligence modifier when setting the saving throw DC for a wizard spell you cast and when making an attack roll with one.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Ritual Casting:</text>
        <text>   You can cast a wizard spell as a ritual if that spell has the ritual tag and you have the spell in your spellbook. You don't need to have the spell prepared.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Spellcasting Focus:</text>
        <text>   You can use an arcane focus as a spellcasting focus for your wizard spells.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Learning Spells of 1st Level and Higher:</text>
        <text>   Each time you gain a wizard level, you can add two wizard spells of your choice to your spellbook. Each of these spells must be of a level for which you have spell slots, as shown on the Wizard table. On your adventures, you might find other spells that you can add to your spellbook (see "Your Spellbook").</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Your Spellbook:</text>
        <text>   The spells that you add to your spellbook as you gain levels reflect the arcane research you conduct on your own, as well as intellectual breakthroughs you have had about the nature of the multiverse. You might find other spells during your adventures. You could discover a spell recorded on a scroll in an evil wizard's chest, for example, or in a dusty tome in an ancient library.</text>
        <text>   A spellbook doesn't contain cantrips.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Copying a Spell into the Book:</text>
        <text>   When you find a wizard spell of 1st level or higher, you can add it to your spellbook if it is of a spell level you can prepare and if you can spare the time to decipher and copy it.</text>
        <text>   Copying a spell into your spellbook involves reproducing the basic form of the spell, then deciphering the unique system of notation used by the wizard who wrote it. You must practice the spell until you understand the sounds or gestures required, then transcribe it into your spellbook using your own notation.</text>
        <text>   For each level of the spell, the process takes 2 hours and costs 50 gp. The cost represents material components you expend as you experiment with the spell to master it, as well as the fine inks you need to record it. Once you have spent this time and money, you can prepare the spell just like your other spells.</text>
        <text>   A wizard spell on a spell scroll can be copied just as spells in spellbooks can be copied. When you copy a spell from a spell scroll, you must succeed on an Intelligence (Arcana) check with a DC equal to 10 + the spell's level. If the check succeeds, the spell is successfully copied. Whether the check succeeds or fails, the spell scroll is destroyed.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Replacing the Book:</text>
        <text>   You can copy a spell from your own spellbook into another book—for example, if you want to make a backup copy of your spellbook. This is just like copying a new spell into your spellbook, but faster and easier, since you understand your own notation and already know how to cast the spell. You need spend only 1 hour and 10 gp for each level of the copied spell.</text>
        <text>   If you lose your spellbook, you can use the same procedure to transcribe the spells that you have prepared into a new spellbook. Filling out the remainder of your spellbook requires you to find new spells to do so, as normal. For this reason, many wizards keep backup spellbooks in a safe place.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>The Book's Appearance:</text>
        <text>   Your spellbook is a unique compilation of spells, with its own decorative flourishes and margin notes. It might be a plain, functional leather volume that you received as a gift from your master, a finely bound gilt-edged tome you found in an ancient library, or even a loose collection of notes scrounged together after you lost your previous spellbook in a mishap.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 112</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Cantrip Versatility</name>
        <text>1st-level wizard feature (enhances Spellcasting)</text>
        <text>Whenever you gain a level in this class, you can replace one cantrip you learned from this Spellcasting feature with another cantrip from the wizard spell list.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 12</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <slots>3, 3</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature>
          <name>Arcane Tradition</name>
        <text>When you reach 2nd level, you choose an arcane tradition from the list of available traditions, shaping your practice of magic. Your choice grants you features at 2nd level and again at 6th, 10th, and 14th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 112</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Artificer (UA): Artificer</name>
        <text>Artificers are a key part of the world of Eberron. They illustrate the evolution of magic from a wild, unpredictable force to one that is becoming available to the masses. Magic items are part of everyday life in the Five Nations of Khorvaire; with an artificer in your party, they become part of every adventuring expedition.</text>
        <text>The artificer was a separate class in prior editions of the Eberron setting, a melee combatant who specialized in mystically enhanced arms and armor. The fifth edition rules treat the artificer as a new wizard tradition that focuses on mystical invention, which you can choose starting at 2nd level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Artificer (UA): Infuse Potions</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can produce magic potions. You spend 10 minutes focusing your magic on a vial of mundane water and expend a spell slot to transform it into a potion. Once you have expended a spell slot to create a potion, you cannot regain that slot until the potion is consumed or after 1 week, at which time the potion loses its effectiveness. You can create up to three potions at a time; creating a fourth potion causes the oldest currently active one to immediately lose its potency. If that potion has been consumed, its effects immediately end.</text>
        <text>The spell slot you expend determines the type of potion you can create.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Infuse Potions</text>
        <text>Spell Slot | Potion Created</text>
        <text>1st | Climbing, growth, or healing</text>
        <text>2nd | Mind reading or greater healing</text>
        <text>3rd | Invisibility, superior healing, or water breathing</text>
        <text>4th | Resistance</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Artificer (UA): Infuse Scrolls</name>
        <text>At 2nd level, you can also tap into your reserves of magical energy to create spell scrolls. You can use your Arcane Recovery ability to create a scroll instead of regaining expended spell slots.</text>
        <text>You must finish a short rest, then spend 10 minutes with parchment, quill, and ink to create a spell scroll containing one spell chosen from those you know. Subtract the spell's level from the total levels worth of slots you regain using Arcane Recovery. This reduction to your Arcane Recovery applies until you use the scroll and then finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Tradition: School of Abjuration</name>
        <text>The School of Abjuration emphasizes magic that blocks, banishes, or protects. Detractors of this school say that its tradition is about denial, negation rather than positive assertion. You understand, however, that ending harmful effects, protecting the weak, and banishing evil influences is anything but a philosophical void. It is a proud and respected vocation.</text>
        <text>Called abjurers, members of this school are sought when baleful spirits require exorcism, when important locations must be guarded against magical spying, and when portals to other planes of existence must be closed.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 115</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Abjuration: Abjuration Savant</name>
        <text>Beginning when you select this school at 2nd level, the gold and time you must spend to copy an abjuration spell into your spellbook is halved.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 115</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Abjuration: Arcane Ward</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can weave magic around yourself for protection. When you cast an abjuration spell of 1st level or higher, you can simultaneously use a strand of the spell's magic to create a magical ward on yourself that lasts until you finish a long rest. The ward has hit points equal to twice your wizard level + your Intelligence modifier. Whenever you take damage, the ward takes the damage instead. If this damage reduces the ward to 0 hit points, you take any remaining damage.</text>
        <text>While the ward has 0 hit points, it can't absorb damage, but its magic remains. Whenever you cast an abjuration spell of 1st level or higher, the ward regains a number of hit points equal to twice the level of the spell.</text>
        <text>Once you create the ward, you can't create it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 115</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Tradition: Bladesinging</name>
        <text>Bladesingers are elves who bravely defend their people and lands. They are elf wizards who master a school of sword fighting grounded in a tradition of arcane magic. In combat, a bladesinger uses a series of intricate, elegant maneuvers that fend off harm and allow the bladesinger to channel magic into devastating attacks and a cunning defense.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 141</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Bladesinging: Bladesinger Styles</name>
        <text>From its inception as a martial and magical art, Bladesinging has been tied to the sword, more specifically the longsword. Yet many generations of study gave rise to various styles of Bladesinging based on the melee weapon employed. The techniques of these styles are passed from master to students in small schools, some of which have a building dedicated to instruction. Even the newest styles are hundreds of years old, but are still taught by their original creators due to the long lives of elves. Most schools of Bladesinging are in Evermeet or Evereska. One was started in Myth Drannor, but the city's destruction has scattered those students who survived.</text>
        <text>Styles of Bladesinging are broadly categorized based on the type of weapon employed, and each is associated with a category of animal. Within that style are specializations named after specific animal types, based on the types of spells employed, the techniques of the master, and the particular weapon used. Bladesingers who apprentice to a master typically get a tattoo of their chosen style's animal. Some bladesingers learn multiple styles and bear many tattoos, wearing a warning on their skin of their deadly skills.</text>
        <name>Bladesinging: Cat</name>
        <text>   Styles that employ a sword belong to this family. The lion style, the eldest, trains practitioners in the use of the longsword and doesn't favor any particular type of spells. Leopard style focuses on the shortsword and spells of illusion and stealth. Red tiger, a style just three centuries old, has its bladesingers using the scimitar in a whirling dance of defense from which they launch into sudden leaps and attacks.</text>
        <name>Bladesinging: Bird</name>
        <text>   Styles that focus on the use of a hafted weapon, such as an axe or hammer, have been grouped together as bird styles, yet they vary wildly. All relatively new styles, they use weapons not typically favored by elves. Eagle-style bladesingers use small handaxes, and many maneuvers in the style focus on fluid ways to throw the weapon and draw a new one. Raven style uses a war pick, and spells associated with it grant the bladesinger more agility in combat.</text>
        <name>Bladesinging: Snake</name>
        <text>   Practitioners of these styles use a flail, chain, or whip. Viper style uses a whip, despite its inelegance as a weapon, and has almost as long a history as the lion style. Its masters punctuate their bladesong with a stunningly rapid rhythm of whip cracks, which can keep many foes at bay and allow the bladesinger space to cast the cruel spells of poison and disease favored by the style.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 141</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Bladesinging: Bladesong</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can invoke a secret elven magic called the Bladesong, provided you aren't wearing medium or heavy armor or using a shield. It graces you with supernatural speed, agility, and focus.</text>
        <text>You can use a bonus action to start the Bladesong, which lasts for 1 minute. It ends early if you are incapacitated, if you don medium or heavy armor or a shield, or if you use two hands to make an attack with a weapon. You can also dismiss Bladesong at any time you choose (no action required).</text>
        <text>While your bladesong is active, you gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• You gain a bonus to your AC equal to your Intelligence modifier (minimum of +1).</text>
        <text>• Your walking speed increases by 10 feet.</text>
        <text>• You have advantage on Dexterity (Acrobatics) checks.</text>
        <text>• You gain a bonus to any Constitution saving throws you make to maintain concentration on a spell. The bonus equals your Intelligence modifier (minimum of +1).</text>
        <text>You can use this feature twice. You regain all expended uses of it when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 141</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Bladesinging: Restriction: Elves Only</name>
        <text>Only elves and half-elves can choose the bladesinger arcane tradition. In the world of Faerûn, elves closely guard the secrets of bladesinging.</text>
        <text>Your DM can lift this restriction to better suit the campaign. The restriction reflects the story of bladesingers in the Forgotten Realms, but it might not apply to your DM's setting or your DM's version of the Realms.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 141</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Bladesinging: Training in War and Song (Bladesinging)</name>
        <text>When you adopt this tradition at 2nd level, you gain proficiency with light armor, and you gain proficiency with one type of one-handed melee weapon of your choice.</text>
        <text>You also gain proficiency in the Performance skill if you don't already have it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 141</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Tradition: School of Conjuration</name>
        <text>As a conjurer, you favor spells that produce objects and creatures out of thin air. You can conjure billowing clouds of killing fog or summon creatures from elsewhere to fight on your behalf. As your mastery grows, you learn spells of transportation and can teleport yourself across vast distances, even to other planes of existence, in an instant.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 116</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Conjuration: Conjuration Savant</name>
        <text>Beginning when you select this school at 2nd level, the gold and time you must spend to copy a conjuration spell into your spellbook is halved.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 116</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Conjuration: Minor Conjuration</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level when you select this school, you can use your action to conjure up an inanimate object in your hand or on the ground in an unoccupied space that you can see within 10 feet of you. This object can be no larger than 3 feet on a side and weigh no more than 10 pounds, and its form must be that of a nonmagical object that you have seen. The object is visibly magical, radiating dim light out to 5 feet.</text>
        <text>The object disappears after 1 hour, when you use this feature again, if it takes any damage, or if it deals any damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 116</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Tradition: School of Divination</name>
        <text>The counsel of a diviner is sought by royalty and commoners alike, for all seek a clearer understanding of the past, present, and future. As a diviner, you strive to part the veils of space, time, and consciousness so that you can see clearly. You work to master spells of discernment, remote viewing, supernatural knowledge, and foresight.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 116</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Divination: Divination Savant</name>
        <text>Beginning when you select this school at 2nd level, the gold and time you must spend to copy a divination spell into your spellbook is halved.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 116</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Divination: Portent</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level when you choose this school, glimpses of the future begin to press in on your awareness. When you finish a long rest, roll two d20s and record the numbers rolled. You can replace any attack roll, saving throw, or ability check made by you or a creature that you can see with one of these foretelling rolls. You must choose to do so before the roll, and you can replace a roll in this way only once per turn.</text>
        <text>Each foretelling roll can be used only once. When you finish a long rest, you lose any unused foretelling rolls.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 116</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Tradition: School of Enchantment</name>
        <text>As a member of the School of Enchantment, you have honed your ability to magically entrance and beguile other people and monsters. Some enchanters are peacemakers who bewitch the violent to lay down their arms and charm the cruel into showing mercy. Others are tyrants who magically bind the unwilling into their service. Most enchanters fall somewhere in between.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 117</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Enchantment: Enchantment Savant</name>
        <text>Beginning when you select this school at 2nd level, the gold and time you must spend to copy an enchantment spell into your spellbook is halved.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 117</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Enchantment: Hypnotic Gaze</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level when you choose this school, your soft words and enchanting gaze can magically enthrall another creature. As an action, choose one creature that you can see within 5 feet of you. If the target can see or hear you, it must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your wizard spell save DC or be charmed by you until the end of your next turn. The charmed creature's speed drops to 0, and the creature is incapacitated and visibly dazed.</text>
        <text>On subsequent turns, you can use your action to maintain this effect, extending its duration until the end of your next turn. However, the effect ends if you move more than 5 feet away from the creature, if the creature can neither see nor hear you, or if the creature takes damage.</text>
        <text>Once the effect ends, or if the creature succeeds on its initial saving throw against this effect, you can't use this feature on that creature again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 117</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Tradition: School of Evocation</name>
        <text>You focus your study on magic that creates powerful elemental effects such as bitter cold, searing flame, rolling thunder, crackling lightning, and burning acid. Some evokers find employment in military forces, serving as artillery to blast enemy armies from afar. Others use their spectacular power to protect the weak, while some seek their own gain as bandits, adventurers, or aspiring tyrants.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 117</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Evocation: Evocation Savant</name>
        <text>Beginning when you select this school at 2nd level, the gold and time you must spend to copy an evocation spell into your spellbook is halved.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 117</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Evocation: Sculpt Spells</name>
        <text>Beginning at 2nd level, you can create pockets of relative safety within the effects of your evocation spells. When you cast an evocation spell that affects other creatures that you can see, you can choose a number of them equal to 1 + the spell's level. The chosen creatures automatically succeed on their saving throws against the spell, and they take no damage if they would normally take half damage on a successful save.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 117</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Tradition: School of Illusion</name>
        <text>You focus your studies on magic that dazzles the senses, befuddles the mind, and tricks even the wisest folk. Your magic is subtle, but the illusions crafted by your keen mind make the impossible seem real. Some illusionists—including many gnome wizards—are benign tricksters who use their spells to entertain. Others are more sinister masters of deception, using their illusions to frighten and fool others for their personal gain.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 118</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Illusion: Illusion Savant</name>
        <text>Beginning when you select this school at 2nd level, the gold and time you must spend to copy an illusion spell into your spellbook is halved.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 118</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Illusion: Improved Minor Illusion</name>
        <text>When you choose this school at 2nd level, you learn the minor illusion cantrip. If you already know this cantrip, you learn a different wizard cantrip of your choice. The cantrip doesn't count against your number of cantrips known.</text>
        <text>When you cast minor illusion, you can create both a sound and an image with a single casting of the spell.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 118</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Technomancy (UA): Technomancy</name>
        <text>Unlike the more common arcane traditions based around the schools of magic, the tradition of Technomancy does not focus on a singular type of spellcraft or magical energy. Rather, students of Technomancy concern themselves with how their spells interact with modern technology.</text>
        <text>Technomancers can make use of technology as both a conduit and a storage space for magic. In a campaign using the optional rules for magic item creation (see the Dungeon Master's Guide), a technomancer might craft disposable electronic devices and smartphone apps in lieu of potions and scrolls.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Technomancy (UA): Bonus Proficiencies</name>
        <text>Beginning when you select this arcane tradition at 2nd level, you gain proficiency with sidearms and hacking tools.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Technomancy (UA): Technological Savant</name>
        <text>Also at 2nd level, you trade out your spellbook for a specially attuned storage device of your choosing, capable of recording magical data. The computing power of this device must be equal to or greater than a tablet computer. Only one storage device can be attuned to you at any given time. Spells can be copied into this device at half the cost of copying spells into a spellbook.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Theurgy (UA): Theurgy</name>
        <text>A number of deities claim arcane magic as their domain, for magic is as much a part of the fabric of the cosmos as wind, fire, lightning, and all other primal forces. Just as there are deities of the sea and gods of warfare, the arcane arts feature their own divine patrons.</text>
        <text>Such deities often have clerics, but many gods of magic bid their followers to take up the study of wizardry. These religious magic-users follow the arcane tradition of Theurgy, and are commonly known as theurgists. Such spellcasters are as dedicated and scholarly as any other wizard, but they blend their arcane study with religious devotion.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Wizard Revisited p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Theurgy (UA): Arcane Initiate</name>
        <text>Beginning when you select this tradition at 2nd level, whenever you gain a wizard level, you can replace one of the wizard spells you add to your spellbook with a cleric domain spell for your chosen domain. The spell must be of a level for which you have spell slots.</text>
        <text>If you add all of your domain spells to your spellbook, you can subsequently add any spell from the cleric spell list instead. The spell must still be of a level for which you have spell slots.</text>
        <text>Any cleric spell you gain from this feature is considered a wizard spell for you, but other wizards can't copy cleric spells from your spellbook into their own spellbooks.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Wizard Revisited p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Theurgy (UA): Channel Arcana</name>
        <text>At 2nd level, you gain the ability to channel arcane energy directly from your deity, using that energy to fuel magical effects. You start with two such effects: Divine Arcana and the Channel Divinity option granted at 2nd level by your chosen domain. You employ that Channel Divinity option by using your Channel Arcana ability.</text>
        <text>When you use your Channel Arcana, you choose which effect to create. You must then finish a short or long rest to use your Channel Arcana again.</text>
        <text>Some Channel Arcana effects require saving throws. When you use such an effect, the save DC equals your wizard spell save DC.</text>
        <text>Beginning at 6th level, you can use your Channel Arcana twice between rests, and beginning at 18th level, you can use it three times between rests. When you finish a short or long rest, you regain your expended uses.</text>
        <text>If you gain additional Channel Divinity options from your domain, you can employ them by using your Channel Arcana feature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Wizard Revisited p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Theurgy (UA): Channel Arcana: Divine Arcana</name>
        <text>As a bonus action, you speak a prayer to control the flow of magic around you. The next spell you cast gains a +2 bonus to any attack roll you make for it or to its saving throw DC, as appropriate.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Wizard Revisited p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Theurgy (UA): Divine Inspiration</name>
        <text>When you choose this tradition at 2nd level, choose a domain from your chosen deity's list of eligible domains (see appendix B, "Gods of the Multiverse," in the Player's Handbook for examples). The Knowledge and Light domains are especially appropriate choices for a theurgist.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Wizard Revisited p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>War Magic (UA): War Magic</name>
        <text>A variety of arcane colleges specialize in training wizards for war. The tradition of War Magic blends principles of evocation and abjuration. It teaches techniques that empower a caster's spells, while also providing methods for a wizard to bolster their own defenses.</text>
        <text>Followers of this tradition are known as war mages. They see their magic as both a weapon and armor, a resource superior to any flimsy piece of steel. War mages strike fast in battle, using their spells to seize tactical control of a situation. Their spells strike hard, while their defensive skills foil their opponents' attempts to counterattack.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Wizard Revisited p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>War Magic (UA): Arcane Deflection</name>
        <text>At 2nd level, you have learned to weave your magic to fortify yourself against harm. When you are hit by an attack or fail a Constitution saving throw, you can use your reaction to gain a +2 bonus to your AC against that attack or a +4 bonus to that saving throw.</text>
        <text>When you use this feature, you can't cast spells other than cantrips until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Wizard Revisited p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>War Magic (UA): Tactical Wit</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, your ability to quickly assess tactical situations allows you to act quickly in battle. You gain a bonus to your initiative rolls equal to your Intelligence modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Wizard Revisited p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Tradition: School of Transmutation</name>
        <text>You are a student of spells that modify energy and matter. To you, the world is not a fixed thing, but eminently mutable, and you delight in being an agent of change. You wield the raw stuff of creation and learn to alter both physical forms and mental qualities. Your magic gives you the tools to become a smith on reality's forge.</text>
        <text>Some transmuters are tinkerers and pranksters, turning people into toads and transforming copper into silver for fun and occasional profit. Others pursue their magical studies with deadly seriousness, seeking the power of the gods to make and destroy worlds.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 119</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Transmutation: Minor Alchemy</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level when you select this school, you can temporarily alter the physical properties of one nonmagical object, changing it from one substance into another. You perform a special alchemical procedure on one object composed entirely of wood, stone (but not a gemstone), iron, copper, or silver, transforming it into a different one of those materials. For each 10 minutes you spend performing the procedure, you can transform up to 1 cubic foot of material. After 1 hour, or until you lose your concentration (as if you were concentrating on a spell), the material reverts to its original substance.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 119</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Transmutation: Transmutation Savant</name>
        <text>Beginning when you select this school at 2nd level, the gold and time you must spend to copy a transmutation spell into your spellbook is halved.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 119</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Tradition: School of Necromancy</name>
        <text>The School of Necromancy explores the cosmic forces of life, death, and undeath. As you focus your studies in this tradition, you learn to manipulate the energy that animates all living things. As you progress, you learn to sap the life force from a creature as your magic destroys its body, transforming that vital energy into magical power you can manipulate.</text>
        <text>Most people see necromancers as menacing, or even villainous, due to the close association with death. Not all necromancers are evil, but the forces they manipulate are considered taboo by many societies.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 118</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Necromancy: Grim Harvest</name>
        <text>At 2nd level, you gain the ability to reap life energy from creatures you kill with your spells. Once per turn when you kill one or more creatures with a spell of 1st level or higher, you regain hit points equal to twice the spell's level, or three times its level if the spell belongs to the School of Necromancy. You don't gain this benefit for killing constructs or undead.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 118</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Necromancy: Necromancy Savant</name>
        <text>Beginning when you select this school at 2nd level, the gold and time you must spend to copy a necromancy spell into your spellbook is halved.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 118</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Lore Mastery (UA): Lore Mastery</name>
        <text>Lore Mastery is an arcane tradition fixated on understanding the underlying mechanics of magic. It is the most academic of all arcane traditions. The promise of uncovering new knowledge or proving (or discrediting) a theory of magic is usually required to rouse its practitioners from their laboratories, academies, and archives to pursue a life of adventure.</text>
        <text>Known as savants, followers of this tradition are a bookish lot who see beauty and mystery in the application of magic. The results of a spell are less interesting to them than the process that creates it. Some savants take a haughty attitude toward those who follow a tradition focused on a single school of magic, seeing them as provincial and lacking the sophistication needed to master true magic. Other savants are generous teachers, countering ignorance and deception with deep knowledge and good humor.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Warlock And Wizard p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Lore Mastery (UA): Altering Spells</name>
        <text>While the Spell Secrets feature offers increased versatility, at the table its effects can be difficult to spot by the other players. If you're playing a savant, take a moment to describe how you alter your spells. Think of a signature change your character is particularly proud of. Be inventive, and make the game more fun for everyone by playing up the sudden, unexpected tricks you character can employ. For example, a fireball transformed to require a Strength save might become a sphere of burning rock that shatters and slams into its target. A charm person that requires a Constitution save might take the form of a vaporous narcotic that alters the target's mood.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Warlock And Wizard p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Lore Mastery (UA): Lore Master</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you become a compendium of knowledge on a vast array of topics. Your proficiency bonus is doubled for any ability check you make that uses the Arcana, History, Nature, or Religion skill if you are proficient in that skill.</text>
        <text>In addition, your analytical abilities are so well-honed that your initiative in combat can be driven by mental agility, rather than physical agility. When you roll initiative, it is either an Intelligence check or a Dexterity check for you (your choice).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Warlock And Wizard p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Lore Mastery (UA): Spell Secrets</name>
        <text>At 2nd level, you master the first in a series of arcane secrets uncovered by your extensive studies.</text>
        <text>When you cast a spell with a spell slot and the spell deals acid, cold, fire, force, lightning, necrotic, radiant, or thunder damage, you can substitute that damage type with one other type from that list (you can change only one damage type per casting of a spell). You replace one energy type for another by altering the spell's formula as you cast it.</text>
        <text>When you cast a spell with a spell slot and the spell requires a saving throw, you can change the saving throw from one ability score to another of your choice. Once you change a saving throw in this way, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Warlock And Wizard p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Tradition: War Magic</name>
        <text>A variety of arcane colleges specialize in training wizards for war. The tradition of War Magic blends principles of evocation and abjuration, rather than specializing in either of those schools. It teaches techniques that empower a caster's spells, while also providing methods for wizards to bolster their own defenses.</text>
        <text>Followers of this tradition are known as war mages. They see their magic as both a weapon and armor, a resource superior to any piece of steel. War mages act fast in battle, using their spells to seize tactical control of a situation. Their spells strike hard, while their defensive skills foil their opponents' attempts to counterattack. War mages are also adept at turning other spellcasters' magical energy against them.</text>
        <text>In great battles, a war mage often works with evokers, abjurers, and other types of wizards. Evokers, in particular, sometimes tease war mages for splitting their attention between offense and defense. A war mage's typical response: "What good is being able to throw a mighty fireball if I die before I can cast it?"</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 59</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>War Magic: Arcane Deflection</name>
        <text>At 2nd level, you have learned to weave your magic to fortify yourself against harm. When you are hit by an attack or you fail a saving throw, you can use your reaction to gain a +2 bonus to your AC against that attack or a +4 bonus to that saving throw.</text>
        <text>When you use this feature, you can't cast spells other than cantrips until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 59</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>War Magic: Tactical Wit</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, your keen ability to assess tactical situations allows you to act quickly in battle. You can give yourself a bonus to your initiative rolls equal to your Intelligence modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 59</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Invention (UA): School of Invention</name>
        <text>The School of Invention claims credit for inventing the other schools of magic—a claim other wizards find absurd. Wizards of this school push magic to its limits. They stretch the known laws of arcane power and strive to reveal important truths about the nature of the multiverse.</text>
        <text>Adherents of this school believe that innovation is best served through experimentation. They have a reputation for acting first, thinking second. Most wizards are scholars who have mastered their craft through careful study, rigorous practice, and endless hours of repetition. These wizards would rather throw spells together and see what happens.</text>
        <text>Many wizards of this tradition are gnomes, alchemists, or both, and they take pride in the magic-infused armor they don. The armor not only provides protection, but it is also designed to help the wizard channel magic in unpredictable ways.</text>
        <text>Wizards of this tradition are regarded as savants to their faces, but wizards of other traditions often think of them as lunatics.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Three Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Invention (UA): Arcanomechanical Armor</name>
        <text>Innovation is a dangerous practice, at least as far as members of this school practice it. As a shield against this risk, you have developed a suit of arcane armor.</text>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you gain proficiency with light armor and gain a suit of arcanomechanical armor—a magic item that only you can attune to. While you are attuned to it and wearing it, it grants you resistance to force damage.</text>
        <text>The armor is light armor and provides an AC of 12 + your Dexterity modifier. It weighs 8 pounds.</text>
        <text>You can create a new suit of it at the end of a long rest by touching a nonmagical suit of studded leather armor, which magically transforms it. Doing so removes the magic from your previous arcanomechanical armor, turning it in to nonmagical studded leather.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Three Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Invention (UA): Reckless Casting</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can attempt to cast a spell you don't have prepared. When you use this ability, you use your action and choose one of the following options:</text>
        <text>• Roll on the Reckless Casting table for cantrips and cast the resulting spell as part of this action.</text>
        <text>• Expend a spell slot and roll twice on the Reckless Casting table for its level, or the 5th-level table if the slot is 6th level or higher. Pick which of the two results you want to use and cast the resulting spell as part of this action.</text>
        <text>If the spell you cast isn't a wizard spell, it is nonetheless a wizard spell for you when you cast it with this feature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Reckless Casting</text>
        <text>d10 | Cantrip</text>
        <text>1 | acid splash</text>
        <text>2 | chill touch</text>
        <text>3 | fire bolt</text>
        <text>4 | light</text>
        <text>5 | poison spray</text>
        <text>6 | ray of frost</text>
        <text>7 | shocking grasp</text>
        <text>8 | sacred flame</text>
        <text>9 | thorn whip</text>
        <text>10 | Roll twice and cast each cantrip, but if you roll another 10 on either die, you cast nothing, wasting your action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>d10 | 1st-Level Spell</text>
        <text>1 | burning hands</text>
        <text>2 | chromatic orb</text>
        <text>3 | color spray</text>
        <text>4 | faerie fire</text>
        <text>5 | false life</text>
        <text>6 | fog cloud</text>
        <text>7 | jump</text>
        <text>8 | magic missile</text>
        <text>9 | thunderwave</text>
        <text>10 | Roll twice and cast each spell, but if you roll another 10 on either die, you cast nothing, wasting your action but not the spell slot.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>d10 | 2nd-Level Spell</text>
        <text>1 | blur</text>
        <text>2 | darkness</text>
        <text>3 | enlarge/reduce</text>
        <text>4 | gust of wind</text>
        <text>5 | invisibility</text>
        <text>6 | levitate</text>
        <text>7 | Melf's acid arrow</text>
        <text>8 | scorching ray</text>
        <text>9 | shatter</text>
        <text>10 | Roll twice and cast each spell, but if you roll another 10 on either die, you cast nothing, wasting your action but not the spell slot.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>d10 | 3rd-Level Spell</text>
        <text>1 | blink</text>
        <text>2 | fear</text>
        <text>3 | feign death</text>
        <text>4 | fireball</text>
        <text>5 | fly</text>
        <text>6 | gaseous form</text>
        <text>7 | lightning bolt</text>
        <text>8 | sleet storm</text>
        <text>9 | stinking cloud</text>
        <text>10 | Roll twice and cast each spell, but if you roll another 10 on either die, you cast nothing, wasting your action but not the spell slot.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>d10 | 4th-Level Spell</text>
        <text>1 | blight</text>
        <text>2 | confusion</text>
        <text>3 | Evard's black tentacles</text>
        <text>4 | fire shield</text>
        <text>5 | greater invisibility</text>
        <text>6 | ice storm</text>
        <text>7 | phantasmal killer</text>
        <text>8 | stoneskin</text>
        <text>9 | wall of fire</text>
        <text>10 | Roll twice and cast each spell, but if you roll another 10 on either die, you cast nothing, wasting your action but not the spell slot.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>d10 | 5th-Level Spell</text>
        <text>1 | cloudkill</text>
        <text>2 | cone of cold</text>
        <text>3 | destructive wave</text>
        <text>4 | flame strike</text>
        <text>5 | hold monster</text>
        <text>6 | insect plague</text>
        <text>7 | mass cure wounds</text>
        <text>8 | wall of force</text>
        <text>9 | wall of stone</text>
        <text>10 | Roll twice and cast each spell, but if you roll another 10 on either die, you cast nothing, wasting your action but not the spell slot.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Three Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Invention (UA): Tools of the Inventor</name>
        <text>At 2nd level, you gain proficiency with two tools of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Three Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Onomancy (UA): Onomancy</name>
        <text>Practitioners of magic well know the power of names, but wizards who follow the tradition of Onomancy use their magic to manipulate the words that encompass existence. Onomancers expand their study into language itself, searching for threads of magical significance that weave through names. Something that is named stands out in the multiverse, distinct from the tapestry of creation all around it.</text>
        <text>That distinction creates power that onomancers seek to tap. By speaking a target's true name, the wizard's spells slip between the cracks of the target's defenses, conforming to its essential nature through the power of its name. To protect themselves, wizards who follow this tradition often hide their true names, typically by adopting monikers and pseudonyms.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Cleric Druid Wizard p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Onomancy (UA): Bonus Proficiencies</name>
        <text>2nd-level Onomancy feature</text>
        <text>You learn one language of your choice and gain proficiency with calligrapher's supplies.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Cleric Druid Wizard p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Onomancy (UA): Extract Name</name>
        <text>2nd-level Onomancy feature</text>
        <text>You can magically compel a creature to divulge its true name. As a bonus action, you target one creature you can see within 60 feet of you. The target must make a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC. On a successful save, you discern that this magic failed, and you can't use this feature on the target again. On a failed save, the target is charmed by you until the end of your next turn, and you mentally learn the charmed target's name or the fact that the target lacks a name.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Intelligence modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses of it when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Cleric Druid Wizard p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Onomancy (UA): Fateful Naming</name>
        <text>2nd-level Onomancy feature</text>
        <text>You can bend magic to assist or hinder creatures through the power of their true names, and even use those names as an anchor to affect others around them. The bane and bless spells are wizard spells for you, and you add them to your spellbook. You always have them prepared, yet they don't count against the number of spells you can prepare.</text>
        <text>You can cast either spell without expending a spell slot if you speak the true name of one target of the spell as part of casting it. You can cast the spells in this way a number of times equal to your Intelligence modifier (a minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Cleric Druid Wizard p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Onomancy (UA): True Names</name>
        <text>Onomancy, or naming magic, is a method of spellcasting that uses a creature's true name to enhance a spell's effects. A true name is the name by which a self-aware creature identifies itself. This name might be the name a person was given at birth, or one a person chose or earned later in life. Whatever a name's origin, the simplest way for you to know your true name is to think truthfully about yourself and then think, "My name is..." Your true name is how you finish that sentence.</text>
        <text>You can try to hide your true name by using a pseudonym, but you must be wary not to inhabit that false name too deeply. If a false name comes to be the best expression of who you are, it becomes your true name. Changing one's true name is never a quick choice; it's something that happens over time as a name becomes the creature's truth.</text>
        <text>As a quick guide, a creature has a true name if it understands at least one language or it has an alignment.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Cleric Druid Wizard p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psionics (UA): Psionics</name>
        <text>Wizards study magical power in all its forms, including the magic of psionics. Those wizards who follow the tradition of Psionics hone the magical potential of their own minds. Sometimes called psionicists or mentalists, these wizards interact with the multiverse through the lens of their psionic aptitude and awareness.</text>
        <text>Psionicists channel their magic by focusing their minds. By doing so they can transcend their physical bodies, adopting forms of pure thought, casting spells psionically to bypass the need for components, and perceiving the world with a broader range of senses.</text>
        <text>As a member of the Psionics tradition, you might have awoken your psionic potential through the strain of your esoteric studies, or perhaps you joined a scholarly order dedicated to unlocking the magic of the mind.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psionics (UA): Psionic Devotion</name>
        <text>2nd-level Psionics feature</text>
        <text>Your study of psionics begins to unleash your mind's potential. When you gain this feature, choose one of the following cantrips: friends, mage hand, or message. You learn that cantrip if you don't already know it, and it doesn't count against the number of wizard cantrips you know. While your psionic focus is on your person, you can cast the chosen cantrip as a bonus action, requiring no components, and with the modification listed below:</text>
        <name>Psionics (UA): Friends</name>
        <text>   When the spell ends, the target doesn't become hostile to you.</text>
        <name>Psionics (UA): Mage Hand</name>
        <text>   You can make the hand invisible when you cast the spell, and controlling the spell is a bonus action for you.</text>
        <name>Psionics (UA): Message</name>
        <text>   You don't need to point toward the target or whisper your message out loud.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psionics (UA): Psionic Focus</name>
        <text>2nd-level Psionics feature</text>
        <text>You have learned to channel psionic energy through a special object: a psionic focus. You gain the object with this feature (see the "Your Psionic Focus" sidebar for how you might have acquired the item).</text>
        <text>While your psionic focus is on your person, you gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• The object is a spellcasting focus for you.</text>
        <text>• When you roll psychic or force damage for any of your wizard spells, you can reroll any of those damage dice that rolls a 1, but you must use the new roll.</text>
        <text>If your psionic focus is lost, you can magically recreate it by meditating for 1 hour during a short or long rest, at the end of which the focus appears in your hand.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psionics (UA): Psionic Spells</name>
        <text>Spell selection is part of what defines a wizard and their individual fields of expertise. When creating your Psionics wizard, consider spells that are thematically appropriate for that tradition. Psionics as a theme generally includes spells that do the following:</text>
        <text>• contact or manipulate minds</text>
        <text>• allow the caster to perceive distant locations or planes</text>
        <text>• alter perception</text>
        <text>• move objects and creatures</text>
        <text>• teleport</text>
        <text>• deal psychic or force damage</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psionics (UA): Your Psionic Focus</name>
        <text>Every member of the Psionics tradition has a story about how their psionic focus came into their life. Consider how you found yours and what form it takes.</text>
        <text>The event that brought your psionic focus to you probably holds personal significance. Did your master give it to you upon the completion of your apprenticeship? Was it awarded to you when you graduated from your academy of wizardry? Did it call to you in a jeweler's shop? Was it associated with the moment when your psionic powers first manifested? One morning, did you wake up with it humming under your pillow?</text>
        <text>The form your psionic focus takes is also yours to define, likely being a reflection of how your magic came into being, a symbol of your own psyche, or an item you use to focus your thoughts. It is a handheld object that has special meaning to you, but that can't be a weapon or magic item. Perhaps it's a childhood memento, the skull of an alien creature, a crystal that makes you feel a certain way, a coin that only lands on its edge, a firescarred planchette, or any other enigmatic personal relic.</text>
        <text>However the object arrived and whatever form it takes, your psionic focus is now yours, and you decide how to handle it. Will you mount it on a wand or staff? Would you prefer to wear it on a necklace or circlet? Have you embedded it into the cover of your spellbook? Wherever you put it, you can now channel your magic through it, and it is a sign of your membership in the revered tradition of psionic wizardry.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Tradition: Chronurgy Magic</name>
        <text>Focusing on the manipulation of time, those who follow the Chronurgy tradition learn to alter the pace of reality to their liking. Using the ramping of anticipatory dunamis energy, these mages can bend the flow of time as adroitly as a skilled musician plays an instrument, lending themselves and their allies an advantage in the blink of an eye.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 184</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Chronurgy Magic: Chronal Shift</name>
        <text>2nd-level Chronurgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>You can magically exert limited control over the flow of time around a creature. As a reaction, after you or a creature you can see within 30 feet of you makes an attack roll, an ability check, or a saving throw, you can force the creature to reroll. You make this decision after you see whether the roll succeeds or fails. The target must use the result of the second roll.</text>
        <text>You can use this ability twice, and you regain any expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 184</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Chronurgy Magic: Temporal Awareness</name>
        <text>2nd-level Chronurgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>You can add your Intelligence modifier to your initiative rolls.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 184</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Tradition: Graviturgy Magic</name>
        <text>Understanding and mastering the forces that draw bodies of matter together or drive them apart, the students of the Graviturgy arcane tradition learn to further bend and manipulate the violent energy of gravity to their benefit, and the terrible detriment of their enemies.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 185</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Graviturgy Magic: Adjust Density</name>
        <text>2nd-level Graviturgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>As an action, you can magically alter the weight of one object or creature you can see within 30 feet of you. The object or creature must be Large or smaller. The target's weight is halved or doubled for up to 1 minute or until your concentration ends (as if you were concentrating on a spell).</text>
        <text>While the weight of a creature is halved by this effect, the creature's speed increases by 10 feet, it can jump twice as far as normal, and it has disadvantage on Strength checks and Strength saving throws. While the weight of a creature is doubled by this effect, the creature's speed is reduced by 10 feet, and it has advantage on Strength checks and Strength saving throws.</text>
        <text>Upon reaching 10th level in this class, you can target an object or a creature that is Huge or smaller.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 185</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Order of Scribes (UA): Order of Scribes</name>
        <text>Magic of the book—that's what many spellcasters call wizardry. The name is apt, given how much time wizards spend poring over their spellbooks, penning theories about the nature of magic, and exploring the farthest recesses of libraries. It's rare to see a wizard traveling without books and scrolls sprouting from their bags, and a wizard would go to great lengths to plumb an archive of ancient knowledge.</text>
        <text>Among wizards, the Order of Scribes is the most bookish. It takes many forms in different worlds, but its primary mission is the same everywhere: recording magical discoveries in tomes and scrolls so that wizardry can flourish. And while every wizard values their spellbook, a scribe in the Order of Scribes dedicates themself to magically awakening their book, turning it into a trusted companion. All wizards study their spellbooks, but a wizardly scribe talks to theirs!</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Revisited p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Order of Scribes (UA): Awakened Spellbook</name>
        <text>2nd-level Order of Scribes feature</text>
        <text>Using specially prepared inks and ancient incantations passed down by your wizardly order, you have awakened an arcane sentience within your spellbook.</text>
        <text>While you are holding the book, it grants you the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• You can use the book as a spellcasting focus for your wizard spells.</text>
        <text>• When you cast a wizard spell with a spell slot, you can temporarily replace its damage type with the damage type of another spell in your spellbook, as your spellbook magically alters the spell's formula for this casting.</text>
        <text>• When you cast a wizard spell as a ritual, you can use the spell's normal casting time, rather than adding 10 minutes to it. Once you use this benefit, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>If necessary, you can replace the book over the course of a short rest by using your Wizardly Quill to write arcane sigils in a blank book or a magic spellbook to which you're attuned. At the end of the rest, your spellbook's consciousness is summoned into the new book, which the consciousness transforms into your spellbook, along with all its spells. If the previous book still existed somewhere, all the spells vanish from its pages.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Revisited p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Order of Scribes (UA): Wizardly Quill</name>
        <text>2nd-level Order of Scribes feature</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, you can magically create a Tiny quill in your free hand. The magic quill has the following properties:</text>
        <text>• The quill doesn't require ink. When you write with it, it produces ink in a color of your choice on the writing surface.</text>
        <text>• The gold and time you must spend to copy a spell into your spellbook are halved if you use the quill for the transcription.</text>
        <text>• You can erase anything you write with the quill if you wave the feather over the text as a bonus action, provided the text is within 5 feet of you.</text>
        <text>This quill disappears if you create another one or if you die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Revisited p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <slots>3, 4, 2</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4">
        <slots>4, 4, 3</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 4th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 112</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>4th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
        <slots>4, 4, 3, 2</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <slots>4, 4, 3, 3</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature>
          <name>Arcane Tradition feature</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain a feature granted by your Arcane Tradition.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 112</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Artificer (UA): Infuse Weapons and Armor</name>
        <text>Beginning at 6th level, you can produce magic weapons and armor. You spend 10 minutes focusing your magic on a mundane weapon, suit of armor, shield, or bundle of twenty pieces of ammunition, and expend a spell slot to infuse it with magical energy. The magic item retains its enhancement for 8 hours or until used (in the case of magic ammunition). You can infuse only one item at a time; if you infuse a second one, the first immediately loses its potency. Once you have expended a spell slot to create such an item, you cannot regain that slot until the item becomes nonmagical.</text>
        <text>The spell slot you expend determines the type of weapon, armor, or shield you can create.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Infuse Weapons and Armor</text>
        <text>Spell Level | Item Created</text>
        <text>2nd | +1 ammunition (20 pieces)</text>
        <text>3rd | +1 weapon or +1 shield</text>
        <text>4th | +1 armor</text>
        <text>5th | +2 weapon or +2 ammunition (20 pieces)</text>
        <text>6th | +2 armor</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Abjuration: Projected Ward</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, when a creature that you can see within 30 feet of you takes damage, you can use your reaction to cause your Arcane Ward to absorb that damage. If this damage reduces the ward to 0 hit points, the warded creature takes any remaining damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 115</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Bladesinging: Extra Attack</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you can attack twice, instead of once, whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 141</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Conjuration: Benign Transposition</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you can use your action to teleport up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space that you can see. Alternatively, you can choose a space within range that is occupied by a Small or Medium creature. If that creature is willing, you both teleport, swapping places.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest or you cast a conjuration spell of 1st level or higher.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 116</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Divination: Expert Divination</name>
        <text>Beginning at 6th level, casting divination spells comes so easily to you that it expends only a fraction of your spellcasting efforts. When you cast a divination spell of 2nd level or higher using a spell slot, you regain one expended spell slot. The slot you regain must be of a level lower than the spell you cast and can't be higher than 5th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 116</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Enchantment: Instinctive Charm</name>
        <text>Beginning at 6th level, when a creature you can see within 30 feet of you makes an attack roll against you, you can use your reaction to divert the attack, provided that another creature is within the attack's range. The attacker must make a Wisdom saving throw against your wizard spell save DC. On a failed save, the attacker must target the creature that is closest to it, not including you or itself. If multiple creatures are closest, the attacker chooses which one to target. On a successful save, you can't use this feature on the attacker again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>You must choose to use this feature before knowing whether the attack hits or misses. Creatures that can't be charmed are immune to this effect.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 117</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Evocation: Potent Cantrip</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, your damaging cantrips affect even creatures that avoid the brunt of the effect. When a creature succeeds on a saving throw against your cantrip, the creature takes half the cantrip's damage (if any) but suffers no additional effect from the cantrip.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 117</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Illusion: Malleable Illusions</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, when you cast an illusion spell that has a duration of 1 minute or longer, you can use your action to change the nature of that illusion (using the spell's normal parameters for the illusion), provided that you can see the illusion.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 118</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Technomancy (UA): Program Spell</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you can insert a spell within an electronic device of your choosing, so that by touching a key or flicking a switch using an action, the spell activates. All variables of the spell are set at the time of casting. The computing power of this device must be equal to or greater than a mobile phone.</text>
        <text>A programmed spell remains placed in its device for 48 hours, and is gone once it is discharged. You can use this feature to place a programmed spell in only one device at a time, and a device can hold only one programmed spell. Only you can activate the programmed spell in the device. If the device is destroyed, the programmed spell is lost.</text>
        <text>A concentration spell placed in a device cannot be activated while you are concentrating on another spell. Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Theurgy (UA): Arcane Acolyte</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain your chosen domain's 1st-level benefits. However, you do not gain any weapon or armor proficiencies from the domain.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Wizard Revisited p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>War Magic (UA): Power Surge</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you can empower your spells that unleash harm on groups of foes. When you force multiple creatures to make saving throws against the damage of one of your spells, you can increase the spell's damage by rolling two more of its damage dice. This increase occurs only on the turn you cast the spell.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Wizard Revisited p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Transmutation: Transmuter's Stone</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you can spend 8 hours creating a transmuter's stone that stores transmutation magic. You can benefit from the stone yourself or give it to another creature. A creature gains a benefit of your choice as long as the stone is in the creature's possession. When you create the stone, choose the benefit from the following options:</text>
        <text>• Darkvision out to a range of 60 feet, as described in chapter 8.</text>
        <text>• An increase to speed of 10 feet while the creature is unencumbered.</text>
        <text>• Proficiency in Constitution saving throws.</text>
        <text>• Resistance to acid, cold, fire, lightning, or thunder damage (your choice whenever you choose this benefit).</text>
        <text>Each time you cast a transmutation spell of 1st level or higher, you can change the effect of your stone if the stone is on your person.</text>
        <text>If you create a new transmuter's stone, the previous one ceases to function.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 119</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Necromancy: Undead Thralls</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you add the animate dead spell to your spellbook if it is not there already. When you cast animate dead, you can target one additional corpse or pile of bones, creating another zombie or skeleton, as appropriate.</text>
        <text>Whenever you create an undead using a necromancy spell, it has additional benefits:</text>
        <text>• The creature's hit point maximum is increased by an amount equal to your wizard level.</text>
        <text>• The creature adds your proficiency bonus to its weapon damage rolls.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 118</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Lore Mastery (UA): Alchemical Casting</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you learn to augment spells in a variety of ways. When you cast a spell with a spell slot, you can expend one additional spell slot to augment its effects for this casting, mixing the raw stuff of magic into your spell to amplify it. The effect depends on the spell slot you expend.</text>
        <text>An additional 1st-level spell slot can increase the spell's raw force. If you roll damage for the spell when you cast it, increase the damage against every target by 2d10 force damage. If the spell can deal damage on more than one turn, it deals this extra force damage only on the turn you cast the spell.</text>
        <text>An additional 2nd-level spell slot can increase the spell's range. If the spell's range is at least 30 feet, it becomes 1 mile.</text>
        <text>An additional 3rd-level spell slot can increase the spell's potency. Increase the spell's save DC by 2.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Warlock And Wizard p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>War Magic: Power Surge</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you can store magical energy within yourself to later empower your damaging spells. In its stored form, this energy is called a power surge.</text>
        <text>You can store a maximum number of power surges equal to your Intelligence modifier (minimum of one). Whenever you finish a long rest, your number of power surges resets to one. Whenever you successfully end a spell with dispel magic or counterspell, you gain one power surge, as you steal magic from the spell you foiled. If you end a short rest with no power surges, you gain one power surge.</text>
        <text>Once per turn when you deal damage to a creature or object with a wizard spell, you can spend one power surge to deal extra force damage to that target. The extra damage equals half your wizard level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 59</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Invention (UA): Alchemical Casting</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you learn to channel magic through your arcanomechanical armor to augment spells in a variety of ways. When you cast a spell while wearing that armor and attuned to it, you can expend one additional spell slot of 1st or 2nd level to alter the spell. The effect depends on the spell slot you expend.</text>
        <text>A 1st-level slot allows you to manipulate the spell's energy. When you cast a spell that deals acid, cold, fire, lightning, or thunder damage, you can substitute that damage type for another one from that list.</text>
        <text>A 2nd-level slot increases the spell's raw force. If you roll damage for the spell when you cast it, increase that damage by 2d10 force damage against one of the spell's targets (your choice) this turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Three Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Onomancy (UA): Resonant Utterance</name>
        <text>6th-level Onomancy feature</text>
        <text>You learn words of power called Resonants, which allow you to tailor your spells through the use of a target's true name.</text>
        <name>Onomancy (UA): Resonants Known</name>
        <text>   When you gain this feature, you learn two Resonants of your choice, which are detailed in the "Resonant Options" section. Each time you gain a level in this class, you can replace one resonant you know with a different one.</text>
        <name>Onomancy (UA): Using a Resonant</name>
        <text>   You can use one Resonant when you cast a wizard spell with a spell slot and speak the true name of one creature targeted by the spell. Speaking the name is part of casting the spell. You can use Resonants a number of times equal to half of your wizard level (round down), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <name>Onomancy (UA): Resonant Options</name>
        <text>   Here are your options when choosing a Resonant:</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Cleric Druid Wizard p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psionics (UA): Thought Form</name>
        <text>6th-level Psionics feature</text>
        <text>While you are carrying your psionic focus, you can use a bonus action to magically transform your body into pure psionic energy. The transformation lasts for 10 minutes, until you use a bonus action to assume your normal form, or until you are incapacitated or die.</text>
        <text>While in thought form, you are a figure of luminous psychic energy, with your psionic focus hovering within. Your form can appear as anything you wish, but it is obviously magical, is the same size as you, and sheds dim light in a 5-foot-radius. Any other equipment you are wearing or carrying transforms with you and melds into your thought form. You also gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>   Psionic Spellcasting</text>
        <text>• When you cast a spell while in thought form, you can cast the spell psionically. If you do so, the spell doesn't require verbal, somatic, or material components that lack a gold cost.</text>
        <text>   Psychic Resilience</text>
        <text>• You gain resistance to psychic damage and to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage from nonmagical attacks.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>You can transform using this feature a number of times equal to your Intelligence modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Chronurgy Magic: Momentary Stasis</name>
        <text>6th-level Chronurgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>As an action, you can magically force a Large or smaller creature you can see within 60 feet of you to make a Constitution saving throw against your spell save DC. Unless the saving throw is a success, the creature is encased in a field of magical energy until the end of your next turn or until the creature takes any damage. While encased in this way, the creature is incapacitated and has a speed of 0.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Intelligence modifier (a minimum of once). You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 184</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Graviturgy Magic: Gravity Well</name>
        <text>6th-level Graviturgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>You've learned how to manipulate gravity around a living being: whenever you cast a spell on a creature, you can move the target 5 feet to an unoccupied space of your choice if the target is willing to move, the spell hits it with an attack, or it fails a saving throw against the spell.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 185</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Order of Scribes (UA): Master Scrivener</name>
        <text>6th-level Order of Scribes feature</text>
        <text>Whenever you finish a long rest, you can create one magic scroll by touching your Wizardly Quill to a blank piece of paper or parchment and causing one spell from your Awakened Spellbook to be copied onto the scroll. The spellbook must be within 5 feet of you when you make the scroll.</text>
        <text>The chosen spell must be of 1st or 2nd level and must have a casting time of 1 action. Once in the scroll, the spell's power is enhanced, counting as one level higher than normal. You can cast the spell from the scroll by reading it as an action. The scroll is unintelligible to anyone else, and the spell vanishes from the scroll when you cast it or when you finish your next long rest.</text>
        <text>You are also adept at crafting spell scrolls, which are described in chapter 7 of the Dungeon Master's Guide. The gold and time you must spend to make such a scroll are halved if you use your Wizardly Quill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Revisited p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <slots>4, 4, 3, 3, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
        <slots>4, 4, 3, 3, 2</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 8th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 112</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>8th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
        <slots>4, 4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <slots>5, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature>
          <name>Arcane Tradition feature</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you gain a feature granted by your Arcane Tradition.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 112</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Artificer (UA): Superior Artificer</name>
        <text>Starting at 10th level, you can create a second magic weapon, suit of armor, shield, or bundle of ammunition using your Infuse Weapons and Armor ability. Attempting to infuse a third item causes the oldest one to immediately lose its potency.</text>
        <text>You can also create one additional potion or scroll using Infuse Potions or Infuse Scrolls.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Abjuration: Improved Abjuration</name>
        <text>Beginning at 10th level, when you cast an abjuration spell that requires you to make an ability check as a part of casting that spell (as in counterspell and dispel magic), you add your proficiency bonus to that ability check.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 115</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Bladesinging: Song of Defense</name>
        <text>Beginning at 10th level, you can direct your magic to absorb damage while your bladesong is active. When you take damage, you can use your reaction to expend one spell slot and reduce that damage to you by an amount equal to five times the spell's slot level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 141</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Conjuration: Focused Conjuration</name>
        <text>Beginning at 10th level, while you are concentrating on a conjuration spell, your concentration can't be broken as a result of taking damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 116</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Divination: The Third Eye</name>
        <text>Starting at 10th level, you can use your action to increase your powers of perception. When you do so, choose one of the following benefits, which lasts until you are incapacitated or you take a short or long rest. You can't use the feature again until you finish a rest.</text>
        <name>School of Divination: Darkvision</name>
        <text>   You gain darkvision out to a range of 60 feet.</text>
        <name>School of Divination: Ethereal Sight</name>
        <text>   You can see into the Ethereal Plane within 60 feet of you.</text>
        <name>School of Divination: Greater Comprehension</name>
        <text>   You can read any language.</text>
        <name>School of Divination: See Invisibility</name>
        <text>   You can see invisible creatures and objects within 10 feet of you that are within line of sight.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 116</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Enchantment: Split Enchantment</name>
        <text>Starting at 10th level, when you cast an enchantment spell of 1st level or higher that targets only one creature, you can have it target a second creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 117</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Evocation: Empowered Evocation</name>
        <text>Beginning at 10th level, you can add your Intelligence modifier to one damage roll of any wizard evocation spell you cast.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 117</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Illusion: Illusory Step</name>
        <text>Beginning at 10th level, you can create an illusory duplicate of yourself as an instant, almost instinctual reaction to danger. When a creature makes an attack roll against you, you can use your reaction to interpose the illusory duplicate between the attacker and yourself. The attack automatically misses you, then the illusion dissipates.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 118</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Technomancy (UA): Online Casting</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you can cast spells through networked electronic devices, including cameras, mobile phones, and computers. For example, if a creature is under the observation of a security camera and you can see the video feed from that camera on a computer, you can cast a spell into the computer and out through the security camera to target that creature.</text>
        <text>If the spell requires the caster to be seen, the target must see you or a live image of you. If the spell requires the caster to be heard, the target must be able to hear you or a live audio transmission of you. The spell's range is determined using the distance from you to your device, and then from the target to its device. You must be able to see or otherwise determine the location of the target. This feature can be used to cast only spells that target specific creatures. Spells that affect an area are not subject to online casting.</text>
        <text>This feature can be used a number of times per day equal to your Intelligence modifier (minimum of once).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Theurgy (UA): Arcane Priest</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you gain your chosen domain's 6th-level benefits. Your faith and your understanding of magic allow you to delve into your god's secrets.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Wizard Revisited p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>War Magic (UA): Durable Magic</name>
        <text>Beginning at 10th level, the magic you channel helps ward off harm. While you maintain concentration on a spell, you have a +2 bonus to AC and all saving throws.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Wizard Revisited p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Transmutation: Shapechanger</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you add the polymorph spell to your spellbook, if it is not there already. You can cast polymorph without expending a spell slot. When you do so, you can target only yourself and transform into a beast whose challenge rating is 1 or lower.</text>
        <text>Once you cast polymorph in this way, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest, though you can still cast it normally using an available spell slot.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 119</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Necromancy: Inured to Undeath</name>
        <text>Beginning at 10th level, you have resistance to necrotic damage, and your hit point maximum can't be reduced. You have spent so much time dealing with undead and the forces that animate them that you have become inured to some of their worst effects.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 118</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Lore Mastery (UA): Prodigious Memory</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you have attained a greater mastery of spell preparation. As a bonus action, you can replace one spell you have prepared with another spell from your spellbook. You can't use this feature again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Warlock And Wizard p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>War Magic: Durable Magic</name>
        <text>Beginning at 10th level, the magic you channel helps ward off harm. While you maintain concentration on a spell, you have a +2 bonus to AC and all saving throws.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 59</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Invention (UA): Prodigious Inspiration</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you have attained a greater mastery of spell preparation. As a bonus action, you can replace one spell you have prepared with another spell from your spellbook. You can't use this ability again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Three Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Onomancy (UA): Inexorable Pronouncement</name>
        <text>10th-level Onomancy feature</text>
        <text>You learn two new Resonant s of your choice from your Resonant Utterance feature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Cleric Druid Wizard p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psionics (UA): Empowered Psionics</name>
        <text>10th-level Psionics feature</text>
        <text>When you deal psychic or force damage with a wizard spell, you can add your Intelligence modifier to the damage against one of the spell's targets.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psionics (UA): Mental Discipline</name>
        <text>10th-level Psionics feature</text>
        <text>Your mind's power expands to greater heights. When you gain this feature, choose one of the following spells: dominate person, scrying, or telekinesis. You can add the spell to your spellbook, and you can cast it without components.</text>
        <text>You can also cast the chosen spell once without expending a spell slot. After you do so, you regain the ability to cast the spell without a slot when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Chronurgy Magic: Arcane Abeyance</name>
        <text>10th-level Chronurgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>When you cast a spell using a spell slot of 4th level or lower, you can condense the spell's magic into a mote. The spell is frozen in time at the moment of casting and held within a gray bead for 1 hour. This bead is a Tiny object with AC 15 and 1 hit point, and it is immune to poison and psychic damage. When the duration ends, or if the bead is destroyed, it vanishes in a flash of light, and the spell is lost.</text>
        <text>A creature holding the bead can use its action to release the spell within, whereupon the bead disappears. The spell uses your spell attack bonus and save DC, and the spell treats the creature who released it as the caster for all other purposes.</text>
        <text>Once you create a bead with this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 184</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Graviturgy Magic: Violent Attraction</name>
        <text>10th-level Graviturgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>When another creature that you can see within 60 feet of you hits with a weapon attack, you can use your reaction to increase the attack's velocity, causing the attack's target to take an extra 1d10 damage of the weapon's type.</text>
        <text>Alternatively, if a creature within 60 feet of you takes damage from a fall, you can use your reaction to increase the fall's damage by 2d10.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Intelligence modifier (a minimum of once). You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 185</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Order of Scribes (UA): Manifest Mind</name>
        <text>10th-level Order of Scribes feature</text>
        <text>You are now able to conjure forth the mind of your Awakened Spellbook. As a bonus action while the book is on your person, you can cause the mind to manifest as a Tiny spectral construct, hovering in an unoccupied space of your choice within 60 feet of you. This presence is intangible and doesn't occupy its space, and it sheds dim light in a 10-foot radius. It looks like a ghostly tome, a cascade of text, or a scholar from the past (your choice). The spectral mind has a number of hit points equal to your wizard level plus your Intelligence modifier, and it uses your Armor Class and saving throw modifiers.</text>
        <text>While manifested, the spectral mind can hear and see, and it has darkvision with a range of 60 feet. As an action, you can hear and see using the its senses, instead of your own, until your concentration ends (as if concentrating on a spell).</text>
        <text>Whenever you cast a wizard spell on your turn, you can cast it as if you were in the spectral mind's space, instead of your own, using its senses. You can do so a number of times per day equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, you can cause the spectral mind to hover up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space that you or it can see. It can pass through creatures but not objects. The spectral mind stops manifesting if it is ever more than 300 feet away from you, if it drops to 0 hit points, if you die, or if you dismiss it as a bonus action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Revisited p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <slots>5, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12">
        <slots>5, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 12th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 112</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>12th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
        <slots>5, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <slots>5, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature>
          <name>Arcane Tradition feature</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you gain a feature granted by your Arcane Tradition.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 112</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Artificer (UA): Master Artificer</name>
        <text>On reaching 14th level, your mastery of arcane magic allows you to produce a variety of magic items. You can create a single item chosen from Magic Item Tables A and B in chapter 7 of the Dungeon Master's Guide (shown below). It takes you 1 week to produce such an item, and you must rest for 1 month before using this ability to craft another item.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Magic Item Table A</text>
        <text>d100 | Magic Item</text>
        <text>01-50 | Potion of healing</text>
        <text>51-60 | Spell scroll (cantrip)</text>
        <text>61-70 | Potion of climbing</text>
        <text>71-90 | Spell scroll (1st level)</text>
        <text>91-94 | Spell scroll (2nd level)</text>
        <text>95-98 | Potion of greater healing</text>
        <text>99 | Bag of holding</text>
        <text>00 | Driftglobe</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Magic Item Table B</text>
        <text>d100 | Magic Item</text>
        <text>01-15 | Potion of greater healing</text>
        <text>16-22 | Potion of fire breath</text>
        <text>23-29 | Potion of resistance</text>
        <text>30-34 | Ammunition +1</text>
        <text>35-39 | Potion of animal friendship</text>
        <text>40-44 | Potion of hill giant strength</text>
        <text>45-49 | Potion of growth</text>
        <text>50-54 | Potion of water breathing</text>
        <text>55-59 | Spell scroll (2nd level)</text>
        <text>60-64 | Spell scroll (3rd level)</text>
        <text>65-67 | Bag of holding</text>
        <text>68-70 | Keoghtom's ointment</text>
        <text>71-73 | Oil of slipperiness</text>
        <text>74-75 | Dust of disappearance</text>
        <text>76-77 | Dust of dryness</text>
        <text>78-79 | Dust of sneezing and choking</text>
        <text>80-81 | Elemental gem</text>
        <text>82-83 | Philter of love</text>
        <text>84 | Alchemy jug</text>
        <text>85 | Cap of water breathing</text>
        <text>86 | Cloak of the manta ray</text>
        <text>87 | Driftglobe</text>
        <text>88 | Goggles of night</text>
        <text>89 | Helm of comprehending languages</text>
        <text>90 | Immovable rod</text>
        <text>91 | Lantern of revealing</text>
        <text>92 | Mariner's armor</text>
        <text>93 | Mithral armor</text>
        <text>94 | Potion of poison</text>
        <text>95 | Ring of swimming</text>
        <text>96 | Robe of useful items</text>
        <text>97 | Rope of climbing</text>
        <text>98 | Saddle of the cavalier</text>
        <text>99 | Wand of magic detection</text>
        <text>00 | Wand of secret</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Abjuration: Spell Resistance</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, you have advantage on saving throws against spells.</text>
        <text>Furthermore, you have resistance against the damage of spells.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 115</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Bladesinging: Song of Victory</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, you add your Intelligence modifier (minimum of +1) to the damage of your melee weapon attacks while your Bladesong is active.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 141</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Conjuration: Durable Summons</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, any creature that you summon or create with a conjuration spell has 30 temporary hit points.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 116</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Divination: Greater Portent</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, the visions in your dreams intensify and paint a more accurate picture in your mind of what is to come. You roll three d20s for your Portent feature, rather than two.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 116</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Enchantment: Alter Memories</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you gain the ability to make a creature unaware of your magical influence on it. When you cast an enchantment spell to charm one or more creatures, you can alter one creature's understanding so that it remains unaware of being charmed.</text>
        <text>Additionally, once before the spell expires, you can use your action to try to make the chosen creature forget some of the time it spent charmed. The creature must succeed on an Intelligence saving throw against your wizard spell save DC or lose a number of hours of its memories equal to 1 + your Charisma modifier (minimum of 1). You can make the creature forget less time, and the amount of time can't exceed the duration of your enchantment spell.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 117</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Evocation: Overchannel</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, you can increase the power of your simpler spells. When you cast a wizard spell of 1st through 5th-level that deals damage, you can deal maximum damage with that spell.</text>
        <text>The first time you do so, you suffer no adverse effect. If you use this feature again before you finish a long rest, you take 2d12 necrotic damage for each level of the spell, immediately after you cast it. Each time you use this feature again before finishing a long rest, the necrotic damage per spell level increases by 1d12. This damage ignores resistance and immunity.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 117</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Illusion: Illusory Reality</name>
        <text>By 14th level, you have learned the secret of weaving shadow magic into your illusions to give them a semireality. When you cast an illusion spell of 1st level or higher, you can choose one inanimate, nonmagical object that is part of the illusion and make that object real. You can do this on your turn as a bonus action while the spell is ongoing. The object remains real for 1 minute. For example, you can create an illusion of a bridge over a chasm and then make it real long enough for your allies to cross.</text>
        <text>The object can't deal damage or otherwise directly harm anyone.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 118</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Technomancy (UA): Chained Device</name>
        <text>By 14th level, you have learned to imprint vestiges of your consciousness on electronic devices with significant computing power. When you cast a concentration spell, you can use a device whose computing power is equal to or greater than a tablet computer to maintain concentration of the spell on your behalf. The device must be held or worn by you to maintain this effect. If the device is destroyed, taken from you, dropped, or turned off, the concentration ends. Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Theurgy (UA): Arcane High Priest</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you gain your chosen domain's 17th-level benefits. Your academic nature and understanding of magic and doctrine allow you to master this ability sooner than a cleric of your domain.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Wizard Revisited p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>War Magic (UA): Durable Magic</name>
        <text>At 14th level, your Arcane Deflection becomes infused with deadly magic. When you use your Arcane Deflection feature, magical energy arcs from you; each creature of your choice within 10 feet of you takes force damage equal to half your wizard level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Wizard Revisited p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Transmutation: Master Transmuter</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, you can use your action to consume the reserve of transmutation magic stored within your transmuter's stone in a single burst. When you do so, choose one of the following effects. Your transmuter's stone is destroyed and can't be remade until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <name>School of Transmutation: Major Transformation</name>
        <text>   You can transmute one nonmagical object—no larger than a 5-foot cube—into another nonmagical object of similar size and mass and of equal or lesser value. You must spend 10 minutes handling the object to transform it.</text>
        <name>School of Transmutation: Panacea</name>
        <text>   You remove all curses, diseases, and poisons affecting a creature that you touch with the transmuter's stone. The creature also regains all its hit points.</text>
        <name>School of Transmutation: Restore Life</name>
        <text>   You cast the raise dead spell on a creature you touch with the transmuter's stone, without expending a spell slot or needing to have the spell in your spellbook.</text>
        <name>School of Transmutation: Restore Youth</name>
        <text>   You touch the transmuter's stone to a willing creature, and that creature's apparent age is reduced by 3d10 years, to a minimum of 13 years. This effect doesn't extend the creature's lifespan.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 119</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Necromancy: Command Undead</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, you can use magic to bring undead under your control, even those created by other wizards. As an action, you can choose one undead that you can see within 60 feet of you. That creature must make a Charisma saving throw against your wizard spell save DC. If it succeeds, you can't use this feature on it again. If it fails, it becomes friendly to you and obeys your commands until you use this feature again.</text>
        <text>Intelligent undead are harder to control in this way. If the target has an Intelligence of 8 or higher, it has advantage on the saving throw. If it fails the saving throw and has an Intelligence of 12 or higher, it can repeat the saving throw at the end of every hour until it succeeds and breaks free.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 118</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Lore Mastery (UA): Master of Magic</name>
        <text>At 14th level, your knowledge of magic allows you to duplicate almost any spell. As a bonus action, you can call to mind the ability to cast one spell of your choice from any class's spell list. The spell must be of a level for which you have spell slots, you mustn't have it prepared, and you follow the normal rules for casting it, including expending a spell slot. If the spell isn't a wizard spell, it counts as a wizard spell when you cast it. The ability to cast the spell vanishes from your mind when you cast it or when the current turn ends.</text>
        <text>You can't use this feature again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Warlock And Wizard p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>War Magic: Deflecting Shroud</name>
        <text>At 14th level, your Arcane Deflection becomes infused with deadly magic. When you use your Arcane Deflection feature, you can cause magical energy to arc from you. Up to three creatures of your choice that you can see within 60 feet of you each take force damage equal to half your wizard level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 59</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>School of Invention (UA): Controlled Chaos</name>
        <text>At 14th level, your ability to improvise magic grows stronger. Whenever you roll on a Reckless Casting table for a spell other than a cantrip, you can roll on the table that is one level higher than the expended spell slot.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Three Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Onomancy (UA): Relentless Naming</name>
        <text>14th-level Onomancy feature</text>
        <text>You have learned how to bypass a named creature's defenses against certain types of damage. When you cast a spell that deals damage to a creature whose true name you speak as part of casting the spell, you can cause the spell to deal force or psychic damage to the creature, instead of the spell's normal damage type.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Cleric Druid Wizard p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Psionics (UA): Thought Travel</name>
        <text>14th-level Psionics feature</text>
        <text>While using your Thought Form, you have a flying speed equal to your walking speed and can hover, and you can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain.</text>
        <text>You take 1d10 force damage if you end your turn inside an object. If you return to your normal form while inside an object, you are shunted to the nearest unoccupied space, and you take 1d10 force damage for every 5 feet traveled.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Chronurgy Magic: Convergent Future</name>
        <text>14th-level Chronurgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>You can peer through possible futures and magically pull one of them into events around you, ensuring a particular outcome. When you or a creature you can see within 60 feet of you makes an attack roll, an ability check, or a saving throw, you can use your reaction to ignore the die roll and decide whether the number rolled is the minimum needed to succeed or one less than that number (your choice).</text>
        <text>When you use this feature, you gain one level of exhaustion. Only by finishing a long rest can you remove a level of exhaustion gained in this way.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 184</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Graviturgy Magic: Event Horizon</name>
        <text>14th-level Graviturgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>As an action, you can magically emit a powerful field of gravitational energy that tugs at other creatures for up to 1 minute or until your concentration ends (as if you were concentrating on a spell). For the duration, whenever a creature hostile to you starts its turn within 30 feet of you, it must make a Strength saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, it takes 2d10 force damage, and its speed is reduced to 0 until the start of its next turn. On a successful save, it takes half as much damage, and every foot it moves this turn costs 2 extra feet of movement.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest or until you expend a spell slot of 3rd level or higher on it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 185</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Order of Scribes (UA): One with the Word</name>
        <text>14th-level Order of Scribes feature</text>
        <text>Your connection to your Awakened Spellbook has become so profound that your soul has become entwined with it. While you are holding the book and its spectral mind is manifest, you can take an action to cause the two of you to teleport, swapping places. You can teleport in this way a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>Moreover, if you die but at least one spell remains in your Awakened Spellbook, you can return to life 1 minute later within 5 feet of the book. You revive with 1 hit point. Then roll 3d6. The book loses spells of your choice that have a combined spell level equal to that roll or higher. For example, if the roll's total is 9, spells vanish from the book that have a combined level of at least 9, which could mean one 9th-level spell, three 3rd-level spells, or some other combination.</text>
        <text>Thereafter, you are incapable of casting the lost spells, even if you find them on a scroll or in another spellbook. The only way to restore your ability to cast one of the lost spells is through the wish spell, which can restore one spell to the book per casting.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Revisited p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <slots>5, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16">
        <slots>5, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 16th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 112</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>16th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <slots>5, 4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <slots>5, 4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature>
          <name>Spell Mastery</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you have achieved such mastery over certain spells that you can cast them at will. Choose a 1st-level wizard spell and a 2nd-level wizard spell that are in your spellbook. You can cast those spells at their lowest level without expending a spell slot when you have them prepared. If you want to cast either spell at a higher level, you must expend a spell slot as normal.</text>
        <text>By spending 8 hours in study, you can exchange one or both of the spells you chose for different spells of the same levels.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 112</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19">
        <slots>5, 4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 19th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 112</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>19th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
        <slots>5, 4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 2, 2, 1, 1</slots>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
        <feature>
          <name>Signature Spells</name>
        <text>When you reach 20th level, you gain mastery over two powerful spells and can cast them with little effort. Choose two 3rd-level wizard spells in your spellbook as your signature spells. You always have these spells prepared, they don't count against the number of spells you have prepared, and you can cast each of them once at 3rd level without expending a spell slot. When you do so, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>If you want to cast either spell at a higher level, you must expend a spell slot as normal.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 112</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
