<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Wizard</name>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Technomancy (UA): Technomancy</name>
        <text>Unlike the more common arcane traditions based around the schools of magic, the tradition of Technomancy does not focus on a singular type of spellcraft or magical energy. Rather, students of Technomancy concern themselves with how their spells interact with modern technology.</text>
        <text>Technomancers can make use of technology as both a conduit and a storage space for magic. In a campaign using the optional rules for magic item creation (see the Dungeon Master's Guide), a technomancer might craft disposable electronic devices and smartphone apps in lieu of potions and scrolls.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Technomancy (UA): Bonus Proficiencies</name>
        <text>Beginning when you select this arcane tradition at 2nd level, you gain proficiency with sidearms and hacking tools.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Technomancy (UA): Technological Savant</name>
        <text>Also at 2nd level, you trade out your spellbook for a specially attuned storage device of your choosing, capable of recording magical data. The computing power of this device must be equal to or greater than a tablet computer. Only one storage device can be attuned to you at any given time. Spells can be copied into this device at half the cost of copying spells into a spellbook.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Technomancy (UA): Program Spell</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you can insert a spell within an electronic device of your choosing, so that by touching a key or flicking a switch using an action, the spell activates. All variables of the spell are set at the time of casting. The computing power of this device must be equal to or greater than a mobile phone.</text>
        <text>A programmed spell remains placed in its device for 48 hours, and is gone once it is discharged. You can use this feature to place a programmed spell in only one device at a time, and a device can hold only one programmed spell. Only you can activate the programmed spell in the device. If the device is destroyed, the programmed spell is lost.</text>
        <text>A concentration spell placed in a device cannot be activated while you are concentrating on another spell. Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Technomancy (UA): Online Casting</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you can cast spells through networked electronic devices, including cameras, mobile phones, and computers. For example, if a creature is under the observation of a security camera and you can see the video feed from that camera on a computer, you can cast a spell into the computer and out through the security camera to target that creature.</text>
        <text>If the spell requires the caster to be seen, the target must see you or a live image of you. If the spell requires the caster to be heard, the target must be able to hear you or a live audio transmission of you. The spell's range is determined using the distance from you to your device, and then from the target to its device. You must be able to see or otherwise determine the location of the target. This feature can be used to cast only spells that target specific creatures. Spells that affect an area are not subject to online casting.</text>
        <text>This feature can be used a number of times per day equal to your Intelligence modifier (minimum of once).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Technomancy (UA): Chained Device</name>
        <text>By 14th level, you have learned to imprint vestiges of your consciousness on electronic devices with significant computing power. When you cast a concentration spell, you can use a device whose computing power is equal to or greater than a tablet computer to maintain concentration of the spell on your behalf. The device must be held or worn by you to maintain this effect. If the device is destroyed, taken from you, dropped, or turned off, the concentration ends. Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
