<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Sorcerer</name>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul (UA): Favored Soul</name>
        <text>You have been chosen by a deity, and bestowed with a fragment of their divine power. You have been fundamentally changed by the touch of this deity, which awakens powerful magical abilities inside you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 8</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul (UA): Bonus Proficiency</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you gain proficiency in light armor, medium armor, shields, and simple weapons.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 8</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul (UA): Chosen of the Gods</name>
        <text>At 1st level, you choose one of the cleric class's divine domains. You add that domain's spells for 1st-level clerics to your known spells. These spells do not count against the number of spells you can know, and they are considered to be sorcerer spells for you. When you reach 3rd, 5th, 7th, and 9th levels in the sorcerer class, you likewise learn your domain's spells that become available at those levels.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 8</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul (UA): Extra Attack</name>
        <text>Beginning at 6th level, you can attack twice, instead of once, whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 8</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul (UA): Divine Wings</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you gain the ability to sprout a pair of wings from your back (feathered or bat-like, your choice), gaining a flying speed equal to your current walking speed. You can create these wings as a bonus action on your turn. They last until you dismiss them as a bonus action on your turn.</text>
        <text>You can't manifest your wings while wearing armor unless the armor is made to accommodate them, and clothing not made to accommodate your wings might be destroyed when you manifest them.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 8</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Favored Soul (UA): Power of the Chosen</name>
        <text>Starting at 18th level, when you cast one of the spells you learned from your Chosen of the Gods class feature, you regain hit points equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of +1) + the spell's level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 8</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
