<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Paladin</name>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Redemption (UA): Oath of Redemption</name>
        <text>The Oath of Redemption sets a paladin on a difficult path, one that requires a holy warrior to use violence only as a last resort. Paladins who dedicate themselves to this oath believe that any person can be redeemed and that the path of benevolence and justice is one that anyone can walk. These paladins face evil creatures in the hope of turning them to the light, and the paladins slay them only when such a deed will clearly save other lives. Paladins who follow this path are known as redeemers.</text>
        <text>While redeemers are idealists, they are no fools. Redeemers know that undead, demons, devils, and other supernatural threats can be inherently evil. Against such foes, the paladins bring the full wrath of their weapons and spells to bear. Yet the redeemers still pray that, one day, even creatures of wickedness will invite their own redemption.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Redemption (UA): Armor of Peace</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, your commitment to peace allows you to walk into the most dangerous situations unarmored. While you aren't wearing armor or wielding a shield, your base AC is 16 + your Dexterity modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Redemption (UA): Channel Divinity: Emissary of Peace</name>
        <text>You can use your Channel Divinity to augment your presence with divine power. As a bonus action, you grant yourself a +5 bonus to the next Charisma (Persuasion) check you make within the next minute.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Redemption (UA): Channel Divinity: Rebuke the Violent</name>
        <text>You can use your Channel Divinity to rebuke those who use violence. As a reaction when an enemy within 10 feet of you deals damage with a melee attack against one creature other than you, you force that attacker to make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the attacker takes radiant damage equal to the damage it just dealt. On a successful save, it takes half as much damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Redemption (UA): Oath Spells</name>
        <text>You gain oath spells at the paladin levels listed.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Oath of Redemption Spells</text>
        <text>Paladin Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | shield, sleep</text>
        <text>5th | hold person, ray of enfeeblement</text>
        <text>9th | counterspell, hypnotic pattern</text>
        <text>13th | Otiluke's resilient sphere, stoneskin</text>
        <text>17th | hold monster, wall of force</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Redemption (UA): Tenets of Redemption</name>
        <text>The tenets of the Oath of Redemption hold a paladin to a high standard of peace and justice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Peace</text>
        <text>   Violence is a weapon of last resort. Diplomacy and understanding are the paths to long-lasting peace.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Innocence</text>
        <text>   All people begin life in an innocent state, and it is their environment or the influence of dark forces that drives them to evil. By setting the proper example, and working to heal the wounds of a deeply flawed world, you can set anyone on a righteous path.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Patience</text>
        <text>   Change takes time. Those who have walked the path of the wicked must be given reminders to keep them honest and true. Once you have planted the seed of righteousness in a creature, you must work day after day to allow it to survive and then flourish.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Wisdom</text>
        <text>   Your heart and mind must stay clear, for eventually you will be forced to admit defeat. While every creature can be redeemed, some are so far along the path of evil that you have no choice but to end their lives for the greater good. Any such action must be carefully weighed and the consequences fully understood, but once you have made the decision, follow through with it knowing your path is just.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Redemption (UA): Warrior of Reconciliation</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you foreswear the weapons of war in favor of simple tools. While wielding a simple weapon that deals bludgeoning damage, you gain a special benefit if you reduce a creature to 0 hit points with that weapon and decide to spare the creature's life. Instead of falling unconscious, the creature is charmed by you for 1 minute. During that time, the charmed creature is peaceful and docile, refusing to move or to take actions or reactions, unless you command it to. You can't order the creature to attack, force someone to make a saving throw, or cause damage to itself or others. This charmed effect ends early if you are incapacitated or if you or your companions attack the creature, deal damage to it, or force it to make a saving throw. When the effect ends, the creature falls unconscious if it still has 0 hit points.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Redemption (UA): Aura of the Guardian</name>
        <text>Starting at 7th level, you can shield your allies from harm at the cost of your own health. As a reaction when an ally within 10 feet of you takes damage, you instead magically take that damage. This feature doesn't transfer any other effects that might accompany the damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Redemption (UA): Protective Spirit</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, a holy presence mends your wounds in combat. You regain hit points equal to 1d6 + half your paladin level if you end your turn in combat with fewer than half of your hit points remaining and you aren't incapacitated.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Redemption (UA): Emissary of Redemption</name>
        <text>At 20th level, you become an avatar of peace, which gives you two benefits:</text>
        <text>• You have resistance to all damage dealt by other creatures (their attacks, spells, and other effects).</text>
        <text>• Whenever a creature damages you, it takes damage equal to half the amount it dealt to you.</text>
        <text>If you attack a creature, deal damage to it, or force it to make a saving throw, neither benefit works against that creature until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
