<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Fighter</name>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier (UA): Cavalier</name>
        <text>The archetypal Cavalier excels at mounted combat. Usually born to nobility and raised in a royal court, a Cavalier is equally at home leading a cavalry charge or exchanging witty repartee at a state dinner.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier (UA): Bonus Proficiencies</name>
        <text>When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you gain proficiency in two of the following skills of your choice: Animal Handling, Insight, Performance, or Persuasion. You can choose to gain one tool proficiency in place of one skill proficiency.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier (UA): Born to the Saddle</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you have advantage on saving throws made to avoid falling off your mount. If you fall off your mount, you always land on your feet if you are capable of taking actions. Mounting or dismounting a creature costs you only 5 feet of movement, rather than half your speed.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier (UA): Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain a set of abilities that are fueled by special dice called superiority dice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Superiority Dice</text>
        <text>   You have four superiority dice, which are d8s. A superiority die is expended when you use it. You regain all of your expended superiority dice when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>   You gain another superiority die at 7th level and one more at 15th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Using Superiority Dice</text>
        <text>   You can expend superiority dice to gain a number of different benefits:</text>
        <text>• When you make a check to influence or control a creature you are riding, you can expend one superiority die to add it to the check. You apply this bonus after making the check but before learning if it was successful.</text>
        <text>• When you make a weapon attack against a creature, you can expend one superiority die to add it to the attack roll. You can use this ability before or after making the attack roll, but before any of the effects of the attack are applied.</text>
        <text>• When you make an attack with a lance while mounted, you can expend one superiority die to add it to your damage roll. In addition, the target of the attack must make a Strength saving throw (DC 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Strength modifier) or be knocked prone.</text>
        <text>• If either you or your mount is hit by an attack while you are mounted, you can expend one superiority die as a reaction, adding the number rolled to your or your mount's AC. If the attack still hits, you or your mount take half damage from it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Scout</name>
        <text>The archetypal Scout excels at finding safe passage through dangerous regions. Scouts usually favor light armor and ranged weapons, but they are comfortable using heavier gear when faced with intense fighting.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Bonus Proficiencies</name>
        <text>When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you gain proficiency in three of the following skills of your choice: Acrobatics, Athletics, Investigation, Medicine, Nature, Perception, Stealth, or Survival. You can choose to gain proficiency with thieves' tools in place of one skill choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain a set of abilities that are fueled by special dice called superiority dice.</text>
        <name>Scout (UA): Superiority Dice</name>
        <text>   You have four superiority dice, which are d8s. A superiority die is expended when you use it. You regain all of your expended superiority dice when you finish a long or short rest. You gain another superiority die at 7th level and one more at 15th level.</text>
        <name>Scout (UA): Using Superiority Dice</name>
        <text>   You can expend superiority dice to gain a number of different benefits:</text>
        <text>• When you make a check that allows you to apply your proficiency in Athletics, Nature, Perception, Stealth, or Survival, you can expend one superiority die to bolster the check. Add half the number rolled on the superiority die (rounding up) to your check. You apply this bonus after making the check but before learning if it was successful.</text>
        <text>• When you make a weapon attack against a creature, you can expend one superiority die to add it to the attack roll. You can use this ability before or after making the attack roll, but before any of the effects of the attack are applied.</text>
        <text>• If you are hit by an attack while wearing light or medium armor, you can expend one superiority die as a reaction, adding the number rolled to your AC. If the attack still hits, you take half damage from it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Natural Explorer</name>
        <text>You are particularly familiar with one type of natural environment and are adept at traveling and surviving in such regions. Choose one type of favored terrain: arctic, coast, desert, forest, grassland, mountain, swamp, or the Underdark. When you make an Intelligence or Wisdom check related to your favored terrain, your proficiency bonus is doubled if you are using a skill that you're proficient in.</text>
        <text>While traveling for an hour or more in your favored terrain, you gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• Difficult terrain doesn't slow your group's travel.</text>
        <text>• Your group can't become lost except by magical means.</text>
        <text>• Even when you are engaged in another activity while traveling (such as foraging, navigating, or tracking), you remain alert to danger.</text>
        <text>• If you are traveling alone, you can move stealthily at a normal pace.</text>
        <text>• When you forage, you find twice as much food as you normally would.</text>
        <text>• While tracking other creatures, you also learn their exact number, their sizes, and how long ago they passed through the area.</text>
        <text>You choose additional favored terrain types at 7th and 15th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier (UA): Ferocious Charger</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain additional benefits when you use superiority dice to increase your damage when you attack with a lance. You can expend up to two superiority dice on the attack, adding both to the damage roll. If you spend two dice, the target has disadvantage on its Strength saving throw to avoid being knocked prone.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Additional Superiority Die</name>
        <text>You gain another superiority die at 7th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier (UA): Improved Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 10th level, your superiority dice turn into d10s. At 18th level, they turn into d12s.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Improved Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 10th level, your superiority dice turn into d10s. At 18th level, they turn into d12s.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier (UA): Relentless</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, when you roll initiative and have no superiority dice remaining, you regain 1 superiority die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Additional Superiority Die</name>
        <text>You gain another superiority die at 15th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Relentless</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, when you roll initiative and have no superiority dice remaining, you regain 1 superiority die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Cavalier (UA): Improved Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 18th level, your superiority dice turn into d12s.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Scout (UA): Improved Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 18th level, your superiority dice turn into d12s.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Kits Of Old p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
