<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Detection (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Half-Elf</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Detection, the dragonmark of House Medani, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Wisdom as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: detect magic, mage hand
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: detect thoughts
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: clairvoyance
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Finding (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Half-Orc, Human</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Finding, the dragonmark of House Tharashk, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Wisdom as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: identify, mage hand
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: locate object
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: clairvoyance
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Handling (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Human</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Handling, the dragonmark of House Vadalis, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Wisdom as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: druidcraft, speak with animals
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: beast sense
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: conjure animals
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Healing (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Halfling</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Healing, the dragonmark of House Jorasco, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Wisdom as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: cure wounds, spare the dying
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: lesser restoration
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: revivify
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Hospitality (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Halfling</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Hospitality, the dragonmark of House Ghallanda, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Charisma as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: friends, unseen servant
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: rope trick
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: Leomund's tiny hut
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Making (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Human</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Making, the dragonmark of House Cannith, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Intelligence as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: identify, mending
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: magic weapon
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: fabricate
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Passage (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Human</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Passage, the dragonmark of House Orien, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Intelligence as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: expeditious retreat, light
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: misty step
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: teleportation circle
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Scribing (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Gnome</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Scribing, the dragonmark of House Sivis, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Intelligence as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: comprehend languages, message
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: sending
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: tongues
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Sentinel (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Human</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Sentinel, the dragonmark of House Deneith, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Wisdom as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: blade ward, compelled duel
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: blur
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: protection from energy
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Shadow (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Elf</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Shadow, the dragonmark of House Phiarlan and House Thuranni, and are a member of one of those houses.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Charisma as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: dancing lights, disguise self
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: darkness
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: nondetection
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Storm (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Half-Elf</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Storm, the dragonmark of House Lyrander, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Intelligence as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: fog cloud, shocking grasp
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: gust of wind
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: sleet storm
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Warding (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Dwarf</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Warding, the dragonmark of House Kundarak, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Intelligence as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: alarm, resistance
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: arcane lock
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: magic circle
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  </compendium>
