<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <feat>
      <name>Resonant: Absorption (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>When you cast a spell that deals damage to the named target, you gain 3d6 temporary hit points. The number of temporary hit points you gain increases by 1d6 when you reach 10th level (4d6) and 14th level (5d6) in this class.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Cleric Druid Wizard p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Resonant: Devastation (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>If the spell requires the named creature to make a saving throw, that creature has disadvantage on the first save it makes against the spell.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Cleric Druid Wizard p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Resonant: Dissolution (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>The first time the named creature takes damage from the spell, that creature takes an extra 2d8 force damage. The extra force damage increases by 1d8 when you reach 10th level (3d8) and 14th level (4d8) in this class.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Cleric Druid Wizard p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Resonant: Nullification (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>If the named target is affected by any other spells, you know what those spells are, and you can attempt to end one of your choice by succeeding on an Intelligence check with a DC equal to 10 + the level of the chosen spell.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Cleric Druid Wizard p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Resonant: Puppetry (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>The first time the named creature takes damage from the spell, you can knock the creature prone or move it up to 10 feet, either directly toward you or away from you.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Cleric Druid Wizard p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Resonant: Sympathy (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>If the named creature is within range of the spell, you can target the creature with the spell even if you can't see the creature or it has total cover against the spell.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Cleric Druid Wizard p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  </compendium>
