<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <!-- Items -->
    <item>
        <name>Battle Standard of Infernal Power</name>
        <type>W</type>
        <detail>very rare (requires attunement)</detail>
        <text>This hell-forged battle standard is made of infernal iron and fitted with a small, unopenable cage containing a quasit. The trapped quasit is incapacitated, and its cage has AC 19, 10 hit points, and immunity to all types of damage except force damage. If killed or somehow released, the quasit disappears in a cloud of smoke, and a new one appears in the cage, provided the cage is intact.</text>
        <text>While you hold the banner, your weapon attacks and those of all allied creatures within 300 feet of you count as magical for the purposes of overcoming damage immunities and resistances.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Baldur’s Gate - Descent into Avernus, p. 223</text>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Gauntlets of Flaming Fury</name>
        <type>W</type>
        <detail>rare (requires attunement)</detail>
        <magic>YES</magic>
        <text>While you wear both of these steel gauntlets, any non-magical weapon you grasp with either gauntlet is treated as a magic weapon. As a bonus action, you can use the gauntlets to cause magical flames to envelop one or two melee weapons in your grasp. Each flaming weapon deals an extra 1d6 fire damage on a hit. The flames last until you sheath or let go of either weapon. Once used, this property can't be used again until the next dawn.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Baldur’s Gate - Descent into Avernus, p. 223</text>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Fane-Eater</name>
        <type>M</type>
        <detail>legendary (requires attunement by an evil cleric or paladin)</detail>
        <magic>YES</magic>
        <text>Fane-Eater is a battleaxe belonging to Arkhan the Cruel.</text>
        <text>You gain a +3 bonus to attack and damage rolls with Fane-Eater. If you attack a creature with this weapon and roll a 20 on the attack roll, the creature takes an extra 2d8 necrotic damage, and you regain a number of hit points equal to the necrotic damage taken.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Proficiency: martial</text>
        <text>Source: Baldur’s Gate - Descent into Avernus, p. 223</text>
        <dmg1>1d8</dmg1>
        <dmg2>1d10</dmg2>
        <dmgType>S</dmgType>
        <property>M,V</property>
        <range></range>
        <modifier category="bonus">melee damage +3</modifier>
        <modifier category="bonus">melee attacks +3</modifier>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Hellfire Weapon</name>
        <type>M</type>
        <detail>uncommon</detail>
        <magic>YES</magic>
        <text>This weapon is fashioned from infernal iron and traced with veins of hellfire that shed dim light in a 5-foot-radius.</text>
        <text>Any humanoid killed by an attack made with this weapon has its soul funneled into the River Styx, where it's reborn instantly as a lemure devil (described in the Monster Manual).</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Baldur’s Gate - Descent into Avernus, p. 223</text>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Helm of Devil Command</name>
        <type>W</type>
        <detail>very rare (requires attunement by a creature that can speak Infernal)</detail>
        <magic>YES</magic>
        <text>This bulky, eyeless helmet is made for a pit fiend but magically resizes to fit the heads of other wearers. While wearing the helm, you can see out of it as though you weren't wearing it. In addition, you know the exact location and type of all devils within 1,000 feet of you. You can telepathically communicate with a devil within range, or you can broadcast your thoughts to all devils within range. The devils receiving your broadcasted thoughts have no special means of replying to them.</text>
        <text>The helm has 3 charges. As an action, you can expend 1 charge to cast dominate monster (save DC 21), which affects devils only. (The spell fails and the charge is wasted if you target any creature that's not a devil.) If a devil can see you when you cast this spell on it, the devil knows you tried to charm it. The helm regains all its charges 24 hours after its last charge is expended.</text>
        <text>If you are not a devil, using the helm's dominate monster property in the Nine Hells has a 20 percent chance of attracting a narzugon, which arrives on the back of a nightmare mount in 1d4 hours. The narzugon tries to recover the helm, killing you if necessary to obtain it. If it gets the helm, the narzugon tries to deliver it to its infernal master.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Baldur’s Gate - Descent into Avernus</text>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Internal Puzzle Box</name>
        <type>W</type>
        <detail>uncommon</detail>
        <weight>3</weight>
        <magic>YES</magic>
        <text>An infernal puzzle box is a cube-shaped container 5 to 6 inches on a side, composed of airtight, interlocking parts made from materials found in the Nine Hells. Most of these boxes are made of infernal iron, though some are carved from bone or horn. Infernal puzzle boxes are used to safeguard diabolical contracts signed between devils and mortals, even after the terms of these contracts are fulfilled. An empty infernal puzzle box weighs 3 pounds regardless of the materials used to fashion it.</text>
        <text>When an object small enough to fit inside an infernal puzzle box is placed in it, the container magically seals shut around the object, and no magic can force the box open. The sealed box becomes immune to all damage as well. Every infernal puzzle box is constructed with a unique means of opening it. The trick to solving the puzzle is always mundane, never magical. Once a creature figures out the trick or sequence of steps needed to open a particular infernal puzzle box, that creature can open the box as an action, allowing access to the box's contents.</text>
        <text>A creature that spends 1 hour holding an infernal puzzle box while trying to open it can make a DC 30 Intelligence (Investigation) check. If the check succeeds, the creature figures out the trick or sequence of steps needed to open the box. If the check fails by 5 or more, the creature must make a DC 18 Wisdom saving throw, taking 42 (12d6) psychic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Baldur’s Gate - Descent into Avernus</text>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Infernal Tack</name>
        <type>W</type>
        <detail>legendary (requires attunement by a creature of evil alignment)</detail>
        <magic>YES</magic>
        <text>A narzugon devil binds a nightmare (described in the Monster Manual) to its service with infernal tack, which consists ofa bridle, bit, reins, saddle, stirrups, and spurs. A nightmare equ.ipped with infernal tack must serve whoever wears the spires until the wearer dies or the tack is removed.</text>
        <text>You can use an action to call the nightmare equipped with infernal tack by clashing the spurs together or scraping them through blood. The nightmare appears at the start of your next turn, within 20 feet ofyou. It acts as your ally and takes its turn on your initiative count. It remains for 1 day, until you or it dies, or until you dismiss it as an action. If the nightmare dies, it reforms in the Nine Hells within 24 hours, after which you can summon it again.</text>
        <text>The tack doesn’t conjure a nightmare from thin air: one must first be subdued so the tack can be placed on it. No nightmare accepts this forced servitude willingly, but some eventually form strong loyalties to their masters and become partners in evil.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Baldur’s Gate - Descent into Avernus</text>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Matalotok</name>
        <type>M</type>
        <detail>Legendary</detail>
        <magic>YES</magic>
        <text>Matalotok, the Frost Father, is an ancient hammer fashioned by Thrym, the god of frost giants. The favored weapon of the demon lord Kostchtchie, Matalotok is frigid to the touch and wreathed in mist.</text>
        <text>You are immune to cold damage while holding Matalotok. Whenever it deals damage to a creature, the hammer radiates a burst of intense cold in a 30-foot-radius sphere. Each creature in that area takes 10 (3d6) cold damage.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Proficiency: martial, warhammer</text>
        <text>Source: Baldur’s Gate - Descent into Avernus</text>
        <dmg1>1d8</dmg1>
        <dmg2>1d10</dmg2>
        <dmgType>B</dmgType>
        <property>M,V</property>
        <range></range>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Obsidian Flint Dragon Plate</name>
        <type>HA</type>
        <detail>legendary</detail>
        <magic>YES</magic>
        <ac>18</ac>
        <text>You gain +2 bonus to AC and resistance to poison damage while you wear this armor. In addition, you gain advantage on ability checks and saving throws made to avoid or end grappled condition on yourself.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Baldur's Gate Descent into Avernus, p. 224</text>
        <modifier category="bonus">ac +2</modifier>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Shield of the Hidden Lord</name>
        <type>S</type>
        <detail>legendary (requires attunement)</detail>
        <magic>YES</magic>
        <ac>2</ac>
        <text>The Shield of the Hidden Lord is of celestial origin and serves as a prison for the pit fiend Gargauth, whose mortal followers revere it as a god. Over time, Gargauth's evil has warped the shield's appearance, so that its celestial motif and designs have become twisted into a fiendish face that subtly moves in disturbing ways. While holding this shield, you gain a +2 bonus to AC and resistance to fire damage.</text>
        <text>Sentience. The Shield ofthe Hidden Lord is sentient as long as it imprisons Gargauth. While sentient, the shield has the following properties:
            • The shield has an Intelligence of 22, a Wisdom of 18, and a Charisma of 24, as well as hearing and truesight out to a range of 120 feet.
            • The shield can speak, read, and understand Common and Infernal, and it can communicate telepathically with any creature it can sense within 120 feet of it. Its voice is a deep, hollow whisper.
            • The shield has 3 charges. You can use an action to expend 1 charge to cast fireball or 2 charges to cast wall offire from the shield (save DC 21 for each). The wall of fire spell lasts for 1 minute (no concentration required). The shield regains all expended charges daily at dawn.
            Anytime during your turn, the shield can choose to radiate an aura of dread for 1 minute. (This is not a power of the shield that you control.) Any creature hostile to you that starts its turn within 20 feet of the shield must make a DC 18 Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the creature is frightened until the start of its next turn. On a successful save, the creature is im- mune to this power of the shield for the next 24 hours. Once the shield uses this power, it can't use it again until the next dawn.</text>
        <text>Gargauth's Personality. Gargauth desperately seeks freedom but can't escape on its own. The pit fiend won't reveal its true nature, referring to itself only as the Hidden Lord. It drops hints and subtle suggestions that it is an angel trapped in an unholy prison. If released from the shield, the pit fiend honors the terms of whatever bargain it struck to facilitate its escape.
            While trapped in the shield, Gargauth carefully steers the shield's current owner toward committing acts of cruelty and domination, hoping to condemn the individual's soul to the Nine Hells. Conflict occurs if the shield's owner does anything that would make it more difficult for Gargauth to escape its prison, such as leaving the shield in a place where others are unlikely to find it.
            Gargauth doesn't know how to escape from the shield. The pit fiend believes (incorrectly) that it can break free of the shield if it's brought to the Nine Hells, for it's convinced that the shield's powers are weaker there.</text>
        <text>Freeing Gargauth. Casting dispel evil and good on the shield has a 1 percent chance of freeing the pit fiend, or automatically succeeds if the spell is cast by a solar, a planetar, or an archdevil. A god can release the pit fiend by touching the shield and speaking Gargauth's name. When released, Gargauth appears in a random, unoccupied space as close to the shield as possible.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Baldur's Gate Descent into Avernus, p. 225</text>
        <modifier category="bonus">ac +2</modifier>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Soul Coin</name>
        <type>W</type>
        <detail>uncommon</detail>
        <magic>YES</magic>
        <text>Soul coins are about 5 inches across and about an inch thick, minted from infernal iron. Each coin weighs one- third of a pound, and is inscribed with Infernal writing and a spell that magically binds a single soul to the coin. Because each soul coin has a unique soul trapped within it, each has a story. A creature might have been imprisoned as a result of defaulting on a deal, while an- other might be the victim of a night hag's curse.</text>
        <text>Carrying Soul Coins. To hold a soul coin is to feel the soul bound within it overcome with rage or fraught with despair.</text>
        <text>An evil creature can carry as many soul coins as it wishes (up to its maximum weight allowance). A non-evil creature can carry a number of soul coins equal to or less than its Constitution modifier without penalty. A non-evil creature carrying a number of soul coins greater than its Constitution modifier has disadvantage on its attack rolls, ability checks, and saving throws.</text>
        <text>Using a Soul Coin. A soul coin has 3 charges. A creature carrying the coin can use its action to expend 1 charge from a soul coin and use it to do one of the following:
            • Drain Life. You siphon away some of the soul's essence and gain 1dlO temporary hit points.
            • Query. You telepathically ask the soul a question and receive a brief telepathic response. which you can understand. The soul knows on ly what it knew in life, but it must answer you truthfully and to the best of its ability. The answer is no more than a sentence or two and might be cryptic.</text>
        <text>Freeing a Soul. Casting a spell that removes a curse on a soul coin frees the soul trapped within it, as does expending all of the coin's charges. The coin itself rusts from within and is destroyed once the soul is released. A freed soul travels to the realm of the god it served or the outer plane most closely tied to its alignment (DM's choice). The souls of lawful evil creatures released from soul coins typically emerge from the River Styx as lemure devils.</text>
        <text>A soul can also be freed by destroying the coin that contains it. A soul coin has AC 19, 1 hit point for each charge it has remaining, and immunity to all damage ex- cept that which is dealt by a hellfire weapon (page 223) or an infernal war machine's furnace (page 217).
            Freeing a soul from a soul coin is considered a good act, even if the soul belongs to an evil creature.
            Hellish Currency. Soul coins are a currency of the Nine Hells and are highly valued by devils. The coins are used among the infernal hierarchy to barter for favors, bribe the unwilling. and reward the faithful for services rendered.</text>
        <text>Soul coins are created by Mammon and his greater devils on Minauros, the third layer of the Nine Hells, in a vast chamber where the captured souls of evil mortals are bound into the coins. These coins are then distributed throughout the Nine Hells to be used for goods and services, infernal deals, dark bargains, and bribes.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Baldur's Gate Descent into Avernus, p. 225</text>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Sword of Zariel</name>
        <type>M</type>
        <detail>artifact (requires attunement by a creature the sword deems worthy)</detail>
        <text>This longsword belonged to the angel Zariel before her fall from grace. Fashioned from celestial steel, it gives off a faint glow and hum. The weapon chooses who can attune to it and who can't. It desires a wielder who em- bodies bravery and heroism.</text>
        <text>Attunement. The sword allows you to attune to it immediately, without having to take a short rest. The first time you attune to the sword, you are transformed into a heavenly, idealized version of yourself, blessed with otherworldly beauty and a touch of heaven in your heart. Neither magic nor divine intervention can reverse this transformation. Your alignment becomes lawful good, and you gain the following traits:
            • Angelic Language. You can speak, read. and write Celestial.
            • Celestial Resistance. You have resistance to necrotic and radiant damage.
            • Divine Presence. Your Charisma score becomes 20, unless it is already 20 or higher.
            • Feathered Wings. You sprout a beautiful pair of feathered wings that grant you a flying speed of 90 feet and the ability to hover. If you already have a different kind of wings, these new wings replace the old ones, which fall off.
            • Truesight. Your eyes become luminous pools of silver. You can see in normal and magical darkness, see invisible creatures and objects, automatically detect visual illusions and succeed on saving throws against them, perceive the original form of a shapechanger or a creature that is transformed by magic, and see into the Ethereal Plane, all within 60 feet.</text>
        <text>New Personality. You gain new personality traits, determined by rolling once on each of the following tables. These traits override any conflicting personality trait, ideal, bond or flaw.</text>
        <text>Personality Traits:
            
            d8 Personality Trait
            1 treat all beings, even enemies, with respect.
            2 I won't tell a lie.
            3 I enjoy sharing my philosophical worldview and experiences with others.
            4 I cut right to the chase in every conversation.
            5 I often quote (or misquote) religious texts.
            6 I anger quickly when I witness cruelty or injustice.
            7 My praise and trust are earned and never given freely.
            8 I like everything clean and organized.</text>
        <text>Ideals:
            
            d6 Ideal
            1 Charity. I always help those in need. (Good)
            2 Faith. I choose to follow the tenets of a particular law- ful good deity to the letter. (Lawful)
            3 Responsibility. It is the duty ofthe strong to protect the weak. (Lawful)
            4 Respect. All people deserve to be treated with dignity. (Good)
            5 Honor. The way I conduct myself determines my reward in the afterlife. (Lawful)
            6 Redemption. All creatures are capable of change for the better. (Good)</text>
        <text>Bonds:
            
            d6 Bond
            1 I have a favorite religious hymn that I constantly hum.
            2 I must keep a written record of my beliefs and the sins that I witness. When finished, this book will be my gift to the multiverse.
            3 I have cherished memories ofldyllglen, though I've only seen this bucolic town in dreams.
            4 I would die for those who fight beside me, regardless of their faults.
            5 I seek to honor the angel Zariel by destroying fiends and other evildoers wherever I find them.
            6 The Sword of Zariel has chosen me. I shall not fail to wield it justly.</text>
        <text>Flaws:
            
            d6 Flaws
            1 I am too quick to judge others.
            2 I offer forgiveness too readily.
            3 I will sacrifice innocent lives for the greater good.
            4 Flaw? What flaw? I am flawless. Utter perfection!
            5 I allow nothing to stand in the way of my crusade to eradicate evi l from the multiverse.
            6 I ignore those who do not support my plans, for my calling is higher than all others.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Holy Light. The sword sheds bright light in a 5-foot radius and dim light for an additional 5 feet. Fiends find the sword's light disconcerting and painful, even if they can't see it, and have disadvantage on attack rolls made within the weapon's radius of bright light.
            As a bonus action, you can intensify the sword's light, causing it to shed bright light in a 15-foot radius and dim light for an additional 15 feet. or reduce its glow to its normal intensity.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Random Properties. The sword has 2 minor beneficial properties, each determined by rolling on the Minor Beneficial Properties table in chapter 7 of the Dungeon Master's Guide.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Searing Radiance. The sword deals an extra 9 (2d8) radiant damage to any creature it hits, or 16 (3d10) radiant damage if you're wielding the weapon with two hands. An evil creature that takes this radiant damage must succeed on a DC 17 Constitution saving throw or be blinded until the end of its next turn.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Sentience. The Sword of Zariel is a sentient, lawful good item with an Intelligence of 10, a Wisdom of 20, and a Charisma of 18. It has hearing and normal vision out to a range of 30 feet.
            The sword communicates by transmitting emotion to the creature carrying or wielding it.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Truth Seer. While holding the sword, you gain advan- tage on all Wisdom (Insight) checks.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Destroying the Sword. Zariel can destroy the sword simply by grasping it. She couldn't bring herself to do so when she was an angel, but as an archdevil she has no compunction about ridding the multiverse of the weapon. The sword is also destroyed if it's used to shatter the Companion (see "Shattering the Companion," page 154), unless the blade is wielded by an angel of challenge rating 15 or higher, or a good-aligned cleric or paladin of at least 10th level.
            If Zariel is killed for good (that is, if she dies in the Nine Hells), the sword becomes no harder to destroy than a normal longsword.</text>
        <text>Source: Baldur's Gate Descent into Avernus, p. 226</text>
        <dmg1>1d8</dmg1>
        <dmg2>1d10</dmg2>
        <dmgType>S</dmgType>
        <property>V</property>
    </item>

    <!-- Backgrounds -->
    <background>
        <name>Faceless</name>
        <proficiency>Deception, Intimidation</proficiency>
        <trait>
            <name>Description</name>
            <text>Being who you are, you could never be a hero. Whether due to your class, your people, your family, or your sins, something about you prevents you from effectively pursuing the path you've chosen. Even so, that doesn't stop you. You've left your old face behind, taking on a new persona, becoming something more.
                Characters with the faceless background don a disguise—literally or otherwise—as they adventure. This persona might be dramatic or subtle. In a way, though, many characters have such larger than life personalities. Therefore, this background largely focuses on detailing the hero behind the mask.
                • Skill Proficiencies: Deception, Intimidation
                • Tool Proficiencies: Disguise kit
                • Languages: One of your choice
                • Equipment: Disguise kit, a costume clothes, a pouch containing 10 gp
                Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 203</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Faceless Persona</name>
            <text>A faceless character adventures behind the mask of a public persona. This persona is as natural to them as their hidden, true face, but it disguises their identity. Roll on the Faceless Persona table to determine your persona, or work with the DM to create a persona that's unique to your character and suits the tone of your game.
                d10 | Faceless Persona
                1 | A flamboyant spy or brigand
                2 | The incarnation of a nation or people
                3 | A scoundrel with a masked guise
                4 | A vengeful spirit
                5 | The manifestation of a deity or your faith
                6 | One whose beauty is greatly accented using makeup
                7 | An impersonation of another hero
                8 | The embodiment of a school of magic
                9 | A warrior with distinctive armor
                10 | A disguise with animalistic or monstrous characteristics, meant to inspire fear
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Feature: Dual Personalities</name>
            <text>Most of your fellow adventurers and the world know you as your persona. Those who seek to learn more about you—your weaknesses, your origins, your purpose—find themselves stymied by your disguise. Upon donning a disguise and behaving as your persona, you are unidentifiable as your true self. By removing your disguise and revealing your true face, you are no longer identifiable as your persona. This allows you to change appearances between your two personalities as often as you wish, using one to hide the other or serve as convenient camouflage. However, should someone realize the connection between your persona and your true self, your deception might lose its effectiveness.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
            <text>A faceless character usually plays their persona—the hero or extraordinary person they are every day. That's all a facade, though, or a part of them expressed to an extreme. To define a persona, feel free to choose characteristics from other backgrounds, particularly folk hero, hermit, or noble. For the person behind the persona, the one who truly strives to be faceless, consider a distinct set of faceless characteristics. As a result, those with this background have two sets of characteristics, one for their persona, and one for their faceless selves.
                d8 | Personality Trait
                1 | I'm earnest and uncommonly direct.
                2 | I strive to have no personality—it's easier to forget what's hardly there.
                3 | I treasure a memento of the person or instance that set me upon my path.
                4 | I sleep just as much as I need to and on an unusual schedule.
                5 | I think far ahead, a detachedness often mistaken for daydreaming.
                6 | I cultivate a single obscure hobby or study and eagerly discuss it at length.
                7 | I am ever learning how to be among others—when to stay quiet, when to laugh.
                8 | I behave like an extreme opposite of my persona.
                
                d6 | Ideal
                1 | Justice. Place in society shouldn't determine one's access to what is right. (Good)
                2 | Security. Doing what must be done can't bring the innocent to harm. (Lawful)
                3 | Confusion. Deception is a weapon. Strike from where your foes won't expect. (Chaotic)
                4 | Infamy. My name will be a malediction, a curse that fulfills my will. (Evil)
                5 | Incorruptibility. Be a symbol, and leave your flawed being behind. (Any)
                6 | Anonymity. It's my deeds that should be remembered, not their instrument. (Any)
                
                d6 | Bond
                1 | I do everything for my family. My first thought is keeping them safe.
                2 | What I do, I do for the world. The people don't realize how much they need me.
                3 | I've seen too many in need. I must not fail them as everyone else has.
                4 | I stand in opposition, lest the wicked go unopposed.
                5 | I am exceptional. I do this because no one else can, and no one can stop me.
                6 | I do everything for those who were taken from me.
                
                d6 | Flaw
                1 | I am callous about death. It comes to us all eventually.
                2 | I never make eye contact or hold it unflinchingly.
                3 | I have no sense of humor. Laughing is uncomfortable and embarrassing.
                4 | I overexert myself, sometimes needing to recuperate for a day or more.
                5 | I think far ahead, a detachedness often mistaken for daydreaming.
                6 | I see morality entirely in black and white.
            </text>
        </trait>
    </background>
    <background>
        <name>Baldur's Gate Acolyte</name>
        <proficiency>Insight, Religion</proficiency>
        <trait>
            <name>Description</name>
            <text>• Skill Proficiencies: Insight, Religion
                • Languages: Two of your choice
                • Equipment: A holy symbol (a gift to you when you entered the priesthood), a prayer book or prayer wheel, 5 sticks of incense, vestments, a set of common clothes, and a belt pouch containing 15 gp
                Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 202</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Feature: Shelter of the Faithful</name>
            <text>As an acolyte, you command the respect of those who share your faith, and you can perform the religious ceremonies of your deity. You and your adventuring companions can expect to receive free healing and care at a temple, shrine, or other established presence of your faith, though you must provide any material components needed for spells. Those who share your religion will support you (but only you) at a modest lifestyle.
                You might also have ties to a specific temple dedicated to your chosen deity or pantheon, and you have a residence there. This could be the temple where you used to serve, if you remain on good terms with it, or a temple where you have found a new home. While near your temple, you can call upon the priests for assistance, provided the assistance you ask for is not hazardous and you remain in good standing with your temple.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Baldur's Gate Feature: Religious Community</name>
            <text>The effects of a Baldur's Gate feature can be used only while the character is in Baldur's Gate—though, at the DM's discretion, they might have applicable effects in situations similar to those in Baldur's Gate.
                You're tightly connected with the religious community of Baldur's Gate. You know if a deity has a following in the city and any places that faith openly congregates and the neighborhoods those faithful typically inhabit. While this isn't remarkable for most of the city's larger faiths, keeping track of the hundreds of religions newcomers bring with them is no mean feat.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
            <text>Acolytes are shaped by their experience in temples or other religious communities. Their study of the history and tenets of their faith and their relationships to temples, shrines, or hierarchies affect their mannerisms and ideals. Their flaws might be some hidden hypocrisy or heretical idea, or an ideal or bond taken to an extreme.
                d8 | Personality Trait
                1 | I idolize a particular hero of my faith, and constantly refer to that person's deeds and example.
                2 | I can find common ground between the fiercest enemies, empathizing with them and always working toward peace.
                3 | I see omens in every event and action. The gods try to speak to us, we just need to listen.
                4 | Nothing can shake my optimistic attitude.
                5 | I quote (or misquote) sacred texts and proverbs in almost every situation.
                6 | I am tolerant (or intolerant) of other faiths and respect (or condemn) the worship of other gods.
                7 | I've enjoyed fine food, drink, and high society among my temple's elite. Rough living grates on me.
                8 | I've spent so long in the temple that I have little practical experience dealing with people in the outside world.
                
                d6 | Ideal
                1 | Tradition. The ancient traditions of worship and sacrifice must be preserved and upheld. (Lawful)
                2 | Charity. I always try to help those in need, no matter what the personal cost. (Good)
                3 | Change. We must help bring about the changes the gods are constantly working in the world. (Chaotic)
                4 | Power. I hope to one day rise to the top of my faith's religious hierarchy. (Lawful)
                5 | Faith. I trust that my deity will guide my actions. I have faith that if I work hard, things will go well. (Lawful)
                6 | Aspiration. I seek to prove myself worthy of my god's favor by matching my actions against his or her teachings. (Any)
                
                d6 | Bond
                1 | I would die to recover an ancient relic of my faith that was lost long ago.
                2 | I will someday get revenge on the corrupt temple hierarchy who branded me a heretic.
                3 | I owe my life to the priest who took me in when my parents died.
                4 | Everything I do is for the common people.
                5 | I will do anything to protect the temple where I served.
                6 | I seek to preserve a sacred text that my enemies consider heretical and seek to destroy.
                
                d6 | Flaw
                1 | I judge others harshly, and myself even more severely.
                2 | I put too much trust in those who wield power within my temple's hierarchy.
                3 | My piety sometimes leads me to blindly trust those that profess faith in my god.
                4 | I am inflexible in my thinking.
                5 | I am suspicious of strangers and expect the worst of them.
                6 | Once I pick a goal, I become obsessed with it to the detriment of everything else in my life.
            </text>
        </trait>
    </background>
    <background>
        <name>Baldur's Gate Charlatan</name>
        <proficiency>Deception, Sleight Of Hand</proficiency>
        <trait>
            <name>Description</name>
            <text>• Skill Proficiencies: Deception, Sleight of Hand
                • Tool Proficiencies: Disguise kit, Forgery kit
                • Equipment: A set of fine clothes, a disguise kit, tools of the con of your choice (ten stoppered bottles filled with colored liquid, a set of weighted dice, a deck of marked cards, or a signet ring of an imaginary duke), and a belt pouch containing 15 gp
                Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 202</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Feature: False Identity</name>
            <text>You have created a second identity that includes documentation, established acquaintances, and disguises that allow you to assume that persona. Additionally, you can forge documents including official papers and personal letters, as long as you have seen an example of the kind of document or the handwriting you are trying to copy.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Baldur's Gate Feature: Long-Lost Heir</name>
            <text>The effects of a Baldur's Gate feature can be used only while the character is in Baldur's Gate—though, at the DM's discretion, they might have applicable effects in situations similar to those in Baldur's Gate.
                You're well-versed in the mannerisms and idiosyncrasies of Baldurian patriars and other nobles, imitating them smoothly enough to convince even the snootiest family heads of your authenticity. You're skilled at posing as the long-lost heir to some imaginary or extinguished patriar lineage.
                Because of your skill in passing yourself off as a patriar, you have a Watch token that allows you alone into the Upper City of Baldur's Gate. You might be able to bluff others through with you, or even convince members of the Watch that you're a patriar. However, any true test of your authenticity is likely to reveal your deception.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Favorite Schemes</name>
            <text>Every charlatan has an angle he or she uses in preference to other schemes. Choose a favorite scam or roll on the table below.
                d6 | Scam
                1 | I cheat at games of chance.
                2 | I shave coins or forge documents.
                3 | I insinuate myself into people's lives to prey on their weakness and secure their fortunes.
                4 | I put on new identities like clothes.
                5 | I run sleight-of-hand cons on street corners.
                6 | I convince people that worthless junk is worth their hard-earned money.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
            <text>Charlatans are colorful characters who conceal their true selves behind the masks they construct. They reflect what people want to see, what they want to believe, and how they see the world. But their true selves are sometimes plagued by an uneasy conscience, an old enemy, or deep-seated trust issues.
                d8 | Personality Trait
                1 | I fall in and out of love easily, and am always pursuing someone.
                2 | I have a joke for every occasion, especially occasions where humor is inappropriate.
                3 | Flattery is my preferred trick for getting what I want.
                4 | I'm a born gambler who can't resist taking a risk for a potential payoff.
                5 | I lie about almost everything, even when there's no reason to.
                6 | Sarcasm and insults are my weapons of choice.
                7 | I keep multiple holy symbols on me and invoke whatever deity might come in useful at any given moment.
                8 | I pocket anything I see that might have some value.
                
                d6 | Ideal
                1 | Independence. I am a free spirit—no one tells me what to do. (Chaotic)
                2 | Fairness. I never target people who can't afford to lose a few coins. (Lawful)
                3 | Charity. I distribute the money I acquire to the people who really need it. (Good)
                4 | Creativity. I never run the same con twice. (Chaotic)
                5 | Friendship. Material goods come and go. Bonds of friendship last forever. (Good)
                6 | Aspiration. I'm determined to make something of myself. (Any)
                
                d6 | Bond
                1 | I fleeced the wrong person and must work to ensure that this individual never crosses paths with me or those I care about.
                2 | I owe everything to my mentor—a horrible person who's probably rotting in jail somewhere.
                3 | Somewhere out there, I have a child who doesn't know me. I'm making the world better for him or her.
                4 | I come from a noble family, and one day I'll reclaim my lands and title from those who stole them from me.
                5 | A powerful person killed someone I love. Some day soon, I'll have my revenge.
                6 | I swindled and ruined a person who didn't deserve it. I seek to atone for my misdeeds but might never be able to forgive myself.
                
                d6 | Flaw
                1 | I can't resist a pretty face.
                2 | I'm always in debt. I spend my ill-gotten gains on decadent luxuries faster than I bring them in.
                3 | I'm convinced that no one could ever fool me the way I fool others.
                4 | I'm too greedy for my own good. I can't resist taking a risk if there's money involved.
                5 | I can't resist swindling people who are more powerful than me.
                6 | I hate to admit it and will hate myself for it, but I'll run and preserve my own hide if the going gets tough.
            </text>
        </trait>
    </background>
    <background>
        <name>Baldur's Gate Criminal</name>
        <proficiency>Deception, Stealth</proficiency>
        <trait>
            <name>Description</name>
            <text>• Skill Proficiencies: Deception, Stealth
                • Tool Proficiencies: One type of gaming set, thieves' tools
                • Equipment: A crowbar, a set of dark common clothes including a hood, and a belt pouch containing 15 gp
                Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 202</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Feature: Criminal Contact</name>
            <text>You have a reliable and trustworthy contact who acts as your liaison to a network of other criminals. You know how to get messages to and from your contact, even over great distances; specifically, you know the local messengers, corrupt caravan masters, and seedy sailors who can deliver messages for you.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Baldur's Gate Feature: Criminal Connections</name>
            <text>The effects of a Baldur's Gate feature can be used only while the character is in Baldur's Gate—though, at the DM's discretion, they might have applicable effects in situations similar to those in Baldur's Gate.
                In Baldur's Gate, crime is just another business. As a result, you can arrange a meeting with a low-ranking operative of nearly any business, patriar family, crew, government institution, or—certainly—the Guild. This operative will hear you out and, at their discretion, take your information or request up their chain of command. These meetings almost always occur in shady venues.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Criminal Origins</name>
            <text>Criminals are pervasive in Baldur's Gate. If you wish, you may roll on the Criminal Origins table for an event that began your life of crime.
                d8 | Origin
                1 | You crippled a Guild kingpin's cousin without realizing the connection. You got the Guild to back off demands for your death by offering to make amends by working for the criminals, but even so the kingpin still plots a personal revenge.
                2 | The Guild took over your family business, ran it into the ground, and burned the building for insurance money. You were driven into crime yourself, but you'll never work for the Guild. You take special joy in hitting its targets first, tipping off its con victims and otherwise frustrating its schemes.
                3 | It's always been about money. You're not paid what you're worth, working for someone who has more than they deserve. But the Guild offered you a way to fix that. You keep doing what you've always done—guard work, dock labor, business accounting—but what you learn you pass on to the Guild.
                4 | The inequality of Baldur's Gate has driven you to take matters into your own hands. You steal from patriars and rich Lower City residents, funneling the money through charitable fronts to help the needy.
                5 | You got into crime as a bored patriar looking for excitement. Your family has no idea of your activities, and neither does the Guild. If either of them ever finds out, your life as you know it will be over.
                6 | A close friend or relative joined the Guild and vanished mysteriously. You've worked your way into the lower ranks hoping to find out what happened to them.
                7 | You've always wanted to be a member of the Guild. As a child, you looked up to the Guild members' swagger, their flashy dress, and their competence, which all marked them as different from the other adults you knew. As soon as you could, you joined the organization.
                8 | To you, this is just a way to earn a living. You go to work, do what needs to be done, and get paid. Anyone who pursues crime for thrill-seeking, to strike back at unjust authorities, or anything else are amateurs, and they're liable to get you arrested or killed with their idiocy.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Specialty</name>
            <text>There are many kinds of criminals, and within a thieves' guild or similar criminal organization, individual members have particular specialties. Even criminals who operate outside of such organizations have strong preferences for certain kinds of crimes over others. Choose the role you played in your criminal life, or roll on the table below.
                d8 | Specialty
                1 | Blackmailer
                2 | Burglar
                3 | Enforcer
                4 | Fence
                5 | Highway robber
                6 | Hired killer
                7 | Pickpocket
                8 | Smuggler
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
            <text>Criminals might seem like villains on the surface, and many of them are villainous to the core. But some have an abundance of endearing, if not redeeming, characteristics. There might be honor among thieves, but criminals rarely show any respect for law or authority.
                d8 | Personality Trait
                1 | I always have a plan for when things go wrong.
                2 | I am always calm, no matter what the situation. I never raise my voice or let my emotions control me.
                3 | The first thing I do in a new place is note the locations of everything valuable—or where such things could be hidden.
                4 | I would rather make a new friend than a new enemy.
                5 | I am incredibly slow to trust. Those who seem the fairest often have the most to hide.
                6 | I don't pay attention to the risks in a situation. Never tell me the odds.
                7 | The best way to get me to do something is to tell me I can't do it.
                8 | I blow up at the slightest insult.
                
                d6 | Ideal
                1 | Honor. I don't steal from others in the trade. (Lawful)
                2 | Freedom. Chains are meant to be broken, as are those who would forge them. (Chaotic)
                3 | Charity. I steal from the wealthy so that I can help people in need. (Good)
                4 | Greed. I will do whatever it takes to become wealthy. (Evil)
                5 | People. I'm loyal to my friends, not to any ideals, and everyone else can take a trip down the Styx for all I care. (Neutral)
                6 | Redemption. There's a spark of good in everyone. (Good)
                
                d6 | Bond
                1 | I'm trying to pay off an old debt I owe to a generous benefactor.
                2 | My ill-gotten gains go to support my family.
                3 | Something important was taken from me, and I aim to steal it back.
                4 | I will become the greatest thief that ever lived.
                5 | I'm guilty of a terrible crime. I hope I can redeem myself for it.
                6 | Someone I loved died because of a mistake I made. That will never happen again.
                
                d6 | Flaw
                1 | When I see something valuable, I can't think about anything but how to steal it.
                2 | When faced with a choice between money and my friends, I usually choose the money.
                3 | If there's a plan, I'll forget it. If I don't forget it, I'll ignore it.
                4 | I have a 'tell' that reveals when I'm lying.
                5 | I turn tail and run when things look bad.
                6 | An innocent person is in prison for a crime that I committed. I'm okay with that.
            </text>
        </trait>
    </background>
    <background>
        <name>Baldur's Gate Entertainer</name>
        <proficiency>Acrobatics, Performance</proficiency>
        <trait>
            <name>Description</name>
            <text>• Skill Proficiencies: Acrobatics, Performance
                • Tool Proficiencies: Disguise kit, one type of musical instrument
                • Equipment: A musical instrument (one of your choice), the favor of an admirer (love letter, lock of hair, or trinket), costume clothes, and a belt pouch containing 15 gp
                Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 202</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Feature: By Popular Demand</name>
            <text>You can always find a place to perform, usually in an inn or tavern but possibly with a circus, at a theater, or even in a noble's court. At such a place, you receive free lodging and food of a modest or comfortable standard (depending on the quality of the establishment), as long as you perform each night. In addition, your performance makes you something of a local figure. When strangers recognize you in a town where you have performed, they typically take a liking to you.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Baldur's Gate Feature: Backstage Pass</name>
            <text>The effects of a Baldur's Gate feature can be used only while the character is in Baldur's Gate—though, at the DM's discretion, they might have applicable effects in situations similar to those in Baldur's Gate.
                You've learned that most of the real business of entertainment (or any other venture) happens behind the scenes. It's easy for you to case what sorts of audiences attend what venue—like how toughs gather at the Blushing Mermaid or how brash patriars congregate at the Helm and Cloak. After a successful performance, you may meet an enthusiastic member of the crowd—someone of an occupation or social class that frequents the establishment. This contact is delighted to talk with you, and to listen.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Specialty</name>
            <text>A good entertainer is versatile, spicing up every performance with a variety of different routines. Choose one to three routines or roll on the table below to define your expertise as an entertainer.
                d10 | Routines
                1 | Actor
                2 | Dancer
                3 | Fire-eater
                4 | Jester
                5 | Juggler
                6 | Instrumentalist
                7 | Poet
                8 | Singer
                9 | Storyteller
                10 | Tumbler
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
            <text>Successful entertainers have to be able to capture and hold an audience's attention, so they tend to have flamboyant or forceful personalities. They're inclined toward the romantic and often cling to high-minded ideals about the practice of art and the appreciation of beauty.
                d8 | Personality Trait
                1 | I know a story relevant to almost every situation.
                2 | Whenever I come to a new place, I collect local rumors and spread gossip.
                3 | I'm a hopeless romantic, always searching for that "special someone".
                4 | Nobody stays angry at me or around me for long, since I can defuse any amount of tension.
                5 | I love a good insult, even one directed at me.
                6 | I get bitter if I'm not the center of attention.
                7 | I'll settle for nothing less than perfection.
                8 | I change my mood or my mind as quickly as I change key in a song.
                
                d6 | Ideal
                1 | Beauty. When I perform, I make the world better than it was. (Good)
                2 | Tradition. The stories, legends, and songs of the past must never be forgotten, for they teach us who we are. (Lawful)
                3 | Creativity. The world is in need of new ideas and bold action. (Chaotic)
                4 | Greed. I'm only in it for the money and fame. (Evil)
                5 | People. I like seeing the smiles on people's faces when I perform. That's all that matters. (Neutral)
                6 | Honesty. Art should reflect the soul; it should come from within and reveal who we really are. (Any)
                
                d6 | Bond
                1 | My instrument is my most treasured possession, and it reminds me of someone I love.
                2 | Someone stole my precious instrument, and someday I'll get it back.
                3 | I want to be famous, whatever it takes.
                4 | I idolize a hero of the old tales and measure my deeds against that person's.
                5 | I will do anything to prove myself superior to my hated rival.
                6 | I would do anything for the other members of my old troupe.
                
                d6 | Flaw
                1 | I'll do anything to win fame and renown.
                2 | I'm a sucker for a pretty face.
                3 | A scandal prevents me from ever going home again. That kind of trouble seems to follow me around.
                4 | I once satirized a noble who still wants my head. It was a mistake that I will likely repeat.
                5 | I have trouble keeping my true feelings hidden. My sharp tongue lands me in trouble.
                6 | Despite my best efforts, I am unreliable to my friends.
            </text>
        </trait>
    </background>
    <background>
        <name>Baldur's Gate Folk Hero</name>
        <proficiency>Animal Handling, Survival</proficiency>
        <trait>
            <name>Description</name>
            <text>• Skill Proficiencies: Animal Handling, Survival
                • Tool Proficiencies: One type of artisan's tools, vehicles (land)
                • Equipment: A set of artisan's tools (one of your choice), a shovel, an iron pot, a set of common clothes, and a belt pouch containing 10 gp
                Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 204</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Feature: Rustic Hospitality</name>
            <text>Since you come from the ranks of the common folk, you fit in among them with ease. You can find a place to hide, rest, or recuperate among other commoners, unless you have shown yourself to be a danger to them. They will shield you from the law or anyone else searching for you, though they will not risk their lives for you.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Baldur's Gate Feature: Social Vengeance</name>
            <text>The effects of a Baldur's Gate feature can be used only while the character is in Baldur's Gate—though, at the DM's discretion, they might have applicable effects in situations similar to those in Baldur's Gate.
                You've lived your entire life in the Lower or Outer City of Baldur's Gate. You grew up seeing arrogant patriars flaunt their wealth while your hardworking neighbors struggled. As a result, you know how eager commoners in Baldur's Gate are to see any patriar get what they deserve. While in a busy part of the Lower City or Outer City of Baldur's Gate, you can spend 2d10} minutes to convince 1d6 {@creature commoner to perform a non-illegal act that inconveniences a member of the Watch or Flaming Fist, a patriar, or some other wealthy looking individual.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Folk Hero Origins</name>
            <text>Folk heroes might rise from a variety of circumstances, or their origins might be a secret as they do their work anonymously. If you wish, you may roll on the Folk Hero Origins table for an event that started you down your heroic path.
                d6 | Origin
                1 | You helped get healing for a sick child. Now the sick come to you, knowing you'll help them find a way to salvation.
                2 | You helped break a Guild protection racket afflicting a community of immigrants in the Outer City. Now, you can't travel through that part of the city without your dozen adopted grandparents inviting you in for a meal.
                3 | Seeing a lost patriar after dark in the Outer City, you guided the wayward noble through back streets to safety. The patriar repaid your help by paying for improved roofs and lamps in your neighborhood, causing the entire community to celebrate your deed.
                4 | Fueled by alcohol, you faced down a carrion crawler that slunk out of the sewer, knocking it out with a single punch. Since then, however, the ale you once credited with your heroism has drowned it, and even your most patient admirers are losing hope. You're hoping for one last chance to win back the goodwill you've drunk away.
                5 | You once defeated a raging bugbear with a hand mirror, a mounted deer's head, and two kicks to the groin. Later, you and the bugbear became friends.
                6 | Last winter, you dove into the frigid river to haul out a foundering fishing boat with your bare hands, saving all aboard. Now, everyone on the docks knows your name.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Specialty</name>
            <text>You previously pursued a simple profession among the peasantry, perhaps as a farmer, miner, servant, shepherd, woodcutter, or gravedigger. But something happened that set you on a different path and marked you for greater things. Choose or randomly determine a defining event that marked you as a hero of the people.
                d10 | Defining Event
                1 | I stood up to a tyrant's agents.
                2 | I saved people during a natural disaster.
                3 | I stood alone against a terrible monster.
                4 | I stole from a corrupt merchant to help the poor.
                5 | I led a militia to fight of an invading army.
                6 | I broke into a tyrant's castle and stole weapons to arm the people.
                7 | I trained the peasantry to use farming implements as weapons against a tyrant's soldiers.
                8 | A lord rescinded an unpopular decree after I led a symbolic act of protest against it.
                9 | A celestial, fey, or similar creature gave me a blessing or revealed my secret origin.
                10 | Recruited into a lord's army, I rose to leadership and was commended for my heroism.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
            <text>A folk hero is one of the common people, for better or for worse. Most folk heroes look on their humble origins as a virtue, not a shortcoming, and their home communities remain very important to them.
                d8 | Personality Trait
                1 | I judge people by their actions, not their words.
                2 | If someone is in trouble, I'm always ready to lend help.
                3 | When I set my mind to something, I follow through no matter what gets in my way.
                4 | I have a strong sense of fair play and always try to find the most equitable solution to arguments.
                5 | I'm confident in my own abilities and do what I can to instill confidence in others.
                6 | Thinking is for other people. I prefer action.
                7 | I misuse long words in an attempt to sound smarter.
                8 | I get bored easily. When am I going to get on with my destiny?
                
                d6 | Ideal
                1 | Respect. People deserve to be treated with dignity and respect. (Good)
                2 | Fairness. No one should get preferential treatment before the law, and no one is above the law. (Lawful)
                3 | Freedom. Tyrants must not be allowed to oppress the people. (Chaotic)
                4 | Might. If I become strong, I can take what I want—what I deserve. (Evil)
                5 | Sincerity. There's no good in pretending to be something I'm not. (Neutral)
                6 | Destiny. Nothing and no one can steer me away from my higher calling. (Any)
                
                d6 | Bond
                1 | I have a family, but I have no idea where they are. One day, I hope to see them again.
                2 | I worked the land, I love the land, and I will protect the land.
                3 | A proud noble once gave me a horrible beating, and I will take my revenge on any bully I encounter.
                4 | My tools are symbols of my past life, and I carry them so that I will never forget my roots.
                5 | I protect those who cannot protect themselves.
                6 | I wish my childhood sweetheart had come with me to pursue my destiny.
                
                d6 | Flaw
                1 | The tyrant who rules my land will stop at nothing to see me killed.
                2 | I'm convinced of the significance of my destiny, and blind to my shortcomings and the risk of failure.
                3 | The people who knew me when I was young know my shameful secret, so I can never go home again.
                4 | I have a weakness for the vices of the city, especially hard drink.
                5 | Secretly, I believe that things would be better if I were a tyrant lording over the land.
                6 | I have trouble trusting in my allies.
            </text>
        </trait>
    </background>
    <background>
        <name>Baldur's Gate Guild Artisan</name>
        <proficiency>Insight, Persuasion</proficiency>
        <trait>
            <name>Description</name>
            <text>• Skill Proficiencies: Insight, Persuasion
                • Tool Proficiencies: One type of artisan's tools
                • Languages: One of your choice
                • Equipment: A set of artisan's tools (one of your choice), a letter of introduction from your guild, a set of traveler's clothes, and a belt pouch containing 15 gp
                Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 204</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Feature: Guild Membership</name>
            <text>As an established and respected member of a guild, you can rely on certain benefits that membership provides. Your fellow guild members will provide you with lodging and food if necessary, and pay for your funeral if needed. In some cities and towns, a guildhall offers a central place to meet other members of your profession, which can be a good place to meet potential patrons, allies, or hirelings.
                Guilds often wield tremendous political power. If you are accused of a crime, your guild will support you if a good case can be made for your innocence or the crime is justifiable. You can also gain access to powerful political figures through the guild, if you are a member in good standing. Such connections might require the donation of money or magic items to the guild's coffers.
                You must pay dues of 5 gp per month to the guild. If you miss payments, you must make up back dues to remain in the guild's good graces.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Baldur's Gate Feature: Professional Courtesy</name>
            <text>The effects of a Baldur's Gate feature can be used only while the character is in Baldur's Gate—though, at the DM's discretion, they might have applicable effects in situations similar to those in Baldur's Gate.
                You're familiar with the city's crews, their territories, and inter-crew politics. Choose one of the three districts of Baldur's Gate: the Upper City, the Lower City, or the Outer City. This is the district where you conduct most of your business. Whenever you need information about something in one of that district's neighborhoods, you can seek out crew members in that area and learn the local gossip. You can also gain unimpeded entry to nearly any bank, guild hall, place of business, workhouse, or crew meeting place in your district.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Specialty</name>
            <text>Guilds are generally found in cities large enough to support several artisans practicing the same trade. However, your guild might instead be a loose network of artisans who each work in a different village within a larger realm. Work with your DM to determine the nature of your guild. You can select your guild business from the Guild Business table or roll randomly.
                d20 | Guild Business
                1 | Alchemists and apothecaries
                2 | Armorers, locksmiths, and finesmiths
                3 | Brewers, distillers, and vintners
                4 | Calligraphers, scribes, and scriveners
                5 | Carpenters, roofers, and plasterers
                6 | Cartographers, surveyors, and chart-makers
                7 | Cobblers and shoemakers
                8 | Cooks and bakers
                9 | Glassblowers and glaziers
                10 | Jewelers and gemcutters
                11 | Leatherworkers, skinners, and tanners
                12 | Masons and stonecutters
                13 | Painters, limners, and sign-makers
                14 | Potters and tile-makers
                15 | Shipwrights and sail-makers
                16 | Smiths and metal-forgers
                17 | Tinkers, pewterers, and casters
                18 | Wagon-makers and wheelwrights
                19 | Weavers and dyers
                20 | Woodcarvers, coopers, and bowyers
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
            <text>Guild artisans are among the most ordinary people in the world—until they set down their tools and take up an adventuring career. They understand the value of hard work and the importance of community, but they're vulnerable to sins of greed and covetousness.
                d8 | Personality Trait
                1 | I believe that anything worth doing is worth doing right. I can't help it—I'm a perfectionist.
                2 | I'm a snob who looks down on those who can't appreciate fine art.
                3 | I always want to know how things work and what makes people tick.
                4 | I'm full of witty aphorisms and have a proverb for every occasion.
                5 | I'm rude to people who lack my commitment to hard work and fair play.
                6 | I like to talk at length about my profession.
                7 | I don't part with my money easily and will haggle tirelessly to get the best deal possible.
                8 | I'm well known for my work, and I want to make sure everyone appreciates it. I'm always taken aback when people haven't heard of me.
                
                d6 | Ideal
                1 | Community. It is the duty of all civilized people to strengthen the bonds of community and the security of civilization. (Lawful)
                2 | Generosity. My talents were given to me so that I could use them to benefit the world. (Good)
                3 | Freedom. Everyone should be free to pursue his or her own livelihood. (Chaotic)
                4 | Greed. I'm only in it for the money. (Evil)
                5 | People. I'm committed to the people I care about, not to ideals. (Neutral)
                6 | Aspiration. I work hard to be the best there is at my craft. (Any)
                
                d6 | Bond
                1 | The workshop where I learned my trade is the most important place in the world to me.
                2 | I created a great work for someone, and then found them unworthy to receive it. I'm still looking for someone worthy.
                3 | I owe my guild a great debt for forging me into the person I am today.
                4 | I pursue wealth to secure someone's love.
                5 | One day I will return to my guild and prove that I am the greatest artisan of them all.
                6 | I will get revenge on the evil forces that destroyed my place of business and ruined my livelihood.
                
                d6 | Flaw
                1 | I'll do anything to get my hands on something rare or priceless.
                2 | I'm quick to assume that someone is trying to cheat me.
                3 | No one must ever learn that I once stole money from guild coffers.
                4 | I'm never satisfied with what I have—I always want more.
                5 | I would kill to acquire a noble title.
                6 | I'm horribly jealous of anyone who can outshine my handiwork. Everywhere I go, I'm surrounded by rivals.
            </text>
        </trait>
    </background>
    <background>
        <name>Baldur's Gate Hermit</name>
        <proficiency>Medicine, Religion</proficiency>
        <trait>
            <name>Description</name>
            <text>• Skill Proficiencies: Medicine, Religion
                • Tool Proficiencies: Herbalism kit
                • Languages: One of your choice
                • Equipment: A Map or Scroll Case stuffed full of notes from your studies or prayers, a winter blanket, a set of common clothes, an herbalism kit, and 5 gp
                Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 204</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Feature: Discovery</name>
            <text>The quiet seclusion of your extended hermitage gave you access to a unique and powerful discovery. The exact nature of this revelation depends on the nature of your seclusion. It might be a great truth about the cosmos, the deities, the powerful beings of the outer planes, or the forces of nature. It could be a site that no one else has ever seen. You might have uncovered a fact that has long been forgotten, or unearthed some relic of the past that could rewrite history. It might be information that would be damaging to the people who or consigned you to exile, and hence the reason for your return to society.
                Work with your DM to determine the details of your discovery and its impact on the campaign.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Baldur's Gate Feature: The Real City</name>
            <text>The effects of a Baldur's Gate feature can be used only while the character is in Baldur's Gate—though, at the DM's discretion, they might have applicable effects in situations similar to those in Baldur's Gate.
                You know the Baldur's Gate most Baldurians ignore, the dog-eat-dog world of the homeless and unfortunate. You know where to go in the Lower City and Outer City for anonymity. In these slums and alley camps, you can get a damp bed and a bad meal, but also a degree of privacy and no questions asked. Living here isn't comfortable, but it's unlikely anyone will find you—and you can stay as long as you want.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Hermit Origins</name>
            <text>Any number of personal choices or ill-fated circumstances might have led you to turn away from society. You may, if you wish, choose or roll an origin event from the Hermit Origins table.
                d6 | Origin
                1 | You led an ill-fated expedition into the Riverveins. Your friends were swept away by flooding, and you've never been able to shake the guilt of causing their deaths over a frivolous lark. You've maintained a solitary vigil outside the cavern entrance ever since.
                2 | You crossed the Guild in a bad way. Fortunately, its members think you're dead. Less fortunately, maintaining that deception might require you to stay in hiding until you actually are.
                3 | You study the puzzles of mortal natures. You've seen followers of evil deities perform miracles for the helpless at Twin Songs, and you've seen patriars who worship good deities turn their backs on the poor daily. Bearing witness to such things, and meditating on their contradictions, fills your hours.
                4 | You tend to some part of the city's forgotten history: the unmarked graves in Cliffside Cemetery, the crumbling remains of dead patriar families' manors, or a collection of religious texts stuffed into an attic and forgotten when a believer's patron deity died. In this solitary work, you've learned secrets no one else knows.
                5 | You killed a patriar's scion in an illegal duel. The family swore revenge, and you fled to the slums rather than risk bringing their wrath down on your kin.
                6 | You aren't originally from Baldur's Gate. You came here seeking something else, only to learn that the quest that drove you had become impossible to fulfill—its object was destroyed or its purpose was negated by some superseding event. Suddenly directionless and unable to return to your homeland, you have lingered, adrift, in this wretched city.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Specialty</name>
            <text>What was the reason for your isolation, and what changed to allow you to end your solitude? You can work with your DM to determine the exact nature of your seclusion, or you can choose or roll on the table below to determine the reason behind your seclusion.
                d8 | Life of Seclusion
                1 | I was searching for spiritual enlightenment.
                2 | I was partaking of communal living in accordance with the dictates of a religious order.
                3 | I was exiled for a crime I didn't commit.
                4 | I retreated from society after a life-altering event.
                5 | I needed a quiet place to work on my art, literature, music, or manifesto.
                6 | I needed to commune with nature, far from civilization.
                7 | I was the caretaker of an ancient ruin or relic.
                8 | I was a pilgrim in search of a person, place, or relic of spiritual significance.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
            <text>Some hermits are well suited to a life of seclusion, whereas others chafe against it and long for company. Whether they embrace solitude or long to escape it, the solitary life shapes their attitudes and ideals. A few are driven slightly mad by their years apart from society.
                d8 | Personality Trait
                1 | I've been isolated for so long that I rarely speak, preferring gestures and the occasional grunt.
                2 | I am utterly serene, even in the face of disaster.
                3 | The leader of my community had something wise to say on every topic, and I am eager to share that wisdom.
                4 | I feel tremendous empathy for all who suffer.
                5 | I'm oblivious to etiquette and social expectations.
                6 | I connect everything that happens to me to a grand, cosmic plan.
                7 | I often get lost in my own thoughts and contemplation, becoming oblivious to my surroundings.
                8 | I am working on a grand philosophical theory and love sharing my ideas.
                
                d6 | Ideal
                1 | Greater Good. My gifts are meant to be shared with all, not used for my own benefit. (Good)
                2 | Logic. Emotions must not cloud our sense of what is right and true, or our logical thinking. (Lawful)
                3 | Free Thinking. Inquiry and curiosity are the pillars of progress. (Chaotic)
                4 | Power. Solitude and contemplation are paths toward mystical or magical power. (Evil)
                5 | Live and Let Live. Meddling in the affairs of others only causes trouble. (Neutral)
                6 | Self-Knowledge. If you know yourself, there's nothing left to know. (Any)
                
                d6 | Bond
                1 | Nothing is more important than the other members of my hermitage, order, or association.
                2 | I entered seclusion to hide from the ones who might still be hunting me. I must someday confront them.
                3 | I'm still seeking the enlightenment I pursued in my seclusion, and it still eludes me.
                4 | I entered seclusion because I loved someone I could not have.
                5 | Should my discovery come to light, it could bring ruin to the world.
                6 | My isolation gave me great insight into a great evil that only I can destroy.
                
                d6 | Flaw
                1 | Now that I've returned to the world, I enjoy its delights a little too much.
                2 | I harbor dark, bloodthirsty thoughts that my isolation and meditation failed to quell.
                3 | I am dogmatic in my thoughts and philosophy.
                4 | I let my need to win arguments overshadow friendships and harmony.
                5 | I'd risk too much to uncover a lost bit of knowledge.
                6 | I like keeping secrets and won't share them with anyone.
            </text>
        </trait>
    </background>
    <background>
        <name>Baldur's Gate Noble</name>
        <proficiency>History, Persuasion</proficiency>
        <trait>
            <name>Description</name>
            <text>• Skill Proficiencies: History, Persuasion
                • Tool Proficiencies: One type of gaming set
                • Languages: One of your choice
                • Equipment: A set of fine clothes, a signet ring, a scroll of pedigree, and a purse containing 25 gp
                Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 204</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Feature: Position of Privilege</name>
            <text>Thanks to your noble birth, people are inclined to think the best of you. You are welcome in high society, and people assume you have the right to be wherever you are. The common folk make every effort to accommodate you and avoid your displeasure, and other people of high birth treat you as a member of the same social sphere. You can secure an audience with a local noble if you need to.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Baldur's Gate Feature: Patriar</name>
            <text>The effects of a Baldur's Gate feature can be used only while the character is in Baldur's Gate—though, at the DM's discretion, they might have applicable effects in situations similar to those in Baldur's Gate.
                As a member of one of the elite families of Baldur's Gate, you may pass through city gates without paying tolls, mingle among the Gate's nobility unquestioned, and impress those on the lookout for wealthy patrons. You are welcome in the Upper City and may stay there after dark without being harassed or evicted. Your word is accepted over others' without question, and any corruption among guards or government officials tends to work in your favor, not against you—at least until you make some effort to expose it.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
            <text>Nobles are born and raised to a very different lifestyle than most people ever experience, and their personalities reflect that upbringing. A noble title comes with a plethora of bonds—responsibilities to family, to other nobles (including the sovereign), to the people entrusted to the family's care, or even to the title itself. But this responsibility is often a good way to undermine a noble.
                d8 | Personality Trait
                1 | My eloquent flattery makes everyone I talk to feel like the most wonderful and important person in the world.
                2 | The common folk love me for my kindness and generosity.
                3 | No one could doubt by looking at my regal bearing that I am a cut above the unwashed masses.
                4 | I take great pains to always look my best and follow the latest fashions.
                5 | I don't like to get my hands dirty, and I won't be caught dead in unsuitable accommodations.
                6 | Despite my noble birth, I do not place myself above other folk. We all have the same blood.
                7 | My favor, once lost, is lost forever.
                8 | If you do me an injury, I will crush you, ruin your name, and salt your fields.
                
                d6 | Ideal
                1 | Respect. Respect is due to me because of my position, but all people regardless of station deserve to be treated with dignity. (Good)
                2 | Responsibility. It is my duty to respect the authority of those above me, just as those below me must respect mine. (Lawful)
                3 | Independence. I must prove that I can handle myself without coddling from my family. (Chaotic)
                4 | Power. If I can attain more power, no one will tell me what to do. (Evil)
                5 | Family. Blood runs thicker than water. (Any)
                6 | Noble Obligation. It is my duty to protect and care for the people beneath me. (Good)
                
                d6 | Bond
                1 | I will face any challenge to win the approval of my family.
                2 | My house's alliance with another noble family must be sustained at all costs.
                3 | Nothing is more important than the other members of my family.
                4 | I am in love with the heir of a family that my family despises.
                5 | My loyalty to my sovereign is unwavering.
                6 | The common folk must see me as a hero of the people.
                
                d6 | Flaw
                1 | I secretly believe that everyone is beneath me.
                2 | I hide a truly scandalous secret that could ruin my family forever.
                3 | I too often hear veiled insults and threats in every word addressed to me, and I'm quick to anger.
                4 | I have an insatiable desire for carnal pleasures.
                5 | In fact, the world does revolve around me.
                6 | By my words and actions, I often bring shame to my family.
            </text>
        </trait>
    </background>
    <background>
        <name>Baldur's Gate Outlander</name>
        <proficiency>Athletics, Survival</proficiency>
        <trait>
            <name>Description</name>
            <text>• Skill Proficiencies: Athletics, Survival
                • Tool Proficiencies: One type of musical instrument
                • Languages: One of your choice
                • Equipment: A staff, a hunting trap, a trophy from an animal you killed, a set of traveler's clothes, and a belt pouch containing 10 gp
                Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 204</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Feature: Wanderer</name>
            <text>You have an excellent memory for maps and geography, and you can always recall the general layout of terrain, settlements, and other features around you. In addition, you can find food and fresh water for yourself and up to five other people each day, provided that the land offers berries, small game, water, and so forth.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Baldur's Gate Feature: Immigrant Experience</name>
            <text>The effects of a Baldur's Gate feature can be used only while the character is in Baldur's Gate—though, at the DM's discretion, they might have applicable effects in situations similar to those in Baldur's Gate.
                Even after your short time in Baldur's Gate, you've learned the city holds more walls and gates than those the Watch and Flaming Fist patrols. You are known within the city's immigrant communities. Should you ever need to learn about a foreign land, people, tradition, or history, you know where to find someone with firsthand experience—likely somewhere in the Outer City.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Outlander Origins</name>
            <text>Foreigners of all kinds come to Baldur's Gate daily, drawn by countless reasons from countless lands. The Outlander Origins table provides ideas for how your character might have come to Baldur's Gate.
                d6 | Origin
                1 | Someone stole something precious from your people. You tracked the thief to the city gates, but finding clues in an urban environment is very different from tracking someone across the wilderness. You don't know where to go from here, but your people need you to succeed.
                2 | You've always been fascinated by the glitter and glamor of city life, so different from the slow pace of life in your homeland. Now you're here, ready to make your mark in the world, but unsure how to begin.
                3 | War, plague, famine, or a marauding monster ravaged your home, forcing you to flee for your life. You don't even know how many of your people survived or where to find them. Alone or accompanied by a handful of equally bereft survivors, you must navigate a new life that you never asked for.
                4 | You were captured by kidnappers and taken far from your home. The Knights of the Unicorn freed you and brought you here, but now you're on your own.
                5 | You were exiled for breaking a trivial-seeming taboo. For this seemingly minor transgression, you lost your friends, family, and homeland in one fell swoop, and were given little choice but to strike out on your own.
                6 | A peddler once brought something astonishing to your homeland—a Gondan clockwork, shimmering cloth of gold, a trained speaking bird, or some other small wonder—and told you that it came from Baldur's Gate. You've come to see the source of such wonders, and perhaps learn to create them.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Specialty</name>
            <text>You've been to strange places and seen things that others cannot begin to fathom. Consider some of the distant lands you have visited, and how they impacted you. You can roll on the following table to determine your occupation during your time in the wild, or choose one that best fits your character.
                d10 | Origin
                1 | Forester
                2 | Trapper
                3 | Homesteader
                4 | Guide
                5 | Exile or outcast
                6 | Bounty hunter
                7 | Pilgrim
                8 | Tribal nomad
                9 | Hunter-gatherer
                10 | Tribal marauder
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
            <text>Often considered rude and uncouth among civilized folk, outlanders have little respect for the niceties of life in the cities. The ties of tribe, clan, family, and the natural world of which they are a part are the most important bonds to most outlanders.
                d8 | Personality Trait
                1 | I'm driven by a wanderlust that led me away from home
                2 | I watch over my friends as if they were a litter of newborn pups.
                3 | I once ran twenty-five miles without stopping to warn to my clan of an approaching orc horde. I'd do it again if I had to.
                4 | I have a lesson for every situation, drawn from observing nature.
                5 | I place no stock in wealthy or well-mannered folk. Money and manners won't save you from a hungry owlbear.
                6 | I'm always picking things up, absently fiddling with them, and sometimes accidentally breaking them.
                7 | I feel far more comfortable around animals than people
                8 | I was, in fact, raised by wolves.
                
                d6 | Ideal
                1 | Change. Life is like the seasons, in constant change, and we must change with it. (Chaotic)
                2 | Greater Good. It is each person's responsibility to make the most happiness for the whole tribe. (Good)
                3 | Honor. If I dishonor myself, I dishonor my whole clan. (Lawful)
                4 | Might. The strongest are meant to rule. (Evil)
                5 | Nature. The natural world is more important than all the constructs of civilization. (Neutral)
                6 | Glory. I must earn glory in battle, for myself and my clan. (Any)
                
                d6 | Bond
                1 | My family, clan, or tribe is the most important thing in my life, even when they are far from me.
                2 | An injury to the unspoiled wilderness of my home is an injury to me.
                3 | I will bring terrible wrath down on the evildoers who destroyed my homeland.
                4 | I am the last of my tribe, and it is up to me to ensure their names enter legend.
                5 | I suffer awful visions of a coming disaster and will do anything to prevent it.
                6 | It is my duty to provide children to sustain my tribe.
                
                d6 | Flaw
                1 | I am too enamored of ale, wine, and other intoxicants.
                2 | There's no room for caution in a life lived to the fullest.
                3 | I remember every insult I've received and nurse a silent resentment toward anyone who's ever wronged me.
                4 | I am slow to trust members of other races, tribes, and societies.
                5 | Violence is my answer to almost any challenge.
                6 | Don't expect me to save those who can't save themselves. It is nature's way that the strong thrive and the weak perish.
            </text>
        </trait>
    </background>
    <background>
        <name>Baldur's Gate Sage</name>
        <proficiency>Arcana, History</proficiency>
        <trait>
            <name>Description</name>
            <text>• Skill Proficiencies: Arcana, History
                • Languages: Two of your choice
                • Equipment: A Ink (1-ounce bottle), a quill, a small knife, a letter from a dead colleague posing a question you have not yet been able to answer, a set of common clothes, and a belt pouch containing 10 gp
                Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 204</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Feature: Researcher</name>
            <text>When you attempt to learn or recall a piece of lore, if you do not know that information, you often know where and from whom you can obtain it. Usually, this information comes from a library, scriptorium, university, or a sage or other learned person or creature, Your DM might rule that the knowledge you seek is secreted away in an almost inaccessible place, or that it simply cannot be found. Unearthing the deepest secrets of the multiverse can require an adventure or even a whole campaign.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Baldur's Gate Feature: Rumor Monger</name>
            <text>The effects of a Baldur's Gate feature can be used only while the character is in Baldur's Gate—though, at the DM's discretion, they might have applicable effects in situations similar to those in Baldur's Gate.
                Via your personal rumor mill and articles published in Baldur's Mouth, you can surmise a great deal about Baldurians' secrets—who's practicing necromancy, who's involved in spying or smuggling, who would purchase or craft dangerous magical wares without batting an eyelash. Whenever a noteworthy crime or mysterious happening occurs in the city, you immediately have a list of 1d4 suspects who, if they aren't involved, have a strong chance of knowing who is.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Specialty</name>
            <text>To determine the nature of your scholarly training, roll a d8 or choose from the options in the table below.
                d8 | Field of Study
                1 | Alchemist
                2 | Astronomer
                3 | Discredited academic
                4 | Librarian
                5 | Professor
                6 | Researcher
                7 | Wizard's apprentice
                8 | Scribe
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
            <text>Sages are defined by their extensive studies, and their characteristics reflect this life of study. Devoted to scholarly pursuits, a sage values knowledge highly—sometimes in its own right, sometimes as a means toward other ideals.
                d8 | Personality Trait
                1 | I use polysyllabic words that convey the impression of great erudition.
                2 | I've read every book in the world's greatest libraries—or I like to boast that I have.
                3 | I'm used to helping out those who aren't as smart as I am, and I patiently explain anything and everything to others.
                4 | There's nothing I like more than a good mystery.
                5 | I'm willing to listen to every side of an argument before I make my own judgment.
                6 | I... speak... slowly... when talking... to idiots,... which... almost... everyone... is... compared... to me.
                7 | I am horribly, horribly awkward in social situations.
                8 | I'm convinced that people are always trying to steal my secrets.
                
                d6 | Ideal
                1 | Knowledge. The path to power and self-improvement is through knowledge. (Neutral)
                2 | Beauty. What is beautiful points us beyond itself toward what is true. (Good)
                3 | Logic. Emotions must not cloud our logical thinking. (Lawful)
                4 | No Limits. Nothing should fetter the infinite possibility inherent in all existence. (Chaotic)
                5 | Power. Knowledge is the path to power and domination. (Evil)
                6 | Self-Improvement. The goal of a life of study is the betterment of oneself. (Any)
                
                d6 | Bond
                1 | It is my duty to protect my students.
                2 | I have an ancient text that holds terrible secrets that must not fall into the wrong hands.
                3 | I work to preserve a library, university, scriptorium, or monastery.
                4 | My life's work is a series of tomes related to a specific field of lore.
                5 | I've been searching my whole life for the answer to a certain question.
                6 | I sold my soul for knowledge. I hope to do great deeds and win it back.
                
                d6 | Flaw
                1 | I am easily distracted by the promise of information.
                2 | Most people scream and run when they see a demon. I stop and take notes on its anatomy.
                3 | Unlocking an ancient mystery is worth the price of a civilization.
                4 | I overlook obvious solutions in favor of complicated ones.
                5 | I speak without really thinking through my words, invariably insulting others.
                6 | I can't keep a secret to save my life, or anyone else's.
            </text>
        </trait>
    </background>
    <background>
        <name>Baldur's Gate Sailor</name>
        <proficiency>Athletics, Perception</proficiency>
        <trait>
            <name>Description</name>
            <text>• Skill Proficiencies: Athletics, Perception
                • Tool Proficiencies: Navigator's tools, vehicles (water)
                • Equipment: A belaying pin (club), silk rope (50 feet), a lucky charm such as a rabbit foot or a small stone with a hole in the center (or you may roll for a random trinket on the Trinkets table in chapter 5), a set of common clothes, and a belt pouch containing 10 gp
                Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 204</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Feature: Ship's Passage</name>
            <text>When you need to, you can secure free passage on a sailing ship for yourself and your adventuring companions. You might sail on the ship you served on, or another ship you have good relations with (perhaps one captained by a former crewmate). Because you're calling in a favor, you can't be certain of a schedule or route that will meet your every need. Your Dungeon Master will determine how long it takes to get where you need to go. In return for your free passage, you and your companions are expected to assist the crew during the voyage.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Baldur's Gate Feature: Smuggler's Sense</name>
            <text>The effects of a Baldur's Gate feature can be used only while the character is in Baldur's Gate—though, at the DM's discretion, they might have applicable effects in situations similar to those in Baldur's Gate.
                You're familiar with the docks of Baldur's Gate, the movement of inspectors and tax collectors, the way cargo and coin flows. As a result, it's easy for you to hustle a load of cargo ashore or see such a cargo onto a cooperative ship without attracting suspicion or taxation. You also know the movements of the Gray Wavers—the Flaming Fist harbor guards—and have a sense of how to operate the city's mechanized cranes.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
            <text>Sailors can be a rough lot, but the responsibilities of life on a ship make them generally reliable as well. Life aboard a ship shapes their outlook and forms their most important attachments.
                d8 | Personality Trait
                1 | My friends know they can rely on me, no matter what.
                2 | I work hard so that I can play hard when the work is done.
                3 | I enjoy sailing into new ports and making new friends over a flagon of ale.
                4 | I stretch the truth for the sake of a good story.
                5 | To me, a tavern brawl is a nice way to get to know a new city.
                6 | I never pass up a friendly wager.
                7 | My language is as foul as an otyugh nest.
                8 | I like a job well done, especially if I can convince someone else to do it.
                
                d6 | Ideal
                1 | Respect. The thing that keeps a ship together is mutual respect between captain and crew. (Good)
                2 | Fairness. We all do the work, so we all share in the rewards. (Lawful)
                3 | Freedom. The sea is freedom—the freedom to go anywhere and do anything. (Chaotic)
                4 | Mastery. I'm a predator, and the other ships on the sea are my prey. (Evil)
                5 | People. I'm committed to my crewmates, not to ideals. (Neutral)
                6 | Aspiration. Someday, I'll own my own ship and chart my own destiny. (Any)
                
                d6 | Bond
                1 | I'm loyal to my captain first, everything else second.
                2 | The ship is most important—crewmates and captains come and go.
                3 | I'll always remember my first ship.
                4 | In a harbor town, I have a paramour whose eyes nearly stole me from the sea.
                5 | I was cheated out of my fair share of the profits, and I want to get my due.
                6 | Ruthless pirates murdered my captain and crewmates, plundered our ship, and left me to die. Vengeance will be mine.
                
                d6 | Flaw
                1 | I follow orders, even if I think they're wrong.
                2 | I'll say anything to avoid having to do extra work.
                3 | Once someone questions my courage, I never back down no matter how dangerous the situation.
                4 | Once I start drinking, it's hard for me to stop.
                5 | I can't help but pocket loose coins and other trinkets I come across.
                6 | My pride will probably lead to my destruction.
            </text>
        </trait>
    </background>
    <background>
        <name>Baldur's Gate Soldier</name>
        <proficiency>Athletics, Intimidation</proficiency>
        <trait>
            <name>Description</name>
            <text>• Skill Proficiencies: Athletics, Intimidation
                • Tool Proficiencies: One type of gaming set, vehicles (land)
                • Equipment: An insignia of rank, a trophy taken from a fallen enemy (a dagger, broken blade, or piece of a banner), a bone dice set or playing card set, a set of common clothes, and a belt pouch containing 10 gp
                Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 204</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Feature: Military Rank</name>
            <text>You have a military rank from your career as a soldier. Soldiers loyal to your former military organization still recognize your authority and influence, and they defer to you if they are of a lower rank. You can invoke your rank to exert influence over other soldiers and requisition simple equipment or horses for temporary use. You can also usually gain access to friendly military encampments and fortresses where your rank is recognized.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Baldur's Gate Feature: City Guard</name>
            <text>The effects of a Baldur's Gate feature can be used only while the character is in Baldur's Gate—though, at the DM's discretion, they might have applicable effects in situations similar to those in Baldur's Gate.
                You may choose to currently serve in either the Flaming Fist or the Watch. If you do, you have responsibilities related to your post. For as long as you perform these responsibilities, you gain benefits. If you stop performing your responsibilities, though, you lose access to the benefits and might suffer further fallout. Should you lose these benefits, you may regain them by having an unpleasant conversation with your commanding officer and fulfilling your responsibilities for a month.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Baldur's Gate Feature: Loyalty Test</name>
            <text>The effects of a Baldur's Gate feature can be used only while the character is in Baldur's Gate—though, at the DM's discretion, they might have applicable effects in situations similar to those in Baldur's Gate.
                You've had enough dealings with crooked soldiers that you can spot the behaviors common to corrupt guards and military officers a mile away. While awareness of such corruption doesn't equate to evidence of it, and your sense certainly isn't foolproof, your instinct proves a useful starting point when determining who might take a bribe, who might turn a blind eye to a crime, or who might have criminal connections. You can also use this sense to get a feeling about who might fulfill their duties strictly by the book.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Specialty</name>
            <text>During your time as a soldier, you had a specific role to play in your unit or army. Roll a d8 or choose from the options in the table below to determine your role:
                d8 | Role
                1 | Officer
                2 | Scout
                3 | Infantry
                4 | Cavalry
                5 | Healer
                6 | Quartermaster
                7 | Standard-bearer
                8 | Support staff (cook, blacksmith, or the like)
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
            <text>The horrors of war combined with the rigid discipline of military service leave their mark on all soldiers, shaping their ideals, creating strong bonds, and often leaving them scarred and vulnerable to fear, shame, and hatred.
                d8 | Personality Trait
                1 | I'm always polite and respectful.
                2 | I'm haunted by memories of war. I can't get the images of violence out of my mind.
                3 | I've lost too many friends, and I'm slow to make new ones.
                4 | I'm full of inspiring and cautionary tales from my military experience relevant to almost every combat situation.
                5 | I can stare down a hell hound without flinching.
                6 | I enjoy being strong and like breaking things.
                7 | I have a crude sense of humor.
                8 | I face problems head-on. A simple, direct solution is the best path to success.
                
                d6 | Ideal
                1 | Greater Good. Our lot is to lay down our lives in defense of others. (Good)
                2 | Responsibility. I do what I must and obey just authority. (Lawful)
                3 | Independence. When people follow orders blindly, they embrace a kind of tyranny. (Chaotic)
                4 | Might. In life as in war, the stronger force wins. (Evil)
                5 | Live and Let Live. Ideals aren't worth killing over or going to war for. (Neutral)
                6 | Nation. My city, nation, or people are all that matter. (Any)
                
                d6 | Bond
                1 | I would still lay down my life for the people I served with.
                2 | Someone saved my life on the battlefield. To this day, I will never leave a friend behind.
                3 | My honor is my life.
                4 | I'll never forget the crushing defeat my company suffered or the enemies who dealt it.
                5 | Those who fight beside me are those worth dying for.
                6 | I fight for those who cannot fight for themselves.
                
                d6 | Flaw
                1 | The monstrous enemy we faced in battle still leaves me quivering with fear.
                2 | I have little respect for anyone who is not a proven warrior.
                3 | I made a terrible mistake in battle that cost many lives—and I would do anything to keep that mistake secret.
                4 | My hatred of my enemies is blinding and unreasoning.
                5 | I obey the law, even if the law causes misery.
                6 | I'd rather eat my armor than admit when I'm wrong.
            </text>
        </trait>
    </background>
    <background>
        <name>Baldur's Gate Urchin</name>
        <proficiency>Sleight Of Hand, Stealth</proficiency>
        <trait>
            <name>Description</name>
            <text>• Skill Proficiencies: Sleight of Hand, Stealth
                • Tool Proficiencies: Disguise kit, Thieves' tools
                • Equipment: A small knife, a map of the city you grew up in, a pet mouse, a token to remember your parents by, a set of common clothes, and a belt pouch containing 10 gp
                Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 204</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Feature: City Secrets</name>
            <text>You know the secret patterns and flow to cities and can find passages through the urban sprawl that others would miss. When you are not in combat, you (and companions you lead) can travel between any two locations in the city twice as fast as your speed would normally allow.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Baldur's Gate Feature: Gateguide Connection</name>
            <text>The effects of a Baldur's Gate feature can be used only while the character is in Baldur's Gate—though, at the DM's discretion, they might have applicable effects in situations similar to those in Baldur's Gate.
                Even though you might not be a member of the Gateguides crew, you've associated with enough of them that you know their torch-based code. From the lighting, placement, and type of torch arranged on or near a structure, you can gather a great deal of information about those who live or do business there, particularly if they deal fairly with strangers, have Guild or government connections, or have either helped or denied the Gateguides in the past.
            </text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
            <text>Urchins are shaped by lives of desperate poverty, for good and for ill. They tend to be driven either by a commitment to the people with whom they shared life on the street or by a burning desire to find a better life—and maybe get some payback on all the rich people who treated them badly.
                d8 | Personality Trait
                1 | I hide scraps of food and trinkets away in my pockets.
                2 | I ask a lot of questions.
                3 | I like to squeeze into small places where no one else can get to me.
                4 | I sleep with my back to a wall or tree, with everything I own wrapped in a bundle in my arms.
                5 | I eat like a pig and have bad manners.
                6 | I think anyone who's nice to me is hiding evil intent.
                7 | I don't like to bathe.
                8 | I bluntly say what others are hinting at or hiding.
                
                d6 | Ideal
                1 | Respect. All people, rich or poor, deserve respect. (Good)
                2 | Community. We have to take care of each other, because no one else is going to do it. (Lawful)
                3 | Change. The low are lifted up, and the high and mighty are brought down. Change is the nature of things. (Chaotic)
                4 | Retribution. The rich need to be shown what life and death are like in the gutters. (Evil)
                5 | People. I help the people who help me—that's what keeps us alive. (Neutral)
                6 | Aspiration. I'm going to prove that I'm worthy of a better life. (Any)
                
                d6 | Bond
                1 | My town or city is my home, and I'll fight to defend it.
                2 | I sponsor an orphanage to keep others from enduring what I was forced to endure.
                3 | I owe my survival to another urchin who taught me to live on the streets.
                4 | I owe a debt I can never repay to the person who took pity on me.
                5 | I escaped my life of poverty by robbing an important person, and I'm wanted for it.
                6 | No one else should have to endure the hardships I've been through.
                
                d6 | Flaw
                1 | If I'm outnumbered, I will run away from a fight.
                2 | Gold seems like a lot of money to me, and I'll do just about anything for more of it.
                3 | I will never fully trust anyone other than myself.
                4 | I'd rather kill someone in their sleep than fight fair.
                5 | It's not stealing if I need it more than someone else.
                6 | People who can't take care of themselves get what they deserve.
            </text>
        </trait>
    </background>
    
    <!-- Monsters -->
    <monster>
        <name>Abyssal Chicken</name>
        <size>T</size>
        <type>fiend (demon)</type>
        <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
        <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>10 (3d4+3)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>6</str>
        <dex>14</dex>
        <con>13</con>
        <int>4</int>
        <wis>9</wis>
        <cha>5</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill></skill>
        <passive>9</passive>
        <languages>understands Abyssal but can't speak</languages>
        <cr>1/4</cr>
        <resist>cold, fire, lightning</resist>
        <immune>poison</immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune>blinded, poisoned</conditionImmune>
        <senses>blindsight 30ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Bad Flier</name>
            <text>The abyssal chicken falls at the end of a turn if it's airborne and the only thing holding it aloft is its flying speed.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>The abyssal chicken makes two attacks: one with its bite and one with its claws.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Bite</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Bite|4|1d4+2</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Claws</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) slashing damage.</text>
            <attack>Claws|4|1d6+2</attack>
        </action>
        <description>Abyssal chickens are carnivorous, temperamental, tasty bottom-feeders native to the Abyss. They beat their leathery wings to scare predators and to help them run faster, and they taste like fatty chicken.
            With your permission, a character who casts the find familiar spell can henceforth choose to conjure an abyssal chicken instead of a raven
            Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 97</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Amrik Vanthampur</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
        <ac>17 (leather armor, charisma modifier)</ac>
        <hp>66 (12d8+12)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>12</str>
        <dex>18</dex>
        <con>12</con>
        <int>14</int>
        <wis>14</wis>
        <cha>15</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill>Acrobatics +6, Athletics +3, Deception +6, Insight +6</skill>
        <passive>12</passive>
        <languages>Common, Infernal</languages>
        <cr>3</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Suave Defense</name>
            <text>While Amrik is wearing light or no armor and wielding no shield, his AC includes his Charisma modifier.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Amrik makes three dagger attacks.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Dagger</name>
            <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 6 (1d4 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Dagger|6|1d4+4</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Smoke Bomb (1/Day)</name>
            <text>Amrik hurls a smoke bomb up to 20 feet away. The bomb explodes on impact, creating a cloud of black smoke that fills a 10-foot-radius sphere. The area within the cloud is heavily obscured. A strong wind disperses the cloud, which otherwise remains until the end of Amrik's next turn.</text>
        </action>
        <description>Second son of Duke Thalamra Vanthampur of Baldur's Gate. Amrik loves to exchange pleasantries over drinks before conducting business. He has trained Laraelra's staff to recognize a variety of innocuous hand gestures that signal them to deliver drinks to the table. If he wants poison added to his clients' drinks, he has a secret sign for that. Hidden behind the bar is a small bottle containing four doses of torpor (see "Poisons" in chapter 8 of the Dungeon Master's Guide), which the kenku bartender can use to spike drinks when Amrik gives the signal.
            Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 30</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Archduke Zariel of Avernus</name>
        <size>L</size>
        <type>fiend (devil)</type>
        <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
        <ac>21 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>580 (40d10+360)</hp>
        <speed>walk 50 ft., fly 150 ft.</speed>
        <str>27</str>
        <dex>24</dex>
        <con>28</con>
        <int>26</int>
        <wis>27</wis>
        <cha>30</cha>
        <save>Int +16, Wis +16, Cha +18</save>
        <skill>Intimidation +18, Perception +16</skill>
        <passive>26</passive>
        <languages>all, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
        <cr>26</cr>
        <resist>cold, fire, radiant; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't silvered</resist>
        <immune>necrotic, poison</immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
        <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Devil's Sight</name>
            <text>Magical darkness doesn't impede Zariel's darkvision.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Weapons</name>
            <text>Zariel's weapon attacks are magical. When she hits with any weapon, the weapon deals an extra 36 (8d8) fire damage (included in the weapon attacks below).</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
            <text>If Zariel fails a saving throw, she can choose to succeed instead.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Resistance</name>
            <text>Zariel has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Regeneration</name>
            <text>Zariel regains 20 hit points at the start of her turn. If she takes radiant damage, this trait doesn't function at the start of her next turn. Zariel dies only if she starts her turn with 0 hit points and doesn't regenerate.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Zariel attacks twice with her longsword or with her javelins. She can substitute Horrid Touch for one of these attacks.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Longsword</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +16 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 17 (2d8 + 8) slashing damage plus 36 (8d8) fire damage, or 19 (2d10 + 8) slashing damage plus 36 (8d8) fire damage if used with two hands.</text>
            <attack>Longsword|16|2d8+8</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Javelin</name>
            <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +16 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. 15 (2d6 + 8) piercing damage plus 36 (8d8) fire damage.</text>
            <attack>Javelin|16|2d6+8</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Horrid Touch (Recharge 5-6)</name>
            <text>Zariel touches one creature within 10 feet of her. The target must succeed on a DC 26 Constitution saving throw or take 44 (8d10) necrotic damage and be poisoned for 1 minute. While poisoned in this way, the target is also blinded and deafened. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Teleport</name>
            <text>Zariel magically teleports, along with any equipment she is wearing and carrying, up to 120 feet to an unoccupied space she can see.</text>
        </action>
        <legendary>
            <text>Archduke can take 2 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Archduke regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
        </legendary>
        <legendary>
            <name>Immolating Gaze (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
            <text>Zariel turns her magical gaze toward one creature she can see within 120 feet of her and commands it to combust. The target must succeed on a DC 26 Wisdom saving throw or take 22 (4d10) fire damage.</text>
        </legendary>
        <legendary>
            <name>Teleport</name>
            <text>Zariel uses her Teleport action.</text>
        </legendary>
        <legendary>
            <name>Lair Actions</name>
            <text>On initiative count 20 (losing initiative ties), Zariel can take a lair action to cause one of the following effects; she can't use the same effect two rounds in a row:</text>
            <text>• Zariel casts major image four times at its lowest level, targeting different areas with the spell. Zariel prefers to create images of intruders' loved ones being burned alive. Zariel doesn't need to concentrate on the spells, which end on initiative count 20 of the next round. Each creature that can see these illusions must succeed on a DC 26 Wisdom saving throw or become frightened of the illusion for 1 minute. A frightened creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
            <text>• Zariel casts her innate fireball spell.</text>
        </legendary>
        <legendary>
            <name>Regional Effects</name>
            <text>The region containing Zariel's lair is warped by her magic, which creates one or more of the following effects:</text>
            <text>• The area within 9 miles of the lair is filled with screaming voices and the stench of burning meat.</text>
            <text>• Once every 60 feet within 1 mile of the lair, 10-foot-high gouts of flame rise from the ground. Any creature or object that touches the flame takes 7 (2d6) fire damage, though it can take this damage no more than once per round.</text>
            <text>• The area within 2 miles, but no closer than 500 feet, of the lair is filled with smoke, which causes the area to be heavily obscured. The smoke can't be cleared away.</text>
            <text>If Zariel dies, these effects fade over the course of 1d10 days.</text>
        </legendary>
        <trait>
            <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
            <text>Zariel's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 26). She can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
            <text>At will: alter self (can become Medium when changing her appearance), detect evil and good, fireball, invisibility (self only), wall of fire</text>
            <text>3/day each: blade barrier, dispel evil and good, finger of death</text>
        </trait>
        <spells>alter self, detect evil and good, fireball, invisibility, wall of fire, blade barrier, dispel evil and good, finger of death</spells>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 243</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Arkhan the Cruel</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (dragonborn)</type>
        <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
        <ac>23 (obsidian flint dragon plate, shield)</ac>
        <hp>221 (26d8+104)</hp>
        <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
        <str>20</str>
        <dex>12</dex>
        <con>18</con>
        <int>10</int>
        <wis>10</wis>
        <cha>18</cha>
        <save>Wis +5, Cha +9</save>
        <skill>Athletics +10, Deception +9, Intimidation +9</skill>
        <passive>10</passive>
        <languages>Common, Draconic</languages>
        <cr>16</cr>
        <resist>fire, poison; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune>frightened</conditionImmune>
        <senses>darkvision 60 ft. (can see invisible creatures out to the same range)</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Aura of Hate</name>
            <text>While Arkhan isn't incapacitated, he and all fiends and undead within 30 feet of him deal 4 extra damage whenever they hit with a melee weapon attack (already factored into Arkhan's attacks). This extra damage is of the same type as the weapon's damage type.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Hand of Vecna</name>
            <text>The Hand of Vecna has 8 charges and regains 1d4 + 4 expended charges daily at dawn. Arkhan can cast the following spells from the hand by expending the specified number of charges (spell save DC 18): finger of death (5 charges), sleep (1 charge), slow (2 charges), and teleport (3 charges).</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Special Equipment</name>
            <text>Arkhan wields Fane-Eater and wears a suit of Obsidian Flint Dragon Plate. The armor gives Arkhan advantage on ability checks and saving throws made to avoid or end the grappled condition on him.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Arkhan makes three weapon attacks.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Fane-Eater (Battleaxe)</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 16 (1d8 + 12) slashing damage, or 17 (1d10 + 12) slashing damage when used with two hands, plus 9 (2d8) cold damage. If the target is a creature and Arkhan rolls a 20 on the attack roll, the creature takes an extra 9 (2d8) necrotic damage, and Arkhan regains an amount of hit points equal to the necrotic damage dealt.</text>
            <attack>Fane-Eater (Battleaxe)|13|1d8+12</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Javelin</name>
            <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 30/120 ft., one target. 8 (1d6 + 5) piercing damage, plus 4 piercing damage and 9 (2d8) cold damage if the javelin was used to make a melee</text>
            <attack>Javelin|10|1d6+5</attack>
        </action>
        <trait>
            <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
            <text>Arkhan's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 17). He can cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
            <text>3/day each: animate dead, branding smite (at 4th level), revivify</text>
            <text>1/day each: geas, raise dead</text>
        </trait>
        <spells>animate dead, branding smite, revivify, geas, raise dead</spells>
        <description>Arkhan the Cruel is an evil dragonborn champion of Tiamat. Arkhan believes he can use the Hand of Vecna to unlock the means of freeing Tiamat from her prison in the Nine Hells, but only if the hand doesn't kill him first. The hand is slowly corrupting Arkhan's flesh and decomposing his body on one side.
            In battle, Arkhan uses branding smite to channel the radiant power of Tiamat into his weapon attacks. If a fight turns against him, he uses the teleport power of the Hand of Vecna to return to his tower with as many allies as possible. Should one or more of his comrades fall in battle, Arkhan uses revivify and raise dead spells to bring them back to life as soon as possible.
            If Arkhan finds himself overwhelmed with opposition, he orders the abishai to attack. Arkhan can also use a bonus action to call forth Asojano, a chimera lairing in the depths of the colossal dragon skull.
            Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 111</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Black Gauntlet of Bane</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (lawful evil)</type>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <ac>16 (chain mail)</ac>
        <cr>6</cr>
        <str>18</str><dex>11</dex><con>18</con><wis>15</wis><int>12</int><cha>18</cha>
        <passive>15</passive>
        <hp>51 (6d8+24)</hp>
        <conditionImmune>Frightened</conditionImmune>
        <languages>Common</languages>
        <save>Wis +5</save>
        <skill>Intimidation +7,Perception +5</skill>
        <trait>
            <name>Source</name>
            <text>Baldur’s Gate Descent Into Avernus, p. 232</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Aura of Terror</name>
            <text>When a hostile creature within 5 feet of the black gauntlet makes an attack roll or a saving throw, it has disadvantage on the roll. Creatures that are immune to the frightened condition are immune to this trait.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Spellcasting</name>
            <text>The black gauntlet is a 5th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 15, +7 to hit with spell attacks). It has the following cleric spells prepared:
                
                Cantrips (at will): guidance, sacred flame, thaumaturgy
                1st level (4 slots): bane, bless, cure wounds, guiding bolt (see Actions below)
                2nd level (3 slots): blindness/deafness, hold person, silence
                3rd level (2 slots): sending, spirit guardians</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Tactical Disciple</name>
            <text>The black gauntlet has advantage on all ability checks and saving throws made during combat.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>The black gauntlet makes two attacks with its mace.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Mace</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit 7 (1d6+4) bludgeoning damage plus 13 (3d8) necrotic damage.</text>
            <attack>Mace|7|1d6+4+3d8</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Guiding Bolt (1st-Level Spell; Requires a Spell Slot)</name>
            <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +7 to hit, range 120 ft., one creature. Hit: 14 (4d6) radiant damage, and the next attack roll made against the target before the end of the black gauntlet’s next turn has advantage. If the black gauntlet casts this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the damage increases by 1d6 for each level above 1st.</text>
        </action>
        <spells>guidance,sacred flame,thaumaturgy,bane,bless,cure wounds,guiding bolt,blindness/deafness,hold person,silence,sending,spirit guardians</spells>
        <slots>4,3,2</slots>
        <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Crokek’toeck (chaotic evil)</name>
        <size>G</size>
        <type>fiend</type>
        <speed>60 ft, swim 60 ft.</speed>
        <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
        <cr>14</cr>
        <str>28</str><dex>10</dex><con>24</con><wis>10</wis><int>6</int><cha>13</cha>
        <passive>10</passive>
        <hp>297 (17d20+119)</hp>
        <resist>cold, fire, lightning, bludgeoning, piercing and slashing that is nonmagical</resist>
        <immune>poison</immune>
        <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
        <senses>darkvision 120 ft</senses>
        <languages>understands Abyssal but can’t speak</languages>
        <save>Con +12, Wis +5</save>
        <trait>
            <name>Source</name>
            <text>Baldur's Gate Descent Into Avernus, p. 230</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Amphibious</name>
            <text>Crokek'toeck can breathe air and water.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Resistance</name>
            <text>Crokek'toeck has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Secure Memory</name>
            <text>Crokek'toeck is immune to the waters of the River Styx as well as any effect that would steal or modify its memories or detect or read its thoughts.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Standing Leap</name>
            <text>Crokek'toeck's long jump is up to 60 feet and its high jump is up to 30 feet, with or without a running start.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Bite</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. Hit 44 (10d6 + 9) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Bite|14|10d6+9</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Disgorge Allies (Recharge 6)</name>
            <text>Crokek'toeck opens its mouth and disgorges 1d4 barlguras, 3d6 gnolls led by 1 gnoll fang of Yeenoghu, 6d6 drenches, or 1d3 vrocks (see the Monster Manual for these creatures' stat blocks). Each creature it disgorges appears in an unoccupied space within 30 feet of Crokek'toeck's mouth, or the closest next unoccupied space.</text>
        </action>
        <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Death’s Head of Bhaal</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human, chaotic evil)</type>
        <speed>50 ft,</speed>
        <ac>15</ac>
        <cr>5</cr>
        <str>20</str><dex>20</dex><con>20</con><wis>13</wis><int>14</int><cha>16</cha>
        <passive>14</passive>
        <hp>76 (8d8+40)</hp>
        <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
        <languages>common</languages>
        <skill>Intimidation +6,Perception +6,Stealth +11</skill>
        <trait>
            <name>Source</name>
            <text>Baldur’s Gate Descent Into Avernus, p. 233</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Aura of Murder</name>
            <text>As long as the death's head is not incapacitated, hostile creatures within 5 feet of it gain vulnerability to piercing damage unless they have resistance or immunity to such damage.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Resistance</name>
            <text>The death's head has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>The death's head uses Stunning Gaze and makes two dagger attacks.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Dagger</name>
            <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft. one target. Hit 7 (1d4+5) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Dagger|7|1d4+5</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Stunning Gaze</name>
            <text>The death's head targets one creature it can see within 30 feet of it. The target must succeed on a DC 14 Wisdom saving throw or be stunned until the end of its next turn.</text>
        </action>
        <reaction>
            <name>Unstoppable (3/Day)</name>
            <text>The death's head reduces the damage it takes from an attack to 0.</text>
        </reaction>
        <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Demon Grinder</name>
        <size>G</size>
        <type>infernal vehicle</type>
        <speed>100</speed>
        <ac>19</ac>
        <str>18</str><dex>10</dex><con>18</con><wis>0</wis><int>0</int><cha>0</cha>
        <hp>200</hp>
        <immune>fire, poison, psychic</immune>
        <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, paralysed, petrified, poisoned, stunned, unconcious</conditionImmune>
        <trait>
            <text>Source: Baldur’s Gate Descent into Avernus, p. 218</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Crushing Wheels</name>
            <text>The Demon Grinder can move through the space ofany Large or smaller creature. When it does, the creature must succeed on a DC 11 Dexterity saving throw or take 22 (4d10) bludgeoning damage and be knocked prone. If the creature was already prone, it takes an extra 22 (4dl0) bludgeoning damage. This trait can't be used against a particular creature more than once each turn.</text>
            <attack>Crushing Wheels|0|4d10</attack>
        </action>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Weapon</name>
            <text>The Demon Grinder’s weapon attacks are magical.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Prone Deficiency</name>
            <text>If the Demon Grinder rolls over and falls prone, it can't right itself and is incapacitated until flipped upright.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Helm (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Three-Quarters Cover)</name>
            <text>Drive and steer the Demon Grinder.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Chomper (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half Cover)</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 25 (6d6+4) piercing damage. A target reduced to 0 hit points by this damage is ground to bits and spit out through pipes on both sides of the Demon Grinder. Any nonmagical items the target was holding or carrying are destroyed as well.</text>
            <attack>Chomper|9|6d6+4</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Wrecking Ball (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half-Cover)</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack:+9 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. Hit: 40 (8d8+4) bludgeoning damage. Double the damage if the target is an object or a structure.</text>
            <attack>Wrecking Ball|9|8d8+4</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>2 Harpoon Flingers (Each Station Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half Cover)</name>
            <text>Ammunition: 10 harpoons per station. Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. Hit: 9 (2d8) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Harpoon Flinger|5|2d8</attack>
        </action>
        <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Devil’s Ride</name>
        <size>L</size>
        <type>infernal vehicle</type>
        <speed>120</speed>
        <ac>23 (19 while motionless)</ac>
        <str>14</str><dex>18</dex><con>12</con><wis>0</wis><int>0</int><cha>0</cha>
        <hp>30</hp>
        <immune>fire, poison, psychic</immune>
        <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, paralysed, petrified, poisoned, stunned, unconcious</conditionImmune>
        <trait>
            <text>Source: Baldur’s Gate Descent into Avernus, p. 218</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Jump</name>
            <text>If the Devil's Ride moves at least 30 feet in a straight line, it can clear a distance of up to 60 feet when jumping over a chasm, ravine, or other gap. Each foot it clears on the jump costs a foot of movement.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Prone Deficiency</name>
            <text>If the Devil's Ride falls prone, it can't right itself and is incapacitated until pulled upright.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Stunt</name>
            <text>On its turn, the driver ofthe Devil's Ride can expend 10 feet of movement to perform one free infernal vehicle stunt, such as a wheelie or a burnout. Before the stunt can be performed, the Devil's Ride must move at least l0 feet in a straight line. If the driver succeeds on DC 10 Dexterity check using the bike's Dexterity, the stunt is successful. Otherwise, the driver is unable to perform the stunt and can't attempt another stunt until the start of its next turn. If the check fails by 5 or more, the Devil's Ride and all creatures riding it immediately fall prone as the bike wipes out and comes to a dead stop.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Helm (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half Cover)</name>
            <text>Drive and steer the Devil’s Ride.</text>
        </trait>
        <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Fiendish Flesh Golem</name>
        <size>L</size>
        <type>construct (unaligned)</type>
        <speed>30 ft., fly 30 ft. (Hover)</speed>
        <ac>12 (natural armor)</ac>
        <cr>8</cr>
        <str>20</str><dex>9</dex><con>20</con><wis>10</wis><int>7</int><cha>5</cha>
        <passive>10</passive>
        <hp>210 (20d10+100)</hp>
        <resist>Cold, fire</resist>
        <immune>lightning, poison, bludgeoning, piercing, sand slashing from non-magical attacks that aren't adamantine or silvered</immune>
        <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralysed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
        <senses>Darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
        <languages>Understands the languages of its creator but cant speak.</languages>
        <trait>
            <name>Source</name>
            <text>Baldur's Gate Descent Into Avernus, p. 236.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Berserk</name>
            <text>Whenever the golem starts its turn with 100 hit points or fewer, roll a d6. On a 6, the golem goes berserk. On each of its turns while berserk, the golem attacks the nearest creature it can see. If no creature is near enough to move to and attack, the golem attacks an object, with preference for an object smaller than itself. Once the golem goes berserk, it continues to do so until it is destroyed or regains all its hit points. If the golem's creator is within 60 feet of the berserk golem, the creator can try to calm it by speaking firmly and persuasively. The golem must be able to hear its creator, who must take an action to make a DC 15 Charisma (Persuasion) check. If the check succeeds, the golem ceases being berserk. If it takes damage while still at 100 hit points or fewer, the golem might go berserk again.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Immutable Form</name>
            <text>The golem is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Lightning Absorption</name>
            <text>Whenever the golem is subjected to lightning damage, it takes no damage and instead gains a number of hit points equal to the lightning damage dealt.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Resistance</name>
            <text>The golem has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Weapons</name>
            <text>The golem's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>The golem makes two slam attacks. </text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Slam</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit 16 (2d10+5) bludgeoning damage.</text>
            <attack>Slam|8|2d10+5</attack>
        </action>
        <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Fist of Bane</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (lawful evil)</type>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <ac>18 (chain mail, shield)</ac>
        <cr>1/2</cr>
        <str>16</str><dex>11</dex><con>13</con><wis>12</wis><int>10</int><cha>11</cha>
        <passive>11</passive>
        <hp>22 (4d8+4)</hp>
        <conditionImmune>Frightened</conditionImmune>
        <languages>common</languages>
        <trait>
            <name>Source</name>
            <text>Baldur’s Gate Descent Into Avernus, p. 232</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Tactical Discipline</name>
            <text>The fist of Bane has advantage on all ability checks and saving throws made during combat.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Mace</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit 6 (1d6+3) bludgeoning damage.</text>
            <attack>Mace|5|1d6+3</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Longbow</name>
            <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, range 150/600 ft., one target. Hit 4 (1d8) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Longbow|2|1d8</attack>
        </action>
        <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Flying Dagger</name>
        <size>T</size>
        <type>construct</type>
        <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
        <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>7 (3d4)</hp>
        <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 50 ft.</speed>
        <str>12</str>
        <dex>15</dex>
        <con>11</con>
        <int>1</int>
        <wis>5</wis>
        <cha>1</cha>
        <save>Dex +4</save>
        <skill></skill>
        <passive>7</passive>
        <languages></languages>
        <cr>1/4</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
        <senses>blindsight 60 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Antimagic Susceptibility</name>
            <text>The dagger is incapacitated while in the area of an antimagic field. If targeted by dispel magic, the dagger must succeed on a Constitution saving throw against the caster's spell save DC or fall unconscious for 1 minute.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>False Appearance</name>
            <text>While the dagger remains motionless and isn't flying, it is indistinguishable from a normal dagger.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Longdagger</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d8 + 1) slashing damage.</text>
            <attack>Longdagger|3|1d8+1</attack>
        </action>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 30</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Hellwasp</name>
        <size>L</size>
        <type>fiend (lawful evil)</type>
        <speed>10 ft., fly 60 ft. (Hover)</speed>
        <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
        <cr>5</cr>
        <str>18</str><dex>15</dex><con>12</con><wis>10</wis><int>10</int><cha>7</cha>
        <passive>10</passive>
        <hp>52 (8d10+8)</hp>
        <vulnerable>cold</vulnerable>
        <immune>fire</immune>
        <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
        <languages>infernal, telepathy 300 ft. (with other hellwasps only)</languages>
        <save>Dex +5, Wis +3</save>
        <trait>
            <name>Source</name>
            <text>Baldur's Gate Descent Into Avernus, p. 236.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Weapons</name>
            <text>The hellwasp's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>The hellwasp makes two attacks: one with its sting and one with its sword talons.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Sting</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. Hit:8 (1d8 + 4) piercing damage plus 7 (2d6) fire damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned for 1 minute. While poisoned in this way, the target is also paralyzed. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end ofeach of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
            <attack>Sting|7|1d8+4+2d6</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Sword Talons</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit 11 (2d6+4) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Sword Talons|7|2d6+4</attack>
        </action>
        <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Hollyphant</name>
        <size>S</size>
        <type>celestial</type>
        <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
        <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>36 (8d6+8)</hp>
        <speed>walk 20 ft., fly 120 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>11</dex>
        <con>12</con>
        <int>16</int>
        <wis>19</wis>
        <cha>16</cha>
        <save>Dex +3, Con +4, Cha +6</save>
        <skill></skill>
        <passive>14</passive>
        <languages>Celestial, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
        <cr>5</cr>
        <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
        <immune>poison</immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Aura of Invulnerability</name>
            <text>An invisible aura forms a 10-foot-radius sphere around the hollyphant for as long as it lives. Any spell of 5th level or lower cast from outside the barrier can't affect creatures or objects within it, even if the spell is cast using a higher level spell slot. Such a spell can target creatures and objects within the barrier, but the spell has no effect on them. Similarly, the area within the barrier is excluded from the areas affected by such spells. The hollyphant can use an action to suppress this trait until its concentration ends (as if concentrating on a spell).</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Weapons</name>
            <text>The hollyphant's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Tusks</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Tusks|3|1d6</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Trumpet (3/Day)</name>
            <text>The hollyphant blows air through its trunk, creating a trumpet sound that can be heard out to a range of 600 feet. The trumpet also creates a 30-foot cone of energy that has one of the following effects, chosen by the hollyphant:</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Trumpet of Blasting</name>
            <text>Each creature in the cone must make a DC 14 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 17 (5d6) thunder damage and is deafened for 1 minute. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage and isn't deafened. Nonmagical objects in the cone that aren't being held or worn take 35 (10d6) thunder damage.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Trumpet of Sparkles</name>
            <text>Creatures in the cone must make a DC 14 Constitution saving throw, taking 22 (4d8 + 4) radiant damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. Evil creatures have disadvantage on the saving throw. Good creatures in the cone take no damage.</text>
        </action>
        <trait>
            <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
            <text>The hollyphant's innate spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 15). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
            <text>At will: light</text>
            <text>2/day each: bless, cure wounds, protection from evil and good</text>
            <text>1/day each: banishment, heal, raise dead, shapechange (into a golden-furred mammoth with feathered wings and a flying speed of 120 ft.), teleport (with no chance of error)</text>
        </trait>
        <spells>light, bless, cure wounds, protection from evil and good, banishment, heal, raise dead, shapechange, teleport</spells>
        <description>Hollyphants are gentle, stalwart creatures native to the Upper Planes. Good-aligned deities and angels use them as messengers and helpers. Hollyphants treasure friendship and honesty.
            A hollyphant looks like a miniature elephant with luminous gold fur and small, rapidly fluttering wings that not only hold it aloft but also propel it at great speed. Although kind, a hollyphant won't bear witness to an evil act without punishing the malefactor. Its pearlescent tusks are far from formidable, but it can unleash trumpet blasts from its trunk that can deafen creatures or engulf evildoers in radiant sparkles of positive energy. A hollyphant is also blessed with powerful innate magic to help it combat evil and protect its friends.
            Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 237</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Iron Consul</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (lawful evil)</type>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <ac>16 (chain mail)</ac>
        <cr>2</cr>
        <str>17</str><dex>11</dex><con>16</con><wis>15</wis><int>12</int><cha>16</cha>
        <passive>14</passive>
        <hp>45 (6d8+18)</hp>
        <conditionImmune>Frightened</conditionImmune>
        <languages>Common</languages>
        <save>Wis +4</save>
        <skill>Intimidation +5,Perception +5</skill>
        <trait>
            <name>Source</name>
            <text>Baldur’s Gate Descent Into Avernus, p. 232</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Tactical Discipline</name>
            <text>The iron consul has advantage on all ability checks and saving throws made during combat.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>The iron consul makes one attack with its spear and can use its Voice of Command ability.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Spear</name>
            <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., or range 20/60 ft., one target. Hit 6 (1d6+3) piercing damage, or 7 (1d8+3) piercing damage when used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
            <attack>Spear|5|1d6+3</attack>
            <attack>Spear|7|1d8+3</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Voice of Command</name>
            <text>The iron consul selects up to two allies within 90 feet of it that can hear its commands. Each ally can immediately use its reaction to make one melee attack.</text>
        </action>
        <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Master of Souls</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (neutral evil)</type>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <ac>12</ac>
        <cr>4</cr>
        <str>10</str><dex>14</dex><con>17</con><wis>14</wis><int>19</int><cha>13</cha>
        <passive>12</passive>
        <hp>45 (6d8+18)</hp>
        <languages>abyssal, common, infernal</languages>
        <save>Wis +4</save>
        <skill>Arcana +6,Religion +6</skill>
        <trait>
            <name>Source</name>
            <text>Baldur’s Gate Descent Into Avernus, p. 234</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Grave Magic</name>
            <text>When the master of souls cast a spell that deals damage, it can change the spell's damage type to necrotic.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Spellcasting</name>
            <text>The master of souls is a 5th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks). It has the following wizard spells prepared:
                
                Cantrips (at will): chill touch (see "Actions" below), mage hand, message, prestidigitation
                1st level (4 slots): burning hands, detect magic, ray of sickness (see "Actions" below), shield
                2nd level (3 slots): darkness, misty step, scorching ray (see "Actions" below)
                3rd level (2 slots): animate dead, fireball</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>The master of souls attacks twice with its flail.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Silver Skull Flail</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 4 (1d8) bludgeoning damage plus 14 (4d6) necrotic damage, and the target has disadvantage on all saving throws until the end of the master of souls' next turn.</text>
            <attack>Skull Flail|2|1d8+4d6</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Chill Touch (Cantrip)</name>
            <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +6 to hit, range 120 ft., one creature. Hit: 13 (2d8) necrotic damage, and the target can't regain hit points until the start of the master of souls' next turn. If the target is undead, it has disadvantage on attack rolls against the master of souls for the same duration.</text>
            <attack>Chill Touch|6|2d8</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Ray of Sickness (1st-level Spell; Requires a Spell Slot)</name>
            <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +6 to hit, range 60 ft., one creature. Hit: 9 (2d8) poison damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 14 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned until the end ofthe master of souls' next turn. Ifthe master ofsouls casts this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the damage increases by 1d8 for each slot level above 1st.</text>
            <attack>Ray of Sickness|6|2d8</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Scorching Ray (2nd-level Spell; Requires a Spell Slot)</name>
            <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +6 to hit, range 120 ft., one target per ray (3 rays if a 2nd-level spell slot is used, 4 rays if a 3rd-level spell slot is used). Hit: 7 (2d6) fire damage per ray.</text>
            <attack>Scorching Ray|6|2d6</attack>
        </action>
        <spells>chill touch,mage hand,message,prestidigitation,burning hands,detect magic,ray of sickness,shield,darkness,misty step,scorching ray,animate dead,fireball</spells>
        <slots>4,3,2</slots>
        <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Necromite of Myrkul</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (neutral evil)</type>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <ac>11</ac>
        <cr>1/2</cr>
        <str>10</str><dex>13</dex><con>15</con><wis>11</wis><int>16</int><cha>10</cha>
        <passive>10</passive>
        <hp>13 (2d8+4)</hp>
        <languages>abyssal, common, infernal</languages>
        <skill>Arcana +5,Religion +5</skill>
        <trait>
            <name>Source</name>
            <text>Baldur’s Gate Descent Into Avernus, p. 234</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Skull Flail</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit 4 (1d8) bludgeoning damage.</text>
            <attack>Skull Flail|2|1d8</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Claws of the Grave</name>
            <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit 8 (2d4+3) necrotic damage.</text>
            <attack>Claws|5|2d4+3</attack>
        </action>
        <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Necrotic Centipede</name>
        <size>H</size>
        <type>monstrosity</type>
        <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
        <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>195 (17d12+85)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft., burrow 20 ft.</speed>
        <str>24</str>
        <dex>13</dex>
        <con>21</con>
        <int>4</int>
        <wis>10</wis>
        <cha>5</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill></skill>
        <passive>10</passive>
        <languages></languages>
        <cr>11</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune>cold, fire</immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses>darkvision 60 ft., tremorsense 60 ft.</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Heated Body</name>
            <text>A creature that touches the centipede or hits it with a melee attack while within 5 feet of it takes 10 (3d6) fire damage.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Bite</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 40 (6d10 + 7) piercing damage plus 10 (3d6) fire damage. If the target is a creature, it is grappled (escape DC 17). Until this grapple ends, the target is restrained, and the centipede can't bite another target.</text>
            <attack>Bite|11|6d10+7</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Swallow</name>
            <text>The centipede makes one bite attack against a Medium or smaller creature it is grappling. If the attack hits, that creature takes the bite's damage and is swallowed, and the grapple ends. While swallowed, the creature is blinded and restrained, it has total cover against attacks and other effects outside the centipede, and it takes 21 (6d6) acid damage at the start of each of the centipede's turns.</text>
            <text>If the centipede takes 30 damage or more on a single turn from a creature inside it, the centipede must succeed on a DC 15 Constitution saving throw at the end of that turn or regurgitate all swallowed creatures, which fall prone in a space within 10 feet oft he centipede. If the centipede dies, a swallowed creature is no longer restrained by it and can escape from the corpse using 15 feet of movement, exiting prone.</text>
        </action>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 119</description>
        <environment>arctic</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Night Blade</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (chaotic evil)</type>
        <speed>40 ft.</speed>
        <ac>12</ac>
        <cr>1/4</cr>
        <str>11</str><dex>15</dex><con>12</con><wis>11</wis><int>10</int><cha>14</cha>
        <hp>11 (2d8+2)</hp>
        <passive>10</passive>
        <languages>Common</languages>
        <skill>Intimidation +4,Stealth +6</skill>
        <trait>
            <name>Source</name>
            <text>Baldur’s Gate Descent Into Avernus, p. 233</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Aura of Murder</name>
            <text>As long as the night blade is not incapacitated, hostile creatures within 5 feet of it gain vulnerability to piercing damage unless they have resistance or immunity to such damage.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Dagger</name>
            <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., or range 20/60 ft., one target. Hit 4 (1d4+2) piercing damage,</text>
            <attack>Dagger|4|1d4+2</attack>
        </action>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Reaper of Bhaal</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human, chaotic evil)</type>
        <speed>40 ft.</speed>
        <ac>12</ac>
        <cr>2</cr>
        <str>11</str><dex>20</dex><con>13</con><wis>12</wis><int>15</int><cha>16</cha>
        <passive>13</passive>
        <hp>11 (2d8+2)</hp>
        <senses>Darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
        <languages>Common</languages>
        <skill>Intimidation +5,Perception +3,Persuasion +5,Stealth +9</skill>
        <trait>
            <name>Source</name>
            <text>Baldur’s Gate Descent Into Avernus, p. 233</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Aura of Murder</name>
            <text>As long as the reaper is not incapacitated, hostile creatures within 5 feet of it gains vulnerability to piercing damage unless they have resistance or immunity to such damage.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
            <text>The reaper’s innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 13). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:
                
                1/day each: charm person, disguise self, sanctuary</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>The reaper makes two dagger attacks and uses Shroud Self.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Dagger</name>
            <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., or range 20/60 ft., one target. Hit 7 (1d4+5) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Dagger|7|1d4+5</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Shroud Self</name>
            <text>The reaper magically turns invisible until the start of its next turn. This invisibility ends if the reaper makes an attack roll, makes a damage roll, or casts a spell.</text>
        </action>
        <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Scavenger</name>
        <size>H</size>
        <type>infernal vehicle</type>
        <speed>100</speed>
        <ac>20</ac>
        <str>20</str><dex>12</dex><con>20</con><wis>0</wis><int>0</int><cha>0</cha>
        <hp>150</hp>
        <immune>fire, poison, psychic</immune>
        <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, paralysed, petrified, poisoned, stunned, unconcious</conditionImmune>
        <trait>
            <text>Source: Baldur’s Gate Descent into Avernus, p. 219</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Crushing Wheels</name>
            <text>The Scavenger can move through the space of any Large or smaller creature. When it does, the creature must succeed on a DC 12 Dexterity saving throw or take 16 (3d10) bludgeoning damage and be knocked prone. If the creature was already prone, it takes an extra 16 (3d10) bludgeoning damage. This trait can't be used against a particular creature more than once each turn.</text>
            <attack>Crushing Wheels|0|3d10</attack>
        </action>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Weapons</name>
            <text>The Scavenger’s weapon attacks are magical.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Prone Deficiency</name>
            <text>If the Scavenger rolls over and falls prone, it can't right itself and is incapacitated until flipped upright.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Helm (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Three-Quarter Cover)</name>
            <text>Drive and steer the Scavenger.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Grappling Claw (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half Cover)</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. Hit: The tar- get is grappled (escape DC 12). If the target is a creature, it is restrained until the grapple ends.
                The grappling claw can grapple only one target at a time, and the claw's operator can use a bonus action to make the claw release whatever it's holding.</text>
        </action>
        <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Skull Lasher of Myrkul</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (neutral evil)</type>
        <speed>30 ft.</speed>
        <ac>12</ac>
        <cr>1</cr>
        <str>10</str><dex>14</dex><con>15</con><wis>13</wis><int>16</int><cha>10</cha>
        <passive>11</passive>
        <hp>32 (5d8+10)</hp>
        <languages>Abyssal, common, infernal</languages>
        <save>Wis +3</save>
        <skill>Arcana +5,Religion +5</skill>
        <trait>
            <name>Source</name>
            <text>Baldur’s Gate Descent Into Avernus, p. 234</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Spellcasting</name>
            <text> The skull lasher is a 3rd-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). It has the following wizard spells prepared:
                
                Cantrips (at will): mage hand, message, prestidigitation
                1st level (4 slots): detect magic, protection from evil and good,
                ray of sickness (see "Actions" below), shield
                2nd level (2 slots): darkness, misty step</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>The skull lasher makes two attacks with its flail.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Iron Skull Flail</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. Hit: 4 (1d8) bludgeoning damage plus 7 (2d6) necrotic damage, and the target has disadvantage on all saving throws until the end of the skull lasher's next turn.</text>
            <attack>Skull Flail|2|1d8+2d6</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Ray of Sickness (1st-level spell; Requires a Spell Slot)</name>
            <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +5 to hit, range 60 ft., one creature. Hit: 9 (2d8) poison damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 13 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned until the end of the skull lasher's next turn. If the skull lasher casts this spell using a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the damage increases by 1d8 for each slot level above 1st.</text>
            <attack>Ray of Sickness|5|2d8</attack>
        </action>
        <spells>mage hand,message,prestidigitation,detect magic,protection from evil and good,ray of sickness,darkness,misty steps</spells>
        <slots>4,2</slots>
        <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Smiler the Defiler</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>fey (elf)</type>
        <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
        <ac>18 (leather armor +2)</ac>
        <hp>165 (22d8+66)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>14</str>
        <dex>20</dex>
        <con>16</con>
        <int>18</int>
        <wis>11</wis>
        <cha>18</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill>Deception +7, Persuasion +7</skill>
        <passive>10</passive>
        <languages>Common, Elvish, Sylvan</languages>
        <cr>7</cr>
        <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Fey Step (Recharge 4-6)</name>
            <text>As a bonus action, Smiler can teleport up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space that he can see or to the empty seat of his infernal war machine.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Resistance</name>
            <text>Smiler has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Equipment</name>
            <text>Smiler wears +2 leather armor. He carries seven soul coins in a bag and a +1 shortsword</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Smiler makes two weapon attacks. He can cast a spell in place of one of these attacks.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>+1 Shortsword</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (1d6 + 6) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>+1 Shortsword|9|1d6+6</attack>
        </action>
        <trait>
            <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
            <text>Smiler's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 15). He can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
            <text>At will: charm person, Tasha's hideous laughter</text>
            <text>3/day each: confusion, enthrall, suggestion</text>
            <text>1/day each: hallucinatory terrain, Otto's irresistible dance</text>
        </trait>
        <spells>charm person, Tasha's hideous laughter, confusion, enthrall, suggestion, hallucinatory terrain, Otto's irresistible dance</spells>
        <description>Smiler has an unnerving smile—hence his name.
            A more apt name for this eladrin would be Smiler the Beguiler, as he's constantly trying to intoxicate others with his relentless optimism and shocking recklessness. Smiler thinks he can accomplish anything with a positive attitude and some death-defying stunt. Although he admits others might end up getting killed by his actions, he believes he can bend the multiverse to his whims if he tries hard enough. He's really quite insane.
            One of Smiler's favorite antics is to use a hallucinatory terrain spell to create a little bit of the Feywild in Avernus: a beautiful woodland glade in which to lose himself for a few hours while he meditates and plots.
            This eladrin adventurer from the Feywild became stranded in Avernus after his companions abandoned him. He has spent the past seventy years roaming Avernus, making deals with fiends to survive. Smiler eventually sold his soul to a pit fiend, who gave him the means to topple a nycaloth warlord named Yarrasto. Smiler took control of the nycaloth's warband and their infernal war machines. Smiler's gang came to be known as Smiler's Defilers, and their ferocity terrified the other warlords of Avernus for a while.
            Three of Smiler's rivals—Bitter Breath, Feonor, and Princeps Kovik—joined forces to wipe out Smiler's Defilers. Smiler escaped and tears around Avernus on a Devil's Ride, looking for adventurers willing to help him get revenge on the warlords who ganged up on him. Mad Maggie remains his only ally, though he refuses to join her gang.
            Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 133</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Sylvira Savikas</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (tiefling)</type>
        <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
        <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
        <hp>99 (18d8+18)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>14</dex>
        <con>12</con>
        <int>20</int>
        <wis>15</wis>
        <cha>16</cha>
        <save>Int +9, Wis +6</save>
        <skill>Arcana +13, History +13, Investigation +2</skill>
        <passive>12</passive>
        <languages>any six languages</languages>
        <cr>12</cr>
        <resist>damage from spells; nonmagical bludgeoning, piercing, slashing (from stoneskin)</resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Resistance</name>
            <text>Sylvira has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Dagger</name>
            <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Dagger|6|1d4+2</attack>
        </action>
        <trait>
            <name>Spellcasting</name>
            <text>Sylvira is an 18th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks). Sylvira can cast disguise self and invisibility at will and has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
            <text>At will: disguise self, invisibility</text>
            <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp</text>
            <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, identify, mage armor*, magic missile</text>
            <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step</text>
            <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fly, lightning bolt</text>
            <text>• 4th level (3 slots): banishment, fire shield, stoneskin*</text>
            <text>• 5th level (3 slots): cone of cold, scrying, wall of force</text>
            <text>• 6th level (1 slots): globe of invulnerability</text>
            <text>• 7th level (1 slots): teleport</text>
            <text>• 8th level (1 slots): mind blank*</text>
            <text>• 9th level (1 slots): time stop</text>
            <text>*Sylvira casts these spells on itself before combat.</text>
        </trait>
        <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
        <trait>
            <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
            <text>Sylvira's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 15). Sylvira can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
            <text>At will: thaumaturgy</text>
            <text>1/day each: darkness, hellish rebuke</text>
        </trait>
        <spells>disguise self, invisibility, fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp, detect magic, identify, mage armor, magic missile, detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step, counterspell, fly, lightning bolt, banishment, fire shield, stoneskin, cone of cold, scrying, wall of force, globe of invulnerability, teleport, mind blank, time stop, thaumaturgy, darkness, hellish rebuke</spells>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 46</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Thavius Kreeg</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
        <ac>10</ac>
        <hp>40 (9d8)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>12</str>
        <dex>10</dex>
        <con>11</con>
        <int>15</int>
        <wis>18</wis>
        <cha>16</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill>Deception +5, Medicine +6, Persuasion +5, Religion +4</skill>
        <passive>14</passive>
        <languages>Abyssal, Common, Infernal</languages>
        <cr>1/2</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Shadow of Guilt</name>
            <text>Thavius's shadow is that of a pudgy, horned devil with small wings.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Mace</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) bludgeoning damage.</text>
            <attack>Mace|3|1d6+1</attack>
        </action>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 42</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Thurstwell Vanthampur</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
        <ac>9</ac>
        <hp>5 (2d8-4)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>7</str>
        <dex>8</dex>
        <con>6</con>
        <int>15</int>
        <wis>17</wis>
        <cha>12</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill>Deception +3, Insight +5, Perception +5, Religion +4</skill>
        <passive>15</passive>
        <languages>Common, Elvish, Infernal</languages>
        <cr>1/8</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Dark Devotion</name>
            <text>Thurstwell has advantage on saving throws against being charmed or frightened.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Sacred Flame (Cantrip)</name>
            <text>Flame-like radiance descends on one creature Thurstwell can see within 60 feet of him. The target must succeed on a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw or take 4 (1d8) radiant damage, gaining no benefit from cover.</text>
        </action>
        <trait>
            <name>Spellcasting</name>
            <text>Thurstwell is a 2nd-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 13). He has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
            <text>Cantrips (at will): guidance, sacred flame (see "Actions" below), thaumaturgy</text>
            <text>• 1st level (3 slots): command, detect evil and good, sanctuary</text>
        </trait>
        <slots>3</slots>
        <spells>guidance, sacred flame, thaumaturgy, command, detect evil and good, sanctuary</spells>
        <description>Thurstwell is a pale and sullen recluse in his forties. A veritable shut-in, he uses imps to spy on his brothers, Amrik and Mortlock. Thurstwell resents both of them—Amrik for being their mother's favorite, and Mortlock for being a monstrous dolt.
            Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 34</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Tormenter</name>
        <size>H</size>
        <type>infernal vehicle</type>
        <speed>100</speed>
        <ac>21 (19 while motionless)</ac>
        <str>16</str><dex>14</dex><con>14</con><wis>0</wis><int>0</int><cha>0</cha>
        <immune>fire, poison, psychic</immune>
        <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, paralysed, petrified, poisoned, stunned, unconcious</conditionImmune>
        <trait>
            <text>Source: Baldur’s Gate Descent into Avernus, p. 218</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Prone Deficiency</name>
            <text>If the Tormentor rolls over and falls prone, it can't right itself and is incapacitated until flipped upright.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Weapons</name>
            <text>The Tormenter’s weapon attacks are magical.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Crushing Wheels</name>
            <text>The Tormentor can move through the space of any Medium or smaller creature. When it does, the creature must succeed on a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw or take 11 (2d10) bludgeoning damage and be knocked prone. If the creature was already prone, it takes an extra 11 (2d10) bludgeoning damage. This trait can't be used against a particular creature more than once each turn.</text>
            <attack>2d10</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Raking Scythes</name>
            <text>When the Tormentor moves within 5 feet of a creature that isn't prone or another  vehicle for the first time on a turn, it can rake the creature or  vehicle with its protruding blades for 13 (2d10+2) slashing damage. A creature moves out of the way and takes no damage if it succeeds on a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw. A vehicle moves out of the way and takes no damage if its driver succeeds on the saving throw.</text>
            <attack>Raking Scythes|0|2d10+2</attack>
        </action>
        <trait>
            <name>Helm (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Three Quarters Cover)</name>
            <text>Drive and steer the Tormentor.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Harpoon Flinger (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half Cover)</name>
            <text>Ammunition: 10 harpoons. Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. Hit 11 (2d8+2) piercing damage. </text>
            <attack>Harpoon Flinger|7|2d8+2</attack>
        </action>
        <reaction>
            <name>Juke</name>
            <text>If the Tormentor is able to move, the driver can use its reaction to grant the Tormentor advantage on a Dexterity saving throw.</text>
        </reaction>
        <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Torogar Steelfist</name>
        <size>L</size>
        <type>monstrosity</type>
        <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
        <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>168 (16d10+80)</hp>
        <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
        <str>25</str>
        <dex>17</dex>
        <con>20</con>
        <int>8</int>
        <wis>9</wis>
        <cha>16</cha>
        <save>Str +11, Con +9</save>
        <skill></skill>
        <passive>9</passive>
        <languages>Abyssal, Common</languages>
        <cr>11</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Goring Rush</name>
            <text>Immediately after using the Dash action, Torogar can make one melee attack with his horns.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Labyrinthine Recall</name>
            <text>Torogar can perfectly recall any path he has traveled.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Rage (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
            <text>As a bonus action, Torogar can enter a rage that lasts for 1 minute. The rage ends early if Torogar is knocked unconscious or if his turn ends and he hasn't attacked a hostile creature or taken damage since his last turn. While raging, Torogar gains the following benefits:</text>
            <text>He has advantage on Strength checks and Strength saving throws.</text>
            <text>He deals an extra 3 damage when he hits a target with a melee weapon attack.</text>
            <text>He has resistance to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Special Equipment</name>
            <text>Torogar wears gauntlets of flaming fury and a belt of fire giant strength. Without the belt, his Strength is 21. He also carries a soul coin.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Torogar makes three attacks: two with his scimitars and one with his horns.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Scimitar</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 14 (2d6 + 7) slashing damage, or 17 (2d6 + 10) slashing damage while raging, plus 3 (1d6) fire damage from the gauntlets of flaming fury.</text>
            <attack>Scimitar|11|2d6+7</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Horns</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 16 (2d8 + 7) piercing damage, or 19 (2d8 + 10) piercing damage while raging.</text>
            <attack>Horns|11|2d8+7</attack>
        </action>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 112</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Traxigor</name>
        <size>T</size>
        <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
        <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
        <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
        <hp>99 (18d8+18)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>14</dex>
        <con>12</con>
        <int>20</int>
        <wis>15</wis>
        <cha>16</cha>
        <save>Int +9, Wis +6</save>
        <skill>Arcana +13, History +13</skill>
        <passive>12</passive>
        <languages>any six languages</languages>
        <cr>12</cr>
        <resist>damage from spells; nonmagical bludgeoning, piercing, slashing (from stoneskin)</resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Resistance</name>
            <text>Traxigor has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Dagger</name>
            <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Dagger|6|1d4+2</attack>
        </action>
        <trait>
            <name>Spellcasting</name>
            <text>Traxigor is an 18th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks). Traxigor can cast disguise self and invisibility at will and has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
            <text>At will: disguise self, invisibility</text>
            <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp</text>
            <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, identify, mage armor*, magic missile</text>
            <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step</text>
            <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fly, lightning bolt</text>
            <text>• 4th level (3 slots): banishment, fire shield, stoneskin*</text>
            <text>• 5th level (3 slots): cone of cold, scrying, wall of force</text>
            <text>• 6th level (1 slots): globe of invulnerability</text>
            <text>• 7th level (1 slots): plane shift</text>
            <text>• 8th level (1 slots): mind blank*</text>
            <text>• 9th level (1 slots): time stop</text>
            <text>*Traxigor casts these spells on itself before combat.</text>
        </trait>
        <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
        <spells>disguise self, invisibility, fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp, detect magic, identify, mage armor, magic missile, detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step, counterspell, fly, lightning bolt, banishment, fire shield, stoneskin, cone of cold, scrying, wall of force, globe of invulnerability, plane shift, mind blank, time stop</spells>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 50</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Tressym (monstrosity)</name>
        <size>T</size>
        <type>beast</type>
        <alignment>Chaotic Neutral</alignment>
        <ac>12</ac>
        <hp>5 (2d4)</hp>
        <speed>walk 40 ft., climb 30 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
        <str>3</str>
        <dex>15</dex>
        <con>10</con>
        <int>11</int>
        <wis>12</wis>
        <cha>12</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill>Perception +5, Stealth +4</skill>
        <passive>15</passive>
        <languages>understands Common but can't speak</languages>
        <cr>0</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune>poison</immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
        <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Detect Invisibility</name>
            <text>Within 60 feet of the tressym, magical invisibility fails to conceal anything from the tressym's sight</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Keen Smell</name>
            <text>The tressym has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Poison Sense</name>
            <text>The tressym can detect whether a substance is poisonous by taste, touch, or smell.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Familiar</name>
            <text>With the DM's permission, a person who casts the find familiar spell can choose to conjure a tressym in stead of a normal cat.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Claws</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +0 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 1 slashing damage.</text>
        </action>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 241, Infernal Machine Rebuild</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Ulder Ravengard</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
        <ac>20 (plate armor, shield)</ac>
        <hp>112 (15d8+45)</hp>
        <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
        <str>17</str>
        <dex>14</dex>
        <con>16</con>
        <int>11</int>
        <wis>10</wis>
        <cha>17</cha>
        <save>Con +6, Wis +3</save>
        <skill>Athletics +6, Intimidation +6, Perception +3</skill>
        <passive>13</passive>
        <languages>Common</languages>
        <cr>5</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Ulder makes three melee attacks, only one of which can be with his shield.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>+1 Longsword</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (1d8 + 4) slashing damage, or 9 (1d10 + 4) slashing damage when used with two hands.</text>
            <attack>+1 Longsword|7|1d8+4</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Shield</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 6 (1d6 + 3) bludgeoning damage, and Ulder pushes the target 5 feet away from him. Ulder then enters the space vacated by the target. If the target is pushed to within 5 feet of a creature friendly to Ulder, the target provokes an opportunity attack from that creature.</text>
            <attack>Shield|6|1d6+3</attack>
        </action>
        <reaction>
            <name>Guardian Strike</name>
            <text>If an enemy within 5 feet of Ulder attacks a target other than him, Ulder can make a melee attack against that enemy.</text>
        </reaction>
        <description>Ulder Ravengard is a fearless soldier who rose up through the ranks of the Flaming Fist to become its supreme marshal. Ravengard used his military position and influence to secure for himself a seat on the Council of Four. Following the deaths of two council members amid a cloud of corruption and scandal, he persuaded the Parliament of Peers to back his election to grand duke.
            Upon ascending to the highest position in the city government, Ravengard refused to relinquish command of the Flaming Fist, making him the most powerful figure in the city by far. This decision has not endeared him to anyone, but Ravengard could care less about his popularity. His only concerns are the stability and prosperity of Baldur's Gate, and he doesn't trust any of the other dukes or anyone in the Parliament of Peers to put the city's interests before their own.
            Ravengard rose to grand duke on a platform largely backed by idealistic commoners and enemies of the other established dukes. While he won election handily, Ravengard has struggled in performing his duties, finding his hands tied at every turn by both overt and invisible bureaucracy. Despite this, he's been a voice of reason and common sense on the Council of Four—if not the egalitarianism some hoped. He's also proven largely resistant to scandal and corruption, though many of his fellow dukes and those in the Parliament of Peers still regularly outmaneuver him politically. One of his only obvious pleasures remains the surprise inspections he regularly visits upon the troops at Wyrm's Rock.
            Ravengard was recently tricked into attending a diplomatic summit in Elturel, unaware that his political enemies in Baldur's Gate orchestrated this meeting in a fiendish plot to remove him from power. In his absence, the Flaming Fist is leaderless, the council rudderless.
            Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 70</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Rilsa Rael</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
        <ac>15 (leather armor)</ac>
        <hp>52 (8d8+16)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>14</str>
        <dex>18</dex>
        <con>14</con>
        <int>10</int>
        <wis>11</wis>
        <cha>15</cha>
        <save>Dex +6, Wis +2</save>
        <skill>Acrobatics +6, Athletics +4, Deception +4, Perception +2, Sleight of hand +6, Stealth +6</skill>
        <passive>12</passive>
        <languages>Common, Thieves' cant</languages>
        <cr>3</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Cunning Action</name>
            <text>On each of her turns in combat, Rilsa can use a bonus action to take the Dash, Disengage, or Hide action.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Focus</name>
            <text>If Rilsa damages a creature with a weapon attack, she gains advantage on attack rolls against that target until the end of her next turn.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Tactical Leadership</name>
            <text>As a bonus action, Rilsa chooses one creature she can see within 30 feet of her. The creature doesn't provoke opportunity attacks until the end of its next turn, provided it can hear Rilsa's commands.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Rilsa makes three weapon attacks.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Shortsword</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Shortsword|6|1d6+4</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Dagger</name>
            <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 6 (1d4 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Dagger|6|1d4+4</attack>
        </action>
        <description>The Guild kingpin of Little Calimshan. Among Little Calimshan's most notorious locations is the Calim Jewel Emporium, widely regarded as the best jeweler in the city—and the best place to fence stolen gems, as it's also the local Guild headquarters. In addition to hosting regular public forums in her shop, Rael tacitly oversees the Garden of Whispers, a maze of wood-and-paper screens where people from across the city can buy and sell secrets with Guild agents and each other, speaking through the barriers so as to maintain anonymity.
            Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 199</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Nine-Fingers Keene</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
        <ac>15 (leather armor)</ac>
        <hp>84 (13d8+26)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>12</str>
        <dex>18</dex>
        <con>14</con>
        <int>13</int>
        <wis>17</wis>
        <cha>14</cha>
        <save>Dex +7, Int +4</save>
        <skill>Acrobatics +10, Deception +5, Insight +6, Intimidation +5, Perception +6, Sleight of hand +10, Stealth +10</skill>
        <passive>16</passive>
        <languages>Common, Thieves' cant</languages>
        <cr>5</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Cunning Action</name>
            <text>On each of her turns in combat, Nine-Fingers can use a bonus action to take the Dash, Disengage, or Hide action.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Dagger Thrower</name>
            <text>Nine-Fingers adds double her proficiency bonus to the damage she deals on ranged attacks made with daggers (already factored into her attacks).</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Nine-Fingers attacks three times with her daggers.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Dagger</name>
            <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 6 (1d4 + 4) piercing damage, plus 6 piercing damage if it's a ranged attack.</text>
            <attack>Dagger|7|1d4+4</attack>
        </action>
        <reaction>
            <name>Uncanny Dodge</name>
            <text>Nine-Fingers halves the damage that she takes from an attack that hits her. She must be able to see the attacker.</text>
        </reaction>
        <description>The current leader of the Guild, Nine-Fingers Keene, disdains flashy garb and illusion magic. She appears to the world as she is: an unassuming woman of middling age and build. Her forgettable looks have proven her greatest asset as a thief, as her victims have trouble recognizing her even when they meet her again face-to-face. Keene's leadership over the years earned her a reputation of thoughtful pragmatism. When necessary, she seeks revenge for offenses against the Guild—provided doing so is profitable. Her methods are vicious when necessary, and she is as feared as she is respected.
            Keene has become increasingly intolerant of the populous tide turning against her organization. While the occasional rabble-rouser has always impeded criminal business, the rise of organized crews and vigilantes is interfering with Guild operations. After a carefully coordinated attack on a patriar's estate fell to pieces when a vigilante clumsily alerted the estate guards, Keene declared open season on do-gooders of all stripes.
            Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 170</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Mortlock Vanthampur</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
        <ac>12</ac>
        <hp>90 (12d8+36)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>18</str>
        <dex>14</dex>
        <con>17</con>
        <int>10</int>
        <wis>12</wis>
        <cha>13</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill>Athletics +6, Intimidation +5</skill>
        <passive>11</passive>
        <languages>Common</languages>
        <cr>3</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Indomitable (2/Day)</name>
            <text>Mortlock can reroll a saving throw that he fails. He must use the new roll.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Mortlock makes two attacks with his greatclub.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Greatclub</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (2d4 + 4) bludgeoning damage, plus 5 (2d4) bludgeoning damage if Mortlock has taken any damage since his last turn.</text>
            <attack>Greatclub|6|2d4+4</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Heavy Crossbow</name>
            <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 100/400 ft., one target. 7 (1d10 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Heavy Crossbow|4|1d10+2</attack>
        </action>
        <description>Mortlock is tolerated by his mother, Duke Thalamra Vanthampur, and despised by his older brothers, Thurstwell and Amrik, who view him as a simpleton and an abomination. Half of Mortlock's face was scarred by fire when he was a child, and his disfigurement gives him a fearsome countenance.
            Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 26</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Mahadi the Rakshasa</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>fiend</type>
        <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
        <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>195 (23d8+92)</hp>
        <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
        <str>14</str>
        <dex>18</dex>
        <con>18</con>
        <int>14</int>
        <wis>18</wis>
        <cha>20</cha>
        <save>Wis +9, Cha +10</save>
        <skill>Arcana +7, Deception +10, Insight +9, Perception +9</skill>
        <passive>19</passive>
        <languages>all (can read only), Common, Infernal</languages>
        <cr>14</cr>
        <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable>piercing from magic weapons wielded by good creatures</vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Limited Magic Immunity</name>
            <text>Mahadi can't be affected or detected by spells of 6th level or lower unless he wishes to be. He has advantage on saving throws against all other spells and magical effects.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Weapons</name>
            <text>Mahadi's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Mahadi makes four claw attacks.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Claw</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (2d6 + 2) slashing damage, and the target is cursed if it's a creature. The curse takes effect whenever the target takes a short or long rest, filling the target's thoughts with horrible images and dreams. The cursed target gains no benefit from finishing a short or long rest. The curse lasts until it is lifted by a remove curse spell or similar magic.</text>
            <attack>Claw|7|2d6+2</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Summon Erinyes (1/Day)</name>
            <text>Mahadi summons Ilzabet, an erinyes bound to him by an infernal contract. The erinyes appears in an unoccupied space within 60 feet of him, acts as his ally, and can't summon other devils. The erinyes remains for 10 minutes or until Mahadi dismisses it as an action. If the erinyes dies, Mahadi loses this action option.</text>
        </action>
        <trait>
            <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
            <text>Mahadi's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 18, +9 to hit with spell attacks). He can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
            <text>At will: detect thoughts, disguise self, mage hand, minor illusion</text>
            <text>3/day each: charm person, detect magic, dispel magic, hellish rebuke, invisibility, major image, speak with dead, suggestion</text>
            <text>1/day each: banishment, demiplane, dominate person, fly, forcecage, geas, plane shift, true seeing</text>
        </trait>
        <spells>detect thoughts, disguise self, mage hand, minor illusion, charm person, detect magic, dispel magic, hellish rebuke, invisibility, major image, speak with dead, suggestion, banishment, demiplane, dominate person, fly, forcecage, geas, plane shift, true seeing</spells>
        <description>Mahadi appears as a wealthy merchant lord. Though extremely powerful, Mahadi doesn't believe in taking unnecessary risks, particularly in the Nine Hells where he can be permanently slain. Mahadi acts as the eyes and ears of Asmodeus in Avernus. As a deal broker and moderator, he's privy to all manner of dealings that might otherwise escape the attention of his patron.
            In his role as the master of the Wandering Emporium, Mahadi has received special dispensation from Asmodeus to travel freely between the Material Plane and the Nine Hells to operate his business, as well as to pursue information and broker contracts and other such arrangements as needed.
            In addition to managing the Wandering Emporium, Mahadi is also the proprietor and host of Infernal Rapture, a restaurant and spa. Since the establishment exists within a demiplane, patrons can comfortably visit it at any time, even while the caravan is on the move. As long as they can pay for services rendered, guests need not fear being trapped within, since Mahadi is very serious about maintaining the contract between host and guest. Each guest must agree to this formal arrangement prior to gaining entrance.
            Mahadi presents himself as a charismatic and gracious host. He makes each guest of Infernal Rapture feel as though they're the most important person in all the planes of existence, catering to their every whim and desire. While he is equally cordial to all guests of the Wandering Emporium, those entering his establishment fall under a special contract and therefore rank most highly in his esteem.
            Of course, guests leaving Infernal Rapture are expected to pay their bills in full prior to departure. If a guest cannot pay for whatever reason, the contract they signed on entry clearly stipulates their soul is forfeit. They're required to pay off their debt through service. All such individuals fall under the effect of a geas cast as a 9th-level spell, which cannot be willingly broken by the affected individual until their debt is paid in full. What Mahadi does with such defaulters depends on their capabilities. Some become indentured servants, working at Infernal Rapture. If they possess a talent for sales, they might eventually obtain a business to run within the Wandering Emporium.
            Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 127</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    
    <monster>
        <name>Krull</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (tortle)</type>
        <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
        <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>117 (18d8+36)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>20</str>
        <dex>14</dex>
        <con>15</con>
        <int>12</int>
        <wis>20</wis>
        <cha>12</cha>
        <save>Wis +8, Cha +4</save>
        <skill>Arcana +4, Medicine +8, Nature +4, Survival +8</skill>
        <passive>15</passive>
        <languages>Aquan, Common, Draconic</languages>
        <cr>6</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Hold Breath</name>
            <text>Krull can hold his breath for 1 hour.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Inescapable Destruction</name>
            <text>Necrotic damage dealt by Krull's spells ignores resistance to necrotic damage.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Claws</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d4 + 5) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Claws|8|1d4+5</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>+1 Maul</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d6 + 6) bludgeoning damage plus 9 (2d8) necrotic damage.</text>
            <attack>+1 Maul|9|2d6+6</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Shell Defense</name>
            <text>Krull withdraws into his shell. Until he emerges as a bonus action, he has a +4 bonus to AC and has advantage on Strength and Constitution saving throws. While in his shell, Krull is prone, his speed is 0 and can't increase, he has disadvantage on Dexterity saving throws, he can't take reactions, and the only action he can take is to emerge from his shell.</text>
        </action>
        <trait>
            <name>Spellcasting</name>
            <text>Krull is a 14th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 16, +8 to hit with spell attacks). He has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
            <text>Cantrips (at will): chill touch, mending, resistance, sacred flame, spare the dying, thaumaturgy</text>
            <text>• 1st level (4 slots): cure wounds, detect evil and good, false life, inflict wounds, ray of sickness</text>
            <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): blindness/deafness, gentle repose, hold person, ray of enfeeblement, spiritual weapon</text>
            <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): animate dead, magic circle, speak with dead, spirit guardians, vampiric touch</text>
            <text>• 4th level (3 slots): banishment, blight, death ward, divination, locate creature</text>
            <text>• 5th level (2 slots): antilife shell, cloudkill, contagion, greater restoration</text>
            <text>• 6th level (1 slots): create undead, true seeing</text>
            <text>• 7th level (1 slots): divine word, regenerate</text>
        </trait>
        <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1</slots>
        <spells>chill touch, mending, resistance, sacred flame, spare the dying, thaumaturgy, cure wounds, detect evil and good, false life, inflict wounds, ray of sickness, blindness/deafness, gentle repose, hold person, ray of enfeeblement, spiritual weapon, animate dead, magic circle, speak with dead, spirit guardians, vampiric touch, banishment, blight, death ward, divination, locate creature, antilife shell, cloudkill, contagion, greater restoration, create undead, true seeing, divine word, regenerate</spells>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 110</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Kostchtchie</name>
        <size>L</size>
        <type>fiend (demon)</type>
        <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
        <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>243 (18d10+144)</hp>
        <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
        <str>30</str>
        <dex>12</dex>
        <con>27</con>
        <int>18</int>
        <wis>22</wis>
        <cha>19</cha>
        <save>Dex +9, Con +16, Wis +14</save>
        <skill>Intimidation +12, Perception +14, Survival +14</skill>
        <passive>24</passive>
        <languages>Abyssal, Giant, telepathy 120 ft</languages>
        <cr>25</cr>
        <resist>fire, lightning</resist>
        <immune>cold, poison; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
        <senses>truesight 120 ft</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
            <text>If Kostchtchie fails a saving throw, he can choose to succeed instead.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Resistance</name>
            <text>Kostchtchie has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Kostchtchie makes two melee attacks, only one of which can be a bite attack.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Bite</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +18 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 13 (1d6 + 10) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Bite|18|1d6+10</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Matalotok (Warhammer)</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +18 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 19 (2d8 + 10) bludgeoning damage, or 21 (2d10 + 10) bludgeoning damage when used with two hands, and the weapon emits a burst of cold that deals 10 (3d6) cold damage to each creature within 30 feet of it.</text>
            <attack>Matalotok (Warhammer)|18|2d8+10</attack>
        </action>
        <legendary>
            <text>Kostchtchie can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Kostchtchie regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
        </legendary>
        <legendary>
            <name>Attack</name>
            <text>Kostchtchie makes one melee weapon attack.</text>
        </legendary>
        <legendary>
            <name>Charge</name>
            <text>Kostchtchie moves up to his speed.</text>
        </legendary>
        <legendary>
            <name>Curse (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
            <text>Kostchtchie curses one creature he can see within 60 feet of him. The cursed creature gains vulnerability to all damage dealt by Kostchtchie until the end of Kostchtchie's next turn.</text>
        </legendary>
        <trait>
            <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
            <text>Kostchtchie's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 20). He can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
            <text>At will: command, darkness</text>
            <text>1/day each: dispel evil and good, gate, harm, telekinesis, teleport, wind walk</text>
        </trait>
        <spells>command, darkness, dispel evil and good, gate, harm, telekinesis, teleport, wind walk</spells>
        <description>The demon lord Kostchtchie resembles a squat hill giant with short, bandy legs and a grossly shaped head.
            Frost giants who forsake their gods and turn to demon worship can summon Kostchtchie with bloody offerings left on altars of hewn ice. If the demon lord chooses to answer the giants' call, he hunts and fights alongside them for a time, infecting the frost giants with savage madness and bloodlust before disappearing back to the Abyss.
            Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 105</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Gideon Lightward</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>undead</type>
        <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
        <ac>11</ac>
        <hp>136 (16d8+64)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>18</str>
        <dex>13</dex>
        <con>18</con>
        <int>10</int>
        <wis>18</wis>
        <cha>13</cha>
        <save>Dex +4, Con +7, Wis +7</save>
        <skill>Insight +7, Religion +6</skill>
        <passive>14</passive>
        <languages>Common</languages>
        <cr>6</cr>
        <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
        <immune>necrotic, poison</immune>
        <vulnerable>radiant</vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune>exhaustion, paralyzed, poisoned</conditionImmune>
        <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Regeneration</name>
            <text>Gideon regains 10 hit points at the start of each of his turns. If he takes radiant damage, this trait doesn't function at the start of his next turn. Gideon is destroyed only if he starts his turn with 0 hit points and doesn't regenerate.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Gideon attacks twice with his fists.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Fist</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
            <attack>Fist|7|2d6+4</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Withering Gaze</name>
            <text>Gideon targets one creature he can see within 60 feet of him. The target must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw, taking 22 (4d10) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
        </action>
        <description>Gideon Lightward was a priest of Lathander who served Elturel and his deity proudly. Zariel saw that his fervor could be an asset to her, so she sent devils to corrupt him in the months leading up to the fall of Elturel. The devils posed as angels, offering Gideon increased power if he would dedicate himself to fighting the ever-present threat of demons.
            Gideon slowly gave up his sanity and free will to the devils, leaving him corrupted by Zariel and fully serving her in the months leading up to Elturel's fall. He died during the destruction wrought as the city was drawn to Avernus, but the priest rose as an undead creature. Even as an undead, Gideon remains his mistress's most loyal servant in Elturel. He sees his cause as a noble one—fighting the demons whose chaos marks the end of all things. But his mind is broken and filled with hatred for those who refuse to follow his commands.
            Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 65</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Duke Thalamra Vanthampur</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human)</type>
        <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
        <ac>10</ac>
        <hp>78 (12d8+24)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>17</str>
        <dex>10</dex>
        <con>15</con>
        <int>13</int>
        <wis>16</wis>
        <cha>18</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill>Deception +6, Insight +5, Intimidation +6, Religion +3</skill>
        <passive>13</passive>
        <languages>Common, Infernal</languages>
        <cr>4</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses>darkvision 120 ft. (see devil's sight below)</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Dark Devotion</name>
            <text>Thalamra has advantage on saving throws against being charmed or frightened.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Devil's Sight</name>
            <text>Thalamra can see normally in darkness, both magical and nonmagical, out to a distance of 120 feet.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Thalamra uses eldritch blast twice or makes two unarmed strikes.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Eldritch Blast (Cantrip)</name>
            <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +6 to hit, range 120 ft., one creature. 9 (1d10 + 4) force damage.</text>
            <attack>Eldritch Blast (Cantrip)|6|1d10+4</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Unarmed Strike</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 bludgeoning damage.</text>
        </action>
        <reaction>
            <name>Hellish Rebuke (1st-Level Spell; 2/Day)</name>
            <text>When Thalamra is damaged by a creature within 60 feet of her that she can see, the creature that damaged her is engulfed in hellish flames and must make a DC 14 Dexterity saving throw, taking 16 (3d10) fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
        </reaction>
        <description>Acid-tongued, shrewd, and aggressive, Duke Thalamra Vanthampur is the matriarch of the Vanthampur family. Born with nothing, she spent years wallowing in obscurity, repairing and renovating the city's ancient sewer system. One promotion after another followed until she was named Master of Drains and Underways. By then, she had been married three times and given birth to three sons. Her lifelong goal has been to lift herself and her family out of the sewers and into high society.
            Years of political dealing, blame shuffling, and bribery paid off when Thalamra was elected to the Council of Four. Although she has served on the council for the shortest amount of time, Duke Vanthampur is easily the most politically savvy council member. She speaks little during meetings of the council, preferring to further her political agenda through meetings in her private offices and at her family estate. When she does choose to debate, she speaks with a strength beyond what it seems like her age should allow, and is known for leveling insults that land unsettlingly close to (supposedly) hidden truths.
            Thalamra Vanthampur is a cunning, devil-worshiping beast of a woman in her late sixties who can stare down a hell hound without flinching. She is barrel-bodied, with strong hands and forearms that speak to her beginnings as a manual laborer. Her youth was spent in the cellars and sewers of Baldur's Gate, repairing pipes and clearing out the city's filth. Thalamra rose from such lowly work to become the minister of the city's sewers and waterworks. Now she dresses in the finery that suits her station as a duke of Baldur's Gate.
            Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 38</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Bone Whelk</name>
        <size>L</size>
        <type>monstrosity</type>
        <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
        <ac>12 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>27 (5d10)</hp>
        <speed>walk 15 ft., climb 15 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>5</dex>
        <con>11</con>
        <int>6</int>
        <wis>9</wis>
        <cha>3</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill></skill>
        <passive>9</passive>
        <languages></languages>
        <cr>1/4</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Adhesive</name>
            <text>The bone whelk can cause Medium or smaller objects to adhere to it. A Medium or smaller creature that touches the bone whelk is grappled by it (escape DC 10).</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Death Scream</name>
            <text>When the bone whelk dies, it emits a blood-curdling shriek than can be heard out to a range of 120 feet. This shriek causes nonmagical, organic material within 10 feet of the bone whelk to rot. Each creature within 10 feet of the bone whelk when it dies takes 9 (2d8) necrotic damage.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Spider Climb</name>
            <text>The bone whelk can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without needing to make an ability check.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Bite</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 4 (1d8) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Bite|2|1d8</attack>
        </action>
        <description>Bone whelks are large mollusks that excrete an adhesive to attach skulls, bones, and other detritus to their bodies for protection.
            Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 119</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Bel</name>
        <size>L</size>
        <type>fiend (devil)</type>
        <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
        <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>364 (27d10+216)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
        <str>28</str>
        <dex>14</dex>
        <con>26</con>
        <int>25</int>
        <wis>19</wis>
        <cha>26</cha>
        <save>Dex +10, Con +16, Wis +12</save>
        <skill>Arcana +14, Deception +15, Insight +11, Persuasion +15</skill>
        <passive>14</passive>
        <languages>Common, Infernal, Telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
        <cr>25</cr>
        <resist>cold; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't silvered</resist>
        <immune>fire, poison</immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
        <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Fear Aura</name>
            <text>Any creature hostile to Bel that starts its turn within 20 feet of him must make a DC 23 Wisdom saving throw, unless Bel is incapacitated. Unless the save succeeds, the creature is frightened until the start of its next turn. If a creature's saving throw is successful, the creature is immune to Bel's Fear Aura for the next 24 hours.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
            <text>If Bel fails a saving throw, he can choose to succeed instead.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Resistance</name>
            <text>Bel has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Weapons</name>
            <text>Bel's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Bel makes three attacks: two with his greatsword and one with his tail.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Greatsword</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +16 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 23 (4d6 + 9) slashing damage plus 21 (6d6) fire damage. If the target is a flammable object that is not being held or worn, it catches fire.</text>
            <attack>Greatsword|16|4d6+9</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Tail</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +16 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 25 (3d10 + 9) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 23 Constitution saving throw or be stunned until the end of its next turn.</text>
            <attack>Tail|16|3d10+9</attack>
        </action>
        <legendary>
            <text>The fiend (devil) can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The fiend (devil) regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
        </legendary>
        <legendary>
            <name>Fireball</name>
            <text>Bel casts fireball.</text>
        </legendary>
        <legendary>
            <name>Tactical Edge (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
            <text>Roll a d6 for Bel. The number rolled on the die is subtracted from the next attack roll made against Bel or an ally of his choice within the next minute.</text>
        </legendary>
        <legendary>
            <name>Summon Ice Devil (Costs 3 Actions)</name>
            <text>Bel magically summons an ice devil with an ice spear (as described in the ice devil's entry in the Monster Manual). The ice devil appears in an unoccupied space within 60 feet of Bel, acts as Bel's ally, and can summon other devils if it has such power. The ice devil remains until Bel dies or until he dismisses it as an action.</text>
        </legendary>
        <trait>
            <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
            <text>Bel's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 23). Bel can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
            <text>At will: detect magic, fireball</text>
            <text>3/day each: dispel magic, hold monster, mirror image, mislead, raise dead, teleport, wall of fire</text>
            <text>1/day each: imprisonment, meteor swarm</text>
        </trait>
        <spells>detect magic, fireball, dispel magic, hold monster, mirror image, mislead, raise dead, teleport, wall of fire, imprisonment, meteor swarm</spells>
        <description>From his bastion, Zariel's second-in-command and the former lord of Avernus oversees the forges that furnish weapons and armor for the Blood War. Though Asmodeus has instructed Zariel to accept Bel as her advisor, Bel and Zariel loathe each other and invent distractions to keep them apart.
            Bel outwardly plays the role of Zariel's loyal vassal. However, Bel rankles at Zariel's rulership of the layer of the Nine Hells that was once his, but he won't challenge her directly as long as he thinks Asmodeus supports Zariel.
            Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 115</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Bitter Breath</name>
        <size>L</size>
        <type>fiend (devil)</type>
        <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
        <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>178 (17d10+85)</hp>
        <speed>walk 20 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
        <str>22</str>
        <dex>17</dex>
        <con>21</con>
        <int>12</int>
        <wis>16</wis>
        <cha>17</cha>
        <save>Str +10, Dex +7, Wis +7, Cha +7</save>
        <skill></skill>
        <passive>13</passive>
        <languages>Infernal, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
        <cr>11</cr>
        <resist>cold; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't silvered</resist>
        <immune>fire, poison</immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
        <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Devil's Sight</name>
            <text>Magical darkness doesn't impede Bitter Breath's darkvision.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Resistance</name>
            <text>Bitter Breath has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Bitter Breath makes three melee attacks: two with its fork and one with its tail. It can use Hurl Flame in place of any melee attack.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Fork</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 15 (2d8 + 6) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Fork|10|2d8+6</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Tail</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 10 (1d8 + 6) piercing damage. If the target is a creature other than an undead or a construct, it must succeed on a DC 17 Constitution saving throw or lose 10 (3d6) hit points at the start of each of its turns due to an infernal wound. Each time Bitter Breath hits the wounded target with this attack, the damage dealt by the wound increases by 10 (3d6). Any creature can take an action to stanch the wound with a successful DC 12 Wisdom (Medicine) check. The wound also closes if the target receives magical healing.</text>
            <attack>Tail|10|1d8+6</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Hurl Flame</name>
            <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +7 to hit, range 150 ft., one target. 14 (4d6) fire damage. If the target is a flammable object that isn't being worn or carried, it also catches fire.</text>
            <attack>Hurl Flame|7|4d6</attack>
        </action>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 90</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Burney the Barber</name>
        <size>G</size>
        <type>dragon</type>
        <alignment>Chaotic Good</alignment>
        <ac>21 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>350 (20d20+140)</hp>
        <speed>walk 40 ft., climb 40 ft., fly 80 ft.</speed>
        <str>27</str>
        <dex>12</dex>
        <con>25</con>
        <int>20</int>
        <wis>17</wis>
        <cha>19</cha>
        <save>Dex +8, Con +14, Wis +10, Cha +11</save>
        <skill>Deception +11, Perception +17, Stealth +8</skill>
        <passive>27</passive>
        <languages>Common, Draconic</languages>
        <cr>21</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune>acid</immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses>blindsight 60 ft., darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
            <text>If Burney fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Burney can use its Frightful Presence. It then makes three attacks: one with its bite and two with its claws.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Bite</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +15 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. 19 (2d10 + 8) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Bite|15|2d10+8</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Claw</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +15 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 15 (2d6 + 8) slashing damage.</text>
            <attack>Claw|15|2d6+8</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Tail</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +15 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. 17 (2d8 + 8) bludgeoning damage.</text>
            <attack>Tail|15|2d8+8</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Frightful Presence</name>
            <text>Each creature of Burney's choice that is within 120 feet of Burney and aware of it must succeed on a DC 19 Wisdom saving throw or become frightened for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. If a creature's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the creature is immune to Burney's Frightful Presence for the next 24 hours.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Breath Weapons (Recharge 5-6)</name>
            <text>Burney uses one of the following breath weapons.</text>
            <text>Acid Breath.Burney exhales acid in a 90-foot line that is 10 feet wide. Each creature in that line must make a DC 22 Dexterity saving throw, taking 63 (14d8) acid damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.
                Slowing Breath.Burney exhales gas in a 90-foot cone. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 22 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the creature can't use reactions, its speed is halved, and it can't make more than one attack on its turn. In addition, the creature can use either an action or a bonus action on its turn, but not both. These effects last for 1 minute. The creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself with a successful save.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Change Shape</name>
            <text>Burney magically polymorphs into a humanoid or beast that has a challenge rating no higher than its own, or back into its true form. It reverts to its true form if it dies. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying is absorbed or borne by the new form (Burney's choice).</text>
            <text>In a new form, Burney retains its alignment, hit points, Hit Dice, ability to speak, proficiencies, Legendary Resistance, lair actions, and Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma scores, as well as this action. Its statistics and capabilities are otherwise replaced by those of the new form, except any class features or legendary actions of that form.</text>
        </action>
        <legendary>
            <text>The dragon can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The dragon regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
        </legendary>
        <legendary>
            <name>Detect</name>
            <text>Burney makes a Wisdom (Perception) check.</text>
        </legendary>
        <legendary>
            <name>Tail Attack</name>
            <text>Burney makes a tail attack.</text>
        </legendary>
        <legendary>
            <name>Wing Attack (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
            <text>Burney beats its wings. Each creature within 15 feet of Burney must succeed on a DC 23 Dexterity saving throw or take 15 (2d6 + 8) bludgeoning damage and be knocked prone. Burney can then fly up to half its flying speed.</text>
        </legendary>
        <legendary>
            <name>Lair Actions</name>
            <text>On initiative count 20 (losing initiative ties), the dragon takes a lair action to cause one of the following effects:</text>
            <text>• The dragon chooses a point on the ground that it can see within 120 feet of it. Stone spikes sprout from the ground in a 20-foot radius centered on that point. The effect is otherwise identical to the spike growth spell and lasts until the dragon uses this lair action again or until the dragon dies.</text>
            <text>• The dragon chooses a 10-foot-square area on the ground that it can see within 120 feet of it. The ground in that area turns into 3-foot-deep mud. Each creature on the ground in that area when the mud appears must succeed on a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw or sink into the mud and become restrained. A creature can take an action to attempt a DC 15 Strength check, freeing itself or another creature within its reach and ending the restrained condition on a success. Moving 1 foot in the mud costs 2 feet of movement. On initiative count 20 on the next round, the mud hardens, and the Strength DC to work free increases to 20.</text>
        </legendary>
        <legendary>
            <name>Regional Effects</name>
            <text>The region containing a legendary copper dragon's lair is warped by the dragon's magic, which creates one or more of the following effects:</text>
            <text>• Magic carvings of the dragon's smiling visage can be seen worked into stone terrain and objects within 6 miles of the dragon's lair.</text>
            <text>• Tiny beasts such as rodents and birds that are normally unable to speak gain the magical ability to speak and understand Draconic while within 1 mile of the dragon's lair. These creatures speak well of the dragon, but can't divulge its whereabouts.</text>
            <text>• Intelligent creatures within 1 mile of the dragon's lair are prone to fits of giggling. Even serious matters suddenly seem amusing.</text>
            <text>If the dragon dies, the magic carvings fade over the course of 1d10 days. The other effects end immediately.</text>
        </legendary>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 129</description>
        <environment>hill</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Chukka</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (kenku)</type>
        <alignment>Chaotic Neutral</alignment>
        <ac>13</ac>
        <hp>13 (3d8)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>16</dex>
        <con>10</con>
        <int>11</int>
        <wis>10</wis>
        <cha>10</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill>Deception +4, Perception +2, Stealth +5</skill>
        <passive>12</passive>
        <languages>understands Auran and Common but speaks only through the use of its Mimicry trait</languages>
        <cr>1/4</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Ambusher</name>
            <text>In the first round of a combat, Chukka has advantage on attack rolls against any creature it surprised.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Mimicry</name>
            <text>Chukka can mimic any sounds it has heard, including voices. A creature that hears the sounds can tell they are imitations with a successful DC 14 Wisdom (Insight) check.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Shortsword</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Shortsword|5|1d6+3</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Shortbow</name>
            <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Shortbow|5|1d6+3</attack>
        </action>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 83</description>
        <environment>forest, urban</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Clonk</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (kenku)</type>
        <alignment>Chaotic Neutral</alignment>
        <ac>13</ac>
        <hp>13 (3d8)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>16</dex>
        <con>10</con>
        <int>11</int>
        <wis>10</wis>
        <cha>10</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill>Deception +4, Perception +2, Stealth +5</skill>
        <passive>12</passive>
        <languages>understands Auran and Common but speaks only through the use of its Mimicry trait</languages>
        <cr>1/4</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Ambusher</name>
            <text>In the first round of a combat, Clonk has advantage on attack rolls against any creature it surprised.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Mimicry</name>
            <text>Clonk can mimic any sounds it has heard, including voices. A creature that hears the sounds can tell they are imitations with a successful DC 14 Wisdom (Insight) check.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Shortsword</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Shortsword|5|1d6+3</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Shortbow</name>
            <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Shortbow|5|1d6+3</attack>
        </action>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 83</description>
        <environment>forest, urban</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Dryad Spirit</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>undead</type>
        <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
        <ac>12</ac>
        <hp>58 (13d8)</hp>
        <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
        <str>1</str>
        <dex>14</dex>
        <con>10</con>
        <int>12</int>
        <wis>11</wis>
        <cha>17</cha>
        <save>Wis +2, Cha +5</save>
        <skill></skill>
        <passive>10</passive>
        <languages>Common, Elvish</languages>
        <cr>4</cr>
        <resist>acid, fire, lightning, thunder; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
        <immune>cold, necrotic, poison</immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, restrained</conditionImmune>
        <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Detect Life</name>
            <text>The dryad can magically sense the presence of living creatures up to 5 miles away that aren't undead or constructs. She knows the general direction they're in but not their exact locations.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Incorporeal Movement</name>
            <text>The dryad can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. She takes 5 (1d10) force damage if she ends her turn inside an object.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Corrupting Touch</name>
            <text>Melee Spell Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 12 (3d6 + 2) necrotic damage.</text>
            <attack>Corrupting Touch|4|3d6+2</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Horrifying Visage</name>
            <text>Each non-undead creature within 60 feet of the dryad that can see her must succeed on a DC 13 Wisdom saving throw or be frightened for 1 minute. A frightened target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, with disadvantage if the dryad is within line of sight, ending the effect on itself on a success. If a target's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the target is immune to the dryad's Horrifying Visage for the next 24 hours.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Wail (1/Day)</name>
            <text>The dryad releases a mournful wail, provided that she isn't in sunlight. This wail has no effect on constructs and undead. All other creatures within 30 feet of her that can hear her must make a DC 13 Constitution saving throw. On a failure, a creature drops to 0 hit points. On a success, a creature takes 10 (3d6) psychic damage.</text>
        </action>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 108</description>
        <environment>forest, coastal</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Elliach</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
        <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
        <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
        <hp>40 (9d8)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>9</str>
        <dex>14</dex>
        <con>11</con>
        <int>17</int>
        <wis>12</wis>
        <cha>11</cha>
        <save>Int +6, Wis +4</save>
        <skill>Arcana +6, History +6</skill>
        <passive>11</passive>
        <languages>any four languages</languages>
        <cr>6</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <action>
            <name>Dagger</name>
            <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Dagger|5|1d4+2</attack>
        </action>
        <trait>
            <name>Spellcasting</name>
            <text>Elliach is a 9th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks). Elliach has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
            <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation</text>
            <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield</text>
            <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): misty step, suggestion</text>
            <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fireball, fly</text>
            <text>• 4th level (3 slots): greater invisibility, ice storm</text>
            <text>• 5th level (1 slots): cone of cold</text>
        </trait>
        <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
        <spells>fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield, misty step, suggestion, counterspell, fireball, fly, greater invisibility, ice storm, cone of cold</spells>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 130</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Feonor</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
        <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
        <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
        <hp>99 (18d8+18)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>14</dex>
        <con>12</con>
        <int>20</int>
        <wis>15</wis>
        <cha>16</cha>
        <save>Int +9, Wis +6</save>
        <skill>Arcana +13, History +13</skill>
        <passive>12</passive>
        <languages>any six languages</languages>
        <cr>12</cr>
        <resist>damage from spells; nonmagical bludgeoning, piercing, slashing (from stoneskin)</resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Resistance</name>
            <text>Feonor has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Dagger</name>
            <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Dagger|6|1d4+2</attack>
        </action>
        <trait>
            <name>Spellcasting</name>
            <text>Feonor is an 18th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks). Feonor can cast disguise self and invisibility at will and has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
            <text>At will: disguise self, invisibility</text>
            <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp</text>
            <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, identify, mage armor*, magic missile</text>
            <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step</text>
            <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fly, lightning bolt</text>
            <text>• 4th level (3 slots): banishment, fire shield, stoneskin*</text>
            <text>• 5th level (3 slots): cone of cold, scrying, wall of force</text>
            <text>• 6th level (1 slots): globe of invulnerability</text>
            <text>• 7th level (1 slots): teleport</text>
            <text>• 8th level (1 slots): mind blank*</text>
            <text>• 9th level (1 slots): time stop</text>
            <text>*Feonor casts these spells on itself before combat.</text>
        </trait>
        <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
        <spells>disguise self, invisibility, fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp, detect magic, identify, mage armor, magic missile, detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step, counterspell, fly, lightning bolt, banishment, fire shield, stoneskin, cone of cold, scrying, wall of force, globe of invulnerability, teleport, mind blank, time stop</spells>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 130</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Harkina Hunt</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
        <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
        <ac>10</ac>
        <hp>4 (1d8)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>10</dex>
        <con>10</con>
        <int>10</int>
        <wis>10</wis>
        <cha>10</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill></skill>
        <passive>10</passive>
        <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
        <cr>0</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <action>
            <name>Club</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
            <attack>Club|2|1d4</attack>
        </action>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 53</description>
        <environment>arctic, desert, coastal, grassland, hill, urban, forest</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Hellwasp Grub</name>
        <size>S</size>
        <type>beast</type>
        <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
        <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>4 (1d6+1)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>5</str>
        <dex>14</dex>
        <con>12</con>
        <int>1</int>
        <wis>7</wis>
        <cha>3</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill></skill>
        <passive>8</passive>
        <languages></languages>
        <cr>1/4</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses>blindsight 30 ft.</senses>
        <action>
            <name>Bite</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 11 Constitution saving throw or take 10 (3d6) poison damage. If the poison damage reduces the target to 0 hit points, the target is stable but poisoned for 1 hour, even after regaining hit points, and is paralyzed while poisoned in this way.</text>
            <attack>Bite|4|1d4+2</attack>
        </action>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 95</description>
        <environment>underdark, urban</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Lulu</name>
        <size>S</size>
        <type>celestial</type>
        <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
        <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>36 (8d6+8)</hp>
        <speed>walk 20 ft., fly 120 ft.</speed>
        <str>10</str>
        <dex>11</dex>
        <con>12</con>
        <int>16</int>
        <wis>19</wis>
        <cha>16</cha>
        <save>Dex +3, Con +4, Cha +6</save>
        <skill></skill>
        <passive>14</passive>
        <languages>Celestial, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
        <cr>5</cr>
        <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
        <immune>poison</immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Aura of Invulnerability</name>
            <text>An invisible aura forms a 10-foot-radius sphere around Lulu for as long as it lives. Any spell of 5th level or lower cast from outside the barrier can't affect creatures or objects within it, even if the spell is cast using a higher level spell slot. Such a spell can target creatures and objects within the barrier, but the spell has no effect on them. Similarly, the area within the barrier is excluded from the areas affected by such spells. Lulu can use an action to suppress this trait until its concentration ends (as if concentrating on a spell).</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Weapons</name>
            <text>Lulu's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Tusks</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Tusks|3|1d6</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Trumpet (3/Day)</name>
            <text>Lulu blows air through its trunk, creating a trumpet sound that can be heard out to a range of 600 feet. The trumpet also creates a 30-foot cone of energy that has one of the following effects, chosen by Lulu:</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Trumpet of Blasting</name>
            <text>Each creature in the cone must make a DC 14 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 17 (5d6) thunder damage and is deafened for 1 minute. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage and isn't deafened. Nonmagical objects in the cone that aren't being held or worn take 35 (10d6) thunder damage.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Trumpet of Sparkles</name>
            <text>Creatures in the cone must make a DC 14 Constitution saving throw, taking 22 (4d8 + 4) radiant damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. Evil creatures have disadvantage on the saving throw. Good creatures in the cone take no damage.</text>
        </action>
        <trait>
            <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
            <text>Lulu's innate spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 15). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
            <text>At will: light</text>
            <text>2/day each: bless, cure wounds, protection from evil and good</text>
            <text>1/day each: banishment, heal, raise dead, shapechange (into a golden-furred mammoth with feathered wings and a flying speed of 120 ft.), teleport (with no chance of error)</text>
        </trait>
        <spells>light, bless, cure wounds, protection from evil and good, banishment, heal, raise dead, shapechange, teleport</spells>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 5</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Mad Maggie</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>fiend</type>
        <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
        <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>112 (15d8+45)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>18</str>
        <dex>15</dex>
        <con>16</con>
        <int>16</int>
        <wis>14</wis>
        <cha>16</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill>Deception +7, Insight +6, Perception +6, Stealth +6</skill>
        <passive>16</passive>
        <languages>Abyssal, Common, Infernal, Primordial</languages>
        <cr>5</cr>
        <resist>cold, fire; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't silvered</resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune>charmed</conditionImmune>
        <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Resistance</name>
            <text>Maggie has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Night Hag Items</name>
            <text>A night hag carries two very rare magic items that she must craft for herself. If either object is lost, the night hag will go to great lengths to retrieve it, as creating a new tool takes time and effort.</text>
            <text>Heartstone: This lustrous black gem allows a night hag to become ethereal while it is in her possession. The touch of a heartstone also cures any disease. Crafting a heartstone takes 30 days.</text>
            <text>Soul Bag: When an evil humanoid dies as a result of a night hag's Nightmare Haunting, Maggie catches the soul in this black sack made of stitched flesh. A soul bag can hold only one evil soul at a time, and only the night hag who crafted the bag can catch a soul with it. Crafting a soul bag takes 7 days and a humanoid sacrifice (whose flesh is used to make the bag).</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Hag Coven</name>
            <text>When hags must work together, they form covens, in spite of their selfish natures. A coven is made up of hags of any type, all of whom are equals within the group. However, each of Maggies continues to desire more personal power.</text>
            <text>A coven consists of three hags so that any arguments between two hags can be settled by the third. If more than three hags ever come together, as might happen if two covens come into conflict, the result is usually chaos.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Hag Eye (Coven Only)</name>
            <text>A hag coven can craft a magic item called a hag eye, which is made from a real eye coated in varnish and often fitted to a pendant or other wearable item. Maggie eye is usually entrusted to a minion for safekeeping and transport. A hag in the coven can take an action to see what Maggie eye sees if Maggie eye is on the same plane of existence. A hag eye has AC 10, 1 hit point, and darkvision with a radius of 60 feet. If it is destroyed, each coven member takes 3d10 psychic damage and is blinded for 24 hours.</text>
            <text>A hag coven can have only one hag eye at a time, and creating a new one requires all three members of the coven to perform a ritual. The ritual takes 1 hour, and Maggies can't perform it while blinded. During the ritual, if Maggies take any action other than performing the ritual, they must start over.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Claws (Hag Form Only)</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d8 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
            <attack>Claws (Hag Form Only)|7|2d8+4</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Change Shape</name>
            <text>Maggie magically polymorphs into a Small or Medium female humanoid, or back into her true form. Her statistics are the same in each form. Any equipment she is wearing or carrying isn't transformed. She reverts to her true form if she dies.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Etherealness</name>
            <text>Maggie magically enters the Ethereal Plane from the Material Plane, or vice versa. To do so, Maggie must have a heartstone in her possession.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Nightmare Haunting (1/Day)</name>
            <text>While on the Ethereal Plane, Maggie magically touches a sleeping humanoid on the Material Plane. A protection from evil and good spell cast on the target prevents this contact, as does a magic circle. As long as the contact persists, the target has dreadful visions. If these visions last for at least 1 hour, the target gains no benefit from its rest, and its hit point maximum is reduced by 5 (1d10). If this effect reduces the target's hit point maximum to 0, the target dies, and if the target was evil, its soul is trapped in Maggie's soul bag. The reduction to the target's hit point maximum lasts until removed by the  greater restoration spell or similar magic.</text>
        </action>
        <trait>
            <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
            <text>Maggie's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks). She can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
            <text>At will: detect magic, magic missile</text>
            <text>2/day each: plane shift (self only), ray of enfeeblement, sleep</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Shared Spellcasting (Coven Only)</name>
            <text>While all three members of a hag coven are within 30 feet of one another, they can each cast the following spells from the wizard's spell list but must share the spell slots among themselves:</text>
            <text>• 1st level (4 slots): identify, ray of sickness</text>
            <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): hold person, locate object</text>
            <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): bestow curse, counterspell, lightning bolt</text>
            <text>• 4th level (3 slots): phantasmal killer, polymorph</text>
            <text>• 5th level (2 slots): contact other plane, scrying</text>
            <text>• 6th level (1 slots): eyebite</text>
            <text>For casting these spells, each hag is a 12th-level spellcaster that uses Intelligence as her spellcasting ability. The spell save DC is 12 + Maggie's Intelligence modifier, and the spell attack bonus is 4 + Maggie's Intelligence modifier.</text>
        </trait>
        <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1</slots>
        <spells>detect magic, magic missile, plane shift, ray of enfeeblement, sleep, identify, ray of sickness, hold person, locate object, bestow curse, counterspell, lightning bolt, phantasmal killer, polymorph, contact other plane, scrying, eyebite</spells>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 74</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Peacock</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>beast</type>
        <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
        <ac>10</ac>
        <hp>5 (1d8+1)</hp>
        <speed>walk 10 ft., fly 50 ft.</speed>
        <str>7</str>
        <dex>10</dex>
        <con>13</con>
        <int>2</int>
        <wis>12</wis>
        <cha>4</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill>Perception +3</skill>
        <passive>13</passive>
        <languages></languages>
        <cr>0</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Keen Sight and Smell</name>
            <text>The peacock has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight or smell.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Pack Tactics</name>
            <text>The peacock has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the peacock's allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Beak</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) piercing damage.</text>
            <attack>Beak|2|1d4</attack>
        </action>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 195</description>
        <environment>grassland, hill, desert</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Princeps Kovik</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>fiend (devil)</type>
        <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
        <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>85 (10d8+40)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>18</str>
        <dex>15</dex>
        <con>18</con>
        <int>11</int>
        <wis>12</wis>
        <cha>14</cha>
        <save>Con +7, Wis +4, Cha +5</save>
        <skill></skill>
        <passive>8</passive>
        <languages>Infernal, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
        <cr>8</cr>
        <resist>cold; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't silvered</resist>
        <immune>fire, poison</immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
        <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Devil's Sight</name>
            <text>Magical darkness doesn't impede Kovik's darkvision.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Magic Resistance</name>
            <text>Kovik has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>Kovik makes two attacks with its chains.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Chain</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) slashing damage. The target is grappled (escape DC 14) if Kovik isn't already grappling a creature. Until this grapple ends, the target is restrained and takes 7 (2d6) piercing damage at the start of each of its turns.</text>
            <attack>Chain|8|2d6+4</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Animate Chains (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
            <text>Up to four chains Kovik can see within 60 feet of it magically sprout razor-edged barbs and animate under Kovik's control, provided that the chains aren't being worn or carried.</text>
            <text>Each animated chain is an object with AC 20, 20 hit points, resistance to piercing damage, and immunity to psychic and thunder damage. When Kovik uses Multiattack on its turn, it can use each animated chain to make one additional chain attack. An animated chain can grapple one creature of its own but can't make attacks while grappling. An animated chain reverts to its inanimate state if reduced to 0 hit points or if Kovik is incapacitated or dies.</text>
        </action>
        <reaction>
            <name>Unnerving Mask</name>
            <text>When a creature Kovik can see starts its turn within 30 feet of Kovik, Kovik can create the illusion that it looks like one of the creature's departed loved ones or bitter enemies. If the creature can see Kovik, it must succeed on a DC 14 Wisdom saving throw or be frightened until the end of its turn.</text>
        </reaction>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 91</description>
        <environment></environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Raggadragga</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>humanoid (human, shapechanger)</type>
        <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
        <ac>10 (in humanoid form, 11 (natural armor) in boar or hybrid form)</ac>
        <hp>120 (12d8+24)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>17</str>
        <dex>10</dex>
        <con>15</con>
        <int>10</int>
        <wis>11</wis>
        <cha>8</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill>Perception +2</skill>
        <passive>12</passive>
        <languages>Common (can't speak in boar form)</languages>
        <cr>4</cr>
        <resist></resist>
        <immune>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't silvered</immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Shapechanger</name>
            <text>Raggadragga can use its action to polymorph into a boar-humanoid hybrid or into a boar, or back into its true form, which is humanoid. Its statistics, other than its AC, are the same in each form. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying isn't transformed. It reverts to its true form if it dies.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Charge (Boar or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
            <text>If Raggadragga moves at least 15 feet straight toward a target and then hits it with its tusks on the same turn, the target takes an extra 7 (2d6) slashing damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 13 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Relentless (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
            <text>If Raggadragga takes 14 damage or less that would reduce it to 0 hit points, it is reduced to 1 hit point instead.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
            <text>Raggadragga makes two attacks, only one of which can be with its tusks.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Maul (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (2d6 + 3) bludgeoning damage.</text>
            <attack>Maul (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)|5|2d6+3</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Tusks (Boar or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (2d6 + 3) slashing damage. If the target is a humanoid, it must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or be cursed with wereboar lycanthropy.</text>
            <attack>Tusks (Boar or Hybrid Form Only)|5|2d6+3</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Variant: Nonhuman Lycanthropes</name>
            <text>The statistics presented in this section assume a base creature of human. However, you can also use the statistics to represent nonhuman lycanthropes, adding verisimilitude by allowing a nonhuman lycanthrope to retain one or more of its humanoid racial traits. For example, an elf werewolf might have the Fey Ancestry trait.</text>
        </action>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 87</description>
        <environment>grassland, forest, hill</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Skeletal Rats</name>
        <size>M</size>
        <type>swarm of Medium beasts</type>
        <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
        <ac>10</ac>
        <hp>24 (7d8-7)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>9</str>
        <dex>11</dex>
        <con>9</con>
        <int>2</int>
        <wis>10</wis>
        <cha>3</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill></skill>
        <passive>10</passive>
        <languages></languages>
        <cr>1/4</cr>
        <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing</resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable></vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, prone, restrained, stunned</conditionImmune>
        <senses>darkvision 30 ft.</senses>
        <trait>
            <name>Keen Smell</name>
            <text>The swarm has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Swarm</name>
            <text>The swarm can occupy another creature's space and vice versa, and the swarm can move through any opening large enough for a Tiny rat. The swarm can't regain hit points or gain temporary hit points.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Bites</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 0 ft., one target in the swarm's space. 7 (2d6) piercing damage, or 3 (1d6) piercing damage if the swarm has half of its hit points or fewer.</text>
            <attack>Bites|2|2d6</attack>
        </action>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 23</description>
        <environment>swamp, urban</environment>
    </monster>
    <monster>
        <name>Undead Tree</name>
        <size>H</size>
        <type>plant</type>
        <alignment>Chaotic Good</alignment>
        <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
        <hp>138 (12d12+60)</hp>
        <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
        <str>23</str>
        <dex>8</dex>
        <con>21</con>
        <int>12</int>
        <wis>16</wis>
        <cha>12</cha>
        <save></save>
        <skill></skill>
        <passive>13</passive>
        <languages>Common, Druidic, Elvish, Sylvan</languages>
        <cr>9</cr>
        <resist>bludgeoning, piercing</resist>
        <immune></immune>
        <vulnerable>fire</vulnerable>
        <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
        <senses></senses>
        <trait>
            <name>False Appearance</name>
            <text>While the treant remains motionless, it is indistinguishable from a normal tree.</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Siege Monster</name>
            <text>The treant deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
        </trait>
        <action>
            <name>Multiattack</name>
            <text>The treant makes two slam attacks.</text>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Slam</name>
            <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 16 (3d6 + 6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
            <attack>Slam|10|3d6+6</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Rock</name>
            <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, range 60/180 ft., one target. 28 (4d10 + 6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
            <attack>Rock|10|4d10+6</attack>
        </action>
        <action>
            <name>Animate Trees (1/Day)</name>
            <text>The treant magically animates one or two trees it can see within 60 feet of it. These trees have the same statistics as a treant, except they have Intelligence and Charisma scores of 1, they can't speak, and they have only the Slam action option. An animated tree acts as an ally of the treant. The tree remains animate for 1 day or until it dies; until the treant dies or is more than 120 feet from the tree; or until the treant takes a bonus action to turn it back into an inanimate tree. The tree then takes root if possible.</text>
        </action>
        <description>Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 23</description>
        <environment>forest</environment>
    </monster>
</compendium>
