<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <feat>
      <name>Aberrant Dragonmark</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have manifested an aberrant dragonmark. Determine its appearance and the flaw associated with it. You gain the following benefits:
• You learn a cantrip of your choice from the sorcerer spell list. In addition, choose a 1st-level spell from the sorcerer spell list. You learn that spell and can cast it through your mark. Once you cast it, you must finish a short or long rest before you can cast it again through the mark. Constitution is your spellcasting ability for these spells.
• When you cast the 1st-level spell through your mark, you can expend one of your Hit Dice and roll it. If you roll an even number, you gain a number of temporary hit points equal to the number rolled. If you roll an odd number, one random creature within 30 feet of you (not including you) takes force damage equal to the number rolled. If no other creatures are in range, you take the damage.
You also develop a random flaw from the Aberrant Dragonmark Flaws table.
Aberrant Dragonmark Flaws
d8 | Flaw
1 | Your mark is a source of constant physical pain.
2 | Your mark whispers to you. Its meaning can be unclear.
3 | When you're stressed, the mark hisses audibly.
4 | The skin around the mark is burned, scaly, or withered.
5 | Animals are uneasy around you.
6 | You have a mood swing any time you use your mark.
7 | Your looks change slightly whenever you use the mark.
8 | You have horrific nightmares after you use your mark.

Source: Eberron: Rising from the Last War p. 52, Wayfinder's Guide to Eberron p. 112</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Constitution +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Acrobat (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You become more nimble, gaining the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Acrobat (UA)ics skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• As a bonus action, you can make a DC 15 Dexterity (Acrobat (UA)ics) check. If you succeed, difficult terrain doesn't cost you extra movement until the end of the current turn.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 1</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Dexterity +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Actor</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Skilled at mimicry and dramatics, you gain the following benefits:
• You have advantage on Charisma (Deception) and Charisma (Performance) checks when trying to pass yourself off as a different person.
• You can mimic the speech of another person or the sounds made by other creatures. You must have heard the person speaking, or heard the creature make the sound, for at least 1 minute. A successful Wisdom (Insight) check contested by your Charisma (Deception) check allows a listener to determine that the effect is faked.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 165</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Charisma +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Alchemist (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have studied the secrets of alchemy and are an expert in its practice, gaining the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency with Alchemist (UA)'s supplies. If you are already proficient with them, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with them.
• As an action, you can identify one potion within 5 feet of you, as if you had tasted it. You must see the liquid for this benefit to work.
• Over the course of any short rest, you can temporarily improve the potency of one potion of healing of any rarity. To use this benefit, you must have Alchemist (UA)'s supplies with you, and the potion must be within reach. If the potion is drunk no more than 1 hour after the short rest ends, the creature drinking the potion can forgo the potion's die roll and regains the maximum number of hit points that the potion can restore.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats p. 4</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Intelligence +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Alert</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Always on the lookout for danger, you gain the following benefits:
• You gain a +5 bonus to initiative.
• You can't be surprised while you are conscious.
• Other creatures don't gain advantage on attack rolls against you as a result of being unseen by you.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 165</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Animal Handler (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You master the techniques needed to train and handle animals. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Animal Handling skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• You can use a bonus action on your turn to command one friendly beast within 60 feet of you that can hear you and that isn't currently following the command of someone else. You decide now what action the beast will take and where it will move during its next turn, or you issue a general command that lasts for 1 minute, such as to guard a particular area.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 1</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Wisdom +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Arcanist (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You study the arcane arts, gaining the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Arcana skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• You learn the prestidigitation and detect magic spells. You can cast detect magic once without expending a spell slot, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 1</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Intelligence +1</modifier>
    <proficiency>Arcana</proficiency>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Artificer Initiate (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You've learned some of an artificer's inventiveness, granting you the following benefits:
• You learn one cantrip of your choice from the artificer spell list, and you learn one 1st-level spell of your choice from that list. Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for these spells. Whenever you gain a level, you can replace one of these spells with another spell of the same level from the artificer spell list.
• You can cast this feat's 1st-level spell without a spell slot, and you must finish a long rest before you can cast it in this way again. You can also cast the spell using any spell slots you have.
• You gain proficiency with one type of artisan's tools of your choice, and you can use that type of tool as a spellcasting focus for any spell you cast that uses Intelligence as its spellcasting ability
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Feats p. 1</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Athlete</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have undergone extensive physical training to gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Dexterity score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• When you are prone, standing up uses only 5 feet of your movement.
• Climbing doesn't cost you extra movement.
• You can make a running long jump or a running high jump after moving only 5 feet on foot, rather than 10 feet.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 165</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Barbed Hide (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Tiefling</prerequisite>
    <text>One of your ancestors was a barbed devil or other spiky fiend. Barbs protrude from your head. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Constitution or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• As a bonus action, you can cause small barbs to protrude all over your body or cause them to retract. At the start of each of your turns while the barbs are out, you deal 1d6 piercing damage to any creature grappling you or any creature grappled by you.
• You gain proficiency in the Intimidation skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 1</text>
    <proficiency>Intimidation</proficiency>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Blade Mastery (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You master the shortsword, longsword, scimitar, rapier, and greatsword. You gain the following benefits when using any of them:
• You gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls you make with the weapon.
• On your turn, you can use your reaction to assume a parrying stance, provided you have the weapon in hand. Doing so grants you a +1 bonus to your AC until the start of your next turn or until you're not holding the weapon.
• When you make an opportunity attack with the weapon, you have advantage on the attack roll.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats p. 2</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Bountiful Luck (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Halfling</prerequisite>
    <text>Whenever an ally you can see within 30 feet of you rolls a 1 on the d20 for an attack roll, an ability check, or a saving throw, you can use your reaction to let the ally reroll the die. The ally must use the new roll.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 1</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Bountiful Luck</name>
    <prerequisite>Halfling</prerequisite>
    <text>Your people have extraordinary luck, which you have learned to mystically lend to your companions when you see them falter. You're not sure how you do it; you just wish it, and it happens. Surely a sign of fortune's favor!
When an ally you can see within 30 feet of you rolls a 1 on the d20 for an attack roll, an ability check, or a saving throw, you can use your reaction to let the ally reroll the die. The ally must use the new roll.
When you use this ability, you can't use your Lucky racial trait before the end of your next turn.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 73</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Brawny (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You become stronger, gaining the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Athletics skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• You count as if you were one size larger for the purpose of determining your carrying capacity.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 1</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Strength +1</modifier>
    <proficiency>Athletics</proficiency>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Burglar (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You pride yourself on your quickness and your close study of certain clandestine activities. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency with thieves' tools. If you are already proficient with them, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with them.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats p. 4</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Dexterity +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Charger</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>When you use your action to Dash, you can use a bonus action to make one melee weapon attack or to shove a creature.
If you move at least 10 feet in a straight line immediately before taking this bonus action, you either gain a +5 bonus to the attack's damage roll (if you chose to make a melee attack and hit) or push the target up to 10 feet away from you (if you chose to shove and you succeed).
Source: Player's Handbook p. 165</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Chef (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Time and effort spent mastering the culinary arts has paid off. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Constitution or Wisdom score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• You gain proficiency with cook's utensils if you don't already have it.
• As part of a short rest, you can cook special food, provided you have ingredients and cook's utensils on hand. You can prepare enough of this food for a number of creatures equal to 4 + your proficiency bonus. At the end of the short rest, any creature who eats the food and spends one or more Hit Dice to regain hit points regains an extra 1d8 hit points.
• With one hour of work or when you finish a long rest, you can cook a number of treats equal to your proficiency bonus. These special treats last 8 hours after being made. A creature can use a bonus action to eat one of those treats to gain temporary hit points equal to your proficiency bonus.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Feats p. 1</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Critter Friend (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Gnome (Forest)</prerequisite>
    <text>Your friendship with animals mystically deepens. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Animal Handling skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• You learn the speak with animals spell and can cast it at will, without expending a spell slot. You also learn the animal friendship spell, and you can cast it once with this feat, without expending a spell slot. You regain the ability to cast it in this way when you finish a long rest. Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for these spells.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 1</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Crossbow Expert</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Thanks to extensive practice with the crossbow, you gain the following benefits:
• You ignore the loading quality of crossbows with which you are proficient.
• Being within 5 feet of a hostile creature doesn't impose disadvantage on your ranged attack rolls.
• When you use the Attack action and attack with a one-handed weapon, you can use a bonus action to attack with a hand crossbow you are holding.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 165</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Crusher (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You are practiced in the art of crushing your enemies, granting you the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Dexterity score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• Once per turn, when you hit a creature with an attack that deals bludgeoning damage, you can move it 5 feet to an unoccupied space, provided the target is no more than one size larger than you.
• When you score a critical hit that deals bludgeoning damage to a creature, attack rolls against that creature are made with advantage until the end of your next turn.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Feats p. 1</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Defensive Duelist</name>
    <prerequisite>Dexterity 13 or higher</prerequisite>
    <text>When you are wielding a finesse weapon with which you are proficient and another creature hits you with a melee attack, you can use your reaction to add your proficiency bonus to your AC for that attack, potentially causing the attack to miss you.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 165</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Diplomat (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You master the arts of diplomacy, gaining the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Persuasion skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• If you spend 1 minute talking to someone who can understand what you say, you can make a Charisma (Persuasion) check contested by the creature's Wisdom (Insight) check. If you or your companions are fighting the creature, your check automatically fails. If your check succeeds, the target is charmed by you as long as it remains within 60 feet of you and for 1 minute thereafter.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 2</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Charisma +1</modifier>
    <proficiency>Persuasion</proficiency>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragon Fear (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Dragonborn</prerequisite>
    <text>When angered, you radiate menace. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• Instead of exhaling destructive energy, you can roar and expend a use of your breath weapon to force each creature of your choice within 30 feet of you to make a Wisdom saving throw (DC 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Charisma modifier). A target automatically succeeds if it can't hear or see you. On a failed save, a target becomes frightened for 1 minute. If the frightened target takes any damage, it can repeat the saving throw, ending the effect on itself on a success.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 2</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragon Fear</name>
    <prerequisite>Dragonborn</prerequisite>
    <text>When angered, you radiate menace. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Constitution or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• Instead of exhaling destructive energy, you can expend a use of your Breath Weapon trait to roar, forcing each creature of your choice within 30 feet of you to make a Wisdom saving throw (DC 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Charisma modifier). A target automatically succeeds on the save if it can't hear or see you. On a failed save, a target becomes frightened of you for 1 minute. If the frightened target takes any damage, it can repeat the saving throw, ending the effect on itself on a success.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 74</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragon Hide (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Dragonborn</prerequisite>
    <text>You inherited the might and majesty of your dragon ancestors. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• You grow retractable claws from the tips of your fingers. Extending or retracting the claws requires no action. The claws are natural weapons, which you can use to make unarmed strikes. If you hit with them, you deal slashing damage equal to 1d4 + your Strength modifier, instead of the bludgeoning damage normal for an unarmed strike.
• Your scales harden; you gain a +1 bonus to AC while you aren't wearing armor.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 2</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragon Hide</name>
    <prerequisite>Dragonborn</prerequisite>
    <text>You manifest scales and claws reminiscent of your draconic ancestors. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Constitution or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• Your scales harden. While you aren't wearing armor, you can calculate your AC as 13 + your Dexterity modifier. You can use a shield and still gain this benefit.
• You grow retractable claws from the tips of your fingers. Extending or retracting the claws requires no action. The claws are natural weapons, which you can use to make unarmed strikes. If you hit with them, you deal slashing damage equal to 1d4 + your Strength modifier, instead of the normal bludgeoning damage for an unarmed strike.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 74</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragon Wings (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Dragonborn</prerequisite>
    <text>You sprout draconic wings. With your wings, you have a flying speed of 20 feet if you aren't wearing heavy armor and aren't exceeding your carrying capacity.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 2</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Detection (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Half-Elf</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Detection, the dragonmark of House Medani, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Wisdom as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: detect magic, mage hand
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: detect thoughts
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: clairvoyance
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Finding (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Half-Orc, Human</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Finding, the dragonmark of House Tharashk, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Wisdom as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: identify, mage hand
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: locate object
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: clairvoyance
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Handling (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Human</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Handling, the dragonmark of House Vadalis, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Wisdom as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: druidcraft, speak with animals
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: beast sense
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: conjure animals
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Healing (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Halfling</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Healing, the dragonmark of House Jorasco, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Wisdom as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: cure wounds, spare the dying
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: lesser restoration
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: revivify
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Hospitality (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Halfling</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Hospitality, the dragonmark of House Ghallanda, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Charisma as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: friends, unseen servant
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: rope trick
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: Leomund's tiny hut
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Making (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Human</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Making, the dragonmark of House Cannith, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Intelligence as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: identify, mending
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: magic weapon
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: fabricate
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Passage (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Human</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Passage, the dragonmark of House Orien, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Intelligence as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: expeditious retreat, light
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: misty step
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: teleportation circle
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Scribing (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Gnome</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Scribing, the dragonmark of House Sivis, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Intelligence as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: comprehend languages, message
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: sending
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: tongues
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Sentinel (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Human</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Sentinel, the dragonmark of House Deneith, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Wisdom as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: blade ward, compelled duel
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: blur
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: protection from energy
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Shadow (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Elf</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Shadow, the dragonmark of House Phiarlan and House Thuranni, and are a member of one of those houses.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Charisma as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: dancing lights, disguise self
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: darkness
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: nondetection
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Storm (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Half-Elf</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Storm, the dragonmark of House Lyrander, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Intelligence as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: fog cloud, shocking grasp
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: gust of wind
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: sleet storm
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dragonmark of Warding (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Dwarf</prerequisite>
    <text>Your have the magical mark of Warding, the dragonmark of House Kundarak, and are a member of that house.
You gain the ability to innately cast spells and cantrips, using Intelligence as your spellcasting ability. You cast each spell at its lowest level. Once you cast a given spell this way, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it innately again. You must still expend any material components. Your dragonmark confers the following benefits:
Least Dragonmark: When you first take this feat, you gain the least dragonmark. You learn the following spells: alarm, resistance
Lesser Dragonmark: At 5th level and higher, your mark becomes more potent, improving to lesser dragonmark. You learn the following spell: arcane lock
Greater Dragonmark: At 9th level and higher, your mark's power increases again, becoming a greater dragonmark. You learn the following spell: magic circle
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eberron p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Drow High Magic (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Elf (Drow)</prerequisite>
    <text>You learn more of the spells typical for your people. You learn detect magic and can cast it at will, without expending a spell slot. You also learn levitate and dispel magic, each of which you can cast once without expending a spell slot. You regain the ability to cast the spell in this way when you finish a long rest. Charisma is your spellcasting ability for these spells.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 2</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Drow High Magic</name>
    <prerequisite>Elf (Drow)</prerequisite>
    <text>You learn more of the magic typical of dark elves. You learn the detect magic spell and can cast it at will, without expending a spell slot. You also learn levitate and dispel magic, each of which you can cast once without expending a spell slot. You regain the ability to cast those two spells in this way when you finish a long rest. Charisma is your spellcasting ability for all three spells.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 74</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dual Wielder</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You master fighting with two weapons, gaining the following benefits:
• You gain a +1 bonus to AC while you are wielding a separate melee weapon in each hand.
• You can use two-weapon fighting even when the one-handed melee weapons you are wielding aren't light.
• You can draw or stow two one-handed weapons when you would normally be able to draw or stow only one.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 165</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dungeon Delver</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Alert to the hidden traps and secret doors found in many dungeons, you gain the following benefits:
• You have advantage on Wisdom (Perception) and Intelligence (Investigation) checks made to detect the presence of secret doors.
• You have advantage on saving throws made to avoid or resist traps.
• You have resistance to the damage dealt by traps.
• Traveling at a fast pace doesn't impose the normal -5 penalty on your passive Wisdom (Perception) score.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 166</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Durable</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Hardy and resilient, you gain the following benefits:
• When you roll a Hit Die to regain hit points, the minimum number of hit points you regain from the roll equals twice your Constitution modifier (minimum of 2).
Source: Player's Handbook p. 166</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Constitution +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dwarf Resilience (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Dwarf</prerequisite>
    <text>You have the blood of dwarf heroes flowing through your veins. You gain the following benefits:
• Whenever you take the Dodge action in combat, you can spend one Hit Die to heal yourself. Roll the die, add your Constitution modifier, and regain a number of hit points equal to the total (minimum of 1).
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 2</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Constitution +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Dwarven Fortitude</name>
    <prerequisite>Dwarf</prerequisite>
    <text>You have the blood of dwarf heroes flowing through your veins. You gain the following benefits:
• Whenever you take the Dodge action in combat, you can spend one Hit Die to heal yourself. Roll the die, add your Constitution modifier, and regain a number of hit points equal to the total (minimum of 1).
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 74</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Constitution +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Eldritch Adept (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Studying occult lore, you have unlocked eldritch power within yourself: you learn one Eldritch Invocation option of your choice from the warlock class. If the invocation has a prerequisite, you can choose that invocation only if you're a warlock and only if you meet the prerequisite.
Whenever you gain a level, you can replace the invocation with another one from the warlock class.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Feats p. 1</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Elemental Adept</name>
    <prerequisite>The ability to cast at least one spell</prerequisite>
    <text>When you gain this feat, choose one of the following damage types: acid, cold, fire, lightning, or thunder.
Spells you cast ignore resistance to damage of the chosen type. In addition, when you roll damage for a spell you cast that deals damage of that type, you can treat any 1 on a damage die as a 2.
You can select this feat multiple times. Each time you do so, you must choose a different damage type.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 166</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Elven Accuracy (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Elf, Half-Elf</prerequisite>
    <text>You have uncanny aim. You gain the following benefits:
• Whenever you have advantage on an attack roll, you can reroll one of the dice once.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 2</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Dexterity +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Elven Accuracy</name>
    <prerequisite>Elf, Half-Elf</prerequisite>
    <text>The accuracy of elves is legendary, especially that of elf archers and spellcasters. You have uncanny aim with attacks that rely on precision rather than brute force. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Dexterity or Intelligence or Wisdom or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• Whenever you have advantage on an attack roll using Dexterity, Intelligence, Wisdom, or Charisma, you can reroll one of the dice once.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 74</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Empathic (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You possess keen insight into how other people think and feel. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Insight skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• You can use your action to try to get uncanny insight about one humanoid you can see within 30 feet of you. Make a Wisdom (Insight) check contested by the target's Charisma (Deception) check. If your check succeeds, you have advantage on attack rolls and ability checks against the target until the end of your next turn.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 2</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Wisdom +1</modifier>
    <proficiency>Insight</proficiency>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Everybody's Friend (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Half-Elf</prerequisite>
    <text>You develop your magnetic personality to ease your way through the world. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Deception and Persuasion skills. If you're already proficient in either skill, your proficiency bonus is doubled for any check you make with that skill.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 2</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Charisma +1</modifier>
    <proficiency>, Persuasion</proficiency>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Fade Away (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Gnome</prerequisite>
    <text>You can draw on your magical heritage to escape danger. You gain the following benefits:
• When you take damage, you can use a reaction to magically become invisible until the end of your next turn or until you attack, deal damage, or force someone to make a saving throw. Once you use this ability, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 2</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Intelligence +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Fade Away</name>
    <prerequisite>Gnome</prerequisite>
    <text>Your people are clever, with a knack for illusion magic. You have learned a magical trick for fading away when you suffer harm. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Dexterity or Intelligence score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• Immediately after you take damage, you can use a reaction to magically become invisible until the end of your next turn or until you attack, deal damage, or force someone to make a saving throw. Once you use this ability, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 74</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Fell Handed (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You master the handaxe, battleaxe, greataxe, warhammer, and maul. You gain the following benefits when using any of them:
• You gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls you make with the weapon.
• Whenever you have advantage on a melee attack roll you make with the weapon and hit, you can knock the target prone if the lower of the two d20 rolls would also hit the target.
• Whenever you have disadvantage on a melee attack roll you make with the weapon, the target takes bludgeoning damage equal to your Strength modifier (minimum of 0) if the attack misses but the higher of the two d20 rolls would have hit.
• If you use the Help action to aid an ally's melee attack while you're wielding the weapon, you knock the target's shield aside momentarily. In addition to the ally gaining advantage on the attack roll, the ally gains a +2 bonus to the roll if the target is using a shield.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats p. 2</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Fey Teleportation (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Elf (High)</prerequisite>
    <text>Drawing on your fey ancestry, you have learned how to teleport. You gain the following benefits:
• You learn the misty step spell and can cast it once without expending a spell slot. You regain the ability to cast it in this way when you finish a short or long rest. Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for this spell.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 3</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Intelligence +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Fey Teleportation</name>
    <prerequisite>Elf (High)</prerequisite>
    <text>Your study of high elven lore has unlocked fey power that few other elves possess, except your eladrin cousins. Drawing on your fey ancestry, you can momentarily stride through the Feywild to shorten your path from one place to another. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Intelligence or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• You learn to speak, read, and write Sylvan.
• You learn the misty step spell and can cast it once without expending a spell slot. You regain the ability to cast it in this way when you finish a short or long rest. Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for this spell.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 74</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Fey Touched (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Your exposure to the Feywild or one of its denizens has left a magical mark on you. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Intelligence or Wisdom or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• You learn the misty step spell and one 1st-level spell of your choice. The 1st-level spell must be from the divination or enchantment school of magic. You can cast each of these spells without expending a spell slot. Once you cast either of these spells in this way, you can't cast that spell in this way again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast these spells using spell slots you have of the appropriate level. The spells' spellcasting ability is the ability increased by this feat.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Feats p. 2</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Fighting Initiate (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Proficiency with martial weapon</prerequisite>
    <text>Your martial training has helped you develop a particular style of fighting. As a result, you learn one Fighting Style option of your choice from the fighter class. If you already have a style, the one you choose must be different.
Whenever you gain a level, you can replace this feat's fighting style with another one from the fighter class that you don't have.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Feats p. 2</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Flail Mastery (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>The flail is a tricky weapon to use, but you have spent countless hours mastering it. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls you make with a flail.
• As a bonus action on your turn, you can prepare yourself to extend your flail to sweep over targets' shield. Until the end of this turn, your attack rolls with a flail gain a +2 bonus against any target using a shield.
• When you hit with an opportunity attack using a flail, the target must succeed on a Strength saving throw (DC 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Strength modifier) or be knocked prone.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats p. 3</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Flames of Phlegethos (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Tiefling</prerequisite>
    <text>You learn to call on hellfire to serve your commands. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Intelligence or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• When you roll fire damage for a spell you cast, you can reroll any roll of 1 on the fire damage dice, but you must use the new roll, even if it is another 1.
• Whenever you cast a spell that deals fire damage, you can cause flames to wreathe you until the end of your next turn. The flames don't harm you or your possessions, and they shed bright light out to 30 feet and dim light for an additional 30 feet. While the flames are present, any creature within 5 feet of you that hits you with a melee attack takes 1d4 fire damage.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 3</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Flames of Phlegethos</name>
    <prerequisite>Tiefling</prerequisite>
    <text>You learn to call on hellfire to serve your commands. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Intelligence or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• When you roll fire damage for a spell you cast, you can reroll any roll of 1 on the fire damage dice, but you must use the new roll, even if it is another 1.
• Whenever you cast a spell that deals fire damage, you can cause flames to wreathe you until the end of your next turn. The flames don't harm you or your possessions, and they shed bright light out to 30 feet and dim light for an additional 30 feet. While the flames are present, any creature within 5 feet of you that hits you with a melee attack takes 1d4 fire damage.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 74</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Gourmand (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have mastered a variety of special recipes, allowing you to prepare exotic dishes with useful effects. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency with cook's utensils. If you are already proficient with them, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with them.
• As an action, you can inspect a drink or plate of food within 5 feet of you and determine whether it is poisoned, provided that you can see and smell it.
• During a long rest, you can prepare and serve a meal that helps you and your allies recover from the rigors of adventuring, provided you have suitable food, cook's utensils, and other supplies on hand. The meal serves up to six people, and each person who eats it regains two additional Hit Dice at the end of the long rest. In addition, those who partake of the meal have advantage on Constitution saving throws against disease for the next 24 hours.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats p. 4</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Constitution +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Grappler</name>
    <prerequisite>Strength 13 or higher</prerequisite>
    <text>You've developed the skills necessary to hold your own in close-quarters grappling. You gain the following benefits:
• You have advantage on attack rolls against a creature you are grappling.
• You can use your action to try to pin a creature grappled by you. To do so, make another grapple check. If you succeed, you and the creature are both restrained until the grapple ends.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 167</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Great Weapon Master</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You've learned to put the weight of a weapon to your advantage, letting its momentum empower your strikes. You gain the following benefits:
• On your turn, when you score a critical hit with a melee weapon or reduce a creature to 0 hit points with one, you can make one melee weapon attack as a bonus action.
• Before you make a melee attack with a heavy weapon that you are proficient with, you can choose to take a -5 penalty to the attack roll. If the attack hits, you add +10 to the attack's damage.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 167</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Grudge-Bearer (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Dwarf</prerequisite>
    <text>You have a deep hatred for a particular kind of creature. Choose your foes, a type of creature to bear the burden of your wrath: aberrations, beasts, celestials, constructs, dragons, elementals, fey, fiends, giants, monstrosities, oozes, plants, or undead. Alternatively, you can choose two races of humanoid (such as gnolls and orcs). You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Constitution or Wisdom score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• During the first round of any combat against your chosen foes, your attack rolls against any of them have advantage.
• When any of your chosen foes makes an opportunity attack against you, it makes the attack roll with disadvantage.
• Whenever you make an Intelligence (Arcana, History, Nature, or Religion) check to recall information about your chosen foes, you add double your proficiency bonus to the check, even if you're not normally proficient.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 3</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Gunner (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have a quick hand and keen eye when employing firearms, granting you the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency with firearms (see "Firearms" in the Dungeon Master's Guide).
• You ignore the loading property of firearms.
• Being within 5 feet of a hostile creature doesn't impose disadvantage on your ranged attack rolls.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Feats p. 2</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Dexterity +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Healer</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You are an able physician, allowing you to mend wounds quickly and get your allies back in the fight. You gain the following benefits:
• When you use a healer's kit to stabilize a dying creature, that creature also regains 1 hit point.
• As an action, you can spend one use of a healer's kit to tend to a creature and restore 1d6 + 4 hit points to it, plus additional hit points equal to the creature's maximum number of Hit Dice. The creature can't regain hit points from this feat again until it finishes a short or long rest.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 167</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Heavily Armored</name>
    <prerequisite>Proficiency with medium armor</prerequisite>
    <text>You have trained to master the use of heavy armor, gaining the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency with heavy armor.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 167</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Strength +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Heavy Armor Master</name>
    <prerequisite>Proficiency with heavy armor</prerequisite>
    <text>You can use your armor to deflect strikes that would kill others. You gain the following benefits:
• While you are wearing heavy armor, bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage that you take from nonmagical weapons is reduced by 3.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 167</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Strength +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Historian (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Your study of history rewards you with the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the History skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• When you take the Help action to aid another creature's ability check, you can make a DC 15 Intelligence (History) check. On a success, that creature's check gains a bonus equal to your proficiency bonus, as you share pertinent advice and historical examples. To receive this bonus, the creature must be able to understand what you're saying.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 2</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Intelligence +1</modifier>
    <proficiency>History</proficiency>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Human Determination (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Human</prerequisite>
    <text>You are filled with a determination that can draw the unreachable within your reach. You gain the following benefits:
• When you make an attack roll, an ability check, or a saving throw, you can do so with advantage. Once you use this ability, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 3</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Infernal Constitution (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Tiefling</prerequisite>
    <text>Fiendish blood runs strong in you. You gain the following benefits:
• You have resistance to cold and poison damage.
• You have advantage on saving throws against being poisoned.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 3</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Constitution +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Infernal Constitution</name>
    <prerequisite>Tiefling</prerequisite>
    <text>Fiendish blood runs strong in you, unlocking a resilience akin to that possessed by some fiends. You gain the following benefits:
• You have resistance to cold and poison damage.
• You have advantage on saving throws against being poisoned.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 75</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Constitution +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Inspiring Leader</name>
    <prerequisite>Charisma 13 or higher</prerequisite>
    <text>You can spend 10 minutes inspiring your companions, shoring up their resolve to fight. When you do so, choose up to six friendly creatures (which can include yourself) within 30 feet of you who can see or hear you and who can understand you. Each creature can gain temporary hit points equal to your level + your Charisma modifier. A creature can't gain temporary hit points from this feat again until it has finished a short or long rest.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 167</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Investigator (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have an eye for detail and can pick out the smallest clues. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Investigation skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• You can take the Search action as a bonus action.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 2</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Intelligence +1</modifier>
    <proficiency>Investigation</proficiency>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Keen Mind</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have a mind that can track time, direction, and detail with uncanny precision. You gain the following benefits:
• You always know which way is north.
• You always know the number of hours left before the next sunrise or sunset.
• You can accurately recall anything you have seen or heard within the past month.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 167</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Intelligence +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Lightly Armored</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have trained to master the use of light armor, gaining the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Dexterity score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• You gain proficiency with light armor.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 167</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Linguist</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have studied languages and codes, gaining the following benefits:
• You learn three languages of your choice.
• You can ably create written ciphers. Others can't decipher a code you create unless you teach them, they succeed on an Intelligence check (DC equal to your Intelligence score + your proficiency bonus), or they use magic to decipher it.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 167</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Intelligence +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Lucky</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have inexplicable luck that seems to kick in at just the right moment.
You have 3 luck points. Whenever you make an attack roll, an ability check, or a saving throw, you can spend one luck point to roll an additional d20. You can choose to spend one of your luck points after you roll the die, but before the outcome is determined. You choose which of the d20s is used for the attack roll, ability check, or saving throw.
You can also spend one luck point when an attack roll is made against you. Roll a d20, and then choose whether the attack uses the attacker's roll or yours. If more than one creature spends a luck point to influence the outcome of a roll, the points cancel each other out; no additional dice are rolled.
You regain your expended luck points when you finish a long rest.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 167</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Mage Slayer</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have practiced techniques useful in melee combat against spellcasters, gaining the following benefits:
• When a creature within 5 feet of you casts a spell, you can use your reaction to make a melee weapon attack against that creature.
• When you damage a creature that is concentrating on a spell, that creature has disadvantage on the saving throw it makes to maintain its concentration.
• You have advantage on saving throws against spells cast by creatures within 5 feet of you.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 168</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Magic Initiate</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Choose a class: bard, cleric, druid, sorcerer, warlock, or wizard. You learn two cantrips of your choice from that class's spell list.
In addition, choose one 1st-level spell from that same list. You learn that spell and can cast it at its lowest level. Once you cast it, you must finish a long rest before you can cast it again using this feat.
Your spellcasting ability for these spells depends on the class you chose: Charisma for bard, sorcerer, or warlock; Wisdom for cleric or druid; or Intelligence for wizard.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 168</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Martial Adept</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have martial training that allows you to perform special combat maneuvers. You gain the following benefits:
• You learn two maneuvers of your choice from among those available to the fighter archetype in the fighter class. If a maneuver you use requires your target to make a saving throw to resist the maneuver's effects, the saving throw DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Strength or Dexterity modifier (your choice).
• You gain one superiority die, which is a d6 (this die is added to any superiority dice you have from another source). This die is used to fuel your maneuvers. A superiority die is expended when you use it. You regain your expended superiority dice when you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 168</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Master of Disguise (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have honed your ability to shape your personality and to read the personalities of others. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency with the disguise kit. If you are already proficient with it, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• If you spend 1 hour observing a creature, you can then spend 8 hours crafting a disguise you can quickly don to mimic that creature. Making the disguise requires a disguise kit. You must make checks as normal to disguise yourself, but you can assume the disguise as an action.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats p. 4</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Charisma +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Medic (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You master the physician's arts, gaining the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Medic (UA)ine skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• During a short rest, you can clean and bind the wounds of up to six willing beasts and humanoids. Make a DC 15 Wisdom (Medic (UA)ine) check for each creature. On a success, if a creature spends a Hit Die during this rest, that creature can forgo the roll and instead regain the maximum number of hit points the die can restore. A creature can do so only once per rest, regardless of how many Hit Dice it spends.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 2</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Wisdom +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Medium Armor Master</name>
    <prerequisite>Proficiency with medium armor</prerequisite>
    <text>You have practiced moving in medium armor to gain the following benefits:
• Wearing medium armor doesn't impose disadvantage on your Dexterity (Stealth) checks.
• When you wear medium armor, you can add 3, rather than 2, to your AC if you have a Dexterity of 16 or higher.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 168</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Menacing (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You become fearsome to others, gaining the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Intimidation skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• When you take the Attack action on your turn, you can replace one attack with an attempt to demoralize one humanoid you can see within 30 feet of you that can see and hear you. Make a Charisma (Intimidation) check contested by the target's Wisdom (Insight) check. If your check succeeds, the target is frightened until the end of your next turn. If your check fails, the target can't be frightened by you in this way for 1 hour.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 2</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Charisma +1</modifier>
    <proficiency>Intimidation</proficiency>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Metabolic Control (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have refined psionic control over your body's functions.
• Increase your Strength or Dexterity or Constitution score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• If your Psionic Talent die is available, you can take an action to channel your psionic power to nourish yourself for the next 24 hours, as if you consumed sufficient food and water for a day. When you take this action, your Psionic Talent die decreases by one die size.
• If your Psionic Talent die is available, you can meditate for 1 minute, at the end of which you gain the benefits of finishing a short rest, and your Psionic Talent die decreases by one die size. You can't meditate in this way again until you finish a long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 8</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Metamagic Adept (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You've learned how to exert your will on your spells to alter how they function. You gain the following benefits:
• You learn two Metamagic options of your choice from the sorcerer class. You can use only one Metamagic option on a spell when you cast it, unless the option says otherwise. Whenever you gain a level, you can replace one of your Metamagic options with another one from the sorcerer class.
• You gain 2 sorcery points to spend on Metamagic (these points are added to any sorcery points you have from another source but can be used only on Metamagic). You regain all spent sorcery points when you finish a long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Feats p. 2</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Mobile</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You are exceptionally speedy and agile. You gain the following benefits:
• Your speed increases by 10 feet.
• When you use the Dash action, difficult terrain doesn't cost you extra movement on that turn.
• When you make a melee attack against a creature, you don't provoke opportunity attacks from that creature for the rest of the turn, whether you hit or not.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 168</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Moderately Armored</name>
    <prerequisite>Proficiency with light armor</prerequisite>
    <text>You have trained to master the use of medium armor and shields, gaining the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Dexterity score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• You gain proficiency with medium armor and shields.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 168</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Mounted Combatant</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You are a dangerous foe to face while mounted. While you are mounted and aren't incapacitated, you gain the following benefits:
• You have advantage on melee attack rolls against any unmounted creature that is smaller than your mount.
• You can force an attack targeted at your mount to target you instead.
• If your mount is subjected to an effect that allows it to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, it instead takes no damage if it succeeds on the saving throw, and only half damage if it fails.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 168</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Naturalist (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Your extensive study of nature rewards you with the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Nature skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• You learn the druidcraft and detect poison and disease spells. You can cast detect poison and disease once without expending a spell slot, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 3</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Intelligence +1</modifier>
    <proficiency>Nature</proficiency>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Observant</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Quick to notice details of your environment, you gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Intelligence or Wisdom score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• If you can see a creature's mouth while it is speaking a language you understand, you can interpret what it's saying by reading its lips.
• You have a +5 bonus to your passive Wisdom (Perception) and passive Intelligence (Investigation) scores.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 168</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Orcish Aggression (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Half-Orc</prerequisite>
    <text>As a bonus action, you can move up to your speed toward an enemy of your choice that you can see or hear. You must end this move closer to the enemy than you started.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 3</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Orcish Fury (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Half-Orc</prerequisite>
    <text>Your fury burns tirelessly. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Constitution score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• When you hit with an attack made with a simple or martial weapon, you can roll one of the weapon's damage dice an additional time and add it as extra damage of the weapon's damage type. Once you use this ability, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.
• Immediately after you use your Relentless Endurance trait, you can use your reaction to make one weapon attack.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 4</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Orcish Fury</name>
    <prerequisite>Half-Orc</prerequisite>
    <text>Your fury burns tirelessly. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Constitution score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• When you hit with an attack using a simple or martial weapon, you can roll one of the weapon's damage dice an additional time and add it as extra damage of the weapon's damage type. Once you use this ability, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.
• Immediately after you use your Relentless Endurance trait, you can use your reaction to make one weapon attack.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 75</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Perceptive (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You hone your senses until they become razor sharp. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Perception skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• Being in a lightly obscured area doesn't impose disadvantage on your Wisdom (Perception) checks if you can both see and hear.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 3</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Wisdom +1</modifier>
    <proficiency>Perception</proficiency>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Performer (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You master performance so that you can command any stage. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Performance skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• While performing, you can try to distract one humanoid you can see who can see and hear you. Make a Charisma (Performance) check contested by the humanoid's Wisdom (Insight) check. If your check succeeds, you grab the humanoid's attention enough that it makes Wisdom (Perception) and Intelligence (Investigation) checks with disadvantage until you stop performing.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 3</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Charisma +1</modifier>
    <proficiency>Performance</proficiency>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Piercer (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have achieved a penetrating precision in combat, granting you the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Dexterity score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• Once per turn, when you hit a creature with an attack that deals piercing damage, you can reroll one of the attack's damage dice, and you must use the new roll.
• When you score a critical hit that deals piercing damage to a creature, you can roll one additional damage die when determining the extra piercing damage the target takes.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Feats p. 2</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Poisoner (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You can prepare and deliver deadly poisons, gaining the following benefits:
• When you make a damage roll, you ignore resistance to poison damage.
• You can coat a weapon in poison as a bonus action, instead of an action.
• You gain proficiency with the Poisoner (UA)'s kit if you don't already have it. With one hour of work using a Poisoner (UA)'s kit and expending 50 gp worth of materials, you can create a number of doses of potent poison equal to your proficiency bonus. Once applied, the poison retains potency for 1 minute, or until you hit with the weapon. When a weapon coated in this poison deals damage to a creature, that creature must succeed on a DC 14 Constitution saving throw or take 2d8 poison damage and become poisoned until the end of your next turn.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Feats p. 2</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Polearm Master</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You can keep your enemies at bay with reach weapons. You gain the following benefits:
• When you take the Attack action and attack with only a glaive, halberd, quarterstaff, or spear, you can use a bonus action to make a melee attack with the opposite end of the weapon; this attack uses the same ability modifier as the primary attack. The weapon's damage die for this attack is a d4, and the attack deals bludgeoning damage.
• While you are wielding a glaive, halberd, pike, quarterstaff, or spear, other creatures provoke an opportunity attack from you when they enter your reach.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 168</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Practiced Expert (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have honed your proficiency with particular skills or tools, gaining the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency with one skill or tool of your choice.
• Choose one of your skill or tool proficiencies. Your proficiency bonus is doubled for any ability check you make that uses the chosen proficiency.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Feats p. 3</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Prodigy (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Half-Elf, Human</prerequisite>
    <text>You have a knack for learning new things. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain one skill proficiency of your choice, one tool proficiency of your choice, and fluency in one language of your choice.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 4</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Prodigy</name>
    <prerequisite>Half-Elf, Half-Orc, Human</prerequisite>
    <text>You have a knack for learning new things. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain one skill proficiency of your choice, one tool proficiency of your choice, and fluency in one language of your choice.
• Choose one skill in which you have proficiency. You gain expertise with that skill, which means your proficiency bonus is doubled for any ability check you make with it. The skill you choose must be one that isn't already benefiting from a feature, such as Expertise, that doubles your proficiency bonus.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 75</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Quick-Fingered (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Your nimble fingers and agility let you perform sleight of hand. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Sleight of Hand skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• As a bonus action, you can make a Dexterity (Sleight of Hand) check to plant something on someone else, conceal an object on a creature, lift a purse, or take something from a pocket.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 3</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Dexterity +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Quicksmithing</name>
    <prerequisite>Intelligence 13 or higher</prerequisite>
    <text>You have mastered the art of on-the-fly invention, improvement, and jury-rigging. You can use your talents to create immediate, short-term magical effects similar to spells, given time and an adequate supply of aether.
When you choose this feat, you master two magical effects, each of which recreates the effect of a 1st-level spell that has the ritual tag. These spells can come from any class list, but Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for them.
If you come across a schematic geared toward quicksmithing or study with another quicksmith, you might be able to add another spell to the effects you have mastered. The spell's level can be no higher than half your level (rounded up), and it must have the ritual tag. The process of mastering the spell takes 2 hours per level of the spell, and costs 50 gp per level. The cost represents aether you use as you experiment with the spell effect to master it.
In addition, you have proficiency with artisan's tools (quicksmith's tools). Using those tools, you can spend 1 hour and 10 gp worth of materials to construct a Tiny clockwork device (AC 5, 1 hp). The device ceases to function after 24 hours unless you spend 1 hour repairing it to keep it functioning. You can use your action to dismantle the device, at which point you can reclaim the materials used to create it. You can have up to three such devices active at a time.
When you create a device, choose one of the following options:
Clockwork Toy: This toy is a clockwork animal, monster, or person, such as a frog, mouse, bird, dragon, or soldier. When placed on the ground, the toy moves 5 feet across the ground on each of your turns in a random direction. It makes noises as appropriate to the creature it represents.
Fire Starter: This device produces a miniature flame, which you can use to light a candle, torch, or campfire. Using the device requires your action.
Music Box: When opened, this music box plays a single song at a moderate volume. The box stops playing when it reaches the song's end or when it is closed.
Source: Plane Shift: Kaladesh p. 13</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Resilient</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Choose one ability score. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in saving throws using the chosen ability.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 168</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Revenant Blade</name>
    <prerequisite>Elf</prerequisite>
    <text>You are descended from a master of the double-bladed scimitar, and some of that mastery has passed on to you. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Dexterity score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• While you are holding a double-bladed scimitar with two hands, you gain a +1 bonus to Armor Class.
• A double-bladed scimitar has the finesse property when you wield it.
Source: Eberron: Rising from the Last War p. 22, Wayfinder's Guide to Eberron p. 74</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Ritual Caster</name>
    <prerequisite>Intelligence or Wisdom 13 or higher</prerequisite>
    <text>You have learned a number of spells that you can cast as rituals. These spells are written in a ritual book, which you must have in hand while casting one of them.
When you choose this feat, you acquire a ritual book holding two 1st-level spells of your choice. Choose one of the following classes: bard, cleric, druid, sorcerer, warlock, or wizard. You must choose your spells from that class's spell list, and the spells you choose must have the ritual tag. The class you choose also determines your spellcasting ability for these spells: Charisma for bard, sorcerer, or warlock; Wisdom for cleric or druid; or Intelligence for wizard.
If you come across a spell in written form, such as a magical spell scroll or a wizard's spellbook, you might be able to add it to your ritual book. The spell must be on the spell list for the class you chose, the spell's level can be no higher than half your level (rounded up), and it must have the ritual tag. The process of copying the spell into your ritual book takes 2 hours per level of the spell, and costs 50 gp per level. The cost represents material components you expend as you experiment with the spell to master it, as well as the fine inks you need to record it.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 169</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Savage Attacker</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Once per turn when you roll damage for a melee weapon attack, you can reroll the weapon's damage dice and use either total.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 169</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Second Chance (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Halfling</prerequisite>
    <text>You have a knack for learning new things. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Dexterity or Constitution or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• When a creature you can see hits you with an attack roll, you can use your reaction to force that creature to reroll. Once you use this ability, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 4</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Second Chance</name>
    <prerequisite>Halfling</prerequisite>
    <text>Fortune favors you when someone tries to strike you. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Dexterity or Constitution or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• When a creature you can see hits you with an attack roll, you can use your reaction to force that creature to reroll. Once you use this ability, you can't use it again until you roll initiative at the start of combat or until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 75</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Sentinel</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have mastered techniques to take advantage of every drop in any enemy's guard, gaining the following benefits:
• When you hit a creature with an opportunity attack, the creature's speed becomes 0 for the rest of the turn.
• Creatures provoke opportunity attacks from you even if they take the Disengage action before leaving your reach.
• When a creature within 5 feet of you makes an attack against a target other than you (and that target doesn't have this feat), you can use your reaction to make a melee weapon attack against the attacking creature.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 169</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Servo Crafting</name>
    <prerequisite>Intelligence 13 or higher</prerequisite>
    <text>You are skilled in the creation of servos—tiny constructs that function as personal assistants. You can cast the find familiar spell as a ritual, creating a servo to serve as your familiar instead of an animal. A servo's statistics appear in the "Artifact Creatures" section of this document. In every other way, a servo familiar functions as described in the find familiar spell.
You can communicate telepathically with your servo familiar and perceive through its senses as long as you are on the same plane of existence. You can speak through your servo in your own voice.
Additionally, when you take the Attack action, you can forgo one of your own attacks to allow your servo familiar to make one attack of its own.
Source: Plane Shift: Kaladesh p. 13</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Shadow Touched (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You learn how to bend shadows from your experience with the Shadowfell. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Intelligence or Wisdom or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• You learn the darkness spell and one 1st-level spell of your choice. The 1st-level spell must be from the illusion or necromancy school of magic. You can cast each of these spells without expending a spell slot. Once you cast either of these spells in this way, you can't cast that spell in this way again until you finish a long rest. You can also cast these spells using spell slots you have of the appropriate level. The spells' spellcasting ability is the ability increased by this feat.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Feats p. 3</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Sharpshooter</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have mastered ranged weapons and can make shots that others find impossible. You gain the following benefits:
• Attacking at long range doesn't impose disadvantage on your ranged weapon attack rolls.
• Your ranged weapon attacks ignore half cover and three-quarters cover.
• Before you make an attack with a ranged weapon that you are proficient with, you can choose to take a -5 penalty to the attack roll. If the attack hits, you add +10 to the attack's damage.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 170</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Shield Master</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You use shields not just for protection but also for offense. You gain the following benefits while you are wielding a shield:
• If you take the Attack action on your turn, you can use a bonus action to try to shove a creature within 5 feet of you with your shield.
• If you aren't incapacitated, you can add your shield's AC bonus to any Dexterity saving throw you make against a spell or other harmful effect that targets only you.
• If you are subjected to an effect that allows you to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, you can use your reaction to take no damage if you succeed on the saving throw, interposing your shield between yourself and the source of the effect.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 170</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Shield Training (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You've trained in the effective use of shields. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Dexterity or Constitution score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• You gain proficiency with shield.
• In combat, you can don or doff a shield as the free object interaction on your turn.
• If you have the Spellcasting or Pact Magic feature, you can use a shield as a spellcasting focus.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Feats p. 3</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Silver-Tongued (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You develop your conversational skill to better deceive others. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Deception skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• When you take the Attack action on your turn, you can replace one attack with an attempt to deceive one humanoid you can see within 30 feet of you that can see and hear you. Make a Charisma (Deception) check contested by the target's Wisdom (Insight) check. If your check succeeds, your movement doesn't provoke opportunity attacks from the target and your attack rolls against it have advantage; both benefits last until the end of your next turn or until you use this ability on a different target. If your check fails, the target can't be deceived by you in this way for 1 hour.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 3</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Charisma +1</modifier>
    <proficiency>Deception</proficiency>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Skilled</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You gain proficiency in any combination of three skills or tools of your choice.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 170</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Skulker</name>
    <prerequisite>Dexterity 13 or higher</prerequisite>
    <text>You are expert at slinking through shadows. You gain the following benefits:
• You can try to hide when you are lightly obscured from the creature from which you are hiding.
• When you are hidden from a creature and miss it with a ranged weapon attack, making the attack doesn't reveal your position.
• Dim light doesn't impose disadvantage on your Wisdom (Perception) checks relying on sight.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 170</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Slasher (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You've learned where to cut to have the greatest results, granting you the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Dexterity score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• Once per turn when you hit a creature with an attack that deals slashing damage, you can reduce the speed of the target by 10 feet until the start of your next turn.
• When you score a critical hit that deals slashing damage to a creature, you grievously wound it. Until the start of your next turn, the target has disadvantage on all attack rolls.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Feats p. 3</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Spear Mastery (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Though the spear is a simple weapon to learn, it rewards you for the time you have taken to master it. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls you make with a spear.
• When you use a spear, its damage die changes from a d6 to a d8, and from a d8 to a d10 when wielded with two hands. (This benefit has no effect if another feature has already improved the weapon's die.)
• You can set your spear to receive a charge. As a bonus action, choose a creature you can see that is at least 20 feet away from you. If that creature moves within your spear's reach on its next turn, you can make a melee attack against it with your spear as a reaction. If the attack hits, the target takes an extra 1d8 piercing damage, or an extra 1d10 piercing damage if you wield the spear with two hands. You can't use this ability if the creature used the Disengage action before moving.
• As a bonus action on your turn, you can increase your reach with a spear by 5 feet for the rest of your turn.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats p. 3</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Spell Sniper</name>
    <prerequisite>The ability to cast at least one spell</prerequisite>
    <text>You have learned techniques to enhance your attacks with certain kinds of spells, gaining the following benefits:
• When you cast a spell that requires you to make an attack roll, the spell's range is doubled.
• Your ranged spell attacks ignore half cover and three-quarters cover.
• You learn one cantrip that requires an attack roll. Choose the cantrip from the bard, cleric, druid, sorcerer, warlock, or wizard spell list. Your spellcasting ability for this cantrip depends on the spell list you chose from: Charisma for bard, sorcerer, or warlock; Wisdom for cleric or druid; or Intelligence for wizard.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 170</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Squat Nimbleness (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Dwarf, Gnome, Halfling</prerequisite>
    <text>You are uncommonly nimble for your race. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Dexterity score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• Increase your walking speed by 5 feet.
• You gain proficiency in the Acrobatics or Athletics skill. If you're already proficient in the skill, your proficiency bonus is doubled for any check you make with it.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 4</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Squat Nimbleness</name>
    <prerequisite>Dwarf, Small Race</prerequisite>
    <text>You are uncommonly nimble for your race. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Dexterity score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• Increase your walking speed by 5 feet.
• You gain proficiency in the Acrobatics or Athletics skill (your choice).
• You have advantage on any Strength (Athletics) or Dexterity (Acrobatics) check you make to escape from being grappled.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 75</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Stealthy (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You know how best to hide. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Stealth skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• If you are hidden, you can move up to 10 feet in the open without revealing yourself if you end the move in a position where you're not clearly visible.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 4</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Dexterity +1</modifier>
    <proficiency>Stealth</proficiency>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Survivalist (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You master wilderness lore, gaining the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Survival skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• You learn the alarm spell. You can cast it once without expending a spell slot, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 4</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Wisdom +1</modifier>
    <proficiency>Survival</proficiency>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Svirfneblin Magic</name>
    <prerequisite>Gnome (Deep)</prerequisite>
    <text>You have inherited the innate spellcasting ability of your ancestors. This ability allows you to cast nondetection on yourself at will, without needing a material component. You can also cast each of the following spells once with this ability: blindness/deafness, blur, and disguise self. You regain the ability to cast these spells when you finish a long rest.
Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for these spells, and you cast them at their lowest possible levels.
Source: Mordenkainen's Tome of Foes p. 114</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Tandem Tactician (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Your presence in a scrap tends to elevate your comrades. You gain the following benefits:
• You can use the Help action as a bonus action.
• When you use the Help action to aid an ally in attacking a creature, increase the range of the Help action by 10 feet. Additionally, you can help two allies targeting the same creature within range when you use the Help action this way.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Feats p. 3</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Tavern Brawler</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Accustomed to rough-and-tumble fighting using whatever weapons happen to be at hand, you gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Constitution score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• You are proficient with improvised weapons.
• Your unarmed strike uses a d4 for damage.
• When you hit a creature with an unarmed strike or an improvised weapon on your turn, you can use a bonus action to attempt to grapple the target.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 170</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Telekinetic (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You learn to move things with your mind. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Intelligence or Wisdom or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• You learn the mage hand cantrip. You can cast it without verbal or somatic components, and you can make the spectral hand invisible. If you already know this spell, its range increases by 30 feet when you cast it. Its spellcasting ability is the ability increased by this feat.
• As a bonus action, you can try to Telekinetic (UA)ally shove one creature you can see within 30 feet of you. When you do so, roll your Psionic Talent die, and the target must succeed on a Strength saving throw (DC 8 + your proficiency bonus + the ability modifier of the score increased by this feat) or be moved toward you or away from you a number of feet equal to 5 times the number you rolled. A creature can willingly fail this save.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 8</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Telekinetic (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You learn to move things with your mind. You gain the following benefits:
• You learn the mage hand cantrip. You can cast it without verbal or somatic components, and you can make the spectral hand invisible.
• As a bonus action, you can try to shove one creature you can see within 5 feet of the spectral hand created by your mage hand spell. When you do so, the target must succeed on a Strength saving throw (DC 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Intelligence modifier) or be pushed 5 feet away from you.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 8</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Intelligence +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Telepathic (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You awaken the ability to mentally connect with others. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Intelligence or Wisdom or Charisma score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• You can speak Telepathic (UA)ally to any creature you can see within 30 feet of you. Your Telepathic (UA) utterances are in a language you know, and the creature understands you only if it knows that language. Your communication doesn't give the creature the ability to respond to you Telepathic (UA)ally.
• If your Psionic Talent die is available, you can cast the detect thoughts spell, requiring no components. When you start casting the spell, your Psionic Talent die decreases by one die size. Your spellcasting ability for the spell is the ability increased by this feat.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 8</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Telepathic (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You awaken the ability to mentally connect with others. You gain the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in one skill of your choice from the following list: Deception, Insight, Intimidation, or Persuasion.
• You can communicate Telepathic (UA)ally with any creature you can see within 30 feet of you. If it understands at least one language, it can respond to you Telepathic (UA)ally.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Rogue Wizard p. 8</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Intelligence +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Theologian (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Your extensive study of religion rewards you with the following benefits:
• You gain proficiency in the Religion skill. If you are already proficient in the skill, you add double your proficiency bonus to checks you make with it.
• You learn the thaumaturgy and detect evil and good spells. You can cast detect evil and good once without expending a spell slot, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Skills p. 4</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Intelligence +1</modifier>
    <proficiency>Religion</proficiency>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Tough</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Your hit point maximum increases by an amount equal to twice your level when you gain this feat. Whenever you gain a level thereafter, your hit point maximum increases by an additional 2 hit points.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 170</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Tower of Iron Will (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Your mind's defenses are formidable. After you or another creature you can see within 30 feet of you fails a saving throw, you can use your reaction to roll your Psionic Talent die and add the number rolled to the saving throw, potentially causing it to succeed.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 9</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Tracker (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have spent time hunting creatures and honed your skills, gaining the following benefits:
• You learn the hunter's mark spell. You can cast it once without expending a spell slot, and you must finish a long rest before you can cast it in this way again. You can also cast the spell using any spell slots you have. Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for this spell.
• You have advantage on Wisdom (Survival) checks to track creatures
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Feats p. 3</text>
    <modifier category="ability score">Wisdom +1</modifier>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Vampiric Exultation</name>
    <prerequisite>Vampire (Ixalan)</prerequisite>
    <text>As an action, you can transform the lower half of your body into an inky black vapor, allowing you to float through the air. While transformed, you have a flying speed of 30 feet. You can maintain this form for up to 10 minutes. Once you use this ability, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Plane Shift: Ixalan p. 14</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>War Caster</name>
    <prerequisite>The ability to cast at least one spell</prerequisite>
    <text>You have practiced casting spells in the midst of combat, learning techniques that grant you the following benefits:
• You have advantage on Constitution saving throws that you make to maintain your concentration on a spell when you take damage.
• You can perform the somatic components of spells even when you have weapons or a shield in one or both hands.
• When a hostile creature's movement provokes an opportunity attack from you, you can use your reaction to cast a spell at the creature, rather than making an opportunity attack. The spell must have a casting time of 1 action and must target only that creature.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 170</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Warhammer Master (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>This feat is presented as an illustrative example of a poorly-designed feat, and is not intended to be used in play. The Fell Handed feat is presented as a well-designed implementation of the same ideas, and should be used instead.
When you hit a creature with a warhammer, the  creature must succeed on a Strength saving  throw (DC 8 + your proficiency bonus + your  Strength modifier) or be knocked prone.
In addition, you can use your warhammer to  knock away a foe's shield. If you hit a creature  that's using a shield, you can have the attack deal  no damage and force the creature to drop its  shield.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats p. 2</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Weapon Master</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You have practiced extensively with a variety of weapons, gaining the following benefits:
• Increase your Strength or Dexterity score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• You gain proficiency with four weapons of your choice. Each one must be a simple or a martial weapon.
Source: Player's Handbook p. 170</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Wild Talent (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You awaken to your psionic potential, which enhances your mind or body. Increase one ability score of your choice by 1, to a maximum of 20, to represent this enhancement.
You also harbor a wellspring of psionic power within yourself, an energy that ebbs and flows as you channel it in various ways. This power is represented by your Psionic Talent die, the starting size of which is a d6.
Psionic Talent Options: You can use your Psionic Talent die in the following ways:
• Psi-Boosted Ability.: When you make an ability check with the ability increased by this feat, you can roll your Psionic Talent die and add the number rolled to the check. You can choose to do so before or after rolling the d20, but before you know whether the check succeeded or failed.
• Psi-Guided Strike.: Once on each of your turns when you hit with an attack roll that uses the ability increased by this feat, you can roll your Psionic Talent die after you make the damage roll and then replace one of the damage dice with the number rolled on the Psionic Talent die.
Changing the Die's Size: If you roll the highest number on your Psionic Talent die, it decreases by one die size after the roll. This represents you burning through your psionic energy. For example, if the die is a d6 and you roll a 6, it becomes a d4. If it's a d4 and you roll a 4, it becomes unusable until you finish a long rest.
Conversely, if you roll a 1 on your Psionic Talent die, it increases by one die size after the roll, up to its starting size. This represents you conserving psionic energy for later use. For example, if you roll a 1 on a d4, the die then becomes a d6.
Whenever you finish a long rest, your Psionic Talent die resets to its starting size. When you reach certain levels, the starting size of your Psionic Talent die increases: at 5th level (d8), 11th level (d10), and 17th level (d12). If you have a Psionic Talent die from another source, such as a class feature, you don't get more than one die; use only the one with the largest starting size.
Psi Replenishment: As a bonus action, you can calm your mind for a moment and restore your Psionic Talent die to its starting size. You then can't use Psi Replenishment again until you finish a long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Psionic Options Revisited p. 9</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Wonder Maker (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Gnome (Rock)</prerequisite>
    <text>You master the tinker techniques of your people. You gain the following benefits:
• Increase your Dexterity or Intelligence score by 1, to a maximum of 20
• When you make a check using your proficiency with tinker's tools, you add double your proficiency bonus to the check.
• When you make a device with your Tinker trait, you have the following additional options for what you make:
This device senses when a creature moves to within 15 feet of it without speaking aloud a password chosen when you create it. One round after a creature moves into range, the alarm makes a shrill ringing that lasts for 1 minute and can be heard from up to 300 feet away.
This device makes doing sums easy.
This device can be used as a block and tackle, allowing its user to hoist five times the weight the user can normally lift.
This pocket watch keeps accurate time.
When used as an action, this device predicts weather conditions in a 1-mile radius over the next 4 hours, showing one symbol (clouds, sun/moon, rain, or snow) for each hour.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 4</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Wood Elf Magic (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Elf (Wood)</prerequisite>
    <text>You learn the magic of the primeval woods. You learn one druid cantrip of your choice. You also learn longstrider and pass without trace, each of which you can cast once without expending a spell slot. You regain the ability to cast the spell in this way when you finish a long rest. Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for these spells.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Feats For Races p. 4</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Wood Elf Magic</name>
    <prerequisite>Elf (Wood)</prerequisite>
    <text>You learn the magic of the primeval woods, which are revered and protected by your people. You learn one druid cantrip of your choice. You also learn the longstrider and pass without trace spells, each of which you can cast once without expending a spell slot. You regain the ability to cast these two spells in this way when you finish a long rest. Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for all three spells.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 75</text>
    </feat>
  </compendium>
