<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <item>
        <name>Bad News</name>
        <type>R</type>
        <weight>25</weight>
        <text>A ranged weapon similar to a sniper rifle.</text>
        <text>Two-Handed, Reload 1, Misfire 3</text>
        <text>Proficiency: firearms</text>
        <text>Ammunition: 10g (5)</text>
        <value></value>
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger 1.3 p. 3</text>
        <dmg1>2d12</dmg1>
        <dmg2></dmg2>
        <dmgType>P</dmgType>
        <property>M,A,LD,2H</property>
        <range>200/800</range>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Blunderbuss</name>
        <type>R</type>
        <weight>10</weight>
        <text>A ranged weapon that is powerful at short range.</text>
        <text>Reload 1, Misfire 2</text>
        <text>Proficiency: firearms</text>
        <text>Ammunition: 5g (20)</text>
        <value></value>
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger 1.3 p. 3</text>
        <dmg1>2d8</dmg1>
        <dmg2></dmg2>
        <dmgType>P</dmgType>
        <property>M,A,LD</property>
        <range>15/60</range>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Hand Mortar</name>
        <type>R</type>
        <weight>10</weight>
        <text>A thrown weapon that explodes on impact, can be volatile.  Deals Fire damage on hit.</text>
        <text>Reload 1, Misfire 2, Explosive</text>
        <text>Proficiency: firearms</text>
        <text>Ammunition: 10g (1)</text>
        <value></value>
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger 1.3 p. 3</text>
        <dmg1>2d8</dmg1>
        <dmg2></dmg2>
        <dmgType>B</dmgType>
        <property>M,T</property>
        <range>30/60</range>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Musket</name>
        <type>R</type>
        <weight>10</weight>
        <text>A two handed ranged weapon that fires at long range.</text>
        <text>Two-Handed, Reload 1, Misfire 2</text>
        <text>Proficiency: firearms</text>
        <text>Ammunition: 5g (20)</text>
        <value></value>
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger 1.3 p. 3</text>
        <dmg1>1d12</dmg1>
        <dmg2></dmg2>
        <dmgType>P</dmgType>
        <property>M,A,LD,2H</property>
        <range>120/480</range>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Palm Pistol</name>
        <type>R</type>
        <weight>1</weight>
        <text>A ranged weapon that fits in the palm of your hand.</text>
        <text>Light, Reload 1, Misfire 1</text>
        <text>Proficiency: firearms</text>
        <text>Ammunition: 2g (20)</text>
        <value>50</value>
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger 1.3 p. 3</text>
        <dmg1>1d8</dmg1>
        <dmg2></dmg2>
        <dmgType>P</dmgType>
        <property>M,A,L,LD</property>
        <range>40/160</range>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Pistol</name>
        <type>R</type>
        <weight>3</weight>
        <text>A ranged weapon that fires bullets.</text>
        <text>Reload 4, Misfire 1</text>
        <text>Proficiency: firearms</text>
        <text>Ammunition: 4g (20)</text>
        <value>150</value>
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger 1.3 p. 3</text>
        <dmg1>1d10</dmg1>
        <dmg2></dmg2>
        <dmgType>P</dmgType>
        <property>M,A,LD</property>
        <range>60/240</range>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Pepperbox</name>
        <type>R</type>
        <weight>5</weight>
        <text>A special, complex one handed ranged weapon that fires quickly.</text>
        <text>Reload 6, Misfire 2</text>
        <text>Proficiency: firearms</text>
        <text>Ammunition: 4g (20)</text>
        <value>250</value>
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger 1.3 p. 3</text>
        <dmg1>1d10</dmg1>
        <dmg2></dmg2>
        <dmgType>P</dmgType>
        <property>M,A,LD</property>
        <range>80/320</range>
    </item>
    
    <class>
        <name>Blood Hunter</name>
        <hd>10</hd>
        <proficiency>Strength, Wisdom</proficiency>
        <spellAbility>Wisdom</spellAbility>
        <autolevel level="1">
            <feature>
                <name>Starting Proficiencies</name>
                <text>You are proficient with the following items, in addition to any proficiencies provided by your race or background.</text>
                <text>Armor: light armor, medium armor</text>
                <text>Weapons: simple weapons, martial weapons</text>
                <text>Tools: alchemist's supplies</text>
                <text>Skills: Choose two from Athletics, Acrobatics, Arcana, Insight, Investigation, and Survival</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Starting Equipment</name>
                <text>You start with the following equipment, in addition to the equipment granted by your background.</text>
                <text />
                <text>• (a) a martial weapon or (b) two simple weapons</text>
                <text>• (a) a light crossbow and 20 bolts or (b) hand crossbow and 20 bolts</text>
                <text>• (a) studded leather armor or (b) scale mail armor</text>
                <text>• an explorer's pack</text>
                <text />
                <text>Alternatively, you may start with 4d4 x 10 gp and purchase starting items of your choice.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="3">
            <slots>2,1,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature>
                <name>Blood Hunter Order</name>
                <text>At 3rd level, you commit to an order of blood hunter martial focus. Choose Order of the Mutant, Order of the Ghostslayer, Order of the Profane Soul, or Order of the Lycan. The order you choose grants you features at 3rd level, and again at 7th, 11th, 15th, and 18th level.</text>
                <text>There are a handful of secretive orders of blood hunters that guard their cryptic techniques and blasphemous rituals. One must adhere to one of these orders to even be granted access to the Hunter's Bane rite that starts their journey, and only once they've proven their ability will the secrets of the order begin to be revealed. Some even wait a few years before they are sure they want to continue down this cursed path. Either or, it's within these small, enigmatic sects that the real power of a blood hunter is learned.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Order of the Ghostslayer</name>
                <text>The Order of the Ghostslayer is the oldest and most driven of the orders, having rediscovered the secrets of blood magic and refined them for combat against the scourge of undeath. Ghostslayers seek out and study the moment of the death, obsessing over the mysteries of the transition. Some will sit with the terminally diseased to closely witness their passing, while others go so far as to deliberately have a near-death experience, allowing them to tune to their body and senses to the ethereal realms beyond.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Order of the Ghostslayer: Rite of the Dawn</name>
                <text>When you join this order at 3rd level, you learn the esoteric Rite of the Dawn.</text>
                <text>  • Rite of the Dawn. Your rite damage is radiant type.</text>
                <text>If you hit an Undead creature with your Rite of the Dawn, it suffers additional radiant damage equal to your Wisdom modifier.</text>
                <text>Upon reaching 11th level, any creature you hit with your Rite of the Dawn suffers this additional radiant damage.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Order of the Profane Soul</name>
                <text>The magics adopted by the wayward blood hunter prove formidable against many an evil across the realm. However, the darkest of abominations draw from an ancient well of cruel, unfathomable power. These terrors can control shadows to do their bidding, hide in plain sight among the noblest of nobles, and bend the minds of the most stalwart warrior with but a glance. These fiends are far trickier to hunt, and many lost their lives in pursuit of such wickedness.</text>
                <text>A small sect of blood hunters had finally had enough and delved into the same well of corrupting arcane knowledge, making pacts with lesser evils to better combat the greater. While they may have lost a part of themselves, the power gained far outweighed the price, for even devils now quake when they know they've drawn the attention of the Order of the Profane Soul.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Profane Soul: Otherworldly Patron</name>
                <text>When you reach 3rd level, you strike a bargain with an otherworldly being of your choice: the Archfey, the Fiend, or the Great Old One, each detailed on page 109 of the PHB or the Undying on page 139 of the Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide. Your choice augments some of your order features.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Profane Soul: Pact Magic</name>
                <text>When you reach 3rd level, you can augment your combat techniques with the ability to cast spells. See chapter 10 of the PHB for the general rules of spellcasting and chapter 11 of the PHB for the Warlock spell list.</text>
                <text>Cantrips. You learn two cantrips of your choice from the Warlock spell list. You learn an additional Warlock cantrip of your choice at 10th level.</text>
                <text>Spell Slots. The Profane Soul Spellcasting table shows how many spell slots you have. The table also shows what the level of those slots is; all of your spell slots are the same level. To cast one of your Warlock spells of 1st level or higher, you must expend a spell slot. You regain all expended spell slots when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
                <text>For example, when you are 8th level, you have two 2nd level spell slots. To cast the 1st-level spell thunderwave, you must spend one of those slots, and you cast it as a 2nd-level spell.</text>
                <text>Spell Known of 1st Level and Higher. At 3rd level, you know two 1st-level spells of your choice from the Warlock spell list.</text>
                <text>The total spell known are equal to the Warlock level divided by 2, rounded up. A spell you choose to learn must be of a level no higher than what's shown in the table's (listed at the beginning of this class description) Slot Level column for our level. When you reach 11th level, for example, you learn a new warlock spell, which can be 1st, 2nd, or 3rd level.</text>
                <text>Additionally when you get a level in this class and order, you can choose one of the warlock spells you know and replace is with another spell from the warlock spell list, which also must be of a level for which you have spell slots.</text>
                <text>Spellcasting Ability. Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for your warlock spells, so you use your Wisdom whenever a spell refers to your spellcasting ability. In addition, you use your Wisdom modifier when setting the saving throw DC for a warlock spell you cast and when making an attack roll with one.</text>
                <text>Spell save DC = 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Wisdom modifier</text>
                <text>Spell attack modifier = your proficiency bonus + your Wisdom modifier</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Profane Soul: Rite Focus</name>
                <text>Beginning at 3rd level, your weapon becomes a core to your pact with your chosen dark patron. While you have an active rite, you can use your weapon as a spellcasting focus (found in chapter 5 of the PHB) for your spells. Your chosen pact also enhances your rite (outlined below).</text>
                <text>  • The Archfey. If you deal rite damage to a creature, that creature loses any half or three-quarters cover bonuses, as well as invisibility, until the beginning of your next turn.</text>
                <text>  • The Fiend. While using the Rite of the Flame, if you roll a 1 on your rite damage die, you may reroll the die. You may reroll only once per attack.</text>
                <text>  • The Great Old One. Whenever you deal a critical hit to a creature, that creature must make a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failure, the creature is frightened of you until the end of your next turn.</text>
                <text>  • The Undying. Whenever you reduce a hostile creature to 0 hit points with a weapon attack, and kill it, you regain hit points equal to your crimson rite damage die.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Mutant</name>
                <text>The process of consuming the Hunter's Bane is a painful, scarring, and often fatal experience. Those that survive find themselves irrevocably changed, enhanced. Some found this experience exalting, embracing the ability to alter one's own physiology through corrupted alchemy.</text>
                <text>Over generations of experimentation, a splinter order of blood hunters began to emerge, one that focused on brewing toxic elixirs to modify their capabilities in battle, altering their blood and, over time become something beyond human. They called themselves the Order of the Mutant.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Mutant: Formulas</name>
                <text>You begin to uncover forbidden alchemical formulas that temporarily alter your mental and physical abilities.</text>
                <text>Beginning at 3rd level, you choose to learn three mutagen formulas. Your formula options are detailed at the end of this order description. You gain an additional formula at 7th, 10th, 15th, and 18th level.</text>
                <text>Additionally, when you gain a new mutagen formula, you can choose one of the formulas you already know and replace it with another mutagen formula.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Mutant: Mutagen Craft</name>
                <text>At 3rd level, you can take a short rest to concoct a single mutagen. Consuming a single mutagen requires a bonus action, and the effects (including side effects) last until you take a short or long rest to mediate and flush the toxins from your system.</text>
                <text>Mutagens are designed for your biology. They have no effect on large or larger creatures, and only impart the side effects on other medium or smaller creatures that drink the entire mutagen. They are also unstable by nature, losing their potency over time and becoming inert if not swallowed before you finish your next short or long rest.</text>
                <text>Your body will begin to better utilize the toxins you instil it with as you grow in power and experience. These advancing mutations may be signified by a Mutation score.</text>
                <text>Mutation Score = your blood hunter level divided by 4, rounded up.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Mutant: Mutagen List</name>
                <text>These mutagens are presented in alphabetical order. You can learn a mutagen at the same time you meet its prerequisites.</text>
                <text>  • Aether. Prerequisite: 11th level. You gain a flying speed of 20 feet. Side effect: you have disadvantage on all Strength and Dexterity ability checks.</text>
                <text>  • Celerity. Your Dexterity score increases by an amount equal to your mutation score, as does your Dexterity maximum. Side effect: Your Wisdom score decreases by amount equal to your mutation score.</text>
                <text>  • Conversant. You gain advantage on Intelligence ability checks. Side effect: You have disadvantage on Charisma ability checks.</text>
                <text>  • Cruelty. Prerequisite: 11th level. You can make a single weapon attack as a bonus action on each of your turns. Side effect: You gain vulnerability to slashing damage.</text>
                <text>  • Impermeable. You gain resistance to piercing damage. Side effect: You gain vulnerability to slashing damage.</text>
                <text>  • Mobility. You gain immunity to the grappled and restrained conditions. At 11th level, you also are immune to the paralyzed condition. Side effect: You gain a penalty to initiative equal to 2 times your mutation score.</text>
                <text>  • Nighteye. You gain darkvision for up to 60 feet. If you already have darkvision, this increases its range by 60 additional feet. Side effect: You gain sunlight sensitivity. (PHB 24)</text>
                <text>  • Potency. Your Strength score increases by an amount equal to your mutation score, as does your Strength maximum. Side effect: Your Dexterity score decreases by an amount equal to your mutation score.</text>
                <text>  • Precision. Prerequisite: 11th level. Your weapon attacks score a critical hit on a roll of 19-20. Side effect: All healing you receive is halved.</text>
                <text>  • Rapidity. Your speed increases by 10 feet. At 15th level, your speed increases by 15 feet instead. Side effect: You have disadvantage on Dexterity ability checks.</text>
                <text>  • Reconstruction. Prerequisite: 7th level. While conscious and in combat, you regenerate hit points equal to 2 times your mutation score (rounded down) at the start of your turn as long as you are above 0 hit points. Side effect: Your speed decreases by 10 feet.</text>
                <text>  • Sagacity. Your Wisdom score increases by an amount equal to your mutation score, as does your Wisdom maximum. Side effect: Your armor class is reduced by an amount equal to your mutation score.</text>
                <text>  • Shielded. You gain resistance to slashing damage. Side effect: You gain vulnerability to bludgeoning damage.</text>
                <text>  • Unbreakable. You gain resistance to bludgeoning damage. Side effect: You gain vulnerability to piercing damage.</text>
                <text>  • Wariness. You gain a bonus to initiative equal to 2 times your mutation score. Side effect: You have disadvantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Lycan</name>
                <text>Of the many terrible curses that plague the realm, few are as ancient or as feared as Lycanthropy. Passed through blood, this affliction seeds a host with the savage strength and hunger for violence of a wild beast. Those that shun the curse spend their lives burying their wild, bestial urges deep inside. However, the power of a rising full moon makes the curse too strong to resist, and the host transforms into a terrifying animal-humanoid hybrid controlled by murderous impulse. Those that embrace the dark nature of their curse learn to harness their bestial gifts, but also succumb to the evil, vicious temperament that drives the beast within.</text>
                <text>The Order of the Lycan is a proud order of blood hunters who undergo "The Taming, " a ceremonial inflicting of lycanthropy from a senior member. These hunters then use their abilities to harness the power of the monster they harbor without losing themselves to it. Through intense honing of one's own willpower, combined with the secrets of the order's blood magic rituals, members learn to control and unleash their hybrid form for short periods of time. Enhanced physical prowess, unnatural resilience, and razor sharp claws make these warriors a terrible foe to any evil that crosses their path. Yet, no training is perfect, and without care and complete focus, even the greatest of blood hunters can temporarily lose themselves to the bloodlust.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Lycan: Heightened Senses</name>
                <text>Starting when you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you begin to adopt the improved abilities of a natural predator. You gain advantage on any Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing or smell.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Lycan: Hybrid Transformation</name>
                <text>Upon choosing this archetype at 3rd level, you begin to learn to control the lycanthropic curse that now lives in your blood. As an action, you can transform into your Hybrid form. This form lasts for 1 minute. You can speak, use equipment, and wear armor in this form. You can revert to your normal form earlier by using an action on your turn. You automatically revert to your normal form if you fall unconscious, drop to 0 hit points, or die. The benefits of this form replace the rules for Lycanthropy within the Monster's Manual.</text>
                <text>You can use this feature twice. You regain expended uses when you finish a short or long rest. While you are transformed, you gain the following features:</text>
                <text>  • Feral Might. You gain a bonus to melee damage rolls equal to half your proficiency bonus (rounded down). You also have advantage on Strength checks and Strength saving throws.</text>
                <text>  • Resilient Hide. While you are not wearing heavy armor, you can a +1 bonus to your AC.</text>
                <text>  • Predatory Strikes. Your unarmed strikes are considered a single weapon in regards to your crimson rite feature. You can use Dexterity instead of Strength for the attack and damage rolls of your unarmed strikes. When you use the Attack action with an unarmed strike, you can make another unarmed strike as a bonus action. Unarmed strikes deal 1d4 slashing damage.</text>
                <text>  • Cursed Weakness. You have vulnerability to damage from silvered weapons.</text>
                <text>  • Bloodlust. At the start of your turn, if you've taken any damage since the beginning of your last turn, you must make a Wisdom saving throw to maintain control. The DC equals 10, or 15 if you have no more than half of your hit points left. On a failed save, you must move directly towards the nearest creature to you and use the Attack action against that creature. If there is more than one possible target, the DM chooses the target. Your turn immediately ends, and you regain control.</text>
                <text>If you are under an effect that prevents you from concentrating (like the Barbarian's rage feature), you automatically fail this saving throw.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="4">
            <slots>2,1,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="4">
            <feature>
                <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
                <text>When you reach 4th level, and again at 8th, 12th, 16th and 19th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1, As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="5">
            <feature>
                <name>Extra Attack</name>
                <text>Beginning at 5th level, you can attack twice, instead of once, whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Crimson Rite Damage Increase</name>
                <text>At 5th level, your Crimson Rite damage die increases to 1d6.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="6">
            <feature>
                <name>Blood Maledict</name>
                <text>At 6th level, you gain the knowledge to further channel, and sacrifice, a part of your vital essence to curse and manipulate your enemies. You gain two (2) blood curses of your choice, detailed in the "blood curses" section below. You learn one (1) additional blood curse of your choice at 9th, 13th, 17th level.</text>
                <text>When you use your Blood Maledict, you choose which curse to invoke. While invoking a blood curse, but before it affects the target, you may choose to AMPLIFY the curse by suffering damage equal to your crimson rite damage die. An amplified curse gains an additional effect, noted in the curses description. Creatures that do not have blood in their bodies are immune to blood curses (DM's discretion).</text>
                <text>You can use this feature twice. You regain expended uses when you finish a short or long rest. Beginning at 11th, you can use your Blood Maledict three times between rests, and at 17th, you can use it four times between rests.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of Binding</name>
                <text>As a bonus action, you can attempt to bind an enemy no more than one size larger than you within 30 feet. The target must succeed on a Strength saving throw (DC equal to 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Wisdom modifier) or have their speed be reduced to 0 until the beginning of your next turn.</text>
                <text>AMPLIFY: This curse becomes ongoing, and can affect a creature no more than two sizes larger than you. At the end of each of its turns, the cursed can make another Strength saving throw. On a success, this curse ends. You can end the curse whenever you like (no action required).</text>
            </feature>
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of the Eyeless</name>
                <text>When an enemy with eyes within 30 feet makes a weapon attack against you, you can use your reaction to impose disadvantage on the attack.</text>
                <text>AMPLIFY: The triggering attack can be targeting a creature other than yourself.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of the Fallen Puppet</name>
                <text>The moment a creature falls unconscious or dies within 30 feet of you, you can use your reaction to give that creature a final act of aggression. That creature immediately makes a single weapon attack against a target of your choice within its attack range. After the attack, the creature returns to being unconscious or dead.</text>
                <text>AMPLIFY: You grant a bonus to the attack roll and damage roll of the cursed creature's attack equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of 1).</text>
            </feature>
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of the Fending Rite</name>
                <text>When an enemy casts a spell that requires a Dexterity saving throw, you can use your reaction to deflect the spell with your crimson rite. You gain a bonus to the initial saving throw against that spell equal to your Wisdom Modifier (minimum of 1). This curse is invoked before the saving throw is rolled.</text>
                <text>AMPLIFY: You grant all allies within 5 feet of you this bonus to their saving throw against the triggering spell as well.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of the Marked</name>
                <text>As a bonus action, you can mark an enemy within 30 feet. Until the end of your turn, all crimson rite damage you deal to the target is doubled.</text>
                <text>AMPLIFY: You cause the marked target to also lose resistance to your rite damage type until the beginning of your next turn.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of Mutual Suffering</name>
                <text>As a bonus action, you can link to a creature within 30 feet for up to a minute, forcing them to share in the pain they inflict upon you. The next time the cursed creature damages you with a weapon attack, this curse deals necrotic damage to the cursed creature equal to half of the damage you suffered. This curse then ends.</text>
                <text>AMPLIFY: This curse instead deals damage equal to the damage you suffered, and it ignores necrotic resistance.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of Purgation</name>
                <text>As a bonus action, you can manipulate the vitality of a creature within 30 feet to expunge a corruption in their blood. The target creature can immediately make a swing throw against a poisoned condition afflicting it.</text>
                <text>AMPLIFY: Your target can instead immediately make a saving throw against one other condition afflicting it. This condition can be blinded, deafened, or paralyzed.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Blood Curse: Blood Curse of Spell Sunder</name>
                <text>When an enemy casts a spell within 30 feet that requires a spell attack roll and targets you, you can use your reaction to rend the spell from the air, imposing disadvantage on the spell attack roll.</text>
                <text>AMPLIFY: You make a Wisdom ability check. The DC equals 10 + the spell's level. On a success, the creature's spell misses you automatically.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="5">
            <slots>2,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="6">
            <slots>2,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="7">
            <slots>2,0,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="7">
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Ghostslayer: Hallowed Veins</name>
                <text>Beginning at 7th level, your blood curses become honed to the fabric of a creature's essence. Your blood curses can now affect any creature, regardless of their form or lack of blood.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Profane Soul: Mystic Frenzy</name>
                <text>Beginning at 7th level, when you use your action to cast a cantrip, you can make one weapon attack as a bonus action.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Profane Soul: Revealed Arcana</name>
                <text>At 7th level, your dark patron grants you the rare use of a dangerous arcane spell based on your pact.</text>
                <text>  • The Archfey. You can cast blur once using a profane soul spell slot. You can't do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
                <text>  • The Fiend. You can cast scorching ray once using a profane soul spell slot. You can't do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
                <text>  • The Great Old One. You can cast detect thoughts once using a profane soul spell slot. You can't do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
                <text>  • The Undying. You can cast blindness/deafness once using a profane soul spell slot. You can't do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Mutant: Advanced Mutagen Craft</name>
                <text>Upon reaching 7th level, when you take a short rest to concoct a mutagen, you can now create two. Mutagens must be different formulas, and can be ingested with overlapping effects that last until you finish your next short or long rest. Each mutagen still takes a separate bonus action to imbibe.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Lycan: Improved Transformation</name>
                <text>At 7th level, when you have an active rite while in your hybrid form, your unarmed strikes are considered magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage.</text>
                <text>In addition, your hybrid form gains the Stalker's Prowess feature.</text>
                <text>Stalker's Prowess. Your speed increases by 10 feet. You also can add 10 feet to your long jump distance and 3 feet to your high jump distance.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="8">
            <slots>2,0,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="8">
            <feature>
                <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
                <text>When you reach 8th level you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
                <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="9">
            <feature>
                <name>Grim Psychometry</name>
                <text>When you reach 9th level, you can take 10 minutes to meditate on an object to discern vague details regarding any lingering evil or wicked past surrounding it. Make a Wisdom ability check. Based on the result, the DM may reveal obscure information about dark events that may have previously surrounded the object, or hints toward a sinister purpose. This feature has no effect on objects untouched by evil. An object can only be targeted by this feature once, and future attempts reveal no further details.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Blood Curses Increase</name>
                <text>At level 9, you now know 3 blood curses</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="9">
            <slots>2,0,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="10">
            <slots>2,0,2,0,0,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="10">
            <feature>
                <name>Dark Velocity</name>
                <text>Upon reaching 10th level, you beckon the surrounding shadows to grant you unnatural swiftness on the battlefield. While in dim light or darkness, your speed increases by 10 feet, and attacks of opportunity made against you have disadvantage.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Crimson Rite Damage Increase</name>
                <text>At level 10, your Crimson Rite damage die increases to 1d8.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="11">
            <slots>2,0,0,2,0,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="11">
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Ghostslayer: Supernal Surge</name>
                <text>Upon reaching 11th level, you can spend a bonus action to allow your body to take on a swift, ghostly form. This effect lasts a number of rounds equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum 1). While this surge lasts, you can make a single weapon attack as a bonus action on each of your turns.</text>
                <text>In addition, you become spectral for the duration, allowing you to move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. You take 1d10 force damage if you end your turn inside an object. If this surge ends while you are inside an object, you are immediately shunted to the nearest unoccupied space that you can occupy and take force damage equal to twice the number of feet you moved.</text>
                <text>Once you use this feature, you must finish a short or long rest before you can use it again.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Profane Soul: Diabolic Channel</name>
                <text>At 11th level, you can temporarily infuse your rite with the seed of a powerful spell. As an action, you can imbue your rite-enhanced weapon with one spell you can cast or is already active, then make a single attack with that weapon. If that attack hits, all spell attack rolls for the imbued spell hit the target automatically and are considered part of the single weapon attack. The target takes weapon damage, and is subject to the effects of the spell, expending a spell slot accordingly. If the attack has advantage, the target's initial saving throw against the spell has disadvantage. If the attack misses, the spell has no effect. Area spells originate from the target's space.</text>
                <text>The spell must be of 1st level or higher, having a casting time of 1 action, or require an action to activate an already active concentration spell.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Mutant: Strange Metabolism</name>
                <text>Beginning at 11th level, you can use a bonus action to install a burst of adrenaline to temporarily resist the negative effects of a mutagen. You can choose to ignore the side effect of a mutagen affecting you for 1 minute.</text>
                <text>Once you use this feature, you must finish a short or long rest before you can use it again.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Lycan: Advanced Transformation</name>
                <text>Starting at 11th level, you learn to unleash and control more of the beast within. Your hybrid transformation now lasts for up to 10 minutes.</text>
                <text>Your unarmed strikes damage increase from 1d4 to 1d6.</text>
                <text>In addition, your hybrid form gains the Improved Resilient Hide feature.</text>
                <text>Improved Resilient Hide. You have resistance to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage from nonmagical weapons that aren't silvered.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="12">
            <slots>3,0,0,2,0,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="12">
            <feature>
                <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
                <text>When you reach 12th level you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
                <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="13">
            <slots>3,0,0,2,0,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="13">
            <feature>
                <name>Blood Curses Increase</name>
                <text>At level 13, you now know 4 blood curses</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="14">
            <slots>3,0,0,3,0,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="14">
            <feature>
                <name>Hardened Soul</name>
                <text>When you reach 14th level, you can no longer become frightened, and you have advantage on saving throws against magical charm effects.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Crimson Rite Damage Increase</name>
                <text>At level 14, your Crimson Rite damage die increases to 1d10.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="15">
            <slots>3,0,0,3,0,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="15">
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Ghostslayer: Gravesight</name>
                <text>At 15th level, you can see in normal darkness, as well as see invisible creatures and objects, up to 30 feet.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Profane Soul: Unsealed Arcana</name>
                <text>At 15th level, your dark patron grants you the rare use of an additional arcane spell based on your pact.</text>
                <text>  • The Archfey. You can cast slow once using a profane soul spell slot. You can't do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
                <text>  • The Fiend. You can cast fireball once using a profane spell slot. You can't do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
                <text>  • The Great Old One. You can cast haste once using a profane soul spell slot. You can't do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
                <text>  • The Undying. You can cast bestow curse once using a profane soul spell slot. You can't do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Mutant: Robust Physiology</name>
                <text>At 15th level, your body has begun to adapt to toxins and venoms, ignoring their corroding effects. You gain immunity to poison damage and the poisoned condition.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Mutant: Advanced Mutagen Craft (2)</name>
                <text>Upon reaching 15th level, you can now create three mutagens during a short rest.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Lycan: Iron Volition</name>
                <text>Beginning at 15th level, you've honed your willpower to better resist the violent urges of your lycanthropic curse. Whenever you make a Wisdom saving throw to maintain control of your hybrid form, you do so with advantage.</text>
                <text>In addition, your hybrid form gains the Pack Hunter feature.</text>
                <text>Pack Hunter. You have disadvantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of your allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="16">
            <slots>3,0,0,3,0,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="16">
            <feature>
                <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
                <text>When you reach 16th level you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
                <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="17">
            <slots>3,0,0,0,3,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="17">
            <feature>
                <name>Blood Curses Increase</name>
                <text>At level 17, you now know 4 blood curses</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="18">
            <slots>3,0,0,0,3,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="18">
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Ghostslayer: Vengeful Spirit</name>
                <text>Upon reaching 18th level, you learn to project your spirit to fight on while on the edge of death. Whenever your hit points drop to 0, you can choose to let your soul emerge from your body to fight on. Your body remains unconscious and subject to death saving throws per normal. At the beginning of your next turn, you manifest a spirit form in your space that picks up your weapons and continues fighting on, acting on your turn and every one of your subsequent turns under your control. Your spirit form has your physical attributes and armor class, as well as your weapons and ammunition, and can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. This form is immune to cold, necrotic, and non-magical weapon damage. Your spirit form has access to all of your abilities other than your blood maledict feature.</text>
                <text>If your spirit form takes any damage, your body dies, or you regain any hit points, your spirit form vanishes. If your spirit form vanishes, it drops your weapons in its space.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Profane Soul: Soul Siphon</name>
                <text>When you reach 18th level, you learn to sacrifice the souls of powerful foes to your dark patron in exchange for immediate power. When you reduce a creature to 0 hit points with an attack, kill the creature, and they have a challenge rating of 15 or above, you recover an expended spell slot.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Mutant: Exalted Mutation</name>
                <text>At 18th level, your body has begun producing one of your toxins naturally. Choose one of your known mutagen formulas. You gain the benefits and side effects of this mutagen permanently, at all times. You cannot change this choice of formula after this feature is acquired.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Order of the Lycan: Hybrid Transformation Mastery</name>
                <text>At 18th level, you have wrestled your inner predator and mastered it. You can now use your hybrid transformation feature three times between rests.</text>
                <text>You also gain the Blood Curse of the Howl for your blood malediction feature. This does not count against your blood curses known.</text>
                <text>Blood Curse of the Howl. As an action, you howl at a creature within 30 feet, chilling their blood and stunning them with fear. If the target creature can hear you, they must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw (DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Wisdom modifier) or be stunned until the end of your next turn. </text>
                <text>AMPLIFY: This curse affects every creature within 15 feet of you.</text>
                <text>Your unarmed strikes damage increases from 1d6 to 1d8.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="19">
            <slots>3,0,0,0,3,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="19">
            <feature>
                <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
                <text>When you reach 19th level you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
                <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature>
                <name>Crimson Rite Damage Increase</name>
                <text>At level 19, your Crimson Rite damage die increases to 1d12.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="20">
            <slots>3,0,0,0,3,0,0,0,0,0</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="20">
            <feature>
                <name>Sanguine Mastery</name>
                <text>Upon becoming 20th level, your crimson rite is perfected, no longer requiring visceral sacrifice. When you have an active crimson rite, you no longer reduce your maximum hit points and you take no damage when amplifying blood curses. In addition, when you are below one fourth of your current maximum hit points and conscious, all your crimson rite damage dice are maximized.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
    </class>
    <class>
        <name>Fighter</name>
        
        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Martial Archetype: Gunslinger</name>
                <text>Most warriors and combat specialists spend their years perfecting the classic arts of swordplay, archery, or polearm tactics.  Whether the duelist of infantry martial weapons were seemingly perfected long ago, and the true challenge is to master them.</text>
                <text>    However, some minds couldn’t stop with the innovation of the crossbow.  Experimentation with alchemical components and rare metals have unlocked the secrets of controlled explosive force.  The few who survive these trials of ingenuity may become the first to create, and deftly wield, the first firearms.</text>
                <text>    This archetype focuses on the ability to design, craft and utilize powerful, yet dangerous ranged weapons.  Through creative innovation and immaculate aim, you become a distant force of death on the battlefield.  However, not being a perfect science, firearms carry an inherent instability that can occasionally leave you without a functional means of attack.  This is the danger of new, untested technologies in a world where the arcane energies that rule the elements are ever present.</text>
                <text>    Should this path of powder, fire and metal call to you, keep your wits about you, hold onto your convictions as a fighter, and let skill meet luck to guide your bullets to strike true.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.3 p. 1</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        
        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Firearm Proficiency (Gunslinger)</name>
                <text>Starting from when you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you gain proficiency in firearms, allowing you to add your proficiency bonus to attacks made with firearms.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.3 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        
        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Gunsmith (Gunslinger)</name>
                <text>Upon choosing this archetype at 3rd level, you gain proficiency in Tinker’s Tools.  You may use them to craft ammunition, repair damaged firearms, or even draft and create new ones (DM’s discretion). Some extremely intricate and experimental features are only available through crafting.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        
        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Firearm Properties</name>
                <text>Firearms are a new and volatile technology, and as such bring their own unique set of weapon properties.  Some properties are followed by a number, and this number signifies an element of their property.  These properties replace the optional ones presented in the DM guide.  Firearms are ranged weapons.</text>
                <text>    RELOAD.  The weapon can be fired a number of times equal to its Reload score before you must spend 1 attack or 1 action to reload.  You must have one free hand to reload a firearm.</text>
                <text>    MISFIRE.  Whenever you make an attack roll with a firearm, and the dice roll is equal to or lower than weapon’s Misfire score, the weapon misfires.  The attack misses, and the weapon cannot be used again until you spend an action to try and repair it.  To repair your firearm, you must make a successful Tinker’s Tools check (DC equal to 8 + Misfire score).  If your check fails, the weapon is broken and must be repaired out of combat at half the cost of the firearm.</text>
                <text>    SCATTER.  An attack is made against each creature within a 30 ft. cone.  These attacks are simultaneous.  If an affected creature is adjacent to you, they suffer double damage on a hit.  This attack cannot be affected by any of your shot features.</text>
                <text>    EXPLOSIVE.  Upon a hit, everything within 5 ft. of the target must make a Dexterity saving throw (DC equal to 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Dexterity modifier) or suffer 1d8 fire damage.  If the weapon misses, the ammunition fails to detonate, or bounces away harmlessly before doing so.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        
        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Adept Marksman (Gunslinger)</name>
                <text>When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you learn to perform powerful trick shots to disable or damage your opponents using your firearms.</text>
                <text>    Trick Shots: You learn two trick shots of your choice.  Many maneuvers enhance an attack in some way.  Each use of a trick shot must be declared before the attack roll is made.  You can use only one trick shot per attack.</text>
                <text>    You learn an additional trick shot of your choice at 7th, 10th, 15th, and 18th level.  Each time you learn a trick shot, you can also replace one trick shot you know with a different one.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Grit: You gain a number of grit points equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of 1).  You regain 1 expended grit point each time you roll a 20 on the d20 roll with a firearm, or deal a killing blow with a firearm to a creature of significant threat (DM’s discretion).  You gain all expended grit points after a short or long rest.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Saving Throws: Some of your trick shots require your targets to make a saving throw to resist the trick shot’s effect.  The saving throw DC is calculated as follows:
                    Trick Shot save DC = 8 + your proficiency bonus + Dexterity Modifier</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.3 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        
        <autolevel level="7">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Quickdraw (Gunslinger)</name>
                <text>When you reach 7th level, you add your proficiency to your initiative.  You can also stow a firearm, then draw another firearm as a single object interaction on your turn</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.3 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        
        <autolevel level="10">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Rapid Repair (Gunslinger)</name>
                <text>Upon reaching 10th level, you learn how to quickly attempt to fix a jammed gun.  You can spend a grit point to attempt to repair a misfired (but not broken) firearm as a bonus action.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        
        <autolevel level="15">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Lightning Reload (Gunslinger)</name>
                <text>Starting at 15th level, you can reload any firearm as a bonus action.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        
        <autolevel level="18">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Vicious Intent (Gunslinger)</name>
                <text>At 18th level, your firearm attacks score a critical hit on a roll of 19-20, and you regain a grit point on a roll of 19 or 20 on a d20 attack roll with a firearm.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        
        <autolevel level="10">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Hemorrrhaging Critical (Gunslinger)</name>
                <text>Upon reaching 18th level, whenever you score a critical hit on an attack with a firearm, the target additionally suffers half of the damage from the attack at the end of its next turn.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
    </class>
    
    <spell>
        <name>Bullying Shot</name>
        <level>1</level>
        <ritual>NO</ritual>
        <time></time>
        <range></range>
        <components>None</components>
        <duration></duration>
        <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger)</classes>
        <text>You can use the powerful blast and thundering sound of your firearm to shake the resolve of a creature.  When making a Charisma (Intimidation) check, you can expend one grit point to gain advantage on the roll.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
    </spell>
    <spell>
        <name>Dazing Shot</name>
        <level>1</level>
        <ritual>NO</ritual>
        <time></time>
        <range></range>
        <components>None</components>
        <duration></duration>
        <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger)</classes>
        <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to attempt to dizzy your opponent.  On a hit, the creature suffers normal damage and must make a Constiution saving throw or suffer disadvantage on attacks until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
    </spell>
    <spell>
        <name>Deadeye Shot</name>
        <level>1</level>
        <ritual>NO</ritual>
        <time></time>
        <range></range>
        <components>None</components>
        <duration></duration>
        <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger)</classes>
        <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to gain advantage on the attack roll.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
    </spell>
    <spell>
        <name>Disarming Shot</name>
        <level>1</level>
        <ritual>NO</ritual>
        <time></time>
        <range></range>
        <components>None</components>
        <duration></duration>
        <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger)</classes>
        <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to attempt to shoot an object from their hands.  On a hit, the creature suffers normal damage and must succeed on a Strength saving throw or drop 1 held object of your choice and have that object pushed 10 feet away from you.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
    </spell>
    <spell>
        <name>Forceful Shot</name>
        <level>1</level>
        <ritual>NO</ritual>
        <time></time>
        <range></range>
        <components>None</components>
        <duration></duration>
        <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger)</classes>
        <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to attempt to trip them up and force them back.  On a hit, the creature suffers normal damage and must succeed on a Strength saving throw or be pushed 15 feet away from you.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
    </spell>
    <spell>
        <name>Piercing Shot</name>
        <level>1</level>
        <ritual>NO</ritual>
        <time></time>
        <range></range>
        <components>None</components>
        <duration></duration>
        <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger)</classes>
        <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to attempt to fire through multiple opponents.  The initial attack gains a +1 to the firearm’s misfire score.  On a hit, the creature suffers normal damage and you make an attack roll with disadvantage against every creature in a line directly behind the target within your first range increment.  Only the initial attack can misfire.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
    </spell>
    <spell>
        <name>Violent Shot</name>
        <level>1</level>
        <ritual>NO</ritual>
        <time></time>
        <range></range>
        <components>None</components>
        <duration></duration>
        <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger)</classes>
        <text>When you make a fireman attack against a creature, you can expend one or more grit points to enhance the volatility of the attack.  For each grit point expended, the attack gains a +2 to the firearm’s misfire score.  If the attack hits, you can roll one additional weapon damage per grit point spent when determining the damage.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 3</text>
    </spell>
    <spell>
        <name>Winging Shot</name>
        <level>1</level>
        <ritual>NO</ritual>
        <time></time>
        <range></range>
        <components>None</components>
        <duration></duration>
        <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger)</classes>
        <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to attempt to topple a moving target.  On a hit, the creature suffers normal damage and must make a Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
    </spell>
</compendium>
