<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium auto_indent="NO" version="5">
  <!-- Items -->
  <item>
    <name>Akmon, Hammer of Purphoros</name>
    <type>M</type>
    <weight>2</weight>
    <value>15.0</value>
    <property>V</property>
    <dmg1>1d8</dmg1>
    <dmg2>1d10</dmg2>
    <dmgType>B</dmgType>
    <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 198</text>
    <text>Purphoros's hammer works wonders and disasters, the god of the forge using it to craft ground-breaking marvels and dangerous inventions in equal measure. Purphoros rarely bestows Akmon on mortals but occasionally leaves it unattended at his forge in Mount Velus. When Purphoros does permit a mortal to use the hammer, it's usually so they might bring an important work into being, wreck a force of destruction, or forge something remarkable somewhere the god isn't welcome.
Hammer of the Forge: This magic warhammer grants a +3 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with it. When you hit with an attack using it, the target takes an extra 3d10 fire damage.
Blessing of the Forge: If you are a worshiper of Purphoros, you gain all the following benefits for which you have the required piety:
• Piety 10+.: The hammer has 1 randomly determined minor beneficial property.
• Piety 25+.: The hammer has 1 randomly determined major beneficial property.
• Piety 50+.: The hammer has 1 additional randomly determined major beneficial property.
If you aren't a worshiper of Purphoros, the hammer has 2 randomly determined minor detrimental properties.
See "Artifacts" in chapter 7 of the Dungeon Master's Guide for details on randomly determined properties.
Reforged: While holding the hammer, you have resistance to fire damage and are immune to exhaustion. Additionally, you have proficiency with smith's tools and have advantage on all ability checks made using them.
Spells: While the hammer is on your person, you can use an action to cast one of the following spells (save DC 18): animate objects, heat metal, fabricate, magic weapon, mending, shatter. Once you use the hammer to cast a spell, the spell can't be cast again from it until the next dusk.
Destroying the Hammer: To destroy the hammer, it must be taken to the realm of Tizerus, in the Underworld. There it must be coated in clay from the Mire of Punishment. The heat of the hammer hardens the clay, which fuses to it after one month. Once fully hardened, the clay-covered hammer must be swallowed and digested by a kraken.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 198</text>
    <roll>3d10</roll>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Dekella, Bident of Thassa</name>
    <type>M</type>
    <weight>4</weight>
    <value>5.0</value>
    <property>T,V</property>
    <dmg1>1d6</dmg1>
    <dmg2>1d8</dmg2>
    <dmgType>P</dmgType>
    <range>20/60</range>
    <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 199</text>
    <text>Thassa wields Dekella, a two-pronged weapon gifted to her by Purphoros. When the god of the sea bestows her weapon on a mortal, it's often so they might work her will far from the ocean, right some wrong affecting those she'd prefer not to harm, or give a mortal a glimpse of her terrible responsibilities.
Bident of the Deep: Thassa's signature weapon thrums with the icy currents of the deep ocean. This weapon functions as a trident that grants a +3 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with it. When you hit with an attack using the bident, the target takes an extra 2d10 cold damage.
Blessing of the Deep: If you are a worshiper of Thassa, you gain all the following benefits for which you have the required piety:
• Piety 10+.: You can breathe underwater, and you gain a swimming speed of 60 feet.
• Piety 25+.: The bident has 1 randomly determined minor beneficial property.
• Piety 50+.: The bident has 1 randomly determined major beneficial property.
If you aren't a worshiper of Thassa, the bident has 1 minor detrimental property and 1 major detrimental property, both randomly determined.
See "Artifacts" in chapter 7 of the Dungeon Master's Guide for details on randomly determined properties.
Command the Deep: The bident holds the power to command the waves and its creatures. As an action, you can change the condition of the sea within 1 mile of you, creating strong winds and heavy rain that cause violent waves (see "Weather at Sea" in chapter 5 of the Dungeon Master's Guide) or calming a storm. In either case, the unnatural weather lasts for 1 hour before returning to normal. Once used, this property of the bident can't be used again until the next dusk.
Additionally, you can cast the dominate monster spell (save DC 18) from the bident, but only on beasts and monstrosities that have an innate swimming speed. Once used, this property of the bident can't be used again until the next dusk.
Aquatic Metamorphosis: You can cast the true polymorph spell (save DC 18) from the bident, but you must cast it on a creature to turn it into a kind of creature that has an innate swimming speed. Once used, this property of the bident can't be used again until the next dusk.
Destroying the Bident: To destroy the bident, it must be heated by the breath of an ancient red dragon and then, while still hot, immersed in the Tartyx River.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 199</text>
    <roll>2d10</roll>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Ephixis, Bow of Nylea</name>
    <type>R</type>
    <weight>2</weight>
    <value>25.0</value>
    <property>A,2H</property>
    <dmg1>1d6</dmg1>
    <dmgType>P</dmgType>
    <range>80/320</range>
    <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 200</text>
    <text>Nylea wields the shortbow Ephixis, the bow whose arrows herald the turning of the seasons. Nylea is quick to let her favored followers borrow her bow, particularly when they intend to use it to perform great deeds, put an end to foul creatures, or cast down the arrogant.
Bow of the Wild: This divine weapon includes a shortbow and a quiver with four arrows, each tied to one of the four seasons. You gain a +3 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with this bow, and you suffer no disadvantage when attacking at the weapon's long range. Additionally, Ephixis scores a critical hit on a d20 roll of 19 or 20.
Blessing of the Wild: If you are a worshiper of Nylea, you gain all the following benefits for which you have the required piety:
• Piety 10+.: The bow has 1 randomly determined minor beneficial property.
• Piety 25+.: The bow has 1 randomly determined major beneficial property.
If you aren't a worshiper of Nylea, the bow has 1 randomly determined major detrimental property.
See "Artifacts" in chapter 7 of the Dungeon Master's Guide for details on randomly determined properties.
Arrows of the Seasons: The four arrows—each associated with a season—that accompany this bow can be fired only from it. Each arrow disappears immediately after it's used, and it reappears in the quiver at the next dusk. The save DC against spells cast with the arrows is 18. Each arrow has a unique property:
Spring: As an action, you can fire this arrow, targeting a beast or a plant creature you can see within 320 feet of you. On a hit, the arrow deals no damage, and the target gains the benefits of the awaken spell for 8 hours.
Summer: As an action, you can fire this arrow at an unoccupied space on the ground that you can see within 320 feet of you, no attack roll required. A Nyxborn lynx is summoned in that space (use the stat block for a tiger with the Nyxborn traits from chapter 6). The lynx understands your verbal commands and obeys them as best it can, and it takes its turns immediately after yours. The emissary remains for 1 hour before fading away.
Autumn: As an action, you can fire this arrow at a space on the ground that you can see within 320 feet of you, no attack roll required, casting the wall of thorns spell there.
Winter: As an action, you can fire this arrow at a space that you can see within 320 feet of you, no attack roll required, casting the ice storm spell there.
Destroying the Bow: The bow can't be destroyed without first destroying all its arrows. The winter arrow must be fed to a cerberus on the winter solstice. The spring arrow must be planted at the base of a Black Oak of Asphodel on the spring equinox. The summer arrow must be broken by a sea giant on the summer solstice. Then the autumn arrow must be shot into the carcass of a hydra on the autumnal equinox. When all four arrows are destroyed, the bow and quiver dissolve into dust.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 200</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Flying Chariot</name>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 196</text>
    <text>The chariot's riders and creatures pulling the chariot gain a +1 bonus to their AC.
If this magic chariot is pulled by one or more flying creatures, it too can fly.
Chariots: Chariots and the creatures pulling them work like controlled mounts, as described in the mounted combat rules in the Player's Handbook, but with the following differences:
• Mounting or dismounting a chariot costs you 5 feet of movement, rather than a number of feet equal to half your speed.
• Being mounted on a chariot grants you half cover.
• A chariot's speed is equal to the speed of the slowest creature pulling it.
• If multiple creatures are pulling the chariot, they all act on the same initiative, and they must take the same action on their turn.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 196</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Helm of the Gods</name>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 196</text>
    <text>While wearing this helm, you know whether there is a celestial or fiend within 30 feet of you, as well as where the creature is located, provided the creature isn't behind total cover.
Whenever you finish a long rest while wearing the helm, you can pray to one of the gods listed on the Helm of the Gods table and store the listed spell in the helm, replacing any spell that is already stored there. The save DC for the spell is 13.
The helm has 3 charges. To cast a spell from the helm, you must expend 1 charge, and the helm regains 1d3 charges daily at dawn.
God | Spell
Athreos | protection from evil and good
Ephara | sanctuary
Erebos | inflict wounds
Heliod | guiding bolt
Iroas | heroism
Karametra | goodberry
Keranos | thunderous smite
Klothys | entangle
Kruphix | dissonant whispers
Mogis | hellish rebuke
Nylea | faerie fire
Pharika | lesser restoration
Phenax | charm person
Purphoros | searing smite
Thassa | identify
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 196</text>
    <roll>1d3</roll>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Khrusor, Spear of Heliod</name>
    <type>M</type>
    <weight>3</weight>
    <value>1.0</value>
    <property>T,V</property>
    <dmg1>1d6</dmg1>
    <dmg2>1d8</dmg2>
    <dmgType>P</dmgType>
    <range>20/60</range>
    <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 200</text>
    <text>Heliod wields Khrusor, a spear blessed with the power of the sun. In his hands, it can be pitched from Nyx to any point on Theros. When Heliod lends his weapon to a mortal, it's typically so they can perform some great work in his name or as a test of their worthiness.
Spear of the Sun: This spear grants a +3 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with it. When you hit with an attack using this spear, the target takes an extra 2d8 radiant damage.
Blessing of the Sun: If you are a worshiper of Heliod, you gain all the following benefits for which you have the required piety:
• Piety 3+.: You gain 15 temporary hit points each dawn.
• Piety 10+.: The spear has 1 randomly determined minor beneficial property.
• Piety 25+.: The spear has 1 additional randomly determined minor beneficial property.
• Piety 50+.: The spear has 1 randomly determined major beneficial property.
If you aren't a worshiper of Heliod, the spear has 2 randomly determined major detrimental properties.
See "Artifacts" in chapter 7 of the Dungeon Master's Guide for details on randomly determined properties.
Luminous: The spear sheds bright light in a 30-foot radius and dim light for an additional 30 feet. The light is sunlight.
Sun's Retaliation: When you take damage from a creature within 5 feet of you, you can use your reaction to make a melee attack with the spear against that creature. On a hit, the spear deals damage as normal, and the creature is blinded until the start of its next turn. This property of the spear can't be used again until the next dawn.
Spells: The spear has 10 charges. While holding it, you can use an action to expend 1 or more of its charges to cast one of the following spells (save DC 18) from it: guiding bolt (1 charge), daylight (3 charges, targeting the tip of the spear only), sunbeam (6 charges). The spear regains 1d6 + 4 expended charges daily at dawn.
Destroying the Spear: If taken to Erebos's palace in Tizerus, and used to sacrifice a champion of Heliod to Erebos, Khrusor is either destroyed or fundamentally twisted to Erebos's service.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 200</text>
    <roll>2d8</roll>
    <roll>1d6+4</roll>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Mastix, Whip of Erebos</name>
    <type>M</type>
    <weight>3</weight>
    <value>2.0</value>
    <property>F,R</property>
    <dmg1>1d4</dmg1>
    <dmgType>S</dmgType>
    <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 201</text>
    <text>Erebos wields Mastix, a whip capable of extending like an impossibly long shadow. In the hands of the god of the dead, the whip snares the reluctant dead and drags them into his realm. When Erebos grants his weapon to a mortal follower, it's typically to reclaim a powerful soul or to humiliate Heliod.
Whip of the Dead: Erebos's whip seethes with the enervating energy of the Underworld. This magic whip grants a +3 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with it. When you hit with an attack using this whip, the target takes an extra 2d8 necrotic damage and you regain hit points equal to half the amount of necrotic damage dealt.
Additionally, when you make an attack with the whip on your turn, you can increase the range of the attack to 300 feet. This property of the weapon can't be used again until the next dusk.
Blessing of the Dead: If you are a worshiper of Erebos, you gain all the following benefits for which you have the required piety:
• Piety 1+.: The whip has 1 randomly determined minor detrimental property—a burden Erebos imposes to test his faithful.
• Piety 25+.: The whip has 1 randomly determined major beneficial property.
• Piety 50+.: The whip has 1 additional randomly determined major beneficial property.
If you aren't a worshiper of Erebos, the whip has 2 randomly determined major detrimental properties.
See "Artifacts" in chapter 7 of the Dungeon Master's Guide for details on randomly determined properties.
Erebos's Claim: While carrying the whip, you can use an action to cast either circle of death or dominate monster (targeting only undead) from the whip. The save DC for these spells is 18. Once you use the whip to cast a spell, that spell can't be cast from it again until the next dusk.
Destroying the Whip: To destroy the whip, it must be taken to the heights of Mount Hiastos in Nyx, unraveled by a Returned, and left to bask in continual daylight for one month.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 201</text>
    <roll>2d8</roll>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Molten Bronze Skin (Breastplate)</name>
    <type>MA</type>
    <weight>20</weight>
    <property></property>
    <ac>14</ac>
    <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
    <text>This magical armor appears as a jug of molten bronze. When you attune to it, the bronze adheres and contours to your skin. The armor can be worn under normal clothes, but it doesn't impede bodily functions. Once you put it on, it can't be removed unless you choose to do so.
While wearing the armor, you have resistance to fire damage. The armor also doesn't impose disadvantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Molten Bronze Skin (Half Plate)</name>
    <type>MA</type>
    <weight>40</weight>
    <property></property>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
    <text>This magical armor appears as a jug of molten bronze. When you attune to it, the bronze adheres and contours to your skin. The armor can be worn under normal clothes, but it doesn't impede bodily functions. Once you put it on, it can't be removed unless you choose to do so.
While wearing the armor, you have resistance to fire damage. The armor also doesn't impose disadvantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Molten Bronze Skin (Plate)</name>
    <type>HA</type>
    <weight>65</weight>
    <property></property>
    <ac>18</ac>
    <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
    <text>This magical armor appears as a jug of molten bronze. When you attune to it, the bronze adheres and contours to your skin. The armor can be worn under normal clothes, but it doesn't impede bodily functions. Once you put it on, it can't be removed unless you choose to do so.
While wearing the armor, you have resistance to fire damage. The armor also doesn't impose disadvantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks.
If the wearer has a Strength score lower than 15, their speed is reduced by 10 feet.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Potion of Aqueous Form</name>
    <type>P</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
    <text>When you drink this potion, you transform into a pool of water. You return to your true form after 10 minutes or if you are incapacitated or die.
You're under the following effects while in this form:
• Liquid Movement.: You have a swimming speed of 30 feet. You can move over or through other liquids. You can enter and occupy the space of another creature. You can rise up to your normal height, and you can pass through even Tiny openings. You extinguish nonmagical flames in any space you enter.
• Watery Resilience.: You have resistance to nonmagical damage. You also have advantage on Strength, Dexterity, and Constitution saving throws.
• Limitations.: You can't talk, attack, cast spells, or activate magic items. Any objects you were carrying or wearing meld into your new form and are inaccessible, though you continue to be affected by anything you're wearing, such as armor.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Pyxis of Pandemonium</name>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
    <text>A creature that touches this ornate wooden vessel for 1 minute gains the benefits of a short rest. That creature also gains the effects of the bless spell until the creature finishes a short or long rest. The creature can't gain these benefits again until it finishes a long rest.
If the vessel is opened, roll on the Pyxis of Pandemonium table to determine what happens. Any spells cast by the vessel have a spell save DC of 17. One minute after the vessel is opened, it disappears. It reappears, sealed, in a random location on the same plane of existence 24 hours later.
Curse: Any creature that gains the benefit of a short rest from the vessel hears cloying telepathic whispers emanating from it. That creature must make a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the creature is charmed by the vessel for 1 hour. The charmed creature does everything it can to open the vessel as soon as possible. On a successful save, the creature is immune to the vessel's whispers for 24 hours.
d8 | Calamity
1 | Androphagia. Each creature within 60 feet of the vessel must succeed on a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw or go berserk for 1 minute. The berserk creature must begin its turn using the Attack action to make one melee or ranged attack (its choice) against the creature nearest to it. The berserk creature can repeat the save at the end of its turn, ending the effect on itself on a success.
2 | Bile Blight. The vessel casts the harm spell on each creature within 30 feet of it.
3 | Flood. The vessel casts the tsunami spell at a point of the DM's choice within 120 feet of it.
4 | Medusa's Gaze. The vessel casts the flesh to stone spell on each creature within 30 feet of it.
5 | Labyrinth. The vessel casts the maze spell on each creature within 30 feet of it.
6 | Nightmare. Tendrils of shadow seep from the vessel and form into 1d4} {@creature shadow demon (see the Monster Manual for their stat block), which appear in unoccupied spaces within 30 feet of it and are hostile.
7 | Swarming Insects. The vessel casts the insect plague spell, centered on itself and with a radius of 30 feet.
8 | Unbridled Revel. The vessel casts the Otto's irresistible dance spell on each creature within 30 feet of it.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
    <roll>1d4</roll>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Siren Song Lyre</name>
    <type>W</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 198</text>
    <text>You can use an action to play this lyre and cast one of the following spells from it: animal friendship, charm person, enthrall, suggestion. If the spell requires a saving throw, the spell save DC is 13.
Once the instrument has been used to cast a spell, it can't be used to cast that spell again until the next dawn.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 198</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Sling Bullets of Althemone</name>
    <type>A</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 198</text>
    <text>The sling bullets come in a pouch, which contains 1d4 + 4 bullets. Roll on the Magic Sling Bullets table for each bullet to determine its magical property.
You have a +2 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with each of these bullets. If a bullet misses its target, the bullet teleports back into the pouch. Once a bullet hits a target, the bullet loses its magic.
d4 | Bullet
1 | Banishment. A creature that takes damage from this bullet must succeed on a DC 15 Charisma saving throw or be banished as though affected by the banishment spell.
2 | Fulguration. On a hit, this bullet deals an extra 2d8 lightning damage to its target. All other creatures within 10 feet of the target must each succeed on a DC 15 Constitution saving throw or take 1d8 thunder damage.
3 | Stunning. On a hit, this bullet deals an extra 1d10 force damage, and the target is stunned until the end of your next turn.
4 | Tracking. A creature that takes damage from this bullet is marked with a glowing rune where the bullet hit. The mark lasts 24 hours. While the creature is marked, you always know the direction to it.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 198</text>
    <roll>1d4+4</roll>
    <roll>2d8</roll>
    <roll>1d8</roll>
    <roll>1d10</roll>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Two-Birds Sling</name>
    <type>R</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <value>0.1</value>
    <property>A</property>
    <dmg1>1d4</dmg1>
    <dmgType>B</dmgType>
    <range>30/120</range>
    <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 198</text>
    <text>You have a +1 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with this weapon.
When you make a ranged attack with this sling and hit a target, you can cause the ammunition to ricochet toward a second target within 10 feet of the first, and then make a ranged attack against the second target.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 198</text>
  </item>
  <item>
    <name>Molten Bronze Skin</name>
    <type>G</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
    <text>Molten Bronze Skin (Breastplate)
Molten Bronze Skin (Half Plate)
Molten Bronze Skin (Plate)
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
  </item>


  <!-- Races -->
  <race>
    <name>Leonin</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>35</speed>
    <ability>Str 1, Con 2</ability>
    <proficiency></proficiency>
    <spellAbility></spellAbility>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Leonin mature and age at about the same rate as humans.
      </text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Leonin tend toward good alignments. Leonin who are focused on the pride lean toward lawful good.
      </text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Leonin are typically over 6 feet tall, with some standing over 7 feet. Your size is Medium.
      </text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Darkvision</name>
      <text>You can see in dim light within 60 feet of you as if it were bright light and in darkness as if it were dim light. You can't discern color in darkness, only shades of gray.
      </text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Your claws are natural weapons, which you can use to make unarmed strikes. If you hit with them, you can deal slashing damage equal to 1d4 + your Strength modifier, instead of the bludgeoning damage normal for an unarmed strike.
      </text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Hunter's Instincts</name>
      <text>You have proficiency in one of the following skills of your choice: Athletics, Intimidation, Perception, or Survival.
      </text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Daunting Roar</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, you can let out an especially menacing roar. Creatures of your choice within 10 feet of you that can hear you must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or become frightened of you until the end of your next turn. The DC of the save equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Constitution modifier. Once you use this trait, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.
      </text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Leonin.
      </text>
    </trait>
  </race>
  <race>
    <name>Satyr</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>35</speed>
    <ability>Cha 2, Dex 1</ability>
    <proficiency>Performance, Persuasion</proficiency>
    <spellAbility></spellAbility>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Age</name>
      <text>Satyrs mature and age at about the same rate as humans.
      </text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Satyrs delight in living a life free of the mantle of law. They gravitate toward being good, but some have devious streaks and enjoy causing dismay.
      </text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Size</name>
      <text>Satyrs range from just under 5 feet to about 6 feet in height, with generally slender builds. Your size is Medium.
      </text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Fey</name>
      <text>Your creature type is fey, rather than humanoid.
      </text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Ram</name>
      <text>You can use your head and horns to make unarmed strikes. If you hit with them, you deal bludgeoning damage equal to 1d4 + your Strength modifier.
      </text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>You have advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.
      </text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Mirthful Leaps</name>
      <text>Whenever you make a long or high jump, you can roll a d8 and add the number rolled to the number of feet you cover, even when making a standing jump. This extra distance costs movement as normal.
      </text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Reveler</name>
      <text>You have proficiency in the Performance and Persuasion skills, and you have proficiency with one musical instrument of your choice.
      </text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Sylvan.
      </text>
    </trait>
  </race>


  <!-- Classes -->
  <class>
      <name>Bard</name>

      <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Bard College: College of Eloquence</name>
          <text>Adherents of the College of Eloquence master the art of oratory. Persuasion is regarded as a high art, and a well-reasoned, well-spoken argument often proves more persuasive than facts. These bards wield a blend of logic and theatrical wordplay, winning over skeptics and detractors with logical arguments and plucking at heartstrings to appeal to the emotions of audiences.</text>
          <text></text>
          <text>Silver Tongue</text>
          <text>   3rd-level College of Eloquence feature</text>
          <text>   You are a master at saying the right thing at the right time. When you make a Charisma (Persuasion) or Charisma (Deception) check, you can treat a d20 roll of 9 or lower as a 10.</text>
          <text></text>
          <text>Unsettling Words</text>
          <text>   3rd-level College of Eloquence feature</text>
          <text>   You can spin words laced with magic that unsettle a creature and cause it to doubt itself. As a bonus action, you can expend one use of your Bardic Inspiration and choose one creature you can see within 60 feet of you. Roll the Bardic Inspiration die. The creature must subtract the number rolled from the next saving throw it makes before the start of your next turn.</text>
          <text></text>
          <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 0</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>

      <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Unfailing Inspiration (College of Eloquence)</name>
          <text>   6th-level College of Eloquence feature</text>
          <text>   Your inspiring words are so persuasive that others feel driven to succeed. When a creature adds one of your Bardic Inspiration dice to its ability check, attack roll, or saving throw and the roll fails, the creature can keep the Bardic Inspiration die.</text>
          <name>Universal Speech (College of Eloquence)</name>
          <text>   6th-level College of Eloquence feature</text>
          <text>   You have gained the ability to make your speech intelligible to any creature. As an action, choose one or more creatures within 60 feet of you, up to a number equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of one creature). The chosen creatures can magically understand you, regardless of the language you speak, for 1 hour.</text>
          <text>   Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend a spell slot to use it again.</text>
          <text></text>
          <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 0</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>

      <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Infectious Inspiration (College of Eloquence)</name>
          <text>   14th-level College of Eloquence feature</text>
          <text>   When you successfully inspire someone, the power of your eloquence can now spread to someone else. When a creature within 60 feet of you adds one of your Bardic Inspiration dice to its ability check, attack roll, or saving throw and the roll succeeds, you can use your reaction to encourage a different creature (other than yourself) that can hear you within 60 feet of you, giving it a Bardic Inspiration die without expending any of your Bardic Inspiration uses.</text>
          <text>   You can use this reaction a number of times equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
          <text></text>
          <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 0</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
  </class>

  <class>
    <name>Paladin</name>

    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Sacred Oath: Oath of Glory</name>
        <text>Paladins who take the Oath of Glory believe they and their companions are destined to achieve glory through deeds of heroism. They train diligently and encourage their companions so they're all ready when destiny calls.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Tenets of Glory</text>
        <text>   The tenets of the Oath of Glory drive a paladin to attempt heroics that might one day shine in legend.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Actions over Words</text>
        <text>   Strive to be known by glorious deeds, not words.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Challenges Are but Tests</text>
        <text>   Face hardships with courage, and encourage your allies to face them with you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Hone the Body</text>
        <text>   Like raw stone, your body must be worked so its potential can be realized.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Discipline the Soul</text>
        <text>   You must marshal the discipline to overcome failings within yourself that threaten to dim the glory of you and your friends.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Oath Spells</text>
        <text>   3rd-level Oath of Glory feature</text>
        <text>   You gain oath spells at the paladin levels listed in the Oath of Glory Spells table. See the Sacred Oath class feature for how oath spells work.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Paladin Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | guiding bolt, heroism</text>
        <text>5th | enhance ability, magic weapon</text>
        <text>9th | haste, protection from energy</text>
        <text>13th | compulsion, freedom of movement</text>
        <text>17th | commune, flame strike</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 0</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature>
        <name>Channel Divinity: Peerless Athlete (Oath of the Crown)</name>
        <text>   As a bonus action, you can use your Channel Divinity to augment your athleticism. For the next 10 minutes, you have advantage on Strength (Athletics) and Dexterity (Acrobatics) checks; you can carry, push, drag, and lift twice as much weight as normal; and the distance of your long and high jumps increases by 10 feet (this extra distance costs movement as normal).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 0</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="3">
      <feature>
        <name>Channel Divinity: Inspiring Smite (Oath of the Crown)</name>
        <text>   Immediately after you deal damage to a creature with your Divine Smite feature, you can use your Channel Divinity as a bonus action and distribute temporary hit points to creatures of your choice within 30 feet of you, which can include you. The total number of temporary hit points equals 2d8 + your level in this class, divided among the chosen creatures however you like.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 0</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>

    <autolevel level="7">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Aura of Alacrity (Oath of Glory)</name>
        <text>   7th-level Oath of Glory feature</text>
        <text>   You emanate an aura that fills you and your companions with supernatural speed, allowing you to race across a battlefield in formation. Your walking speed increases by 10 feet. In addition, if you aren't incapacitated, the walking speed of any ally who starts their turn within 5 feet of you increases by 10 feet until the end of that turn.</text>
        <text>   When you reach 18th level in this class, the range of the aura increases to 10 feet.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 0</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Glorious Defense (Oath of Glory)</name>
        <text>   15th-level Oath of Glory feature</text>
        <text>   You can turn defense into a sudden strike. When you or another creature you can see within 10 feet of you is hit by an attack roll, you can use your reaction to grant a bonus to the target's AC against that attack, potentially causing it to miss. The bonus equals your Charisma modifier (minimum of +1). If the attack misses, you can make one weapon attack against the attacker as part of this reaction, provided the attacker is within your weapon's range.</text>
        <text>   You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 0</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
      <feature optional="YES">
        <name>Living Legend (Oath of Glory)</name>
        <text>   20th-level Oath of Glory feature</text>
        <text>   You can empower yourself with the legends—whether true or exaggerated—of your great deeds. As a bonus action, you gain the following benefits for 1 minute:</text>
        <text>• You are blessed with an otherworldly presence, gaining advantage on all Charisma checks.</text>
        <text>• Once on each of your turns when you make a weapon attack and miss, you can cause that attack to hit instead.</text>
        <text>• If you fail a saving throw, you can use your reaction to reroll it. You must use this new roll.</text>
        <text>   Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend a 5th-level spell slot to use it again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 0</text>
      </feature>
    </autolevel>
  </class>


  <!-- Backgrounds -->
  <background>
    <name>Athlete</name>
    <proficiency>Acrobatics, Athletics</proficiency>
    <trait>
      <name>Description</name>
      <text>You strive to perfect yourself physically and in execution of everything you do. The thrill of competition lights fire in your blood, and the roar of the crowd drives you forward. Tales of your exploits precede you and might open doors or loosen tongues.
Whether in one of the poleis, between them, or among the nonhuman peoples of Theros, physical contests and those who pursue them command respect bordering on reverence. Athletes arise from all walks of life and all cultures and quite often cross paths with one another.
• Skill Proficiencies: Acrobatics, Athletics
• Languages: One of your choice
• Tool Proficiencies: Vehicles (land)
• Equipment: A bronze discus or leather ball, a lucky charm or past trophy, a set of traveler's clothes, and a pouch containing 10 gp
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Feature: Echoes of Victory</name>
      <text>You have attracted admiration among spectators, fellow athletes, and trainers in the region that hosted your past athletic victories. When visiting any settlement within 100 miles of where you grew up, there is a 50 percent chance you can find someone there who admires you and is willing to provide information or temporary shelter.
Between adventures, you might compete in athletic events sufficient enough to maintain a comfortable lifestyle, as per the "Practicing a Profession" downtime activity in chapter 8 of the Player's Handbook.
      </text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Favored Event</name>
      <text>While many athletes practice various games and events, most excel at a single form of competition. Roll or choose from the options in the Favored Event table to determine the athletic event in which you excel.
d8 | Favored Event
1 | Marathon
2 | Long-distance running
3 | Wrestling
4 | Boxing
5 | Chariot or horse race
6 | Pankration (mixed unarmed combat)
7 | Hoplite race (racing in full armor with a unit)
8 | Pentathlon (running, long jump, discus, javelin, wrestling)
      </text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Suggested Characteristics</name>
      <text>Competition can forge strong bonds between teammates and rivals or ignite bitter feuds that burn outside the arena. Athletes often apply lessons from their training to their lives in general.
d8 | Personality Trait
1 | I feel most at peace during physical exertion, be it exercise or battle.
2 | I don't like to sit idle.
3 | I have a daily exercise routine that I refuse to break.
4 | Obstacles exist to be overcome.
5 | When I see others struggling, I offer to help.
6 | I love to trade banter and gibes.
7 | Anything worth doing is worth doing best.
8 | I get irritated if people praise someone else and not me.

d6 | Ideal
1 | Competition. I strive to test myself in all things. (Chaotic)
2 | Triumph. The best part of winning is seeing my rivals brought low. (Evil)
3 | Camaraderie. The strongest bonds are forged through struggle. (Good)
4 | People. I strive to inspire my spectators. (Neutral)
5 | Tradition. Every game has rules, and the playing field must be level. (Lawful)
6 | Growth. Lessons hide in victory and defeat. (Any)

d6 | Bond
1 | My teammates are my family.
2 | I will overcome a rival and prove myself their better.
3 | My mistake got someone hurt. I'll never make that mistake again.
4 | I will be the best for the honor and glory of my home.
5 | The person who trained me is the most important person in my world.
6 | I strive to live up to a specific hero's example.

d6 | Flaw
1 | I indulge in a habit that threatens my reputation or my health.
2 | I'll do absolutely anything to win.
3 | I ignore anyone who doesn't compete and anyone who loses to me.
4 | I have lingering pain from old injuries.
5 | Any defeat or failure on my part is because my opponent cheated.
6 | I must be the captain of any group I join.
      </text>
    </trait>
  </background>



  <!-- Monsters -->
  <monster>
    <name>Abhorrent Overlord</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>fiend</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>136 (16d10+48)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Con +7, Cha +7</save>
    <skill>Deception +7, Intimidation +7, Persuasion +7</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist>cold, necrotic</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 219</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Insatiable Greed</name>
      <text>The abhorrent overlord can sense the presence of gold within 1,000 feet of itself. It can determine which location has the greatest amount of gold and can sense the direction to that site. If the gold is being moved, it knows the direction of the movement. It can't locate gold if any thickness of clay or lead, even a thin sheet, blocks a direct path between it and the gold.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The abhorrent overlord has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The abhorrent overlord makes two attacks with its claws.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 14 (2d8 + 5) slashing damage plus 14 (4d6) necrotic damage. The abhorrent overlord regains hit points equal to half the amount of necrotic damage dealt if the target is a creature.</text>
      <attack>Claws|9|2d8+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Storm of Crows (Recharge 6)</name>
      <text>The abhorrent overlord conjures a swarm of spectral crows and harpies in a 20-foot-radius sphere centered on a point the overlord can see within 120 feet of it. The sphere remains for 1 minute or until the overlord loses concentration (as if concentrating on a spell), and its area is lightly obscured and difficult terrain.</text>
      <text>Any creature that moves into the area for the first time on a turn or starts its turn there must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw. A creature takes 16 (3d10) slashing damage plus 16 (3d10) psychic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
    </action>
    <trait>
      <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The abhorrent overlord's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 15). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>1/day each: confusion, crown of madness, suggestion</text>
    </trait>
    <spells>confusion, crown of madness, suggestion</spells>
    <description>Abhorrent overlords are gaunt, bipedal creatures whose gray, leathery skin is in stark contrast to the gleaming jewelry made of Underworld gold that they adorn themselves with. Their appetite for pain and death is eclipsed only by their greed; these fiends delight in searching out treasure and slaughtering all who stand in their way.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 219</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Akroan Hoplite</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>18 (breastplate, shield)</ac>
    <hp>52 (8d8+16)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save>Str +5, Dex +5</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 228</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Hold the Line</name>
      <text>While the hoplite is holding a spear, other creatures provoke an opportunity attack from the hoplite when they move within 5 feet of it. When the hoplite hits a creature with an opportunity attack using its spear, the creature takes an extra 4 (1d8) piercing damage, and the creature's speed becomes 0 for the rest of the turn.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The hoplite makes three melee attacks or two ranged attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., or range 20/60 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage, or 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Spear|5|1d6+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Shield Bash</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 5 (1d4 + 3) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Medium or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 13 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Shield Bash|5|1d4+3</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Akroan hoplites, also called stratians, number among the fiercest soldiers on Theros. They train relentlessly and possess unflinching resolve. In the annals of Akros, tales abound of squads of stratians that defended a key location against a much larger force or crept behind enemy lines and wreaked havoc in the opposing army.
Hoplites are highly trained warriors, versed not only in strategy and tactics but in the glorification of the warrior's spirit, the basis of an ethos that forges an unbreakable bond between members of a military unit. In combat, hoplites typically work in groups and use coordinated tactics to win victories.
The three Hoplite Unit Names tables present the sorts of titles used by hoplite contingents hailing from Theros's great poleis. Consider using these names for military forces characters encounter during their adventures or that they were once a part of.
D8 | Name
1 | Spears of Iroas
2 | Iron Fangs
3 | Arrows of Anax
4 | The Unbroken
5 | Anvil of Purphoros
6 | Skewering Squad
7 | Shield of Akros
8 | Cymede's Heart

Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 228</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Alseid</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>fey</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Good</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>22 (4d8+4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Persuasion +6</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Sylvan</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist>radiant</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 235</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Hide in Plain Sight</name>
      <text>The alseid has advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks made to hide while it is in grassland.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The alseid has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The alseid makes two radiant touch attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Radiant Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (1d10 + 4) radiant damage.</text>
      <attack>Radiant Touch|6|1d10+4</attack>
    </action>
    <trait>
      <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The alseid's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 14). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>3/day each: cure wounds, charm person, sleep</text>
      <text>1/day each: calm emotions, lesser restoration, plant growth</text>
    </trait>
    <spells>cure wounds, charm person, sleep, calm emotions, lesser restoration, plant growth</spells>
    <description>Touched with the golden light of the sun, alseids inhabit meadows, plains, and lands of cultivated natural beauty. Many live in closer proximity to human civilization than other nymphs. Farmers are grateful for the presence of alseids on their lands and often leave them offerings of mead, honey, flowers, and dates in return for protecting their flocks and making their crops more abundant.
Nymphs:
Divine servants that inhabit unspoiled corners of the world, nymphs protect places of natural power and infuse their surroundings with the magic of Nyx. Some are benevolent and aid those who live off the land, while others embody violent aspects of nature. In either case, nymphs generally avoid other sapient creatures, preferring to mind the cycles of nature, the daily interplay of wild animals, or other cosmic forces. Occasionally, though, groups of the same kind of nymphs congregate in a place of natural power or beauty. In times of special need, deities tied to facets of nature might employ nymphs as messengers, guardians, or scouts.
A nymph doesn't require food, drink, or sleep.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 235</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Anvilwrought Raptor</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>18 (4d4+8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 10 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>understands one language of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 209</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Keen Sight</name>
      <text>The raptor has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Recorded Mimicry</name>
      <text>The raptor can mimic any sound, including voices, it has heard in the last 24 hours. A creature that hears the sounds can tell they are imitations with a successful DC 12 Wisdom (Insight) check.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The raptor makes two attacks with its beak.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Beak</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Beak|5|1d4+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Variant: Anvilwrought Raptor Familiar</name>
      <text>Some anvilwrought raptors are created expressly to be familiars. Such creatures have the following trait.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Familiar</name>
      <text>The anvilwrought can serve another creature as a familiar, forming a magical, telepathic bond with its willing master. While the two are bonded, the master can sense what the anvilwrought senses, as long as they are within 1 mile of each other.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Prized among Meletis's thaumaturges, anvilwrought raptors are often crafted in the form of a hawk or an owl. Most serve as messengers and spies, flying over the busy streets or high over the land while carrying or seeking vital information for their masters.
The first anvilwroughts were created by the god of the forge, Purphoros. He gave the secret of breathing life into these metal creatures to his most devoted followers so they could mimic his works and invent new forms at their own forges.
Some anvilwroughts are vigilant guardians at holy shrines, others serve as familiars and messengers, and a few were created to emulate beauty found among the animals of the mortal world. Each exhibits abilities suited to its role, with some behaving like companionable creatures or stoic guardians.
A few extremely rare and valuable anvilwroughts were crafted by the hand of Purphoros himself. A number of these magnificent creations are now heirlooms of monarchs; others are lost to the sands of time or are guarded by ancient monsters.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 209</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Aphemia</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>52 (8d8+16)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., fly 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Dex +6, Cha +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +4, Intimidation +6, Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist>necrotic</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 226</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (2/Day)</name>
      <text>If Aphemia fails a saving throw, she can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Aphemia has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Aphemia makes two attacks: one with her bite and one with her claws.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (2d4 + 3) piercing damage plus 13 (3d8) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|6|2d4+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (2d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|6|2d6+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Discordant Song</name>
      <text>Aphemia shrieks a cacophony of magical sounds. Each humanoid within 120 feet of her must succeed on a DC 14 Wisdom saving throw or be frightened of her until the song ends. A frightened creature takes 7 (2d6) psychic damage at the start of its turn while Aphemia is singing. A frightened creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. If a creature's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the creature is immune to Aphemia's Discordant Song for the next 24 hours. Aphemia must take a bonus action on her subsequent turns to continue singing. She can stop singing at any time. The song ends if Aphemia is incapacitated or dies.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Grave Calling Song</name>
      <text>Aphemia intones a low, growling magical melody. Every undead within 300 feet of her must succeed on a DC 14 Wisdom saving throw or fall under her control until the song ends. Aphemia must take a bonus action on her subsequent turns to continue singing, and she can mentally command the undead under her control as part of the same bonus action. She can stop singing at any time. The song ends if Aphemia is incapacitated or dies.</text>
    </action>
    <description>The notorious Nyxborn harpy Aphemia prowls the marshy wastes around the necropolis of Asphodel. Her shrill songs enthrall the necropolis's undead inhabitants, which she leads on raids to waylay unsuspecting travelers and settlements.
Cruel, corpse-eating creatures, harpies endlessly seek their next meal, careless of whether it comes from the living or the dead. With equal zeal, these vicious scavengers set upon travelers or claw open fresh graves, stripping bodies of riches and flesh. Then they carry back any treasures or appealing bones they find to reeking nests situated in cramped caves or rotten trees.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 226</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Arasta</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>300 (24d12+144)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., climb 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>24</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>23</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>22</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save>Dex +10, Con +13, Wis +13</save>
    <skill>Arcana +9, Deception +10, Intimidation +10, Nature +9, Perception +13, Stealth +10</skill>
    <passive>23</passive>
    <languages>Celestial, Common, Sylvan</languages>
    <cr>21</cr>
    <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>acid, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft., darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 248</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Armor of Spiders (Mythic Trait; Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>If Arasta is reduced to 0 hit points, she doesn't die or fall unconscious. Instead, she regains 200 hit points. In addition, Arasta's children immediately swarm over her body to protect her, granting her 100 temporary hit points.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If Arasta fails a saving throw, she can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Arasta has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spider Climb</name>
      <text>Arasta can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without needing to make an ability check.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Web Walker</name>
      <text>Arasta ignores movement restrictions caused by webbing.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Arasta makes three attacks: one with her bite and two with her claws.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 20 (3d8 + 7) piercing damage, and the target must make a DC 21 Constitution saving throw, taking 32 (5d12) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. If the damage reduces the target to 0 hit points, the target is stable but poisoned for 1 hour, even after regaining hit points, and is paralyzed while poisoned in this way.</text>
      <attack>Bite|14|3d8+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 17 (3d6 + 7) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|14|3d6+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Web of Hair (Recharge 4-6)</name>
      <text>Arasta unleashes her hair in the form of webbing that fills a 30-foot cube next to her. The web is difficult terrain, its area is lightly obscured, and it lasts for 1 minute. Any creature that moves into the web or that starts its turn there must make a DC 21 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, the creature is restrained while in the web. A creature can use an action to make a DC 21 Strength check. On a success, it can free itself or a creature within 5 feet of it that is restrained by the web. This webbing is immune to all damage except magical fire. A 5-foot cube of the web is destroyed if it takes at least 20 fire damage from a spell or other magical source on a single turn.</text>
    </action>
    <legendary>
      <text>Arasta can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Arasta regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Arasta makes one attack with her claws.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Swarm (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Arasta causes two swarms of spiders (see the Monster Manual) to appear in unoccupied spaces within 5 feet of her.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Toxic Web (Costs 3 Actions)</name>
      <text>Each creature restrained by Arasta's Web of Hair takes 18 (4d8) poison damage.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Mythic Actions</name>
      <text>If Arasta's mythic trait is active, she can use the options below as legendary actions, as long as she has temporary hit points from her Armor of Spiders.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Swipe</name>
      <text>Arasta makes two attacks with her claws.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Web of Hair (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Arasta recharges Web of Hair and uses it.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Nyx Weave (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Each creature restrained by Arasta's Web of Hair must succeed on a DC 21 Constitution saving throw, or the creature takes 26 (4d12) force damage and any spell of 6th level or lower on it ends.</text>
    </legendary>
    <description>A victim of the gods' petty rivalries, Arasta was once one of Nylea's most beloved dryad companions. Phenax's bitterness saw her transformed into an arachnid monstrosity and driven into the darkest depths of the Nessian Wood. Now she broods on her unjust fate and the fickleness of the gods who left her cursed with monstrous immortality.
Arasta appears as a gigantic spiderlike creature, her few humanoid features made monstrous by cruel magic and ages of hatred. Webs fill her lair deep in the Nessian Wood, sticky strands made not of silk but of her own endless hair. In her darkened realm, Arasta broods on her hatred of the gods and their servants. She doesn't do so alone, though, as innumerable arachnids fawn over her, serving as her eyes throughout the wilderness, disposing of victims trapped within her hair, and sacrificing themselves in her defense if they must.
See " Myths of Nylea" in chapter 2for more details on the tragedy of Arasta.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 248</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Archon of Falling Stars</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>144 (17d8+68)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>19</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>21</wis>
    <cha>19</cha>
    <save>Str +9, Con +8, Wis +9, Cha +8</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, History +6, Insight +9, Perception +9</skill>
    <passive>19</passive>
    <languages>all</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>radiant</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 212</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The archon has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Mount</name>
      <text>If the archon isn't mounted, it can use a bonus action to magically teleport onto the creature serving as its mount, provided the archon and its mount are on the same plane of existence. When it teleports, the archon appears astride the mount, along with any equipment it is wearing or carrying. While mounted and not incapacitated, the archon can't be surprised, and both it and its mount have advantage on Dexterity saving throws. If the archon is reduced to 0 hit points while riding its mount, the mount is reduced to 0 hit points as well.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Radiant Rebirth (Recharges after a Long Rest)</name>
      <text>If the archon is reduced to 0 hit points, it regains 30 hit points and springs back to its feet with a burst of radiance. Each creature of the archon's choice within 30 feet of it must succeed on a DC 16 Constitution saving throw, or the creature takes 13 (3d8) radiant damage and is blinded until the start of the archon's turn.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The archon makes two attacks with its radiant spear.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Radiant Spear</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 12 (2d6 + 5) piercing damage plus 10 (3d6) radiant damage.</text>
      <attack>Radiant Spear|9|2d6+5</attack>
    </action>
    <legendary>
      <text>The celestial can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The celestial regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Attack</name>
      <text>The archon makes a radiant spear attack or casts guiding bolt.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Coordinated Assault (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>The archon makes a radiant spear attack, and then its mount can use its reaction to make a melee weapon attack.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Return to Nyx (Costs 3 Actions)</name>
      <text>The archon causes a corpse it can see within 30 feet of it to burst into a shower of radiant stars leaving no trace of it behind. Everything it is wearing or carrying remains. Each creature within 10 feet of the corpse when it bursts must succeed on a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw or take 22 (4d10) radiant damage.</text>
    </legendary>
    <trait>
      <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The archon's spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks). The archon can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: command, guiding bolt, spare the dying</text>
      <text>1/day each: crusader's mantle, spirit guardians</text>
    </trait>
    <spells>command, guiding bolt, spare the dying, crusader's mantle, spirit guardians</spells>
    <description>The epic accounting of the world's earliest histories calledThe Cosmogonyrecounts the battle between a group of the gods' champions and a mighty archon, which took place at the mysterious eastern edge of the world. Defeated, the falling archon is said to have met the rising sun. But Heliod showed mercy to the penitent archon, who swore to uphold justice and righteousness in the world's wildest places. As a sign of his mercy, Heliod gave the archon a spear that rivaled his own in its brilliance. This was the first archon of falling stars.
The mysterious conquerors known as archons once ruled vast empires. These armored warlords saw themselves as champions of merciless justice, and they ruled with iron fists. But their dominance ultimately came to an end. As the archon overlords toppled, they scattered to the fringes of the world, and their holdings developed into the poleis of today.
Even though the age of archons is long past, many wonder if the few surviving archons might someday attempt to reestablish their empire or if they are truly resigned to their lesser role in the world.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 212</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Ashen Rider</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>178 (21d8+84)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>19</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>21</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Str +10, Con +9, Wis +10, Cha +9</save>
    <skill>History +7, Insight +10, Perception +10</skill>
    <passive>20</passive>
    <languages>all</languages>
    <cr>16</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>thunder</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 213</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Aura of Silence</name>
      <text>When a creature starts its turn within 30 feet of the ashen rider, the rider can force that creature to make a DC 18 Wisdom saving throw if the rider can see it. On a successful save, the creature is immune to this aura for the next 24 hours. On a failed save, the creature can't speak and is deafened until the start of its next turn.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Mount</name>
      <text>If the ashen rider isn't mounted, it can use a bonus action to magically teleport onto the creature serving as its mount, provided the ashen rider and its mount are on the same plane of existence. When it teleports, the ashen rider appears astride the mount along with any equipment it is wearing or carrying.</text>
      <text>While mounted and not incapacitated, the ashen rider can't be surprised, and both it and its mount have advantage on Dexterity saving throws. If the ashen rider is reduced to 0 hit points while riding its mount, the mount is reduced to 0 hit points as well.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The ashen rider makes three attacks with its ashen blade or two attacks with its bolt of ash.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Ashen Blade</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 14 (2d8 + 5) slashing damage plus 13 (2d12) radiant damage.</text>
      <attack>Ashen Blade|10|2d8+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bolt of Ash</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +10 to hit, range 120 ft., one creature. 22 (4d10) necrotic damage, and the target can't regain hit points until the start of the ashen rider's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Bolt of Ash|10|4d10</attack>
    </action>
    <legendary>
      <text>The celestial can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The celestial regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Attack</name>
      <text>The ashen rider makes an attack using its ashen blade or bolt of ash.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Coordinated Assault (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>The ashen rider makes an attack using its ashen blade or bolt of ash, and then its mount can use its reaction to make a melee weapon attack.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Reduce to Ash (Costs 3 Actions)</name>
      <text>The ashen rider targets a creature it can see within 60 feet of it. The target must succeed on a DC 18 Constitution saving throw, or it takes 27 (5d10) necrotic damage and its hit point maximum is reduced by an amount equal to the necrotic damage taken. This reduction lasts until the target finishes a long rest. If the target's hit point maximum is reduced to 0, its body and everything it is wearing and carrying, except for magic items, are reduced to ash. A creature reduced to ash can't be revived by any means short of a wish spell.</text>
    </legendary>
    <trait>
      <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The ashen rider's spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 18). The rider can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: command, compelled duel</text>
      <text>1/day each: banishment, blade barrier</text>
    </trait>
    <spells>command, compelled duel, banishment, blade barrier</spells>
    <description>The fall of the ancient archon empires left some archons bitter and resentful. Seeking to avoid the spread of human civilization, these archons made their way to the Underworld. The horrors of the place broke their minds, bodies, and spirits and twisted them into the terrifying archons known as ashen riders. When they ride forth upon the mortal world, terrified mortals make offerings in a desperate attempt to appease them, but the ashen riders aren't merciful, and they delight in reducing the paragons of the mortal world to ash.
The mysterious conquerors known as archons once ruled vast empires. These armored warlords saw themselves as champions of merciless justice, and they ruled with iron fists. But their dominance ultimately came to an end. As the archon overlords toppled, they scattered to the fringes of the world, and their holdings developed into the poleis of today.
Even though the age of archons is long past, many wonder if the few surviving archons might someday attempt to reestablish their empire or if they are truly resigned to their lesser role in the world.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 213</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Blood-Toll Harpy</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>9 (2d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Intimidation +3</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 227</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Blood Frenzy</name>
      <text>The harpy has advantage on melee attack rolls against any creature that doesn't have all its hit points.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Dark Devotion</name>
      <text>The harpy has advantage on saving throws against being charmed or frightened.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The harpy makes two melee attacks: one with its bite and one with its claws.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d4 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|3|1d4+1</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d4 + 1) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|3|1d4+1</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Murderous gangs of harpies collect in grim places across Theros, preying on any who pass by. Many merchants face regular losses at the harpies' claws, common casualties often referred to as a "blood toll."
Cruel, corpse-eating creatures, harpies endlessly seek their next meal, careless of whether it comes from the living or the dead. With equal zeal, these vicious scavengers set upon travelers or claw open fresh graves, stripping bodies of riches and flesh. Then they carry back any treasures or appealing bones they find to reeking nests situated in cramped caves or rotten trees.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 227</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Broken King Antigonos</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>38 (9d10+27)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 189</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Charge</name>
      <text>If Antigonos moves at least 10 feet straight toward a target and then hits it with a gore attack on the same turn, the target takes an extra 9 (2d8) piercing damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 14 Strength saving throw or be pushed up to 10 feet away and knocked prone.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Labyrinthine Recall</name>
      <text>Antigonos can perfectly recall any path he has traveled.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Reckless</name>
      <text>At the start of his turn, Antigonos can gain advantage on all melee weapon attack rolls he makes during that turn, but attack rolls against him have advantage until the start of his next turn.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Decrepit State</name>
      <text>Antigonos has disadvantage on his attack rolls.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Greataxe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 17 (2d12 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Greataxe|6|2d12+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Gore</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d8 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Gore|6|2d8+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Amphora</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one Medium or smaller creature. 8 (1d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage. If there is not already a creature inside the amphora, the target is restrained inside. As an action, the restrained creature can make a DC 14 Dexterity (Acrobatics) check, escaping from the amphora on a success. The effect also ends if the amphora is destroyed. The amphora has AC 8, 20 hit points, and immunity to poison and psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Amphora|6|1d8+4</attack>
    </action>
    <description>He is old and decrepit, garbed in ancient finery worn to tatters. A dented crown rests on his brow, and one of his horns ends in a jagged stump. He drags a rusty greataxe in the dirt, and tied to his back is a 30-pound, clay amphora painted with images of warring hoplites—all of whom have had horns crudely painted on them to make them look like minotaurs. The broad-mouthed amphora is large enough to hold roughly 55 gallons of wine.
He claims that he was a great king who was cursed by Mogis after he defied his war advisors by making his sickly but beloved child his heir. He was cast out and has since become tragically obsessed with finding a worthy heir.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 189</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Bronze Sable</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>32 (5d8+10)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>understands one language of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 210</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>False Appearance</name>
      <text>While the sable remains motionless, it is indistinguishable from a normal statue.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>The sable has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the sable's allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Surprise Attack</name>
      <text>If the sable surprises a creature and hits it with an attack during the first round of combat, the target takes an extra 10 (3d6) damage from the attack.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The sable makes two bite attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|5|1d8+3</attack>
    </action>
    <description>The first bronze sables were presented to Karametra as a gift by Purphoros to serve primarily as guardians in Karametra's temples. But as others have been created, some have been used as nimble scouts, always on alert for danger.
The first anvilwroughts were created by the god of the forge, Purphoros. He gave the secret of breathing life into these metal creatures to his most devoted followers so they could mimic his works and invent new forms at their own forges.
Some anvilwroughts are vigilant guardians at holy shrines, others serve as familiars and messengers, and a few were created to emulate beauty found among the animals of the mortal world. Each exhibits abilities suited to its role, with some behaving like companionable creatures or stoic guardians.
A few extremely rare and valuable anvilwroughts were crafted by the hand of Purphoros himself. A number of these magnificent creations are now heirlooms of monarchs; others are lost to the sands of time or are guarded by ancient monsters.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 210</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Burnished Hart</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>45 (6d8+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>17</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>understands one language of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 211</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Charge</name>
      <text>If the hart moves at least 20 feet straight toward a target and then hits it with an antlers attack on the same turn, the target takes an extra 7 (2d6) fire damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 13 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Heated Body</name>
      <text>A creature that touches the hart or hits it with a melee attack while within 5 feet of it takes 5 (1d10) fire damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Sure-Footed</name>
      <text>The hart has advantage on Strength and Dexterity saving throws made against effects that would knock it prone.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The hart makes two attacks: one with its antlers and one with its hooves.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Antlers</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Antlers|5|1d8+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Hooves</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) bludgeoning damage plus 2 (1d4) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Hooves|5|1d4+3</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Among the first anvilwroughts to be forged by Purphoros, elegant burnished harts wander the mortal realm in search of new sights to bring back to the god of the forge. On every trip from Mount Velus, where Purphoros has his forge, they seek out the far reaches of the world so they can witness beauty in all its forms, then later reunite with their creator, their minds filled with tales of how life's splendor continues to develop.
The first anvilwroughts were created by the god of the forge, Purphoros. He gave the secret of breathing life into these metal creatures to his most devoted followers so they could mimic his works and invent new forms at their own forges.
Some anvilwroughts are vigilant guardians at holy shrines, others serve as familiars and messengers, and a few were created to emulate beauty found among the animals of the mortal world. Each exhibits abilities suited to its role, with some behaving like companionable creatures or stoic guardians.
A few extremely rare and valuable anvilwroughts were crafted by the hand of Purphoros himself. A number of these magnificent creations are now heirlooms of monarchs; others are lost to the sands of time or are guarded by ancient monsters.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 211</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Colossus of Akros</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>21 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>350 (20d20+140)</hp>
    <speed>walk 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>28</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>25</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save>Str +16, Con +14</save>
    <skill>Athletics +16, Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>understands Common and Celestial but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>23</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire, poison, psychic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 218</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Crumbling Destruction</name>
      <text>When the colossus drops to 0 hit points, it crumbles and is destroyed. Any creature on the ground within 30 feet of the crumbling statue must make a DC 22 Dexterity saving throw, taking 22 (4d10) bludgeoning damage and 22 (4d10) fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Fire Absorption</name>
      <text>Whenever the colossus is subjected to fire damage, it takes no damage and instead regains a number of hit points equal to the fire damage dealt.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The colossus is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Weapons</name>
      <text>The colossus's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The colossus deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The colossus of Akros makes two melee attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +16 to hit, reach 15 ft., or range 200/600 ft., one target. 23 (4d6 + 9) piercing damage, or 27 (4d8 + 9) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack. If the colossus makes a ranged attack with this spear, the spear magically returns to its hand after the attack.</text>
      <attack>Spear|16|4d6+9</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Sword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +16 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. 36 (6d8 + 9) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Sword|16|6d8+9</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Flames of Akros (Recharge 6)</name>
      <text>Magical flames issue from the colossus toward up to three creatures the colossus can see within 90 feet of it. Each target must make a DC 24 Dexterity saving throw, taking 36 (8d8) fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. On a failed save, a target also magically catches fire for 1 minute. At the end of each of its turns thereafter, the burning target repeats the saving throw. It takes 18 (4d8) fire damage on a failed save, and the effect ends on a successful one.</text>
    </action>
    <description>An enormous golem of bronze and iron overlooks the path leading to the polis of Akros. Though it is rarely called on to defend the polis, the sight of its towering form is enough to ease the minds of the populace. In truly desperate times, priests of Purphoros work their magic to call the colossus to life, whereupon the earth rumbles as it steps down from its twin plinths to place itself before the threat.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 218</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Doomwake Giant</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>162 (13d12+78)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>24</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>22</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Con +10, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Intimidation +7, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Giant</languages>
    <cr>11</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>necrotic, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 224</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Aura of Erebos</name>
      <text>Any creature that starts its turn within 10 feet of the giant must succeed on a DC 18 Constitution saving throw, or it takes 10 (3d6) necrotic damage and can't regain hit points until the start of its next turn. On a successful saving throw, the creature is immune to the giant's Aura of Erebos for 24 hours.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The giant has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The giant makes two slam attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. 20 (3d8 + 7) bludgeoning damage plus 10 (3d6) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|11|3d8+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Noxious Gust (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The giant exhales a mighty gust that creates a blast of deadly mist in a 60-foot line that is 10 feet wide. Each creature in that line must make a DC 18 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the creature takes 36 (8d8) necrotic damage and is knocked prone. On a successful save, a creature takes half as much damage and isn't knocked prone.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Belief is a powerful force in Theros, capable of bringing about wonders and changing the world—but not always for the better. Doomwake giants arise from pernicious fears that infect a whole city or region. If enough mortals dread destruction for long enough, their terror can manifest as one of these massive Nyxborn beings. Once unleashed, a doomwake giant goes on a rampage, fulfilling the prophecy mortals believed into being. After doing so, these terrors typically roam to the edges of the world, where they either fade away over time or become legends that take on their own terrible life.
A spectrum of giants claims territory across Theros, drawing strength from aspects of the world itself—from ancient stone and roiling flames to the depths of the seas and skies. Unlike many creatures of legend, most giants owe their existence not to Nyx and the dreams of mortals, but to natural forces in the land. As a result, Theran giants are typically infused with the elements they embody, which might manifest as flaming beards, frozen skin, hair crackling with lightning, or other primal incarnations.
Beyond these primal giants, though, other giants fill the tales of Theros.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 224</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Eater of Hope</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>fiend</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>90 (12d10+24)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Con +5, Cha +6</save>
    <skill>Deception +6, Intimidation +6, Persuasion +6</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist>cold, necrotic</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 220</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Insatiable Greed</name>
      <text>The eater of hope can sense the presence of gold within 1,000 feet of itself. It can determine which location has the greatest amount of gold and can sense the direction to that site. If the gold is being moved, it knows the direction of the movement. It can't locate gold if any thickness of clay or lead, even a thin sheet, blocks a direct path between it and the gold.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The eater of hope has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The eater of hope makes two attacks with its claws.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (1d8 + 4) slashing damage plus 7 (2d6) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|7|1d8+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Breath of Hopelessness (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The eater of hope exhales a miasma of Underworld winds in a 30-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 14 Charisma saving throw. On a failed save, the target takes 26 (4d12) necrotic damage and is cursed for 1 minute. While cursed in this way, the target takes an extra 6 (1d12) necrotic damage whenever the eater of hope hits it with an attack. On a successful save, the target takes half as much damage and isn't cursed.</text>
    </action>
    <description>An eater of hope is bitter to the core, resentful of all forms of life and joy. Although these demons can strike down most foes, they prefer to let terror and despair overtake their victims first, letting their victims marinate in fear before the fiend devours them.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 220</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Fleecemane Lion</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>45 (6d10+12)</hp>
    <speed>walk 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Str +6, Con +4</save>
    <skill>Perception +4, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 223</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>The lion has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Pounce</name>
      <text>If the lion moves at least 20 feet straight toward a creature and then hits it with a claw attack on the same turn, that target must succeed on a DC 14 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone. If the target is prone, the lion can make one bite attack against it as a bonus action.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Running Leap</name>
      <text>With a 10-foot running start, the lion can long jump up to 25 feet.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spell Turning</name>
      <text>The lion has advantage on saving throws against any spell that targets only the lion (not an area). If the lion's saving throw succeeds and the spell is of 4th level or lower, the spell has no effect on the lion and instead targets the caster.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The lion makes two attacks: one with its bite and one with its claw.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (1d8 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|6|1d8+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|6|1d6+4</attack>
    </action>
    <legendary>
      <text>The monstrosity can take 2 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The monstrosity regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Claw</name>
      <text>The lion makes one claw attack.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Roar (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>The lion emits a magical roar. Each creature within 60 feet of the lion that can hear the roar must succeed on a DC 12 Wisdom saving throw or be frightened of the lion until the end of the lion's next turn.</text>
    </legendary>
    <description>Twice the size of normal lions and with resplendent manes of silvery or golden hair, fleecemane lions prowl and protect sites imbued with the power of Nyx. While the specifics of these massive lions' connection to Nyx is unclear, many myths tell of the deadly predators stalking mortals and spreading fear until they're ultimately defeated by a brave hunter. As a result, overcoming a fleecemane lion is widely considered an early step on the road to becoming a true hero.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 223</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Flitterstep Eidolon</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>14</ac>
    <hp>44 (8d8+8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>8</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +3, Stealth +8</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>the languages it knew in life</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist>necrotic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 222</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Blurred Form</name>
      <text>Attack rolls against the eidolon are made with disadvantage unless the eidolon is incapacitated.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Evasion</name>
      <text>If the eidolon is subjected to an effect that allows it to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, the eidolon instead takes no damage if it succeeds on the saving throw, and only half damage if it fails. It can't use this trait if it's incapacitated.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Incorporeal Movement</name>
      <text>The eidolon can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. It takes 5 (1d10) force damage if it ends its turn inside an object.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Turn Resistance</name>
      <text>The eidolon has advantage on saving throws against any effect that turns undead.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The eidolon makes two melee attacks. Immediately before or after one of its attacks, it can use Flitterstep if it is available.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Flickering Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d4 + 4) piercing damage plus 3 (1d6) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Flickering Dagger|6|1d4+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Flitterstep (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The eidolon magically teleports to an unoccupied space it can see within 30 feet of it. If it makes an attack immediately after teleporting, it has advantage on the attack roll.</text>
    </action>
    <description>When a mortal soul traumatically sacrifices its identity in order to escape the Underworld as a Returned, its identity manifests as a spirit-like eidolon. While eidolons possess many of the skills and details related to their past lives, they're disconnected from those experiences, choosing to wander the world or brood in haunts they're drawn to in death. They care nothing for morbid reunions with their lost bodies or Returned remnants.
Of the various types of eidolons, flitterstep eidolons are the most common and wander without purpose.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 222</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Ghostblade Eidolon</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>55 (10d8+10)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +5, Athletics +6, Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>the languages it knew in life</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist>necrotic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 222</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Blurred Form</name>
      <text>Attack rolls against the eidolon are made with disadvantage unless the eidolon is incapacitated.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Incorporeal Movement</name>
      <text>The eidolon can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. It takes 5 (1d10) force damage if it ends its turn inside an object.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Turn Resistance</name>
      <text>The eidolon has advantage on saving throws against any effect that turns undead.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The eidolon makes two ghostblade attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Ghostblade</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (1d8 + 3) slashing damage plus 11 (2d10) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Ghostblade|6|1d8+3</attack>
    </action>
    <description>When a mortal soul traumatically sacrifices its identity in order to escape the Underworld as a Returned, its identity manifests as a spirit-like eidolon. While eidolons possess many of the skills and details related to their past lives, they're disconnected from those experiences, choosing to wander the world or brood in haunts they're drawn to in death. They care nothing for morbid reunions with their lost bodies or Returned remnants.
Of the various types of eidolons, ghostblade eidolons typically arise from fallen warriors and believe they're endlessly embroiled in great battles.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 222</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Gold-Forged Sentinel</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>76 (8d10+32)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>19</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>understands one language of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 211</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Charge</name>
      <text>If the sentinel moves at least 20 feet straight toward a target and then hits it with a ram attack on the same turn, the target takes an extra 10 (3d6) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 15 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spell Turning</name>
      <text>The sentinel has advantage on saving throws against any spell that targets only the sentinel (not an area). If the sentinel's saving throw succeeds and the spell is of 4th level or lower, the spell has no effect on the sentinel and instead targets the caster.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The sentinel makes two ram attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Ram</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Ram|7|2d8+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Fire Breath (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The sentinel exhales fire in a 15-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw, taking 27 (6d8) fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
    </action>
    <description>The original purpose of gold-forged sentinels is a mystery, and of all Purphoros's original anvilwroughts, this construct is the most difficult to control. A sentinel often operates without a master, stalking the high places of the mortal world or waiting, still as a statue, for what could be decades before reanimating to carry out their mysterious purpose.
The first anvilwroughts were created by the god of the forge, Purphoros. He gave the secret of breathing life into these metal creatures to his most devoted followers so they could mimic his works and invent new forms at their own forges.
Some anvilwroughts are vigilant guardians at holy shrines, others serve as familiars and messengers, and a few were created to emulate beauty found among the animals of the mortal world. Each exhibits abilities suited to its role, with some behaving like companionable creatures or stoic guardians.
A few extremely rare and valuable anvilwroughts were crafted by the hand of Purphoros himself. A number of these magnificent creations are now heirlooms of monarchs; others are lost to the sands of time or are guarded by ancient monsters.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 211</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Hippocamp</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Good</alignment>
    <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>22 (4d10)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., swim 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>5</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist>cold</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 227</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The hippocamp can breathe air and water.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Charge</name>
      <text>If the hippocamp moves at least 20 feet straight toward a target and then hits it with a ram attack on the same turn, the target takes an extra 7 (2d6) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 12 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Hooves</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (2d6 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Hooves|4|2d6+2</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Ram</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Ram|4|1d6+2</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Noble steeds of the sea, hippocamps feature in countless tales as guides and mounts to tritons and other ocean-faring heroes. While these curious but cautious aquatic equines naturally travel in herds, many hold valued places in triton society. Considered to be servants of Thassa, hippocamps are often unpredictable, but their great speed and strength can prove awe-inspiring when harnessed by the god's will.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 227</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Hundred-Handed One</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>243 (18d12+126)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>26</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>25</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Con +12, Wis +8</save>
    <skill>Intimidation +8, Perception +8</skill>
    <passive>18</passive>
    <languages>Giant</languages>
    <cr>15</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 225</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Reactive</name>
      <text>The giant can take one reaction on every turn in a combat.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Vigilant</name>
      <text>The giant can't be surprised.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The giant makes four longsword attacks or two rock attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Longsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. 21 (3d8 + 8) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Longsword|13|3d8+8</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Rock</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, range 60/240 ft., one target. 30 (4d10 + 8) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 21 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Rock|13|4d10+8</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Deflect Attack</name>
      <text>The giant adds 5 to its AC against one weapon attack that would hit it. To do so, the giant must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
    </reaction>
    <description>Extra pairs of arms magically orbit the bodies of the titanic, nearly forgotten artisans known as hundred-handed ones. These giants often dwell in remote mountains and seaside cliffs, where they carve their memories into the ancient stone, covering their territories with intricate reliefs and massive statues of bygone ages. Some linger near ancient temples and palaces, ruins they once raised to the gods or archons of old.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 225</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Hythonia</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>199 (21d10+84)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., climb 40 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>21</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>19</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Str +11, Con +10, Cha +10</save>
    <skill>Deception +10, Insight +9, Perception +9, Stealth +9</skill>
    <passive>19</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>17</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 252</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If Hythonia fails a saving throw, she can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Petrifying Gaze</name>
      <text>When a creature that can see Hythonia's eyes starts its turn within 30 feet of her, Hythonia can force it to make a DC 18 Constitution saving throw if she isn't incapacitated and can see the creature. If the saving throw fails by 5 or more, the creature is instantly petrified. Otherwise, on a failed save the creature begins to turn to stone and is restrained. The restrained creature must repeat the saving throw at the end of its next turn, becoming petrified on a failure or ending the effect on a success. The petrification lasts until the creature is freed by the greater restoration spell or other magic. Unless surprised, a creature can avert its eyes to avoid the saving throw at the start of its turn. If the creature does so, it can't see Hythonia until the start of its next turn, when it can avert its eyes again. If the creature looks at Hythonia in the meantime, it must immediately make the save. If Hythonia sees herself reflected on a polished surface within 30 feet of her and in an area of bright light, she is affected by her own gaze.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Shed Skin (Mythic Trait; Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>If Hythonia is reduced to 0 hit points, she doesn't die or fall unconscious. Instead, she sheds her skin, regains 199 hit points, and moves up to her speed without provoking opportunity attacks.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Hythonia makes three attacks: one with her claws, one to constrict, and one with her snaky hair.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (1d8 + 5) slashing damage plus 4 (1d8) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|11|1d8+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Constrict</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 15 ft., one Large or smaller creature. 16 (2d10 + 5) bludgeoning damage, and the target is grappled (escape DC 19). Until this grapple ends, the target is restrained and takes 15 (3d6 + 5) bludgeoning damage at the start of each of its turns, and Hythonia can't constrict another target.</text>
      <attack>Constrict|11|2d10+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Snaky Hair</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 31 (4d12 + 5) bludgeoning damage, and Hythonia can pull the target up to 5 feet closer to her if it is a Large or smaller creature.</text>
      <attack>Snaky Hair|11|4d12+5</attack>
    </action>
    <legendary>
      <text>Hythonia can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Hythonia regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Move</name>
      <text>Hythonia moves up to her speed without provoking opportunity attacks.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Snaky Hair</name>
      <text>Hythonia makes one attack with her snaky hair.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Petrified Earth (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Hythonia causes stone spikes to erupt from the ground in a 30-foot radius centered on her. The area becomes difficult terrain until the start of her next turn. Any creature, other than Hythonia, takes 9 (2d8) piercing damage for every 5 feet it moves on those spikes.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Mythic Actions</name>
      <text>If Hythonia's mythic trait is active, she can use the options below as legendary actions for 1 hour after using Shed Skin.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Numbing Claws</name>
      <text>Hythonia makes two attacks with her claws. If both attacks hit the same creature, it takes an extra 7 (2d6) poison damage and must succeed on a DC 18 Constitution saving throw or become paralyzed until the start of her next turn.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Look at Me (Costs 3 Actions)</name>
      <text>Hythonia can force a sighted creature she has grappled to see her eyes and be affected by her gaze.</text>
    </legendary>
    <trait>
      <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Hythonia's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 18). She can innately cast animate objects once per day requiring no material components.</text>
      <text>1/day: animate objects</text>
    </trait>
    <spells>animate objects</spells>
    <description>Theros's reclusive medusas often delight in collecting and expanding their galleries of petrified victims. Unlike other medusas, Hythonia isn't merely a collector; she's an artist.
When Hythonia came to the island of Skathos, the inhabitants worshiped her as an avatar of the god Pharika. The cultists eagerly offered themselves up to the medusa's petrifying gaze in hopes of gaining Pharika's favor. Seeing herself surrounded by willing devotees, Hythonia formulated a cruel plan. After encouraging them to engage in wild rituals, Hythonia began turning her followers to stone, weaving their forms to create a grisly throne made of their petrified bodies.
While the medusa's victims have dwindled, tales of the medusa queen and the divine secrets she hoards have not. Hythonia eagerly trades the mysteries she knows but demands a constant price: a beautiful individual to become part of her throne.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 252</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Ironscale Hydra</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>181 (11d20+66)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>22</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>22</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +8</skill>
    <passive>18</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>acid</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 231</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Acidic Blood</name>
      <text>When the hydra takes piercing or slashing damage, each creature within 5 feet of the hydra takes 9 (2d8) acid damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>The hydra can hold its breath for 1 hour.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Multiple Heads</name>
      <text>The hydra has five heads. While it has more than one head, the hydra has advantage on saving throws against being blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, stunned, or knocked unconscious. Whenever the hydra takes 35 or more damage in a single turn, one of its heads dies. If all its heads die, the hydra dies. At the end of its turn, it grows two heads for each of its heads that died since its last turn, unless it has taken fire damage since its last turn. The hydra regains 10 hit points for each head regrown in this way.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Reactive Heads</name>
      <text>For each head the hydra has beyond one, it gets an extra reaction that can be used only for opportunity attacks.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Wakeful</name>
      <text>While the hydra sleeps, at least one of its heads is awake.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The hydra makes as many bite attacks as it has heads.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. 17 (2d10 + 6) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|10|2d10+6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Five-headed ironscale hydras lurk in the wild places of the world, being common foes for heroes seeking to test their mettle against terrors worthy of the gods' notice. Most ironscale hydras inhabit lakes and boggy caverns, from which they hunt unwary creatures that come for a drink or swim.
What krakens are to the sea and dragons are to the sky, hydras are to the lands of Theros. Various hydras dwell at the fringes of civilization, from the bog-dwelling hydras known across the multiverse to massive ironscale hydras that lurk in deep wildernesses. Beyond even these exist serpentine horrors born of the whims of foul gods, like the legendary hydra Polukranos.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 231</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Lampad</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>fey</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>52 (8d8+16)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +6, Intimidation +6</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common, Sylvan</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist>necrotic</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 235</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Corpse Stride</name>
      <text>Once on its turn, the lampad can use 10 feet of its movement to step magically into one creature's corpse within its reach and emerge from a second creature's corpse within 60 feet of the first corpse, appearing in an unoccupied space within 5 feet of the second corpse. Both corpses must be Medium or bigger.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The lampad has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The lampad attacks twice with its necrotic touch or chill touch.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Necrotic Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (1d10 + 4) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Necrotic Touch|6|1d10+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Chill Touch (Cantrip)</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +6 to hit, range 120 ft., one creature. 9 (2d8) necrotic damage, and the target can't regain hit points until the start of the lampad's next turn. If the target is undead, it has disadvantage on attack rolls against the lampad until the end of the lampad's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Chill Touch (Cantrip)|6|2d8</attack>
    </action>
    <trait>
      <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The lampad's spellcasting ability is Charisma (+6 to hit with spell attacks). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: chill touch (see "Actions" below), gentle repose</text>
    </trait>
    <spells>chill touch, gentle repose</spells>
    <description>Lampads guard the shadowed paths of the world, depths typically trod by souls destined for the Underworld. These rarely seen nymphs assist Athreos in guiding the dead, moving among the spirits that collect along the Tartyx River and reclaiming wayward souls that try to slip back to the mortal world. This means lampads are most often spotted in graveyards, crumbling crypts, and tunnels that bore deep into the earth, and near portals to the Underworld.
Nymphs:
Divine servants that inhabit unspoiled corners of the world, nymphs protect places of natural power and infuse their surroundings with the magic of Nyx. Some are benevolent and aid those who live off the land, while others embody violent aspects of nature. In either case, nymphs generally avoid other sapient creatures, preferring to mind the cycles of nature, the daily interplay of wild animals, or other cosmic forces. Occasionally, though, groups of the same kind of nymphs congregate in a place of natural power or beauty. In times of special need, deities tied to facets of nature might employ nymphs as messengers, guardians, or scouts.
A nymph doesn't require food, drink, or sleep.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 235</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Leonin Iconoclast</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (leonin)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>17 (Unarmored Defense)</ac>
    <hp>67 (9d8+27)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Dex +7, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +4, Insight +6, Intimidation +3, Stealth +7, Survival +6</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common, Leonin</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 232</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Evasion</name>
      <text>If the leonin is subjected to an effect that allows it to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, it instead takes no damage if it succeeds on the saving throw, and only half damage if it fails. It can't use this trait if it's incapacitated.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Unarmored Defense</name>
      <text>While the leonin is wearing no armor and wielding no shield, its AC includes its Wisdom modifier.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The leonin makes three weapon attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) slashing damage plus 7 (2d6) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|7|2d6+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Dart</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 6 (1d4 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dart|7|1d4+4</attack>
    </action>
    <trait>
      <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The leonin's spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 14). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>1/day each: banishment, detect evil and good</text>
    </trait>
    <spells>banishment, detect evil and good</spells>
    <description>While leonin don't deny the existence of the gods, most denounce them, believing the deities are more likely to spread doom than peace and bounty. Some leonin, known as iconoclasts, devote themselves to thwarting the gods by hunting down their followers and all things born of Nyx that impede on Oreskos and the safety of the leonin prides.
Prides of leonin roam the plains of Oreskos, protecting the land and its creatures from interlopers, both mortal and immortal. As many leonin suffered at the hands of archon tyrants in ages past, today their prides largely avoid contact with other peoples and spurn the gods that ignored their plight. Since then, the leonin have flourished, finding strength in their bonds with one another and the land. Only in recent times have some leonin started guardedly looking beyond their homeland and wondering what role they might take in the wider world.
Most leonin hunters are tribal warriors, but those who hunt the servants of the gods rather than game are known as leonin iconoclasts.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 232</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Medusa</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>127 (17d8+51)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +5, Insight +4, Perception +4, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 206</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Petrifying Gaze</name>
      <text>When a creature that can see the medusa's eyes starts its turn within 30 feet of the medusa, the medusa can force it to make a DC 14 Constitution saving throw if the medusa isn't incapacitated and can see the creature. If the saving throw fails by 5 or more, the creature is instantly petrified. Otherwise, a creature that fails the save begins to turn to stone and is restrained. The restrained creature must repeat the saving throw at the end of its next turn, becoming petrified on a failure or ending the effect on a success. The petrification lasts until the creature is freed by the  greater restoration spell or other magic.</text>
      <text>Unless surprised, a creature can avert its eyes to avoid the saving throw at the start of its turn. If the creature does so, it can't see the medusa until the start of its next turn, when it can avert its eyes again. If the creature looks at the medusa in the meantime, it must immediately make the save.</text>
      <text>If the medusa sees itself reflected on a polished surface within 30 feet of it and in an area of bright light, the medusa is, due to its curse, affected by its own gaze.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The medusa makes either three melee attacks—one with its snake hair, one to constrict, and one with its shortsword—or two ranged attacks with its longbow.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Snake Hair</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage plus 14 (4d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Snake Hair|5|1d4+2</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|5|1d6+2</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Longbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 150/600 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage plus 7 (2d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Longbow|5|1d8+2</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Constrict</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 7 (2d6) bludgeoning damage, and the target is grappled (escape DC 11). Until this grapple ends, the target is restrained, and the medusa can't constrict another target.</text>
      <attack>Constrict|3|2d6</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 206</description>
    <environment>desert</environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Meletian Hoplite</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>18 (breastplate, shield)</ac>
    <hp>49 (9d8+9)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Dex +4, Int +5</save>
    <skill>Arcana +5, History +5, Perception +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 229</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The hoplite makes three weapon attacks. It can replace one weapon attack with ray of frost.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage, or 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Spear|5|1d6+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Shield Bash</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 5 (1d4 + 3) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Medium or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 13 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Shield Bash|5|1d4+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Ray of Frost (Cantrip)</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +5 to hit, range 60 ft., one creature. 4 (1d8) cold damage, and the target's speed is reduced by 10 feet until the start of the hoplite's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Ray of Frost (Cantrip)|5|1d8</attack>
    </action>
    <trait>
      <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The hoplite is a 3rd-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). It has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): mage hand, minor illusion, ray of frost (see "Actions" below)</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): color spray, expeditious retreat, sleep</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (2 slots): blur, cloud of daggers, invisibility</text>
    </trait>
    <slots>4, 2</slots>
    <spells>mage hand, minor illusion, ray of frost, color spray, expeditious retreat, sleep, blur, cloud of daggers, invisibility</spells>
    <description>Meletian hoplites use a combination of cunning, faith, and magic to defend their coastal home. Most of these skilled soldiers serve in the Reverent Army, the defenders of Meletis, which uses an array of proven strategies and flexible troop formations to gain the advantage over foes. Bolstered by trained griffon and pegasus steeds, they strike foes where they least expect.
Hoplites are highly trained warriors, versed not only in strategy and tactics but in the glorification of the warrior's spirit, the basis of an ethos that forges an unbreakable bond between members of a military unit. In combat, hoplites typically work in groups and use coordinated tactics to win victories.
The three Hoplite Unit Names tables present the sorts of titles used by hoplite contingents hailing from Theros's great poleis. Consider using these names for military forces characters encounter during their adventures or that they were once a part of.
D8 | Name
1 | Kraken's Claw
2 | Hands of Justice
3 | Thassa's Spear
4 | Ephara's Shield
5 | Kindred of the Deep
6 | Riders of Heliod
7 | Keepers of Pyrgnos
8 | The Skysworn

Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 229</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Naiad</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>fey</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>31 (7d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Persuasion +6, Sleight of hand +5</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Sylvan</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist>psychic</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 236</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The naiad can breathe air and water.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Invisible in Water</name>
      <text>The naiad is invisible while fully immersed in water.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The naiad has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The naiad makes two psychic touch attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Psychic Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (1d10 + 4) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Psychic Touch|6|1d10+4</attack>
    </action>
    <trait>
      <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The naiad's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 14). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: minor illusion</text>
      <text>3/day: phantasmal force</text>
      <text>1/day each: fly, hypnotic pattern</text>
    </trait>
    <spells>minor illusion, phantasmal force, fly, hypnotic pattern</spells>
    <description>Naiads live in and near water. They might be spotted among rivers and lakes, on isolated shores, or amid coral labyrinths and deep sea fumaroles. Wherever rivers and seas show their variety and force, naiads gather to revel in nature's might. Individual naiads often grow fixated with a single type or body of water, potentially preferring a deep sea trench, coastline, or river system above all others. Over time, such a resident nymph often becomes connected with their aquatic home through sightings and stories, becoming a guardian of the place and, in effect, a manifestation of its personality.
Curious by nature, naiads often seek out what the seas and rivers claim. As a result, they might be found among sunken ruins and shipwrecks, sifting through the remains for whatever catches their eye. Living creatures aren't exempt from this curiosity, either. Naiads are known to befriend aquatic creatures, or even to keep modest menageries. The occasional star-crossed castaway has even been known to become part of such collections.
Sailors across the world claim that naiads know all the secret aquatic routes of Theros. Using this hidden system of currents and arteries, a ship might reach any destination in record time, be it across the sea or along a river a hundred miles inland. Naiads do nothing to dissuade sailors from this belief, and certainly numerous reports tell of charmed nymphs leading lost seafarers home. Yet, if tales of naiad-led galleys appearing amid the headwaters of mountain rivers are true, only the nymphs know for sure.
Nymphs:
Divine servants that inhabit unspoiled corners of the world, nymphs protect places of natural power and infuse their surroundings with the magic of Nyx. Some are benevolent and aid those who live off the land, while others embody violent aspects of nature. In either case, nymphs generally avoid other sapient creatures, preferring to mind the cycles of nature, the daily interplay of wild animals, or other cosmic forces. Occasionally, though, groups of the same kind of nymphs congregate in a place of natural power or beauty. In times of special need, deities tied to facets of nature might employ nymphs as messengers, guardians, or scouts.
A nymph doesn't require food, drink, or sleep.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 236</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Nightmare Shepherd</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>fiend</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>133 (14d10+56)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>20</cha>
    <save>Con +8, Wis +7</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, Deception +9, Perception +7, Persuasion +9</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>11</cr>
    <resist>cold, necrotic</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 221</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Aura of Nightmares</name>
      <text>Undead creatures within 30 feet of the shepherd gain a +5 bonus to attack and damage rolls. When any other creature that isn't undead or a construct starts its turn within 30 feet of the shepherd, that creature must succeed on a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw or take 11 (2d10) psychic damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The shepherd has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The shepherd makes two attacks: one with its claws and one with its staff.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d8 + 4) slashing damage plus 16 (3d10) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|8|2d8+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Staff</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) bludgeoning damage, or 13 (2d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage if used with two hands, plus 26 (4d12) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Staff|8|2d6+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Herd the Underworld (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>The shepherd pulls twisted souls from the Underworld; 1d6 shadows (without Sunlight Weakness; see the Monster Manual) arise in unoccupied spaces within 20 feet of the shepherd. The shadows act right after the shepherd on the same initiative count and fight until they're destroyed. They disappear when the shepherd dies.</text>
    </action>
    <trait>
      <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The shepherd's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 17). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>1/day each: confusion, dispel magic, hold person, suggestion</text>
    </trait>
    <spells>confusion, dispel magic, hold person, suggestion</spells>
    <description>A nightmare shepherd is a gaunt, ashen fiend with leathery wings. It carries a shepherd's crook, which it uses to direct a flock of wandering dead that it torments and occasionally feeds upon.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 221</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Nyx-Fleece Ram</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 233</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Charge</name>
      <text>If the ram moves at least 20 feet straight toward a target and then hits it with a ram attack on the same turn, the target takes an extra 5 (2d4) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 13 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The ram has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Sure-Footed</name>
      <text>The ram has advantage on Strength and Dexterity saving throws against effects that would knock it prone.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Ram</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (2d4 + 3) bludgeoning damage plus 3 (1d6) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Ram|5|2d4+3</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Touched by the gods, Nyx-fleece rams grow remarkable magical wool. This makes the beasts valuable to heroes and scoundrels alike, who would use their wool for either protection or profit. Divine servants guard the few herds of Nyx-fleece rams dwelling among Theros's loftiest peaks, assuring they don't fall into unworthy hands.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 233</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Oracle</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (Blessings Of The Gods)</ac>
    <hp>44 (8d8+8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Wis +5, Cha +4</save>
    <skill>Insight +5, Persuasion +4, Religion +5</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Celestial, Common</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 238</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Blessings of the Gods</name>
      <text>While the oracle is wearing no armor and wielding no shield, its AC includes its Wisdom modifier. In addition, a creature that hits the oracle with a melee attack while within 5 feet of it takes 9 (2d8) force damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Eldritch Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) force damage.</text>
      <attack>Eldritch Touch|5|1d6+3</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Divine Insight (3/Day)</name>
      <text>When the oracle or a creature it can see makes an attack roll, a saving throw, or an ability check, the oracle can cause the roll to be made with advantage or disadvantage.</text>
    </reaction>
    <trait>
      <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The oracle's spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: guidance, light, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>3/day each: bless, guiding bolt, healing word, hold person</text>
      <text>1/day each: augury, scrying</text>
    </trait>
    <spells>guidance, light, thaumaturgy, bless, guiding bolt, healing word, hold person, augury, scrying</spells>
    <description>Oracles posses the ability to interpret the patterns and language of Nyx, divining from it the flow of fates and the will of the gods. Most of these gifted—or cursed—mortals communicate with a single god, interpreting their intentions for the wider world. Others aren't aligned with a god and observe the night sky, reading Nyx like a vast, cryptic scroll for insights.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 238</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Oread</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>fey</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>49 (9d8+9)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +4, Athletics +4, Performance +6</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common, Sylvan</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 237</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Invisible in Fire</name>
      <text>The oread is invisible while fully immersed in fire.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The oread has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The oread attacks twice with its fiery touch or fire bolt.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Fiery Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (1d10 + 4) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Fiery Touch|6|1d10+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Fire Bolt (Cantrip)</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +6 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. 5 (1d10) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Fire Bolt (Cantrip)|6|1d10</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Hellish Rebuke (2nd-Level Spell; 1/Day)</name>
      <text>When the oread is damaged by a creature within 60 feet of the oread that it can see, the creature that damaged the oread must make a DC 14 Dexterity saving throw, taking 16 (3d10) fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
    </reaction>
    <trait>
      <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The oread's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: fire bolt (see "Actions" below)</text>
      <text>3/day: burning hands</text>
      <text>1/day each: hellish rebuke (see "Reactions" below), scorching ray</text>
    </trait>
    <spells>fire bolt, burning hands, hellish rebuke, scorching ray</spells>
    <description>Aggressive oreads number among the most dangerous nymphs, as they embody the wild might of flames, volcanism, and the hidden forces of the earth. These creatures typically dwell in remote mountain crags and near volcanoes, where they caper among the forces of dissolution and rebirth. During avalanches and volcanic eruptions, groups of oreads might race ahead of the destruction, dancing, singing, and doing what they can to maximize the impending devastation.
Hearkening back to some ages-old conflict, oreads refuse to knowingly destroy any land inhabited by another nymph. While they won't work to alter the natural course of destruction, neither will they make another nymph's home part of any calamity they encourage. As a result, part of what makes an alseid's field or a dryad's grove seem so blessed is that oreads go out of their way to leave such sites alone.
The followers of Purphoros regard oreads with special reverence, as myths tell of cagey smiths befriending these nymphs and convincing them to aid in creating phenomenal works. In some tales, a smith finds an oread and allows it to relish in the destruction of a novel or remarkable item. In recompense, the oread provides the smith with materials drawn from the burning heart of the world, allowing the smith to create an even greater wonder. In more tales, though, a smith pursues an oread, then later the mortal's associates find familiar tools and a heap of ashes.
Nymphs:
Divine servants that inhabit unspoiled corners of the world, nymphs protect places of natural power and infuse their surroundings with the magic of Nyx. Some are benevolent and aid those who live off the land, while others embody violent aspects of nature. In either case, nymphs generally avoid other sapient creatures, preferring to mind the cycles of nature, the daily interplay of wild animals, or other cosmic forces. Occasionally, though, groups of the same kind of nymphs congregate in a place of natural power or beauty. In times of special need, deities tied to facets of nature might employ nymphs as messengers, guardians, or scouts.
A nymph doesn't require food, drink, or sleep.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 237</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Phylaskia</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>104 (11d10+44)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Con +8, Wis +7</save>
    <skill>Insight +7, Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>all</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>necrotic, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 239</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Gatekeeper's Aura</name>
      <text>Any creature that starts its turn within 10 feet of the phylaskia must make a DC 15 Wisdom saving throw. On a successful save, the creature is immune to this aura for the next 24 hours. On a failed save, the creature has disadvantage on saving throws and its speed is halved until the start of its next turn.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Undead Fortitude</name>
      <text>If damage reduces the phylaskia to 0 hit points, it must make a Constitution saving throw with a DC equal to 5 + the damage taken, unless the damage is radiant or from a critical hit. On a success, the phylaskia drops to 1 hit point instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Vigilant</name>
      <text>The phylaskia can't be surprised.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The phylaskia makes two longsword attacks and uses its Strength Drain once.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Longsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 14 (2d8 + 5) slashing damage, or 16 (2d10 + 5) slashing damage if used with two hands, plus 11 (2d10) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Longsword|9|2d8+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Strength Drain</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 12 (2d6 + 5) necrotic damage. Unless the target is immune to necrotic damage, its Strength score is reduced by 1d4. The target dies if this reduces its Strength to 0. Otherwise, the reduction lasts until the target finishes a short or long rest.</text>
      <attack>Strength Drain|9|2d6+5</attack>
    </action>
    <description>These armored skeletal spirits guard the borders of the Underworld and its various wards. Sleepless and merciless, they scrutinize all who would pass, and they slay those who defy them.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 239</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Polukranos</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>232 (15d20+75)</hp>
    <speed>walk 50 ft., swim 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>25</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>4</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +14</skill>
    <passive>24</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>19</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>acid</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 231</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Acidic Blood</name>
      <text>When Polukranos takes piercing or slashing damage, each creature within 5 feet of Polukranos takes 10 (3d6) acid damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>Polukranos can hold its breath for 1 hour.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If Polukranos fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Multiple Heads</name>
      <text>Polukranos has five heads. While it has more than one head, Polukranos has advantage on saving throws against being blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, stunned, or knocked unconscious. Whenever Polukranos takes 40 or more damage in a single turn, one of its heads dies. If all its heads die, Polukranos dies. At the end of its turn, it grows two heads for each of its heads that died since its last turn, unless it has taken 40 or more fire damage since its last turn. Polukranos regains 20 hit points for each head regrown in this way.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Reactive Heads</name>
      <text>For each head Polukranos has beyond one, it gets an extra reaction that can be used only to make opportunity attacks.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>Polukranos deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Wakeful</name>
      <text>While Polukranos sleeps, at least one of its heads is awake.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Polukranos makes as many bite attacks as it has heads.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. 18 (2d10 + 7) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|13|2d10+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Stomp</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. 16 (2d8 + 7) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Stomp|13|2d8+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. 18 (2d10 + 7) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 21 Strength saving throw or be pushed up to 20 feet away from Polukranos.</text>
      <attack>Tail|13|2d10+7</attack>
    </action>
    <legendary>
      <text>Polukranos can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Polukranos regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Detect</name>
      <text>Polukranos makes a Wisdom (Perception) check.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Tail Swipe</name>
      <text>Polukranos makes a tail attack.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Trampling Charge (Costs 3 Actions)</name>
      <text>Polukranos moves up to 50 feet in a straight line and can move through the space of any creature Huge or smaller. The first time it enters each creature's space during this move, it can make a stomp attack against that creature.</text>
    </legendary>
    <description>Polukranos, called the World Eater, is the mortal manifestation of the eternal ideal of a hydra. In its first incarnation, it fell from Nyx to the mortal world, and so great were its size and strength that the gods Nylea and Heliod combined their power to bind the monster deep within the Nessian Wood. That incarnation was slain, but the eternal ideal remains. A new incarnation of the World Eater is a fearsome omen, as the monster only appears when the pillars of the world tremble and terrible things are afoot in the realm of the gods. Its rampages often presage an age of menace for all civilization.
What krakens are to the sea and dragons are to the sky, hydras are to the lands of Theros. Various hydras dwell at the fringes of civilization, from the bog-dwelling hydras known across the multiverse to massive ironscale hydras that lurk in deep wildernesses. Beyond even these exist serpentine horrors born of the whims of foul gods, like the legendary hydra Polukranos.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 231</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Returned Drifter</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>13 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>11 (2d8+2)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>the languages it knew in life</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist>necrotic</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 240</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Turn Resistance</name>
      <text>The Returned has advantage on saving throws against any effect that turns undead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Unreadable Face</name>
      <text>The Returned is immune to any effect that would sense its emotions or read its thoughts. Wisdom (Insight) checks to ascertain the Returned's intentions or sincerity are made with disadvantage.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Scimitar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) slashing damage plus 3 (1d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Scimitar|4|1d6+2</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Sling</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Sling|4|1d4+2</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Many Returned are pitiable souls who managed to escape from the Underworld only to find themselves stripped of the passions that motivated their flight. Lacking purpose and shunned by the living, these Returned typically seek places where they'll be left in peace, such as lonely tombs or the necropoleis of Asphodel and Odunos. There they go through half-hearted parodies of life, impeded by distraction and ennui. Despite this, even the most languorous Returned defend themselves if threatened and might be pressed into the service of their more willful brethren.
Returned have escaped the Underworld and dwell among the living once more, but their second lives are rarely what they expected—not that they remember what it was they expected. As a result of having followed the Path of Phenax (see chapter 4), the Returned lose their identities, which manifest as separate beings known as eidolons. The experience of escaping the Underworld also causes them to lose their faces, which become expressionless surfaces with empty eye sockets and gaping mouths. These blank surfaces they cover with distinctive golden masks.
Returned reenter the world blank and undead. No longer possessing the ability to form long-term memories, they generally can't build meaningful relationships or establish new lives. Instead, most experience fleeting emotions and follow hollow routines, their existences reduced to shadow plays without weight or substance.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 240</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Returned Kakomantis</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>65 (10d8+20)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +5, Athletics +2, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>the languages it knew in life</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist>necrotic</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 240</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Fleeting Anger</name>
      <text>If another creature deals damage to the Returned, the Returned makes attack rolls with advantage until the end of its next turn.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Turn Resistance</name>
      <text>The Returned has advantage on saving throws against any effect that turns undead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Unreadable Face</name>
      <text>The Returned is immune to any effect that would sense its emotions or read its thoughts. Wisdom (Insight) checks to ascertain the Returned's intentions or sincerity are made with disadvantage.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage plus 10 (3d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|5|1d6+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Underworld Bolt</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +4 to hit, range 120 ft., one creature. 13 (2d8 + 2) necrotic damage, and the target can't regain hit points until the start of the Returned's next turn. If the target is missing any of its hit points, it instead takes 17 (2d12 + 2) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Underworld Bolt|4|2d8+2</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Although the dead typically recall little of their lives, some have an obsession with magic that survives both death and rebirth as a Returned. These Returned, called kakomanteis, use their magical prowess to control the energy that suffuses the Underworld.
Returned have escaped the Underworld and dwell among the living once more, but their second lives are rarely what they expected—not that they remember what it was they expected. As a result of having followed the Path of Phenax (see chapter 4), the Returned lose their identities, which manifest as separate beings known as eidolons. The experience of escaping the Underworld also causes them to lose their faces, which become expressionless surfaces with empty eye sockets and gaping mouths. These blank surfaces they cover with distinctive golden masks.
Returned reenter the world blank and undead. No longer possessing the ability to form long-term memories, they generally can't build meaningful relationships or establish new lives. Instead, most experience fleeting emotions and follow hollow routines, their existences reduced to shadow plays without weight or substance.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 240</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Returned Palamnite</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>65 (10d8+20)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +5, Athletics +2, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>the languages it knew in life</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist>necrotic</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 241</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Fleeting Anger</name>
      <text>If another creature deals damage to the Returned, the Returned makes attack rolls with advantage until the end of its next turn.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Turn Resistance</name>
      <text>The Returned has advantage on saving throws against any effect that turns undead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Unreadable Face</name>
      <text>The Returned is immune to any effect that would sense its emotions or read its thoughts. Wisdom (Insight) checks to ascertain the Returned's intentions or sincerity are made with disadvantage.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The Returned makes two shortsword attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage plus 10 (3d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|5|1d6+3</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Even death and the loss of their identities can't erase the rage that inspires Returned palamnites. These Returned led violent lives, existences filled with such pain and hatred that violence now suffuses their deathless bodies. Such makes them exceptionally dangerous to the living, as these aimless killers know only suffering and seek to spread it whenever the opportunity arises. While palamnites might wander the world as dangerous, lone murderers, many gravitate to Odunos, where they serve the vicious will of Tymaret the Murder King (see chapter 3).
Returned have escaped the Underworld and dwell among the living once more, but their second lives are rarely what they expected—not that they remember what it was they expected. As a result of having followed the Path of Phenax (see chapter 4), the Returned lose their identities, which manifest as separate beings known as eidolons. The experience of escaping the Underworld also causes them to lose their faces, which become expressionless surfaces with empty eye sockets and gaping mouths. These blank surfaces they cover with distinctive golden masks.
Returned reenter the world blank and undead. No longer possessing the ability to form long-term memories, they generally can't build meaningful relationships or establish new lives. Instead, most experience fleeting emotions and follow hollow routines, their existences reduced to shadow plays without weight or substance.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 241</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Returned Sentry</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (leather armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>22 (4d8+4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>the languages it knew in life</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist>necrotic</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 241</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>The Returned has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the Returned's allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Turn Resistance</name>
      <text>The Returned has advantage on saving throws against any effect that turns undead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Unreadable Face</name>
      <text>The Returned is immune to any effect that would sense its emotions or read its thoughts. Wisdom (Insight) checks to ascertain the Returned's intentions or sincerity are made with disadvantage.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage, or 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack, plus 7 (2d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Spear|5|1d6+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Sling</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Sling|4|1d4+2</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 241</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Satyr Reveler</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>fey</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>33 (6d8+6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +5, Performance +7, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Sylvan</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 242</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Enthralling Performance</name>
      <text>If the satyr performs for at least 1 minute, it chooses up to four humanoids within 60 feet of it who watched or listened to the entire performance. Each target must succeed on a DC 13 Wisdom saving throw or be charmed. While charmed in this way, the target idolizes the satyr and will take part in the satyr's revels. The charmed condition ends for the creature after 1 hour, if it takes any damage, if the satyr attacks the target, or if the target witnesses the satyr attacking or damaging any of the target's allies.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The satyr has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Sleepless Reveler</name>
      <text>Magic can't put the satyr to sleep.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The satyr makes two ram attacks or two shortbow attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Ram</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (2d4 + 1) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Ram|3|2d4+1</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Shortbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow|5|1d6+3</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Pursuing lives of endless reverie, satyr revelers eagerly participate in celebrations wherever they find them. Their boisterous natures go far toward tempting others to eat, drink, and carouse with them. Faced with stodgier individuals or outright rivals, satyr revelers don't balk at using the magic of their music, dance, or other performances to charm opponents into joining their festivities. In the aftermath, these satyrs' foes are more likely to suffer embarrassment and groggy mornings than any lasting harm.
While most satyrs are known for their high spirits, love of revels, and gregarious personalities, these outgoing people are neither naive nor defenseless. Some satyrs delightedly torment stuffy individuals or pull pranks on the unwary, pastimes that can predictably lead to scuffles. If a satyr can't talk their way out of a conflict—or diffuse it with a good-natured distraction—they readily defend themselves, their friends, and their homes in the Skola Vale. With diversions aside, satyrs bend their cleverness toward tactics and methods of ending conflicts as swiftly as possible. This often means turning the same skills that make them famed celebrants toward battle, be it captivating performances or the aim developed through endless games of skill. Once a threat is overcome, though, satyrs are quick to engage in their favorite part of battle: the victory celebration.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 242</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Satyr Thornbearer</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>fey</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>15 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>38 (7d8+7)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +5, Performance +6, Stealth +6</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Common, Sylvan</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 243</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The satyr has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Sleepless Reveler</name>
      <text>Magic can't put the satyr to sleep.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The satyr makes three ram attacks or three shortbow attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Ram</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (2d4 + 1) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Ram|3|2d4+1</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Shortbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow|6|1d6+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Hail of Arrows (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>The satyr fires an arrow that magically transforms into a flurry of missiles in a 30-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 14 Dexterity saving throw, taking 17 (5d6) piercing damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Not all satyrs live lives of pure whimsy. When forced to defend their friends and homes, satyr thornbearers are quick to take up their bows and strike against danger. Particularly amid the dense trees of the Skola Vale, these satyr skirmishers cooperate in loose teams, using guerrilla tactics to harass foes then melt back into the forest. The blessings of Nylea aid the satyrs in protecting their home, and a single arrow from a thornbearer's bow might rain down like a volley from a whole army.
While most satyrs are known for their high spirits, love of revels, and gregarious personalities, these outgoing people are neither naive nor defenseless. Some satyrs delightedly torment stuffy individuals or pull pranks on the unwary, pastimes that can predictably lead to scuffles. If a satyr can't talk their way out of a conflict—or diffuse it with a good-natured distraction—they readily defend themselves, their friends, and their homes in the Skola Vale. With diversions aside, satyrs bend their cleverness toward tactics and methods of ending conflicts as swiftly as possible. This often means turning the same skills that make them famed celebrants toward battle, be it captivating performances or the aim developed through endless games of skill. Once a threat is overcome, though, satyrs are quick to engage in their favorite part of battle: the victory celebration.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 243</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Setessan Hoplite</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>16 (leather armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>58 (9d8+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Dex +5, Wis +5</save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +5, Perception +5, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 229</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>The hoplite has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the hoplite's allies is within 5 feet of the hoplite and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The hoplite makes two scimitar attacks or two longbow attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Scimitar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) slashing damage plus 10 (3d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Scimitar|5|1d6+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Longbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 150/600 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage plus 10 (3d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Longbow|5|1d8+3</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Most Setessan hoplites begin their training as hunters, making them skilled in traversing the woods and adept at both guerrilla tactics and archery. Their strategies often emulate the favored servants of Nylea—especially wild beasts like wolves and lynxes. Typically a few soldiers harry an enemy while the rest capitalize on their foe's distraction.
Hoplites are highly trained warriors, versed not only in strategy and tactics but in the glorification of the warrior's spirit, the basis of an ethos that forges an unbreakable bond between members of a military unit. In combat, hoplites typically work in groups and use coordinated tactics to win victories.
The three Hoplite Unit Names tables present the sorts of titles used by hoplite contingents hailing from Theros's great poleis. Consider using these names for military forces characters encounter during their adventures or that they were once a part of.
d8 | Name
1 | Nylea's Arrows
2 | The Watchers
3 | Fangs of Ophis
4 | The Swiftswords
5 | Karametra's Wolves
6 | Defenders of the Grove
7 | Bronze Blades
8 | The Jackals

Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 229</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Theran Chimera</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>95 (10d10+40)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>19</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Con +7, Wis +5</save>
    <skill>Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>understands Draconic but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>7</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 216</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spell Turning</name>
      <text>The chimera has advantage on a saving throw against any spell that targets only the chimera (not an area). If the chimera's saving throw is successful and the spell is of 4th level or lower, the spell has no effect on the chimera and instead targets the caster.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The chimera makes three attacks: one with its claws, one with its head, and one with its tail. When its breath weapon is available, it can use the breath in place of its head or its claws.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d8 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|7|2d8+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Head</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (1d12 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Head|7|1d12+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Tail|7|2d6+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Breath Weapon (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The chimera exhales fire in a 15-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw, taking 32 (5d12) fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
    </action>
    <description>The term chimera applies to a wide variety of disparate monsters that combine the features of multiple beasts. While many artistic depictions represent chimeras as an amalgam of lion, ram, and dragon, these beasts appear with nearly endless variations.
The Akroans tell a tale of the first chimera's origin, wherein the god Keranos sought to test Nylea's favorite champion, Renata of Setessa, by creating a beast so deadly that even she would balk at trying to hunt it. When Renata slayed this lion-ram-dragon creation effortlessly, Keranos created another combination of deadlier beasts to challenge her. She slayed that beast, too. Despite countless attempts, Keranos was unable to create a beast that Renata couldn't best.
Chimeras typically roam the deep wilds of the world, constantly seeking a lair that would perfectly suit one of its heads, but then finding it unsatisfying to two-thirds of its being. As a result, a hungry chimera might appear out of a clear sky to pick off prey nearly anywhere. This threat grows even more significant in regions where magic runs rampant or where portals to the realm of Nyx exist, as unrestrained magical energy often causes more chimeras to appear in a region. As such chaotic magic is inherent to a chimera's being, these monsters often manage to shrug off spells cast against them.
Customizing a Chimera
The Theran chimera stat block presents one possible chimera configuration. You may customize these statistics to design your own unique chimera. To do so, simply roll once on one or all of the following tables. Results from the Body Composition table adjust the Theran chimera as described, while results on the Breath Weapons, Head Attacks, and Tail Attacks tables replace those respective actions in the stat block. Theran chimeras always have the Claws action. If the results of multiple tables conflict, chose your preferred result.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 216</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Triton Master of Waves</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (triton)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>105 (14d8+42)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>19</cha>
    <save>Dex +3, Int +3, Cha +7</save>
    <skill>Athletics +6, Nature +6, Survival +4</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist>cold, fire</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 245</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The triton can breathe air and water.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Summon Water Weird (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, the triton magically summons 1d4} {@creature water weird. The summoned weirds appear in unoccupied spaces in water within 60 feet of the triton. The water weirds act immediately after the triton on the same initiative count and fight until they're destroyed. They disappear if the triton dies.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The triton makes two attacks using Wave Touch and casts ray of frost.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Wave Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 22 (4d10) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Wave Touch|7|4d10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Ray of Frost (Cantrip)</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +7 to hit, range 60 ft., one creature. 13 (3d8) cold damage, and the target's speed is reduced by 10 feet until the start of the triton's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Ray of Frost (Cantrip)|7|3d8</attack>
    </action>
    <reaction>
      <name>Frigid Shield</name>
      <text>When a creature the triton can see targets the triton with an attack, the triton gains 10 temporary hit points. If the attack hits and reduces the temporary hit points to 0, each creature within 5 feet of the triton takes 9 (2d8) cold damage.</text>
    </reaction>
    <trait>
      <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The triton's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 15, +7 to hit with spell attacks). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: ray of frost (see "Actions" below)</text>
      <text>2/day: cone of cold</text>
      <text>1/day each: fog cloud, gust of wind, wind wall</text>
    </trait>
    <spells>ray of frost, cone of cold, fog cloud, gust of wind, wind wall</spells>
    <description>Triton masters of waves sculpt storms and change the tides, bending the sea to their will. Drawing forth living currents and the icy cold of the deep, these mages make the ocean their ally, using it to defend their people or enact Thassa's wishes. While dire threats from the land might bring them to coastal shallows, most masters of waves keep to the ocean's depths.
Although many masters of waves resent land-dwellers and strike out at those who trespass upon their waters, most are devoted followers of the sea god. Those who share their faith or who bear earnest offerings to Thassa might defuse the tritons' ire—that is, if they survive the deadly winds and waves that typically herald these sea guardians' appearance.
Clever, far-ranging people of the sea, tritons live rich lives unknown to most land-dwelling individuals. While the waves separate most tritons from land-dwellers, occasionally the inhabitants of the surface and the deep come into conflict. In such cases, tritons prove skilled at sabotaging ocean-going vessels, employing water-based magic, and otherwise whipping up the fury of the sea. Few dare insult tritons in their home environment, but those who do and survive often learn that the tritons' wrath doesn't end at the shore.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 245</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Triton Shorestalker</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (triton)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>32 (5d8+10)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Nature +4, Perception +4, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist>cold</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 244</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The triton can breathe air and water.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Nimble Escape</name>
      <text>The triton can take the Disengage or Hide actions as a bonus action on each of its turns.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The triton makes two urchin-spine shortsword attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Urchin-Spine Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage plus 10 (3d6) poison damage. If the damage reduces a creature to 0 hit points, that creature is stable but poisoned for 1 hour, even after regaining hit points, and is paralyzed while poisoned in this way.</text>
      <attack>Urchin-Spine Shortsword|5|1d6+3</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Poisoned Spine</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 30/60 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage plus 10 (3d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Poisoned Spine|5|1d4+3</attack>
    </action>
    <trait>
      <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The triton's spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 12). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>1/day each: fog cloud, gust of wind</text>
    </trait>
    <spells>fog cloud, gust of wind</spells>
    <description>Some insults don't wash away with the tides. When surface dwellers threaten the safety of triton communities, impede upon Thassa's holiest depths, or steal the treasures of the deep, triton shorestalkers seek vengeance. Using speed and poison harvested from deadly sea beasts, these triton assassins slip into shallow waters and strike when least expected. Often, surface dwellers don't even realize they've been attacked by shorestalkers, chalking disappearances and deaths up to the innumerable dangers of the sea.
Clever, far-ranging people of the sea, tritons live rich lives unknown to most land-dwelling individuals. While the waves separate most tritons from land-dwellers, occasionally the inhabitants of the surface and the deep come into conflict. In such cases, tritons prove skilled at sabotaging ocean-going vessels, employing water-based magic, and otherwise whipping up the fury of the sea. Few dare insult tritons in their home environment, but those who do and survive often learn that the tritons' wrath doesn't end at the shore.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 244</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Tromokratis</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>monstrosity (titan)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>22 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>409 (21d20+189)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 80 ft.</speed>
    <str>30</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>29</con>
    <int>22</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Int +14, Wis +8</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>26</cr>
    <resist>cold, lightning, thunder</resist>
    <immune>fire; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, paralyzed, restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 254</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>Tromokratis can breathe air and water.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Hearts of the Kraken (Mythic Trait; Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>When Tromokratis is reduced to 0 hit points, it doesn't die or fall unconscious. Instead, the damage creates cracks in its carapace, revealing its hearts. Tromokratis has four hearts: two on its chest, one on its back, and one at the base of its tail. A heart has an AC of 22 and 100 hit points. It is immune to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage from nonmagical attacks, and it is immune to all conditions. If it is forced to make a saving throw, treat its ability scores as 10 (+0). If it finishes a short or long rest, the carapace heals, any destroyed hearts regenerate, and the hearts are covered again. Tromokratis dies when all the hearts are destroyed.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If Tromokratis fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Magic Weapons</name>
      <text>Tromokratis's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>Tromokratis deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Spell-Resistant Carapace</name>
      <text>Tromokratis has advantage on saving throws against spells, and any creature that makes a spell attack against Tromokratis has disadvantage on the attack roll.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Tromokratis makes three attacks: one with its pincer, one with its tail, and one with its tentacle grasp.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Pincer</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +18 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. 20 (3d6 + 10) bludgeoning damage, and if the target is a creature, it is grappled (escape DC 26). Until the grapple ends, the target is restrained, and Tromokratis can't use this attack on anyone else.</text>
      <attack>Pincer|18|3d6+10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +18 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. 23 (3d8 + 10) bludgeoning damage, and if the target is a creature, it is knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Tail|18|3d8+10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Tentacle Grasp</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +18 to hit, reach 20 ft., one creature. 20 (3d6 + 10) bludgeoning damage, and the target is grappled (escape DC 26). If the target doesn't escape by the end of its next turn, Tromokratis throws the target up to 60 feet in a straight line. The target lands prone and takes 21 (6d6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Tentacle Grasp|18|3d6+10</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +18 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 29 (3d12 + 10) piercing damage. If the target is a Large or smaller creature grappled by Tromokratis, that creature is swallowed, and the grapple ends. While swallowed, the creature is blinded and restrained, it has total cover against attacks and other effects outside Tromokratis, and it takes 42 (12d6) acid damage at the start of each of Tromokratis's turns. If Tromokratis takes 50 damage or more on a single turn from a creature inside it, Tromokratis must succeed on a DC 20 Constitution saving throw at the end of that turn or regurgitate all swallowed creatures, which fall prone in a space within 10 feet of Tromokratis. If Tromokratis dies, a swallowed creature is no longer restrained by it and can escape from the corpse by using 15 feet of movement, exiting prone.</text>
      <attack>Bite|18|3d12+10</attack>
    </action>
    <legendary>
      <text>Tromokratis can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Tromokratis regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Move</name>
      <text>Tromokratis moves up to half its speed.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Tromokratis makes one tail attack.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Bite (Costs 3 Actions)</name>
      <text>Tromokratis makes one bite attack.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Mythic Actions</name>
      <text>If Tromokratis's mythic trait is active, it can use the options below as legendary actions for 1 hour after using Hearts of the Kraken.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Rampage</name>
      <text>Tromokratis makes two attacks: one with its tail and one with its tentacle grasp.</text>
    </legendary>
    <legendary>
      <name>Coral Growth (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Each creature within 10 feet of Tromokratis must make a DC 25 Dexterity saving throw, taking 13 (3d8) slashing damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. Until the start of its next turn, Tromokratis and its hearts gain a +2 bonus to AC.</text>
    </legendary>
    <description>Most krakens roam the seas, shattering hulls and scattering fleets, but the kraken Tromokratis notoriously vents its wrath on coastal settlements. Whether it acts at the command of the god Thassa or to sate its own hunger, Tromokratis numbers among the most feared threats in the sea, having no fixed lair and wandering where it will. In recent memory, the massive menace rose from the waves to topple the Pyrgnos, Meletis's great repository of scholarly knowledge. Since that day, the polis keeps a watch specifically for Tromokratis.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 254</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Two-Headed Cerberus</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>39 (6d8+12)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +5, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire, necrotic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, stunned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 215</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Aggressive</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, the cerberus can move up to its speed toward a hostile creature that it can see.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Multiheaded</name>
      <text>The cerberus can't be surprised, and it has advantage on saving throws against being knocked unconscious.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>The cerberus has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the cerberus's allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The cerberus makes two bite attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage plus 2 (1d4) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|4|1d6+2</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Breath Weapon (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The cerberus exhales a 15-foot cone of molten rock. Each creature in the cone must make a DC 12 Dexterity saving throw, taking 10 (3d6) fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. On a failed save, a creature is also restrained by the hardening rock. A creature can make a DC 12 Strength (Athletics) check as an action, freeing itself or a creature within reach from the rock on a success. The rock has AC 17 and 10 hit points, and it is immune to fire, poison, and psychic damage.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Thought to be a lesser breed of cerberi that have interbred with mortal wolves, two-headed cerberi typically roam the mortal side of the Tartyx River. There they generally ignore—or only modestly menace—the souls of the dead. Such isn't the case for mortals, though, and they eagerly set upon those who tread too close to the Underworld's borders.
Feared by the living and the dead, cerberi patrol both banks of the Tartyx River. These multiheaded hounds of the Underworld breathe gouts of molten rock that sear and imprison those who trespass upon the borders of life and death. Most cerberi have a boundless hunger for fresh meat, especially the flesh of humanoids. Villains have been known to exploit that hunger by luring cerberi away from the river and setting them loose on mortal settlements.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 215</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Typhon</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>195 (17d12+85)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>24</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>7</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save>Con +10</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>15</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>acid, necrotic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 246</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>The typhon has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Regeneration</name>
      <text>The typhon regains 20 hit points at the start of its turn. If it takes radiant damage, this trait doesn't function at the start of its next turn. The typhon dies only if it starts its turn with 0 hit points and doesn't regenerate.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The typhon makes three attacks: one with its Flurry of Bites, one to constrict, and one with its maw.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Flurry of Bites</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 35 (8d6 + 7) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Flurry of Bites|12|8d6+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Constrict</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 15 ft., one Large or smaller creature. 17 (3d6 + 7) bludgeoning damage, and the target is grappled (escape DC 19). Until this grapple ends, the target is restrained and takes 17 (3d6 + 7) bludgeoning damage at the start of each of its turns. The typhon can have up to two creatures constricted.</text>
      <attack>Constrict|12|3d6+7</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Maw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 26 (3d12 + 7) piercing damage plus 19 (3d12) acid damage.</text>
      <attack>Maw|12|3d12+7</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Titanic horrors of writhing flesh and gnashing maws, typhons slither through the Underworld seeking only to consume. Once the souls of mortal warlords and cruel tyrants, typhons come into being over ages of festering bitterness and rage. Over time, these souls twist into eternally ravenous monstrosities, which rampage through the realm of the dead, consuming souls by the thousands. The Underworld remains their prison, though, and most would relish nothing more than to escape and slaughter the living once more.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 246</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Underworld Cerberus</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>104 (11d10+44)</hp>
    <speed>walk 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +7, Perception +9, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>19</passive>
    <languages>understands all languages but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire, necrotic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, stunned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 215</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Aggressive</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, the cerberus can move up to its speed toward a hostile creature that it can see.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Multiheaded</name>
      <text>The cerberus can't be surprised, and it has advantage on saving throws against being knocked unconscious.</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>The cerberus has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the cerberus's allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The cerberus makes three bite attacks.</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) piercing damage plus 3 (1d6) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|7|2d6+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Breath Weapon (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The cerberus exhales a 30-foot cone of molten rock. Each creature in the cone must make a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw, taking 21 (6d6) fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. On a failed save, a creature is also restrained by the hardening rock. A creature can make a DC 15 Strength (Athletics) check as an action, freeing itself or a creature within reach from the rock on a success. The rock has AC 17 and 20 hit points, and it is immune to fire, poison, and psychic damage.</text>
    </action>
    <description>Three-headed cerberi dwell deep in the Underworld. Terrifying and cunning, they guard portals between the wards of the Underworld, Erebos's greatest treasures, and noteworthy souls who might attempt to escape the realm of the dead. Three-headed cerberi commonly serve demons, but if left to their own devices, they often herd wily souls into labyrinthine Underworld wildernesses, then hunt them for sport.
Feared by the living and the dead, cerberi patrol both banks of the Tartyx River. These multiheaded hounds of the Underworld breathe gouts of molten rock that sear and imprison those who trespass upon the borders of life and death. Most cerberi have a boundless hunger for fresh meat, especially the flesh of humanoids. Villains have been known to exploit that hunger by luring cerberi away from the river and setting them loose on mortal settlements.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 215</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Winged Bull</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>95 (10d10+40)</hp>
    <speed>walk 60 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands Celestial but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 214</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Charge</name>
      <text>If the bull moves at least 20 feet straight toward a creature and then hits it with a gore attack on the same turn, the target takes an extra 19 (3d12) piercing damage.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Gore</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 18 (2d12 + 5) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Gore|7|2d12+5</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Archons always ride into battle on fearsome winged mounts. Some legends suggest that the mount is actually a physical manifestation of the archon's will, allowing the pair to act with a single mind. The two most common archon mounts are winged bulls and winged lions.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 214</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Winged Lion</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>114 (12d10+48)</hp>
    <speed>walk 60 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>understands Celestial but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 214</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Pounce</name>
      <text>If the lion moves at least 20 feet straight toward a creature and then hits it with a claw attack on the same turn, that target must succeed on a DC 15 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone. If the target is prone, the lion can make one bite attack against it as a bonus action.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 16 (2d10 + 5) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|7|2d10+5</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 14 (2d8 + 5) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|7|2d8+5</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Archons always ride into battle on fearsome winged mounts. Some legends suggest that the mount is actually a physical manifestation of the archon's will, allowing the pair to act with a single mind. The two most common archon mounts are winged bulls and winged lions.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 214</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
  <monster>
    <name>Woe Strider</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>110 (13d10+39)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., climb 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>8</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Intimidation +5, Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>7</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
      <name>Source</name>
      <text>Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 247</text>
    </trait>
    <trait>
      <name>Antimagic Cone</name>
      <text>The woe strider's open mouth creates an area of antimagic, as in the antimagic field spell, in a 60-foot cone. At the start of each of its turns, the woe strider decides which way the cone faces and whether its mouth is open or closed.</text>
    </trait>
    <action>
      <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The woe strider makes two claw attacks and one bite attack. If both claws hit the same creature, the target is grappled (escape DC 14).</text>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) slashing damage plus 3 (1d6) psychic damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|7|1d6+4</attack>
    </action>
    <action>
      <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature that is grappled, incapacitated, or restrained. 13 (2d8 + 4) piercing damage plus 16 (3d10) psychic damage. In addition, each magic item the creature is carrying that isn't an artifact has its magical properties suppressed for 1 minute.</text>
      <attack>Bite|7|2d8+4</attack>
    </action>
    <description>Woe striders form from the souls of those who've broken the bonds of destiny. Over centuries, these cosmic blasphemers transform into hunched, long-limbed horrors. Sadistic things, woe striders seek ways to reweave themselves into the tapestry of destiny. This leads them to search for answers within the bowels of other beings, performing murderous haruspicy in pursuit of their discarded cosmic purpose. When they fail to find answers, their unnatural cries cause reality to shudder, undermining magic and sane minds alike.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 247</description>
    <environment></environment>
  </monster>
</compendium>
