<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <!-- Races -->
    <race>
        <name>Grung</name>
        <size>S</size>
        <speed>25</speed>
        <ability>Dex 2, Con 1</ability>
        <spellAbility></spellAbility>
        <proficiency>Perception</proficiency>
        <trait>
            <name>Natural Climber</name>
            <text>You have a climb speed of 25 feet.</text>
            <text> </text>
            <text>Source: One Grung Above, p. 4</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Arboreal Alertness</name>
            <text>You have proficiency in the Perception skill.</text>
            <text> </text>
            <text>Source: One Grung Above, p. 4</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Amphibious</name>
            <text>You can breathe air and water.</text>
            <text> </text>
            <text>Source: One Grung Above, p. 4</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Poison Immunity</name>
            <text>You're immune to poison damage and the poisoned condition.</text>
            <text> </text>
            <text>Source: One Grung Above, p. 4</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Poisonous Skin</name>
            <text>Any creature that grapples you or otherwise comes into direct contact with your skin must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or become poisoned for 1 minute. A poisoned creature no longer in direct contact with you can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. </text>
            <text>    You can also apply this poison to any piercing weapon as part of an attack with that weapon, though when you hit the poison reacts differently. The target must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or take 2d4 poison damage.</text>
            <text>     </text>
            <text>Poisoned:</text>
            <text>&#8226; A poisoned creature has disadvantage on attack rolls and ability checks.</text>
            <text> </text>
            <text>Source: One Grung Above, p. 4</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Standing Leap</name>
            <text>Your long jump is up to 25 feet and your high jump is up to 15 feet, with or without a running start.</text>
            <text> </text>
            <text>Source: One Grung Above, p. 4</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Water Dependency</name>
            <text>If you fail to immerse yourself in water for at least 1 hour during a day, you suffer one level of exhaustion at the end of that day. You can only recover from this exhaustion through magic or by immersing yourself in water for at least 1 hour.</text>
            <text> </text>
            <text>Source: One Grung Above, p. 4</text>
        </trait>
        <trait>
            <name>Languages</name>
            <text>You can speak, read, and write Grung.</text>
            <text> </text>
            <text>Source: One Grung Above, p. 4</text>
        </trait>
    </race>
    
    <!-- Monsters -->
    
</compendium>
