<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <monster>
      <name>Airship (Unearthed Arcana)</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>vehicle (80 ft. x 20 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>300</hp>
    <speed>9 miles per hour (216 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, incapacitated, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>300</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hull:</name>
      <text>Armor Class: 13</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 300</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Control:</name>
      <text>Helm</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 16</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50</text>
      <text>Move up to the speed of its elemental engine, with one 90-degree turn. If the helm is destroyed, the Airship (Unearthed Arcana) can't turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Elemental Engine</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 18</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -20 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      <text>Locomotion (air): elemental power, speed 80 ft. If the engine is destroyed, the ship immediately crashes.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Ballistas (4)</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50 each</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. 16 (3d10) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+6|3d10</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Of Ships And Sea p. 2</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Astral Brig</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>vehicle (90 ft. x 30 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac></ac>
    <hp>0</hp>
    <speed>12 miles per hour (288 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>-</str>
    <dex>-</dex>
    <con>-</con>
    <int>-</int>
    <wis>-</wis>
    <cha>-</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text></text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Ballistas (2)</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. 16 (3d10) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+6|3d10</attack>
      </action>
    <description>The astral brig is the standard githyanki military vessel. It requires a crew of five and can transport up to sixty passengers. A brig is 90 feet long and 30 feet wide, with two levels below decks for quarters and storage space. It is equipped with two ballistae, each one operated by a pair of crew members, and has a top speed of 12 miles per hour.
Source: Mordenkainen's Tome of Foes p. 90</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Astral Skiff</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>vehicle (30 ft. x 10 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac></ac>
    <hp>0</hp>
    <speed>15 miles per hour (360 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>-</str>
    <dex>-</dex>
    <con>-</con>
    <int>-</int>
    <wis>-</wis>
    <cha>-</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text></text>
      </trait>
    <description>An astral skiff is operated by a crew of three and carries up to a dozen passengers. The githyanki employ this small vessel, 30 feet long and 10 feet wide, for patrols in the Astral Plane and for quick raids in pursuit of specific objects on the Material Plane. A skiff has a top speed of 15 miles per hour. It lacks weapons aside from those carried by its passengers and has a limited amount of storage space.
Source: Mordenkainen's Tome of Foes p. 90</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Battle Balloon</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>vehicle (80 ft. x 20 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>500</hp>
    <speed>9 miles per hour (216 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, incapacitated, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>500</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hull:</name>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 500 (damage threshold 15)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Control:</name>
      <text>Helm</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 18</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50</text>
      <text>Move up to the speed of the ship's propeller, with one 90-degree turn. If the helm is destroyed, the ship can't turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Control:</name>
      <text>Balloon</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 75</text>
      <text>If its balloon is destroyed, a battle balloon cannot maintain altitude.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Propeller</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -5 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <text>On its turn the battle balloon can take 3 actions if it has twenty or more crew, 2 actions if it has ten or more crew, or 1 action if it has fewer than ten crew, choosing from the options below. It cannot take any actions if it has no remaining crew.</text>
      <text>• Fire Ballista. The battle balloon can fire its harpoon guns.</text>
      <text>• Fire Green Flame Arbalester. The battle balloon can fire its green flame arbalester.</text>
      <text>• Move. The battle balloon can use its helm to move using its propeller. If the battle balloon enters a Large or smaller creature's space, that creature is automatically pushed to the edge of the battle balloon's space. The creature must also succeed on a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw or take 5 (1d10) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>||1d10</attack>
      <text>• Harpoon Haul. The battle balloon can pull each target grappled by it up to 30 feet toward the battle balloon.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Green Flame Arbalester</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 75</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, range 200/800 ft. (can't hit targets within 60 ft. of it) one target. 16 (3d10) piercing damage and 22 (4d10) fire damage. If the attack misses, the DM determines where the arbalester bolt hits. Each creature within 10 feet of that spot must make a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw to avoid the bolt as it shatters, taking 5 (1d10) piercing damage and 5 (1d10) fire damage on a failed save.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+8|3d10</attack>
      <attack>Weapons:||1d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Harpoon Gun (3)</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50 each</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. 11 (2d10) piercing damage, and the target is grappled (escape DC 16). Until the grapple ends, the target's speed is halved, and it can't move farther away from the battle balloon. Each of the battle balloon's harpoon guns can grapple one target. While it has one or more targets grappled with its harpoon gun attack, the battle balloon's speed is not halved.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+8|2d10</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Through the winter clouds that surround the castle on this desolate hill, you see a shape emerge. Something so gigantic, you can't believe it can actually fly.
Airships are relatively rare in Acquisitions Incorporated, which is thought to hold no more than five in its fleet. But the unparalleled usefulness of these craft in commerce—and in combat—makes the company-standard battle balloon a much-coveted upgrade for any franchise.
Origins and Operations. Professional secrecy and aggressive marketing make it unclear where the airship originated. Some say battle balloons were an original design created by the Heuristic Arcane Research and Development department of Acquisitions Incorporated. But the wizards of Halruaa developed similar skyships in ages past, and the Cult of the Dragon has been seen with flying ships of its own. Still, among the small number of factions and organizations known to possess or build airships, Acquisitions Incorporated might be the best known for its high-profile aerial escapades. It's certain that neither the mages of Halruaa nor the members of the Cult of the Dragon ever crewed a battle balloon with keg robots, or used one to squash a tyrannosaurus flat.
The Hard Cloud. 
------
The Hard Cloud is Acquisitions Incorporated's company flagship, and as such, bears special note. The great battle balloon bristles with armaments, including a vicious dragon-slaying spear at the fore that has seen use more than once. The Hard Cloud is a veteran of numerous combat operations, and it has so far come out in one piece. Beyond the tales told of the vessel's exploits, rumors abound regarding the wondrous vehicle. Is it powered by a bound efreeti, as some have said? Does the hold contain clones of every high-ranking member of Acquisitions Incorporated, including Omin Dran himself? Does the mess, in fact, employ a terrifying ghostly chef? The answers lie below decks, where few have had the opportunity to learn the truth.
------
Flying Battle Vehicle. The standard design of an Acquisitions Incorporated-grade airship features an enormous balloon covered in a rope net. Trailing lines connect the balloon to the vessel of metal and wood suspended below. In the center of the deck, directly below the balloon, sits a large magic furnace, whose formidable lifting power is rumored to involve trapped elementals. The airship's captain controls the arcane furnace and directs forward thrust by way of a propeller located at the back of the ship, helming the craft with a wheel positioned in the bow. Metal runners below the ship allow a battle balloon to land on the ground.
Options and Armaments. Each franchise or organization customizes the offensive capability of its airships, but most battle balloons feature multiple harpoon guns, perfect for fighting and snaring aerial threats. Battle balloons that see a lot of combat are typically well stocked with other ranged weapons and polearms for ship-to-ship and crew-to-crew fighting.
Whether privately financed or loaned out by Head Office under extraordinarily cautious terms, battle balloons can be customized with unique equipment—different siege weapons, lifting and cargo gear, and so forth—to make each airship unique. However, the most potent weapon featured on most Acquisitions Incorporated battle balloons is the green flame arbalester, a massive ballista whose bolts pulse with arcane power and detonate with formidable explosive force wherever they hit.
Vehicle Rules. 
------
Battle balloons and mechanical beholders are vehicles, and as such, they have special rules associated with them. Most pertinently, a vehicle has the six ability scores (Strength, Dexterity, Constitution, Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma) and the corresponding modifiers. The Strength of a vehicle expresses its size and weight. Dexterity represents its ease of handling. A vehicle's Constitution covers its durability and the quality of its construction. Vehicles usually have a score of 0 in Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma. If a vehicle has a 0 in a score, it automatically fails any ability check or saving throw that uses that score. How a vehicle is crewed and what actions it can take on its turn are described in the stat block for the vehicle.
------
Mobile Franchise Headquarters. A battle balloon is perhaps the most sought-after of the mobile headquarters options available to Acquisitions Incorporated franchises. The versatility of an airship allows for the rapid shipping of goods, mercenaries, and loot. Such a vessel also allows a quick escape from sticky developments and deals gone bad.
Source: Acquisitions Incorporated p. 218</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Demon Grinder</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>vehicle (12,000 lb.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>19 (19 while motionless)</ac>
    <hp>200</hp>
    <speed>100 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire, poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>200 (damage threshold 10, mishap threshold 20)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Crushing Wheels</name>
      <text>The Demon Grinder can move through the space of any Large or smaller creature. When it does, the creature must succeed on a DC 11 Dexterity saving throw or take 22 (4d10) bludgeoning damage and be knocked prone. If the creature was already prone, it takes an extra 22 (4d10) bludgeoning damage. This trait can't be used against a particular creature more than once each turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Weapons</name>
      <text>The Demon Grinder's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Prone Deficiency</name>
      <text>If the Demon Grinder rolls over and falls prone, it can't right itself and is incapacitated until flipped upright.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Helm (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Three-Quarters Cover)</name>
      <text>Drive and steer the Demon Grinder.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Chomper (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half Cover)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 25 (6d6 + 4) piercing damage. A target reduced to 0 hit points by this damage is ground to bits and spit out through pipes on both sides of the Demon Grinder.Any nonmagical items the target was holding or carrying are destroyed as well.</text>
      <attack>Chomper (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half Cover)|+9|6d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Wrecking Ball (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half Cover)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. 40 (8d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage. Double the damage if the target is an object or a structure.</text>
      <attack>Wrecking Ball (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half Cover)|+9|8d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>2 Harpoon Flingers (Each Station Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half Cover)</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. 9 (2d8) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>2 Harpoon Flingers (Each Station Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half Cover)|+5|2d8</attack>
      </action>
    <description>A Demon Grinder is a bulky, armored coach that rumbles loudly as it crushes obstacles and enemies in its path with the help of a swinging wrecking ball. Iron jaws are mounted on the front of the vehicle, which handles like a garbage truck.
Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 219</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Devil's Ride</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>vehicle (500 lb.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>23 (19 while motionless)</ac>
    <hp>30</hp>
    <speed>120 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire, poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>30 (damage threshold 5, mishap threshold 10)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Jump</name>
      <text>If the Devil's Ride moves at least 30 feet in a straight line, it can clear a distance of up to 60 feet when jumping over a chasm, ravine, or other gap. Each foot it clears on the jump costs a foot of movement.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Prone Deficiency</name>
      <text>If the Devil's Ride falls prone, it can't right itself and is incapacitated until pulled upright.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Stunt</name>
      <text>On its turn, the driver of the Devil's Ride can expend 10 feet of movement to perform one free vehicle stunt, such as a wheelie or a burnout. Before the stunt can be performed, the Devil's Ride must move at least 10 feet in a straight line. If the driver succeeds on a DC 10 Dexterity check using the bike's Dexterity, the stunt is successful. Otherwise, the driver is unable to perform the stunt and can't attempt another stunt until the start of its next turn. If the check fails by 5 or more, the Devil's Ride and all creatures riding it immediately fall prone as the bike wipes out and comes to a dead stop.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Helm (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half Cover)</name>
      <text>Drive and steer the Devil's Ride.</text>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Juke</name>
      <text>If the Devil's Ride is able to move, the driver can use its reaction to grant the Devil's Ride advantage on a Dexterity saving throw.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>A Devil's Ride is a two-wheeled infernal war machine that handles like a motorcycle. It has spiked wheels, a screaming engine, and a cowl shaped vaguely like a grinning devil's visage, with horns for handle bars. What the vehicle lacks in weapons, it makes up for with speed and maneuverability.
Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 218</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Galley</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>vehicle (130 ft. x 20 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>500</hp>
    <speed>4 miles per hour (96 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>24</str>
    <dex>4</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, incapacitated, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>500</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hull:</name>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 500 (damage threshold 20)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Control:</name>
      <text>Helm</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 16</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50</text>
      <text>Move up to the speed of one of its movement components, with one 90-degree turn. If the helm is destroyed, the galley can't turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Oars</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -5 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Sails</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -10 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <text>On its turn, the galley can take 3 actions, choosing from the options below. It can take only 2 actions if it has fewer than forty crew and only 1 action if it has fewer than twenty. It can't take these actions if it has fewer than three crew.</text>
      <text>• Fire Ballistas. The galley can fire its ballista (DMG, ch. 8).</text>
      <text>• Fire Mangonels. The galley can fire its mangonel (DMG, ch. 8).</text>
      <text>• Move. The galley can use its helm to move with its oars or sails. As part of this move, it can use its naval ram.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Ballistas (4)</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50 each</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. 16 (3d10) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+6|3d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Mangonels (2)</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100 each</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 200/800 ft. (can't hit targets within 60 ft. of it), one target. 27 (5d10) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+5|5d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Naval Ram</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 20</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100 (damage threshold 10)</text>
      <text>The galley has advantage on all saving throws relating to crashing when it crashes into a creature or an object. Any damage it takes from the crash is applied to the naval ram rather than to the ship. These benefits don't apply if another vessel crashes into the galley.</text>
      </action>
    <description>Example Galley Crew
A galley requires a crew of eighty to properly sail or row the vessel and might carry extra passengers or soldiers. If the characters are guests on a galley, the crew consists of the following creatures, all of which have proficiency with water vehicles in addition to their normal statistics:
• One captain (bandit captain)
• Five other officers: a first mate, a bosun, a quartermaster, a surgeon, and a cook (scout)
• Forty-two sailors (commoner)
• Twelve siege engineers (guard)
• Twenty guard
Main Deck
The main deck of the galley has the following features:
• Ballistas. Four ballistas (DMG, ch. 8) are attached to the fore of the deck. Ten ballista arrows are stacked and secured near each.
• Mangonels. Two mangonels (DMG, ch. 8) are attached to the aft of the deck. Ten mangonel stones are stacked and secured near each catapult.
• Naval Ram. The galley's stern features an iron naval ram used for attacking other ships.
• Opening. A 10-foot-wide, 80-foot-long open space in the middle of the deck stretches fore to aft and leads down to the lower deck.
• Railing. A 3-foot-high rail is built around the deck's perimeter, providing half cover for Medium creatures and three-quarters cover for Small creatures behind it.
• Rowboats. Eight rowboats are stacked in two groups of four on this deck. Ropes and pulleys can hoist these boats in and out of the water.
• Timpani. A timpani with two attached mallets sits on the aft of the main deck just before the opening to the lower deck. A crew member plays this instrument while the sailors on the lower deck row, the beat helping to synchronize the rowers' strokes.
• Wheel. The ship's wheel stands at the aft of the deck.
Lower Deck
The cramped lower deck of the galley ship reeks of body odor and has the following features:
• Cargo Holds. Cargo holds at the fore and aft of the lower deck hold crates, barrels, and ammunition secured with rope.
• Oars. Thirty-two benches are built into the deck, each with a 20-foot-long oar. When the ship is rowed, crew members sit on these benches to work the oars. Ten spare oars hang on the walls.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 187</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Galley (Unearthed Arcana)</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>vehicle (130 ft. x 20 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>500</hp>
    <speed>4 miles per hour (96 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>24</str>
    <dex>4</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, incapacitated, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>500</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hull:</name>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 500 (damage threshold 20)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Control:</name>
      <text>Helm</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 16</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50</text>
      <text>Move up to the speed of one of its movement components, with one 90-degree turn. If the helm is destroyed, the Galley (Unearthed Arcana) can't turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Sails</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -10 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      <text>Locomotion (water): sails, speed 35 ft.; 15 ft. while sailing into the wind; 50 ft. while sailing with the wind.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Oars</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -5 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      <text>Locomotion (water): oars, speed 30 ft.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Ballistas (4)</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50 each</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. 16 (3d10) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+6|3d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Mangonels (2)</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100 each</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 200/800 ft. (can't hit targets within 60 ft. of it), one target. 27 (5d10) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+5|5d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Ram</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 20</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100 (damage threshold 10)</text>
      <text>The Galley (Unearthed Arcana) has advantage on all saving throws relating to crashing when it crashes into a creature or object, and any damage it suffers from the crash is instead applied to the ram. These benefits do not apply if a vehicle crashes into the Galley (Unearthed Arcana).</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Of Ships And Sea p. 2</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Keelboat</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>vehicle (60 ft. x 20 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>100</hp>
    <speed>3 miles per hour (72 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>7</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, incapacitated, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>100</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hull:</name>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100 (damage threshold 10)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Control:</name>
      <text>Helm</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50</text>
      <text>Move up to the speed of one of its movement components, with one 90-degree turn. If the helm is destroyed, the keelboat can't turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Oars</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -5 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Sails</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -5 ft. speed per 20 damage taken </text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <text>On its turn, the keelboat can take 2 actions, choosing from the options below. It can take only 1 action if it has only one crew. It can't take these actions if it has no crew.</text>
      <text>• Fire Ballista. The keelboat can fire its ballista (DMG, ch. 8).</text>
      <text>• Move. The keelboat can use its helm to move with its oars or sails.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Ballista</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. 16 (3d10) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+6|3d10</attack>
      <text>Keelboats typically include a ballista only when they are equipped for combat.</text>
      </action>
    <description>Example Keelboat Crew
A keelboat requires a single crew member to operate smoothly. If the characters are guests on a keelboat, the crew consists of a single captain who has the statistics of a bandit captain with proficiency with water vehicles.
Keelboat Deck
The deck of the keelboat has the following features:
• Ballista. A ballista (DMG, ch. 8) is mounted on the fore of the deck. Ten ballista arrows are stacked and secured nearby.
• Oars. The deck of the ship holds twelve benches and four 15-foot-long oars. When the ship is rowed, crew members sit on these benches to work the oars.
• Railing. The deck has a 3-foot-high rail around its perimeter that provides half cover for Medium creatures and three-quarters cover for Small creatures behind it.
Keelboat Cabin
The keelboat cabin has the following features:
• Footlockers. Beneath each bed is a footlocker. The footlockers are iron and have AC 19, 18 hit points, and immunity to poison and psychic damage.
• Furnishings. Two beds and a desk with a chair stand at the aft of the cabin.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 188</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Keelboat (Unearthed Arcana)</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>vehicle (60 ft. x 20 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>100</hp>
    <speed>3 miles per hour (72 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>7</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, incapacitated, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>100</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hull:</name>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100 (damage threshold 10)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Control:</name>
      <text>Helm</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50</text>
      <text>Move up to the speed of one of its movement components, with one 90-degree turn. If the helm is destroyed, the Keelboat (Unearthed Arcana) can't turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Sails</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -5 ft. speed per 20 damage taken </text>
      <text>Locomotion (water): sails, speed 25 ft.; 15 ft. while sailing into the wind; 35 ft. while sailing with the wind.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Oars</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -5 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      <text>Locomotion (water): oars, speed 20 ft.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Ballista</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. 16 (3d10) piercing damage. Keelboat (Unearthed Arcana)s typically include a ballista only when they are equipped for combat.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+6|3d10</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Of Ships And Sea p. 3</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Longship</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>vehicle (70 ft. x 20 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>300</hp>
    <speed>5 miles per hour (120 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>6</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, incapacitated, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>300</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hull:</name>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 300 (damage threshold 15)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Control:</name>
      <text>Helm</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 16</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50</text>
      <text>Move up to the speed of one of its movement components, with one 90-degree turn. If the helm is destroyed, the longship can't turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Oars</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -5 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Sails</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -10 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <text>On its turn, the longship can take the move action below. It can't take this action if it has no crew.</text>
      <text>• Move. The longship can use its helm to move with its oars or sails.</text>
      </action>
    <description>Example Longship Crew
A longship requires a crew of forty to properly sail or row the vessel and often carries extra passengers or soldiers. If the characters are guests on a longship, the crew consists of the following creatures, all of which have proficiency with water vehicles in addition to their normal statistics:
• One captain (berserker)
• Five other officers: a first mate, a bosun, a quartermaster, a surgeon, and a cook (berserker)
• Thirty-four sailors (commoner)
Longship Deck
The deck of the longship has the following features:
• Oars. Sixteen benches are built into the deck, each with a 15-foot-long oar. When the ship is rowed, crew members sit on these benches to work the oars. Five spare oars hang on the walls.
• Railing. The deck has a 3-foot-high rail covered in wooden shields around its perimeter that provides half cover for Medium creatures and three-quarters cover for Small creatures behind it.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 190</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Longship (Unearthed Arcana)</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>vehicle (70 ft. x 20 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>300</hp>
    <speed>5 miles per hour (120 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>6</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, incapacitated, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>300</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hull:</name>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 300 (damage threshold 15)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Control:</name>
      <text>Helm</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 16</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50</text>
      <text>Move up to the speed of one of its movement components, with one 90-degree turn. If the helm is destroyed, the Longship (Unearthed Arcana) can't turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Sails</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -10 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      <text>Locomotion (water): sails, speed 45 ft.; 15 ft. while sailing into the wind; 60 ft. while sailing with the wind.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Oars</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -5 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      <text>Locomotion (water): oars, speed 20 ft.</text>
      </trait>
    <description>
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Of Ships And Sea p. 4</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Mechanical Beholder</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>vehicle (15 ft. x 15 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>18</ac>
    <hp>200</hp>
    <speed>3 miles per hour (72 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, incapacitated, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>200</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hull:</name>
      <text>Armor Class: 18</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 200 (damage threshold 10)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Control:</name>
      <text>Helm</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 16</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 25</text>
      <text>Move up to the speed of the ship's magical propulsion unit, with one 90-degree turn. The helm can be attacked only if the hull has taken 100 or more damage. If the helm is destroyed, the mechanical beholder can't move.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Magical Propulsion Unit</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 16</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -5 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <text>On its turn the mechanical beholder can take 1 action. It cannot take any actions if it has no crew.</text>
      <text>• Eye Rays. The mechanical beholder can use its eye ray tentacles.</text>
      <text>• Move. The mechanical beholder can use its helm to move using its magical propulsion unit.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Eye Ray Tentacles (6)</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 14</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50 each</text>
      <text>g The mechanical beholder shoots the following magical eye rays at up to three targets that would be visible to the crew and are within 120 feet of it.</text>
      <text>• Disintegration Ray. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw or take 18 (4d8) force damage. If this damage reduces the creature to 0 hit points, its body becomes a pile of fine gray dust. If the target is a Large or smaller nonmagical object or creation of magical force, it is disintegrated without a saving throw. If the target is a Huge or larger object or creation of magical force, this ray disintegrates a 10-foot cube of it.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:||4d8</attack>
      <text>• Enervation Ray. The targeted creature must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw, taking 18 (4d8) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:||4d8</attack>
      <text>• Paralyzing Ray. The targeted creature must succeed on a DC 15 Constitution saving throw or be paralyzed for 1 minute. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      </action>
    <description>When you hear the mechanical beholder click to life, it sounds like death itself snapping its fingers.
A mechanical beholder takes the form of an oversized eye tyrant whose central eye is a viewport window. Part conveyance, part laboratory, and part siege engine, the vehicle can transport up to six humanoids through any terrain or medium, including underwater and through solid stone. A complex and often dangerous manipulation of gears, levers, and buttons controlled the original mechanical beholders, but more recent models feature magical controls that respond to voice commands—though not always accurately.
Equipment and Options. The mechanical beholder can be outfitted with a variety of sensors, probes, and gauges, allowing for functions as varied as determining alchemical composition, picking up on magical auras, or making masterfully dry martinis. Its range of armaments includes a disintegration ray modeled after that of its monstrous namesake (which for reasons of liability is advertised as being designed exclusively for waste removal). Portholes and hatches allow characters inside the beholder to make ranged and magical attacks from within it.
Source: Acquisitions Incorporated p. 219</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Planar Raider</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>vehicle (120 ft. x 40 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac></ac>
    <hp>0</hp>
    <speed>12 miles per hour (288 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>-</str>
    <dex>-</dex>
    <con>-</con>
    <int>-</int>
    <wis>-</wis>
    <cha>-</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text></text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Ballistas (2)</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. 16 (3d10) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+6|3d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Catapult</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 200/800 ft. (can't hit targets within 60 feet of it), one target. 27 (5d10) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+5|5d10</attack>
      </action>
    <description>The largest of the githyanki ships, the planar raider serves as a mobile headquarters during a major attack on the githyanki's enemies. It needs a crew of ten and can carry more than a hundred passengers. A planar raider can travel up to 12 miles per hour. It is 40 feet wide and 120 feet long, with two levels below decks, and is equipped with three ballistae and a catapult.
Source: Mordenkainen's Tome of Foes p. 90</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Rowboat</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>vehicle (10 ft. x 5 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>50</hp>
    <speed>3 miles per hour (72 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, incapacitated, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>50</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hull:</name>
      <text>Armor Class: 11</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Oars</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 25</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <text>On its turn, the rowboat can take the move action below. It can't take this action if it has no crew.</text>
      <text>• Move. The rowboat can move using its oars.</text>
      </action>
    <description>The humble rowboat serves to ferry passengers back and forth from larger ships or to navigate lakes and rivers. Due to its simple, versatile design, a rowboat has no decks or typical crew. Weighing 100 pounds, a rowboat is easy to transport and might be carried by larger ships.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 190</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Rowboat (Unearthed Arcana)</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>vehicle (10 ft. x 5 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>50</hp>
    <speed>3 miles per hour (72 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, incapacitated, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>50</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hull:</name>
      <text>Armor Class: 11</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50 (damage threshold 0)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Oars</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 25</text>
      <text>Locomotion (water): oars, speed 15 ft. Move up to its speed, with one 90-degree turn. Without oars, the Rowboat (Unearthed Arcana)'s speed is 0.</text>
      </trait>
    <description>
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Of Ships And Sea p. 4</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sailing Ship</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>vehicle (100 ft. x 20 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>300</hp>
    <speed>5 miles per hour (120 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>7</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, incapacitated, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>300</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hull:</name>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 300 (damage threshold 15)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Control:</name>
      <text>Helm</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 18</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50</text>
      <text>Move up to the speed of its sails, with one 90-degree turn. If the helm is destroyed, the ship can't turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Sails</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -5 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <text>On its turn, the ship can take 3 actions, choosing from the options below. It can take only 2 actions if it has fewer than twenty crew and only 1 action if it has fewer than ten. It can't take these actions if it has fewer than three crew.</text>
      <text>• Fire Ballista. The ship can fire its ballista (DMG, ch. 8).</text>
      <text>• Fire Mangonel. The ship can fire its mangonel (DMG, ch. 8).</text>
      <text>• Move. The ship can use its helm to move with its sails.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Ballista</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. 16 (3d10) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+6|3d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Mangonel</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 200/800 ft. (can't hit targets within 60 ft. of it), one target. 27 (5d10) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+5|5d10</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Example Crew
A sailing ship requires a large crew to properly sail the vessel. If the characters are guests on a sailing ship, the crew consists of the following creatures, all of which have proficiency with water vehicles in addition to their normal statistics:
• One captain (bandit captain)
• Four other officers: a first mate, a bosun, a quartermaster, and a cook (noble)
• Twenty-five sailors (commoner)
1. Main Deck
The main deck of the ship has the following features:
• Mangonel. Sailing ships have one mangonel (DMG, ch. 8) attached to the deck.  Each weapon has 10 mangonel stones stacked and secured near it.
• Hatch. A covered, 10-foot-square opening leads to the lower deck (area W8).
• Railing. The main deck has a 3-foot-high rail around its perimeter that provides half cover for Medium creatures and three-quarters cover for Small creatures behind it.
• Rowboats. Four rowboat are stacked on top of each other on this deck. Ropes and pulleys can hoist these boats in and out of the water.
2. Officers' Quarters
Four beds stand in the officer's quarters. Beneath each is an iron footlocker that holds the officers' belongings. The officers sleep in shifts so someone remains on duty to command the crew and carry out the captain's orders.
3. Captain's Quarters
The captain's quarters hold a bed and a desk. Beneath the bed is an iron footlocker that holds the captain's belongings.
4. Siege Weapon Ammunition
Shelves and rope on the walls of this cabin secure mangonel stones and ballista arrows.
5. Supplies
This area holds tools, barrels of tar, rope, extra material to repair sails, and other supplies needed to maintain the ship.
6. Forecastle
The forecastle has the following features:
• Ballista. A ballista (DMG, ch. 8) is attached to the deck. Ten ballista arrows are stacked and secured nearby.
• Railing. The forecastle has a 3-foot-high rail around its perimeter that provides half cover for Medium creatures and three-quarters cover for Small creatures behind it.
7. Quarterdeck
The quarterdeck has the following features:
• Railing. The quarterdeck has a 3-foot-high rail around its perimeter that provides half cover for Medium creatures and three-quarters cover for Small creatures behind it.
• Wheel. The ship's wheel stands at the aft of the quarterdeck.
8. Oar Deck
Twenty-two benches are built into the deck of the lower deck, each with a 20-foot-long oar. When the ship is rowed, crew members sit on these benches to work the oars. Ten spare oars hang on the walls of the ship.
9. Privy
Benches line the walls of this room. Four holes carved in them house chamber pots.
10. Medical Cabin
Hooks and shelves on the walls hold medical instruments, bandages, balms, tonics, jars of leeches, and more, ready to treat injuries from combat or sailing mishaps.
11. Guest Cabin
This cabin is meant for guests and visiting high-ranking officials along for the journey.
12. Hold
This area houses both passengers and cargo. The ship's off-duty crew sleep on bedrolls among the crates and barrels of food, water, and other supplies.
13. Armory
The ship's supply of weapons and armor is held in this cabin. Its walls are fitted with built-in weapon and armor racks. The door to this cabin is usually locked, the key kept by one of the ship's officers.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 192</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sailing Ship (Unearthed Arcana)</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>vehicle (80 ft. x 20 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>300</hp>
    <speed>5 miles per hour (120 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>7</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, incapacitated, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>300</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hull:</name>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 300 (damage threshold 15)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Control:</name>
      <text>Helm</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 18</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50</text>
      <text>Move up to the speed of its sails, with one 90-degree turn. If the helm is destroyed, the ship can't turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Sails</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -5 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      <text>Locomotion (water): sails, speed 45 ft.; 15 ft. while sailing into the wind; 60 ft. while sailing with the wind.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Ballista</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. 16 (3d10) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+6|3d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Mangonel</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 200/800 ft. (can't hit targets within 60 ft. of it), one target. 27 (5d10) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+5|5d10</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Of Ships And Sea p. 4</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Scavenger</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>vehicle (9,000 lb.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>20 (19 while motionless)</ac>
    <hp>150</hp>
    <speed>100 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire, poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>150 (damage threshold 10, mishap threshold 20)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Crushing Wheels</name>
      <text>The Scavenger can move through the space of any Large or smaller creature. When it does, the creature must succeed on a DC 12 Dexterity saving throw or take 16 (3d10) bludgeoning damage and be knocked prone. If the creature was already prone, it takes an extra 16 (3d10) bludgeoning damage. This trait can't be used against a particular creature more than once each turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Weapons</name>
      <text>The Scavenger's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Prone Deficiency</name>
      <text>If the Scavenger rolls over and falls prone, it can't right itself and is incapacitated until flipped upright.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Helm (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Three-Quarters Cover)</name>
      <text>Drive and steer the Scavenger.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Grappling Claw (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half Cover)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. The target is grappled (escape DC 12). If the target is a creature, it is restrained until the grapple ends.The grappling claw can grapple only one target at a time, and the claw's operator can use a bonus action to make the claw release whatever it's holding.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>2 Harpoon Flingers (Each Station Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half Cover)</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. 10 (2d8 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>2 Harpoon Flingers (Each Station Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half Cover)|+6|2d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>The Scavenger handles like a small bus and is used to sift through battlefield detritus for scrap metal and other materials worth salvaging. Attached to the back of the vehicle is a swinging crane with an iron grappling claw fastened to the end of a winch and a 50-foot-long chain.
Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 219</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Stahlmaster</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>CREATURE</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>U (n, k, n, o, w, n)</ac>
    <hp>67 (9d10+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Pilot</name>
      <text>The Stahlmaster requires a Medium humanoid to pilot it. While inside the Stahlmaster, the pilot uses the vehicle's speed and action options and can't take reactions or use bonus actions, and the pilot has total cover. If the Stahlmaster drops to 0 hit points, the pilot is ejected from it and lands prone in an unoccupied space within 5 feet of the vehicle.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The Stahlmaster makes two melee attacks, or one melee attack and one ranged attack.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (1d10 + 4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+6|1d10+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shoulder-Mounted Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. 6 (1d12) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shoulder-Mounted Crossbow|+2|1d12</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Wildemount: Dangerous Designs p. 235</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Tormentor</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>vehicle (3,000 lb.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>21 (19 while motionless)</ac>
    <hp>60</hp>
    <speed>100 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire, poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>60 (damage threshold 10, mishap threshold 20)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Crushing Wheels</name>
      <text>The Tormentor can move through the space of any Medium or smaller creature.When it does, the creature must succeed on a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw or take 11 (2d10) bludgeoning damage and be knocked prone.If the creature was already prone, it takes an extra 11 (2d10) bludgeoning damage.This trait can't be used against a particular creature more than once each turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Prone Deficiency</name>
      <text>If the Tormentor rolls over and falls prone, it can't right itself and is incapacitated until flipped upright.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Weapons</name>
      <text>The Tormentor's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Raking Scythes</name>
      <text>When the Tormentor moves within 5 feet of a creature that isn't prone or another vehicle for the first time on a turn, it can rake the creature or vehicle with its protruding blades for 13 (2d10 + 2) slashing damage. A creature moves out of the way and takes no damage if it succeeds on a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw.A vehicle moves out of the way and takes no damage if its driver succeeds on the saving throw.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>(Requires 1 Crew and Grants Three-Quarters Cover)</name>
      <text>Drive and steer the Tormentor</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Harpoon Flinger (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half Cover)</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. 11 (2d8 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Harpoon Flinger (Requires 1 Crew and Grants Half Cover)|+7|2d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Juke</name>
      <text>If the Tormentor is able to move, the driver can use its reaction to grant the Tormentor advantage on a Dexterity saving throw.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>The Tormentor handles like a dune buggy and is designed for raiding and scouting. Bladed iron wheels drive the vehicle forward.
Source: Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus p. 218</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Warship</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>vehicle (100 ft. x 20 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>500</hp>
    <speed>4 miles per hour (96 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>4</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, incapacitated, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>500</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hull:</name>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 500 (damage threshold 20)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Control:</name>
      <text>Helm</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 18</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50</text>
      <text>Move up to the speed of one of its movement components, with one 90-degree turn. If the helm is destroyed, the warship can't turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Oars</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -5 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Sails</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -10 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <text>On its turn, the warship can take 3 actions, choosing from the options below. It can take only 2 actions if it has fewer than twenty crew and only 1 action if it has fewer than ten. It can't take these actions if it has fewer than three crew.</text>
      <text>• Fire Ballistas. The warship can fire its ballista (DMG, ch. 8).</text>
      <text>• Fire Mangonels. The warship can fire its mangonel (DMG, ch. 8).</text>
      <text>• Move. The warship can use its helm to move with its oars or sails. As part of this move, it can use its naval ram.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Ballistas (2)</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50 each</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. 16 (3d10) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+6|3d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Mangonels (2)</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100 each</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 200/800 ft. (can't hit targets within 60 ft. of it), one target. 27 (5d10) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+5|5d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Naval Ram</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 20</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100 (damage threshold 10)</text>
      <text>The warship has advantage on all saving throws relating to crashing when it crashes into a creature or object. Any damage it takes from the crash is applied to the naval ram rather than to the ship. These benefits don't apply if another vessel crashes into the warship.</text>
      </action>
    <description>Example Crew
A warship requires a large crew to properly sail the vessel. Warships carry extra soldiers to fight battles and fire the siege weapons. If the characters are guests on a warship, the crew consists of the following creatures, all of which have proficiency with water vehicles in addition to their normal statistics:
• One captain (bandit captain)
• Four other officers: a first mate, a bosun, a quartermaster, and a cook (noble)
• Twenty-five sailors (commoner)
A warship typically includes the following additional crew to augment its fighting ability:
• Forty soldiers (guard)
• Eight siege engineers (guard)
• One priest (the ship's surgeon)
1. Main Deck
The main deck of the ship has the following features:
• Mangonel. Sailing ships have one mangonel (DMG, ch. 8) attached to the deck. Warships have two mangonels (DMG, ch. 8). Each weapon has 10 mangonel stones stacked and secured near it.
• Hatch. A covered, 10-foot-square opening leads to the lower deck (area W8).
• Railing. The main deck has a 3-foot-high rail around its perimeter that provides half cover for Medium creatures and three-quarters cover for Small creatures behind it.
• Rowboats. Four rowboat are stacked on top of each other on this deck. Ropes and pulleys can hoist these boats in and out of the water.
2. Officers' Quarters
Four beds stand in the officer's quarters. Beneath each is an iron footlocker that holds the officers' belongings. The officers sleep in shifts so someone remains on duty to command the crew and carry out the captain's orders.
3. Captain's Quarters
The captain's quarters hold a bed and a desk. Beneath the bed is an iron footlocker that holds the captain's belongings.
4. Siege Weapon Ammunition
Shelves and rope on the walls of this cabin secure mangonel stones and ballista arrows.
5. Supplies
This area holds tools, barrels of tar, rope, extra material to repair sails, and other supplies needed to maintain the ship.
6. Forecastle
The forecastle has the following features:
• Ballista. A ballista (DMG, ch. 8) is attached to the deck. Ten ballista arrows are stacked and secured nearby.
• Figurehead. Warships have an iron figurehead at the front of their forecastle, often shaped to look like a fearsome sea predator. This figurehead serves as the ship's naval ram.
• Railing. The forecastle has a 3-foot-high rail around its perimeter that provides half cover for Medium creatures and three-quarters cover for Small creatures behind it.
7. Quarterdeck
The quarterdeck has the following features:
• Ballista. On a warship, a ballista (DMG, ch. 8) is attached to the deck. Ten ballista arrows are stacked and secured nearby.
• Railing. The quarterdeck has a 3-foot-high rail around its perimeter that provides half cover for Medium creatures and three-quarters cover for Small creatures behind it.
• Wheel. The ship's wheel stands at the aft of the quarterdeck.
8. Oar Deck
Twenty-two benches are built into the deck of the lower deck, each with a 20-foot-long oar. When the ship is rowed, crew members sit on these benches to work the oars. Ten spare oars hang on the walls of the ship.
9. Privy
Benches line the walls of this room. Four holes carved in them house chamber pots.
10. Medical Cabin
Hooks and shelves on the walls hold medical instruments, bandages, balms, tonics, jars of leeches, and more, ready to treat injuries from combat or sailing mishaps.
11. Brig
This cabin is meant for guests and visiting high-ranking officials along for the journey. Since warships often have a greater need to house prisoners rather than guests, each bed aboard such a vessel also has a set of manacles (see chapter 5 in the Player's Handbook) attached to its frame.
12. Hold
This area houses both passengers and cargo. The ship's off-duty crew sleep on bedrolls among the crates and barrels of food, water, and other supplies.
13. Armory
The ship's supply of weapons and armor is held in this cabin. Its walls are fitted with built-in weapon and armor racks. The door to this cabin is usually locked, the key kept by one of the ship's officers.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 194</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Warship (Unearthed Arcana)</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>vehicle (100 ft. x 20 ft.)</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>500</hp>
    <speed>4 miles per hour (96 miles per day)</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>4</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>0</int>
    <wis>0</wis>
    <cha>0</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, incapacitated, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, stunned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>500</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hull:</name>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 500 (damage threshold 20)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Control:</name>
      <text>Helm</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 18</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50</text>
      <text>Move up to the speed of one of its movement components, with one 90-degree turn. If the helm is destroyed, the Warship (Unearthed Arcana) can't turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Sails</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -10 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      <text>Locomotion (water): sails, speed 35 ft.; 15 ft. while sailing into the wind; 50 ft. while sailing with the wind.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Movement:</name>
      <text>Oars</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 12</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100; -5 ft. speed per 25 damage taken</text>
      <text>Locomotion (water): oars, speed 20 ft. with 80 or more rowers, 10 feet with 40 or more rowers, 5 ft. with 20 or more rowers.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Ballistas (2)</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 50 each</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 120/480 ft., one target. 16 (3d10) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+6|3d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Mangonels (2)</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 15</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100 each</text>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 200/800 ft. (can't hit targets within 60 ft. of it), one target. 27 (5d10) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Weapons:|+5|5d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weapons:</name>
      <text>Ram</text>
      <text>Armor Class: 20</text>
      <text>Hit Points: 100 (damage threshold 10)</text>
      <text>The Warship (Unearthed Arcana) has advantage on all saving throws relating to crashing when it crashes into a creature or object. Any damage it suffers from the crash is instead applied to the ram. These benefits do not apply if another vessel crashes into the Warship (Unearthed Arcana).</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Of Ships And Sea p. 5</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  </compendium>
