<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Monk</name>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monastic Tradition: Way of the Drunken Master</name>
        <text>The Way of the Drunken Master teaches its students to move with the jerky, unpredictable movements of a drunkard. A drunken master sways, tottering on unsteady feet, to present what seems like an incompetent combatant who proves frustrating to engage. The drunken master's erratic stumbles conceal a carefully executed dance of blocks, parries, advances, attacks, and retreats.</text>
        <text>A drunken master often enjoys playing the fool to bring gladness to the despondent or to demonstrate humility to the arrogant, but when battle is joined, the drunken master can be a maddening, masterful foe.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 33</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Drunken Master: Bonus Proficiencies</name>
        <text>When you choose this tradition at 3rd level, you gain proficiency in the Performance skill if you don't already have it. Your martial arts technique mixes combat training with the precision of a dancer and the antics of a jester. You also gain proficiency with brewer's supplies if you don't already have it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 33</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Drunken Master: Drunken Technique</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn how to twist and turn quickly as part of your Flurry of Blows. Whenever you use Flurry of Blows, you gain the benefit of the Disengage action, and your walking speed increases by 10 feet until the end of the current turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 33</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monastic Tradition: Way of the Kensei</name>
        <text>Monks of the Way of the Kensei train relentlessly with their weapons, to the point where the weapon becomes an extension of the body. Founded on a mastery of sword fighting, the tradition has expanded to include many different weapons.</text>
        <text>A kensei sees a weapon in much the same way a calligrapher or painter regards a pen or brush. Whatever the weapon, the kensei views it as a tool used to express the beauty and precision of the martial arts. That such mastery makes a kensei a peerless warrior is but a side effect of intense devotion, practice, and study.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 34</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei: Path of the Kensei</name>
        <text>When you choose this tradition at 3rd level, your special martial arts training leads you to master the use of certain weapons. This path also includes instruction in the deft strokes of calligraphy or painting. You gain the following benefits.</text>
        <name>Way of the Kensei: Kensei Weapons</name>
        <text>   Choose two types of weapons to be your kensei weapons: one melee weapon and one ranged weapon. Each of these weapons can be any simple or martial weapon that lacks the heavy and special properties. The longbow is also a valid choice. You gain proficiency with these weapons if you don't already have it. Weapons of the chosen types are monk weapons for you. Many of this tradition's features work only with your kensei weapons. When you reach 6th, 11th, and 17th level in this class, you can choose another type of weapon—either melee or ranged—to be a kensei weapon for you, following the criteria above.</text>
        <name>Way of the Kensei: Way of the Brush</name>
        <text>   You gain proficiency with your choice of calligrapher's supplies or painter's supplies.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 34</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei: Agile Parry</name>
        <text>If you make an unarmed strike as part of the Attack action on your turn and are holding a kensei weapon, you can use it to defend yourself if it is a melee weapon. You gain a +2 bonus to AC until the start of your next turn, while the weapon is in your hand and you aren't incapacitated.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 34</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei: Kensei's Shot</name>
        <text>You can use a bonus action on your turn to make your ranged attacks with a kensei weapon more deadly. When you do so, any target you hit with a ranged attack using a kensei weapon takes an extra 1d4 damage of the weapon's type. You retain this benefit until the end of the current turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 34</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monastic Tradition: Way of the Sun Soul</name>
        <text>Monks of the Way of the Sun Soul learn to channel their life energy into searing bolts of light. They teach that meditation can unlock the ability to unleash the indomitable light shed by the soul of every living creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 35</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Radiant Sun Bolt</name>
        <text>Starting when you choose this tradition at 3rd level, you can hurl searing bolts of magical radiance.</text>
        <text>You gain a new attack option that you can use with the Attack action. This special attack is a ranged spell attack with a range of 30 feet. You are proficient with it, and you add your Dexterity modifier to its attack and damage rolls. Its damage is radiant, and its damage die is a d4. This die changes as you gain monk levels, as shown in the Martial Arts column of the Monk table.</text>
        <text>When you take the Attack action on your turn and use this special attack as part of it, you can spend 1 ki point to make the special attack twice as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>When you gain the Extra Attack feature, this special attack can be used for any of the attacks you make as part of the Attack action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 35</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Drunken Master: Tipsy Sway</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you can move in sudden, swaying ways. You gain the following benefits.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 33</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Drunken Master: Leap to Your Feet</name>
        <text>When you're prone, you can stand up by spending 5 feet of movement, rather than half your speed.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 33</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Drunken Master: Redirect Attack</name>
        <text>When a creature misses you with a melee attack roll, you can spend 1 ki point as a reaction to cause that attack to hit one creature of your choice, other than the attacker, that you can see within 5 feet of you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 33</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei: One with the Blade</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you extend your ki into your kensei weapons, granting you the following benefits.</text>
        <name>Way of the Kensei: Magic Kensei Weapons</name>
        <text>   Your attacks with your kensei weapons count as magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage.</text>
        <name>Way of the Kensei: Deft Strike</name>
        <text>   When you hit a target with a kensei weapon, you can spend 1 ki point to cause the weapon to deal extra damage to the target equal to your Martial Arts die. You can use this feature only once on each of your turns.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 34</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Searing Arc Strike</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to channel your ki into searing waves of energy. Immediately after you take the Attack action on your turn, you can spend 2 ki points to cast the burning hands spell as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>You can spend additional ki points to cast burning hands as a higher-level spell. Each additional ki point you spend increases the spell's level by 1. The maximum number of ki points (2 plus any additional points) that you can spend on the spell equals half your monk level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 35</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Drunken Master: Drunkard's Luck</name>
        <text>Starting at 11th level, you always seem to get a lucky bounce at the right moment. When you make an ability check, an attack roll, or a saving throw and have disadvantage on the roll, you can spend 2 ki points to cancel the disadvantage for that roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 33</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei: Sharpen the Blade</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to augment your weapons further with your ki. As a bonus action, you can expend up to 3 ki points to grant one kensei weapon you touch a bonus to attack and damage rolls when you attack with it. The bonus equals the number of ki points you spent. This bonus lasts for 1 minute or until you use this feature again. This feature has no effect on a magic weapon that already has a bonus to attack and damage rolls.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 34</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Searing Sunburst</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to create an orb of light that erupts into a devastating explosion. As an action, you magically create an orb and hurl it at a point you choose within 150 feet, where it erupts into a sphere of radiant light for a brief but deadly instant.</text>
        <text>Each creature in that 20-foot-radius sphere must succeed on a Constitution saving throw or take 2d6 radiant damage. A creature doesn't need to make the save if the creature is behind total cover that is opaque.</text>
        <text>You can increase the sphere's damage by spending ki points. Each point you spend, to a maximum of 3, increases the damage by 2d6.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 35</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Drunken Master: Intoxicated Frenzy</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you gain the ability to make an overwhelming number of attacks against a group of enemies. When you use your Flurry of Blows, you can make up to three additional attacks with it (up to a total of five Flurry of Blows attacks), provided that each Flurry of Blows attack targets a different creature this turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 33</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei: Unerring Accuracy</name>
        <text>At 17th level, your mastery of weapons grants you extraordinary accuracy. If you miss with an attack roll using a monk weapon on your turn, you can reroll it. You can use this feature only once on each of your turns.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 34</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Sun Soul: Sun Shield</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you become wreathed in a luminous, magical aura. You shed bright light in a 30-foot radius and dim light for an additional 30 feet. You can extinguish or restore the light as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>If a creature hits you with a melee attack while this light shines, you can use your reaction to deal radiant damage to the creature. The radiant damage equals 5 + your Wisdom modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 35</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
