<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Aspect of the Moon</name>
    <prerequisite>Pact of the Tome</prerequisite>
    <text>You no longer need to sleep and can't be forced to sleep by any means. To gain the benefits of a long rest, you can spend all 8 hours doing light activity, such as reading your Book of Shadows and keeping watch.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 56</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Arcane Shot: Banishing Arrow</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You use abjuration magic to try to temporarily banish your target to a harmless location in the Feywild. The creature hit by the arrow must also succeed on a Charisma saving throw or be banished. While banished in this way, the target's speed is 0, and it is incapacitated. At the end of its next turn, the target reappears in the space it vacated or in the nearest unoccupied space if that space is occupied.
After you reach 18th level in this class, a target also takes 2d6 force damage when the arrow hits it.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 29</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Arcane Shot: Beguiling Arrow</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Your enchantment magic causes this arrow to temporarily beguile its target. The creature hit by the arrow takes an extra 2d6 psychic damage, and choose one of your allies within 30 feet of the target. The target must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw, or it is charmed by the chosen ally until the start of your next turn. This effect ends early if the chosen ally attacks the charmed target, deals damage to it, or forces it to make a saving throw.
The psychic damage increases to 4d6 when you reach 18th level in this class.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 29</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Arcane Shot: Bursting Arrow</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You imbue your arrow with force energy drawn from the school of evocation. The energy detonates after your attack. Immediately after the arrow hits the creature, the target and all other creatures within 10 feet of it take 2d6 force damage each.
The force damage increases to 4d6 when you reach 18th level in this class.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 29</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Cloak of Flies</name>
    <prerequisite>5th level</prerequisite>
    <text>As a bonus action, you can surround yourself with a magical aura that looks like buzzing flies. The aura extends 5 feet from you in every direction, but not through total cover. It lasts until you're incapacitated or you dismiss it as a bonus action.
The aura grants you advantage on Charisma (Intimidation) checks but disadvantage on all other Charisma checks. Any other creature that starts its turn in the aura takes poison damage equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of 0 damage).
Once you use this invocation, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 56</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Eldritch Smite</name>
    <prerequisite>5th level, Pact of the Blade</prerequisite>
    <text>Once per turn when you hit a creature with your pact weapon, you can expend a warlock spell slot to deal an extra 1d8 force damage to the target, plus another 1d8 per level of the spell slot, and you can knock the target prone if it is Huge or smaller.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 56</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Arcane Shot: Enfeebling Arrow</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You weave necromantic magic into your arrow. The creature hit by the arrow takes an extra 2d6 necrotic damage. The target must also succeed on a Constitution saving throw, or the damage dealt by its weapon attacks is halved until the start of your next turn.
The necrotic damage increases to 4d6 when you reach 18th level in this class.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 29</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Ghostly Gaze</name>
    <prerequisite>7th level</prerequisite>
    <text>As an action, you gain the ability to see through solid objects to a range of 30 feet. Within that range, you have darkvision if you don't already have it. This special sight lasts for 1 minute or until your concentration ends (as if you were concentrating on a spell). During that time, you perceive objects as ghostly, transparent images.
Once you use this invocation, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 56</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Gift of the Depths</name>
    <prerequisite>5th level</prerequisite>
    <text>You can breathe underwater, and you gain a swimming speed equal to your walking speed.
You can also cast water breathing once without expending a spell slot. You regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 57</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Gift of the Ever-Living Ones</name>
    <prerequisite>Pact of the Chain</prerequisite>
    <text>Whenever you regain hit points while your familiar is within 100 feet of you, treat any dice rolled to determine the hit points you regain as having rolled their maximum value for you.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 57</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Grasp of Hadar</name>
    <prerequisite>Eldritch Blast cantrip</prerequisite>
    <text>Once on each of your turns when you hit a creature with your eldritch blast, you can move that creature in a straight line 10 feet closer to you.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 57</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Arcane Shot: Grasping Arrow</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>When this arrow strikes its target, conjuration magic creates grasping, poisonous brambles, which wrap around the target. The creature hit by the arrow takes an extra 2d6 poison damage, its speed is reduced by 10 feet, and it takes 2d6 slashing damage the first time on each turn it moves 1 foot or more without teleporting. The target or any creature that can reach it can use its action to remove the brambles with a successful Strength (Athletics) check against your Arcane Shot save DC. Otherwise, the brambles last for 1 minute or until you use this option again.
The poison damage and slashing damage both increase to 4d6 when you reach 18th level in this class.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 29</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Improved Pact Weapon</name>
    <prerequisite>Pact of the Blade</prerequisite>
    <text>You can use any weapon you summon with your Pact of the Blade feature as a spellcasting focus for your warlock spells.
In addition, the weapon gains a +1 bonus to its attack and damage rolls, unless it is a magic weapon that already has a bonus to those rolls.
Finally, the weapon you conjure can be a shortbow, longbow, light crossbow, or heavy crossbow.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 57</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Lance of Lethargy</name>
    <prerequisite>Eldritch Blast cantrip</prerequisite>
    <text>Once on each of your turns when you hit a creature with your eldritch blast, you can reduce that creature's speed by 10 feet until the end of your next turn.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 57</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Maddening Hex</name>
    <prerequisite>The ability to cast Hex/Curse#X, 5th level</prerequisite>
    <text>As a bonus action, you cause a psychic disturbance around the target cursed by your hex spell or by a warlock feature of yours, such as Hexblade's Curse or Sign of Ill Omen. When you do so, you deal psychic damage to the cursed target and each creature of your choice that you can see within 5 feet of it. The psychic damage equals your Charisma modifier (minimum of 1 damage). To use this invocation, you must be able to see the cursed target, and it must be within 30 feet of you.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 57</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Arcane Shot: Piercing Arrow</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You use transmutation magic to give your arrow an ethereal quality. When you use this option, you don't make an attack roll for the attack. Instead, the arrow shoots forward in a line, which is 1 foot wide and 30 feet long, before disappearing. The arrow passes harmlessly through objects, ignoring cover. Each creature in that line must make a Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes damage as if it were hit by the arrow, plus an extra 1d6 piercing damage. On a successful save, a target takes half as much damage.
The piercing damage increases to 2d6 when you reach 18th level in this class.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 29</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Relentless Hex</name>
    <prerequisite>The ability to cast Hex/Curse#X, 7th level</prerequisite>
    <text>Your curse creates a temporary bond between you and your target. As a bonus action, you can magically teleport up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space you can see within 5 feet of the target cursed by your hex spell or by a warlock feature of yours, such as Hexblade's Curse or Sign of Ill Omen. To teleport in this way, you must be able to see the cursed target.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 57</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Arcane Shot: Seeking Arrow</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Using divination magic, you grant your arrow the ability to seek out a target. When you use this option, you don't make an attack roll for the attack. Instead, choose one creature you have seen in the past minute. The arrow flies toward that creature, moving around corners if necessary and ignoring three-quarters cover and half cover. If the target is within the weapon's range and there is a path large enough for the arrow to travel to the target, the target must make a Dexterity saving throw. Otherwise, the arrow disappears after traveling as far as it can. On a failed save, the target takes damage as if it were hit by the arrow, plus an extra 1d6 force damage, and you learn the target's current location. On a successful save, the target takes half as much damage, and you don't learn its location.
The force damage increases to 2d6 when you reach 18th level in this class.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 30</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Arcane Shot: Shadow Arrow</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>You weave illusion magic into your arrow, causing it to occlude your foe's vision with shadows. The creature hit by the arrow takes an extra 2d6 psychic damage, and it must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or be unable to see anything farther than 5 feet away until the start of your next turn.
The psychic damage increases to 4d6 when you reach 18th level in this class.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 30</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Shroud of Shadow</name>
    <prerequisite>15th level</prerequisite>
    <text>You can cast invisibility at will, without expending a spell slot.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 57</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Tomb of Levistus</name>
    <prerequisite>5th level</prerequisite>
    <text>As a reaction when you take damage, you can entomb yourself in ice, which melts away at the end of your next turn. You gain 10 temporary hit points per warlock level, which take as much of the triggering damage as possible. Immediately after you take the damage, you gain vulnerability to fire damage, your speed is reduced to 0, and you are incapacitated. These effects, including any remaining temporary hit points, all end when the ice melts.
Once you use this invocation, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 57</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Trickster's Escape</name>
    <prerequisite>7th level</prerequisite>
    <text>You can cast freedom of movement once on yourself without expending a spell slot. You regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest.
Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 57</text>
    </feat>
  </compendium>
