<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Bard</name>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Eloquence (UA): College of Eloquence</name>
        <text>Adherents of the College of Eloquence master the art of oratory. Persuasion is regarded as a high art, and a well-reasoned, well-spoken argument often proves more powerful than objective truth. These bards wield a blend of logic and theatrical wordplay, winning over skeptics and detractors with logical arguments, and plucking at heartstrings to appeal to the emotions of entire audiences.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Bard And Paladin p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Eloquence (UA): Soothing Words</name>
        <text>3rd-level College of Eloquence feature</text>
        <text>You can now cast calm emotions without expending a spell slot. You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Charisma modifier. You regain all expended uses of this feature when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Bard And Paladin p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Eloquence (UA): Universal Speech</name>
        <text>3rd-level College of Eloquence feature</text>
        <text>You have gained the ability to speak and reason with any creature. As a bonus action, you can expend one of your uses of Bardic Inspiration. When you do so, roll your Bardic Inspiration die, and choose a number of creatures within 60 feet of you that you can see equal to the roll. For 10 minutes, the chosen creatures can magically understand you, regardless of the language you speak, and you have advantage on Charisma checks made to influence them. This feature works even on a creature that doesn't speak any languages.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Bard And Paladin p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Eloquence (UA): Undeniable Logic</name>
        <text>6th-level College of Eloquence feature</text>
        <text>You can spin words laced with magic into a knot of reasoning that can be encouraging or impossible to follow.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, you can expend one of your uses of Bardic Inspiration. When you do so, choose a creature you can see within 60 of you that can hear you, then roll your Bardic Inspiration die and choose one of the following:</text>
        <text>• The creature takes psychic damage equal to the number you roll on the Bardic Inspiration die, and the creature must succeed on an Intelligence saving throw against your spell save DC or have disadvantage on the next saving throw it makes before the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text>• The creature regains hit points equal to the number you roll on the Bardic Inspiration die, and the creature has advantage on the next saving throw it makes before the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Bard And Paladin p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Eloquence (UA): Infectious Inspiration</name>
        <text>14th-level College of Eloquence feature</text>
        <text>When a creature adds one of your Bardic Inspiration dice to its ability check, attack roll, or saving throw and the roll fails, the creature can keep the Bardic Inspiration die.</text>
        <text>In addition, when a creature adds one of your Bardic Inspiration dice to its ability check, attack roll, or saving throw and the roll succeeds, you can use your reaction to encourage a different creature (other than yourself) that can hear you within 60 feet of you, giving it a Bardic Inspiration die without expending any of your Bardic Inspiration uses. You can use this reaction a number of times equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Bard And Paladin p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
