<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Monk</name>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei v2 (UA): Way of the Kensei v2</name>
        <text>Monks of the Way of Kensei train relentlessly with their weapons, to the point that the weapon becomes like an extension of the body. A kensei sees a weapon in much the same way a painter regards a brush or a writer sees parchment, ink, and quill. A sword or bow is a tool used to express the beauty and elegance of the martial arts. That such mastery makes a kensei a peerless warrior is but a side effect of intense devotion, practice, and study.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei v2 (UA): Path of the Kensei</name>
        <text>When you choose this tradition at 3rd level, you learn to extend your knowledge of the martial arts beyond the standard array of monk weapons.</text>
        <text>You gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• Choose two types of weapons to be your kensei weapons: one melee weapon and one ranged weapon. Each of these weapons can be any simple or martial weapon that lacks the heavy and special properties. The longbow is also a valid choice. You gain proficiency with these weapons if you don't already have it. Weapons of the chosen types are monk weapons for you. Many of this tradition's features work only with your kensei weapons. When you reach 6th, 11th, and 17th level in this class, you can choose another type of weapon—melee or ranged—to be a kensei weapon for you, following the criteria above.</text>
        <text>• If you make an unarmed strike as part of the Attack action on your turn and are holding a kensei weapon, you can use it to defend yourself if it is a melee weapon. You gain a +2 bonus to AC until the start of your next turn, while the weapon is in your hand and you aren't incapacitated.</text>
        <text>• You can use a bonus action on your turn to make your ranged attacks with a kensei weapon more deadly. When you do so, any target you hit with a ranged attack using a kensei weapon takes an extra 1d4 damage of the weapon's type. You retain this benefit until the end of the current turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei v2 (UA): One with the Blade</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you extend your ki into the weapons you hold, granting you the following benefits.</text>
        <name>Way of the Kensei v2 (UA): Magic Kensei Weapons</name>
        <text>   Your attacks with your kensei weapons count as magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage.</text>
        <name>Way of the Kensei v2 (UA): Precise Strike</name>
        <text>   When you hit a target with a kensei weapon, you can spend 1 ki point to cause the weapon to deal extra damage to the target equal to your Martial Arts die. You can use this feature only once on each of your turns.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei v2 (UA): Sharpen the Blade</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to augment your weapons with the strength of your ki. As a bonus action, you can expend up to 3 ki points to grant one kensei weapon you touch a bonus to attack and damage rolls while you wield it. The bonus equals the number of ki points you spent. This bonus lasts for 1 minute or until you use this feature again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Kensei v2 (UA): Unerring Accuracy</name>
        <text>At 17th level, your mastery of weapons grants you extraordinary accuracy. If you make an attack roll with a monk weapon and miss, you can reroll it. You can use this feature only once on each of your turns.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
