<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Warlock</name>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Noble Genie (UA): The Noble Genie</name>
        <text>You made a pact with one of the rarest of geniekind, a noble genie. Such entities are rulers of vast fiefs on the Elemental Planes and have great influence over lesser genies and elemental creatures. Noble genies are varied in their motivations but are all arrogant collectors of creatures, knowledge, and treasure. A genie values their collection and will protect that which they claim ownership over. Through your connection to the noble, you can leverage their influence and extend their ownership of things in the multiverse.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Expanded Spell List</text>
        <text>   1st-level Noble Genie feature</text>
        <text>   The Noble Genie lets you choose from an expanded list of spells when you learn a warlock spell. The following spells are added to the warlock spell list for you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Noble Genie Expanded Spells</text>
        <text>Spell Level | Spells</text>
        <text>1st | fog cloud, sleep</text>
        <text>2nd | enlarge/reduce, phantasmal force</text>
        <text>3rd | create food and water, protection from energy</text>
        <text>4th | polymorph, phantasmal killer</text>
        <text>5th | Bigby's hand, creation</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt1 p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Noble Genie (UA): Collector's Vessel</name>
        <text>1st-level Noble Genie feature</text>
        <text>Your patron gives you a magical vessel with which you can bind a creature to you and to your patron's menagerie. The vessel is a Tiny object, and it is a spellcasting focus for you. You decide what the object is, or you can determine what it is randomly by rolling on the Collector's Vessel table.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Collector's Vessel</text>
        <text>d6 | Vessel</text>
        <text>1 | Oil lamp</text>
        <text>2 | Urn</text>
        <text>3 | Ring with a compartment</text>
        <text>4 | Stoppered bottle</text>
        <text>5 | Hollow statuette</text>
        <text>6 | Ornate lantern</text>
        <text>If you lose your vessel, you can perform a 1 hour ceremony to receive a replacement from your patron. This ceremony can be performed during a short or long rest, and it destroys the previous vessel. The vessel vanishes in a flare of elemental power when you die.</text>
        <text>As an action while you are holding the vessel, you target a willing creature you can see within 100 feet of you and create a tether of wispy elemental material that links the target to you. The tether lasts for 1 hour, until you use this feature to create another tether, until the bound target is reduced to 0 hit points, or until the target ends its turn more than 100 feet from you.</text>
        <text>While you are tethered to a creature, you gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• You gain a bonus to your Wisdom (Perception) checks equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of +1).</text>
        <text>• When you can cast a spell, you can deliver the spell from your space or the bound creature's space.</text>
        <text>You can create the tether a number of times equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Collector's Vessel and Pact Boons</text>
        <text>   When you create a tether with your Collector's Vessel, the tether takes on a form that reflects your patron's type of geniekind: swirling mist and wind for a djinni, sand and flecks of rock or gems for a dao, smoke and embers for an efreeti, and foamy water for a marid.</text>
        <text>   When you gain the Pact Boon feature at 3rd level, if you choose a boon that grants you a physical object, your vessel transforms into that object. For example, a warlock whose patron is a noble efreeti and chooses the Pact of the Tome might find their bottle transformed into an elaborate scroll made of a red dragon's wing, with brass and iron rolling rods.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt1 p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Noble Genie (UA): Elemental Resistance</name>
        <text>6th-level Noble Genie feature</text>
        <text>Your patron grants you protection from an element. Whenever you finish a long rest, you gain resistance to acid, cold, fire, or lightning damage (your choice) until the end of your next long rest.</text>
        <text>While the tether of your Collector's Vessel is active, the tethered creature gains resistance to the damage type you chose.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt1 p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Noble Genie (UA): Genie's Entertainment</name>
        <text>10th-level Noble Genie feature</text>
        <text>As an action, you attempt to send a creature you can see within 90 feet to your patron's court. The target must succeed on a Charisma saving throw against your warlock spell save DC or be magically drawn into your vessel and teleported to your patron's court in the Elemental Planes. While there, the target is stunned and your patron marvels at the target with amusement but brings no harm to it. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, reappearing in the space it left or in the nearest unoccupied space if that space is occupied on a success.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest. If the target remains in your patron's court for 1 minute, the genie sends the target back at the end of its turn as if it successfully saved, and you regain the use of this feature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt1 p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Noble Genie (UA): Protective Wish</name>
        <text>10th-level Noble Genie feature</text>
        <text>You're now able to use your Collector's Vessel to wish for protection for yourself or your tethered creature. If you or the tethered creature is hit by an attack, you can use your reaction to teleport, swapping places with the creature and switching which one of you is hit by the attack.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt1 p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Noble Genie (UA): Collector's Call</name>
        <text>14th-level Noble Genie feature</text>
        <text>In exchange for extending your patron's influence over the multiverse, you can call on more of their power. As an action, you can implore your patron for aid by making a Charisma (Persuasion) check against your warlock spell save DC. If the check succeeds, you can choose one of the following effects:</text>
        <text>• A creature you can see within 60 feet of you regains 8d6 hit points and ends one disease or condition afflicting it: blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, paralyzed, or poisoned.</text>
        <text>• A creature you can see within 60 feet of you has disadvantage on attack rolls and saving throws until the start of your next turn.</text>
        <text>• You cast the legend lore spell without material components.</text>
        <text>Whether the check succeeds or fails, you can't use this feature again until you finish a long rest. Alternatively, you can regain the use of this feature by sacrificing nonmagical treasure worth at least 500 gp to your patron. This sacrifice requires the treasure to be within 10 feet of you for at least 1 minute, at the end of which you use an action to teleport the treasure to your patron's realm, provided you have the vessel of your Collector's Vessel in hand.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt1 p. 4</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
