<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Cleric</name>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Divine Domain: City Domain (UA)</name>
        <text>The City domain is concerned with the citizenry, commerce, traffic, and even architecture of modern civilization. In the eyes of a cleric of the city, the center of modern life is a sense and spirit of community, and the gravest enemies of the city are those who seek to harm the common weal of its citizens.</text>
        <text>At each indicated cleric level, add the listed spells to your spells prepared. They do not count towards your limit.</text>
        <text>Spells marked with an asterisk can be found in Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>City Domain Spells</text>
        <text>Cleric Level | Spells</text>
        <text>1st | comprehend languages, remote access (UA)*</text>
        <text>3rd | find vehicle (UA)*, heat metal</text>
        <text>5th | lightning bolt, protection from ballistics (UA)*</text>
        <text>7th | locate creature, synchronicity (UA)*</text>
        <text>9th | commune with city (UA)*, shutdown (UA)*</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>City Domain (UA): Bonus Cantrip</name>
        <text>When you choose this domain at 1st level, you gain the On/Off (UA) cantrip in addition to your chosen cantrips.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>City Domain (UA): Bonus Proficiencies</name>
        <text>Also starting at 1st level, you gain proficiency with sidearms and proficiency with vehicles (land).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>City Domain (UA): Heart of the City</name>
        <text>From 1st level, you are able to tap into the spirit of community found in the city. While you are within any city, you can gain advantage on a single Charisma (Deception, Intimidation, or Persuasion) check, and you are considered proficient in the appropriate skill. You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (a minimum of once). You regain any expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>City Domain (UA): Channel Divinity: Spirits of the City</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can use your Channel Divinity to call on the city for aid. As an action, you present your holy symbol, and any city utility within 30 feet of you either works perfectly or shuts down entirely for 1 minute (your choice).</text>
        <text>Additionally, each hostile creature within 30 feet of you must make a Charisma saving throw. On a failed save, the creature is knocked prone or restrained (your choice) by hazards such as entangling wires, high-pressure water erupting from fire hydrants, pavement collapsing to unseen potholes, and so on. A restrained creature can escape by making a successful Strength (Athletics) or Dexterity (Acrobatics) check against your spell save DC.</text>
        <text>This effect is entirely local and affects only utilities within 30 feet of you. Determination of what utilities are available within range and how the physical effects of those utilities manifest are left to the DM.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>City Domain (UA): Block Watch</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, your awareness while in the city extends preternaturally. While in an urban environment, you are considered proficient in the Insight and Perception skills, and you add double your proficiency bonus to Wisdom (Insight) and Wisdom (Perception) checks, instead of your normal proficiency bonus.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>City Domain (UA): Divine Strike</name>
        <text>At 8th level, you gain the ability to infuse your weapon strikes with psychic energy borrowed from the citizens of your city. Once on each of your turns when you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can cause the attack to deal an extra 1d8 psychic damage to the target. When you reach 14th level, the extra psychic damage increases to 2d8.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>City Domain (UA): Express Transit</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you can use mass transit routes to transport instantaneously to other points in the city. Starting from a bus stop, train station, subway stop, or other suitable mass transit site within the city, you can teleport to any other similar transit stop within the city, as if you had cast a teleport spell whose destination is a permanent teleportation circle you know. Once you use this feature, you must finish a short or long rest before using it again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
