<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Ranger (Spell-less) (UA)</name>
    <hd>10</hd>
    <proficiency>Strength, Dexterity, Animal Handling, Athletics, Insight, Investigation, Nature, Perception, Stealth, Survival</proficiency>
    <numSkills>3</numSkills>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Starting Ranger (Spell-less) (UA)</name>
        <text>As a 1st-level Ranger (Spell-less) (UA), you begin play with 10+your Constitution modifier hit points.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>You are proficient with the following items, in addition to any proficiencies provided by your race or background.</text>
        <text>• Armor: light, medium, shields</text>
        <text>• Weapons: simple, martial</text>
        <text>• Tools: none</text>
        <text>• Skills: Choose 3 from Animal Handling, Athletics, Insight, Investigation, Nature, Perception, Stealth, Survival</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>You begin play with the following equipment, in addition to any equipment provided by your background.</text>
        <text>• (a) scale mail or (b) leather armor</text>
        <text>• (a) two shortsword or (b) two simple melee weapons</text>
        <text>• (a) a dungeoneer's pack or (b) an explorer's pack</text>
        <text>• A longbow and a quiver of arrows (20)</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Alternatively, you may start with 5d4 x 10 gp and choose your own equipment.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <armor>light, medium, shields</armor>
    <weapons>simple, martial</weapons>
    <tools>none</tools>
    <wealth>5d4x10</wealth>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Favored Enemy</name>
        <text>Beginning at 1st level, you have significant experience studying, tracking, hunting, and even talking to a certain type of enemy.</text>
        <text>Choose a type of favored enemy: aberrations, beasts, celestials, constructs, dragons, elementals, fey, fiends, giants, monstrosities, oozes, plants, or undead. Alternatively, you can select two races of humanoid (such as gnoll and orc) as favored enemies.</text>
        <text>You have advantage on Wisdom (Survival) checks to track your favored enemies, as well as on Intelligence checks to recall information about them.</text>
        <text>When you gain this feature, you also learn one language of your choice that is spoken by your favored enemies, if they speak one at all.</text>
        <text>You choose one additional favored enemy, as well as an associated language, at 6th and 14th level. As you gain levels, your choices should reflect the types of monsters you have encountered on your adventures.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Favored Foe</name>
        <text>1st-level ranger feature (replaces Favored Enemy)</text>
        <text>Note that this feature is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger feature.</text>
        <text>You can call on your bond with nature to mark a creature as your favored enemy for a time: you know the hunter's mark spell, and Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for it. You can use it a certain number of times without expending a spell slot and without requiring concentration—a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (a minimum of once). You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>When you gain the Spellcasting feature at 2nd level, hunter's mark doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 7</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Favored Foe</name>
        <text>1st-level ranger optional class features, which replaces the Favored Enemy feature and works with the Foe Slayer feature</text>
        <text>Note that this feature is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger feature.</text>
        <text>When you hit a creature with an attack roll, you can call on your mystical bond with nature to mark the target as your favored enemy for 1 minute or until you lose your concentration (as if you were concentrating on a spell).</text>
        <text>The first time on each of your turns that you hit the favored enemy and deal damage to it, including when you mark it, you can increase that damage by 1d4.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature to mark a favored enemy a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>This feature's extra damage increases when you reach certain levels in this class: to 1d6 at 6th level and to 1d8 at 14th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Natural Explorer</name>
        <text>You are particularly familiar with one type of natural environment and are adept at traveling and surviving in such regions. Choose one type of favored terrain: arctic, coast, desert, forest, grassland, mountain, swamp, or the Underdark. When you make an Intelligence or Wisdom check related to your favored terrain, your proficiency bonus is doubled if you are using a skill that you're proficient in.</text>
        <text>While traveling for an hour or more in your favored terrain, you gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• Difficult terrain doesn't slow your group's travel.</text>
        <text>• Your group can't become lost except by magical means.</text>
        <text>• Even when you are engaged in another activity while traveling (such as foraging, navigating, or tracking), you remain alert to danger.</text>
        <text>• If you are traveling alone, you can move stealthily at a normal pace.</text>
        <text>• When you forage, you find twice as much food as you normally would.</text>
        <text>• While tracking other creatures, you also learn their exact number, their sizes, and how long ago they passed through the area.</text>
        <text>You choose additional favored terrain types at 6th and 10th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Deft Explorer</name>
        <text>1st-level ranger feature (replaces Natural Explorer)</text>
        <text>Note that this feature is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger feature.</text>
        <text>You are an unsurpassed explorer and survivor. Choose one of the following benefits, and then choose another one at 6th and 10th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 7</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Deft Explorer: Canny</name>
        <text>Choose one skill: Animal Handling, Athletics, History, Insight, Investigation, Medicine, Nature, Perception, Stealth, or Survival. You gain proficiency in the chosen skill if you don't already have it, and you can add double your proficiency bonus to ability checks using that skill.</text>
        <text>In addition, thanks to your extensive wandering, you are able to speak, read, and write two languages of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 7</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Deft Explorer: Roving</name>
        <text>Your walking speed increases by 5, and you gain a climbing speed and a swimming speed equal to your walking speed.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 7</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Deft Explorer: Tireless</name>
        <text>As an action, you can give yourself a number of temporary hit points equal to 1d10 + your Wisdom modifier. You can use this special action a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (a minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>In addition, whenever you finish a short rest, your exhaustion level, if any, is decreased by 1.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 7</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature>
          <name>Deft Explorer</name>
        <text>1st-level ranger optional class features, which replaces the Natural Explorer feature</text>
        <text>Note that this feature is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger feature.</text>
        <text>You are an unsurpassed explorer and survivor, both in the wilderness and in dealing with others on your travels. You gain the Canny benefit below, and you gain an additional benefit below when you reach 6th level and 10th level in this class.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Deft Explorer: Canny</name>
        <text>You are an unsurpassed explorer and survivor, both in the wilderness and in dealing with others on your travels. You gain the Canny benefit below, and you gain an additional benefit below when you reach 6th level and 10th level in this class.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Deft Explorer: Roving</name>
        <text>Choose one of your skill proficiencies. Your proficiency bonus is doubled for any ability check you make that uses the chosen skill.</text>
        <text>You can also speak, read, and write two additional languages of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Deft Explorer: Tireless</name>
        <text>As an action, you can give yourself a number of temporary hit points equal to 1d8 + your Wisdom modifier (minimum of 1 temporary hit point). You can use this action a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>In addition, whenever you finish a short rest, your exhaustion level, if any, is decreased by 1.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature>
          <name>Fighting Style</name>
        <text>At 2nd level, you adopt a particular style of fighting as your specialty. Choose one of the following options. You can't take a Fighting Style option more than once, even if you later get to choose again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Archery</name>
        <text>You gain a +2 bonus to attack rolls you make with ranged weapons.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Close Quarters Shooter</name>
        <text>When making a ranged attack while you are within 5 feet of a hostile creature, you do not have disadvantage on the attack roll. Your ranged attacks ignore half cover and three-quarters cover against targets within 30 feet of you. You have a +1 bonus to attack rolls on ranged attacks.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Defense</name>
        <text>While you are wearing armor, you gain a +1 bonus to AC.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Dueling</name>
        <text>When you are wielding a melee weapon in one hand and no other weapons, you gain a +2 bonus to damage rolls with that weapon.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Mariner</name>
        <text>As long as you are not wearing heavy armor or using a shield, you have a swimming speed and a climbing speed equal to your normal speed, and you gain a +1 bonus to AC.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Waterborne Adventures p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Tunnel Fighter</name>
        <text>As a bonus action, you can enter a defensive stance that lasts until the start of your next turn. While in your defensive stance, you can make opportunity attacks without using your reaction, and you can use your reaction to make a melee attack against a creature that moves more than 5 feet while within your reach.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Two-Weapon Fighting</name>
        <text>When you engage in two-weapon fighting, you can add your ability modifier to the damage of the second attack.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Blind Fighting</name>
        <text>Being unable to see a creature doesn't impose disadvantage on your attack rolls against it, provided the creature isn't hidden from you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Interception</name>
        <text>When a creature you can see hits a target that is within 5 feet of you with an attack, you can use your reaction to reduce the damage the target takes by 1d10 + your proficiency bonus (to a minimum of 0 damage). You must be wielding a shield or a simple or martial weapon to use this reaction.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Thrown Weapon Fighting</name>
        <text>You can draw a weapon that has the thrown property as part of the attack you make with the weapon.</text>
        <text>In addition, when you hit with a ranged attack using a thrown weapon, you gain a +1 bonus to the damage roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Unarmed Fighting</name>
        <text>Your unarmed strikes can deal bludgeoning damage equal to 1d6 + your Strength modifier. If you strike with two free hands, the d6 becomes a d8.</text>
        <text>When you successfully start a grapple, you can deal 1d4 bludgeoning damage to the grappled creature. Until the grapple ends, you can also deal this damage to the creature whenever you hit it with a melee attack.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Druidic Warrior</name>
        <text>You learn two cantrips of your choice from the druid spell list. They count as druid spells for you, and Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for them. Whenever you gain a level in this class, you can replace one of these cantrips with another cantrip from the druid spell list.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Blind Fighting</name>
        <text>You have blindsight with a range of 10 feet. Within that range, you can effectively see anything that isn't behind total cover, even if you're blinded or in darkness. Moreover, you can see an invisible creature within that range, unless the creature successfully hides from you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Druidic Warrior</name>
        <text>You learn two cantrips of your choice from the druid spell list. They count as ranger spells for you, and Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for them. Whenever you gain a level in this class, you can replace one of these cantrips with another cantrip from the druid spell list.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fighting Style: Thrown Weapon Fighting</name>
        <text>You can draw a weapon that has the thrown property as part of the attack you make with the weapon.</text>
        <text>In addition, when you hit with a ranged attack using a thrown weapon, you gain a +2 bonus to the damage roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature>
          <name>Martial Versatility</name>
        <text>2nd-level feature (enhances Fighting Style)</text>
        <text>Note that this feature is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger feature.</text>
        <text>Whenever you gain a level in this class, you can replace a fighting style you know with another style available to your class. This change represents a shift of focus in your martial training and practice, causing you to lose the benefits of one style and gain the benefits of another style.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 12</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature>
          <name>Combat Superiority</name>
        <text>At 2nd level, you learn maneuvers that are fueled by special dice called superiority dice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Maneuvers:</text>
        <text>   You learn two maneuvers of your choice, which are chosen from the list of maneuvers available to fighters with the Battle Master archetype. Many maneuvers enhance an attack in some way. You can use only one maneuver per attack.</text>
        <text>   You learn one additional maneuver of your choice at 5th, 9th, 13th, and 17th levels. Each time you learn a new maneuver, you can also replace one maneuver you know with a different one.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Superiority Dice:</text>
        <text>   You have four superiority dice, which are d8s. A superiority die is expended when you use it. You regain all of your expended superiority dice when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>   You gain another superiority die at 9th level and one more at 17th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Saving Throws:</text>
        <text>   Some of your maneuvers require your target to make a saving throw to resist the maneuver's effects. The saving throw DC is calculated as follows:</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature>
          <name>Ranger Archetype</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you choose an archetype that you strive to emulate from the list of available archetypes. Your choice grants features at 3rd level, and again at 7th, 11th, and 15th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Beast Master</name>
        <text>The Beast Master archetype embodies a friendship between the civilized races and the beasts of the world. United in focus, beast and ranger work as one to fight the monstrous foes that threaten civilization and the wilderness alike. Emulating the Beast Master archetype means committing yourself to this ideal, working in partnership with an animal as its companion and friend.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Beast Master: Ranger's Companion</name>
        <text>You gain a beast companion that accompanies you on your adventures and is trained to fight alongside you. Choose a beast that is no larger than Medium and that has a challenge rating of 1/4 or lower. Add your proficiency bonus to the beast's AC, attack rolls, and damage rolls, as well as to any saving throws and skills it is proficient in. Its hit point maximum equals its normal maximum or four times your ranger level, whichever is higher. Like any creature, the beast can spend Hit Dice during a short rest.</text>
        <text>The beast obeys your commands as best as it can. It takes its turn on your initiative. On your turn, you can verbally command the beast where to move (no action required by you). You can use your action to verbally command it to take the Attack, Dash, Disengage, or Help action. If you don't issue a command, the beast takes the Dodge action. Once you have the Extra Attack feature, you can make one weapon attack yourself when you command the beast to take the Attack action.</text>
        <text>If you are incapacitated or absent, your beast companion acts on its own, focusing on protecting you and itself. It never requires your command to use its reaction, such as when making an opportunity attack.</text>
        <text>While traveling through your favored terrain with only the beast, you can move stealthily at a normal pace.</text>
        <text>If the beast dies, you can obtain another one by spending 8 hours magically bonding with another beast that isn't hostile to you, either the same type of beast as before or a different one.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Beast Master</name>
        <text>The Beast Master archetype embodies a friendship between the civilized races and the beasts of the world. United in focus, beast and ranger work as one to fight the monstrous foes that threaten civilization and the wilderness alike. Emulating the Beast Master archetype means committing yourself to this ideal, working in partnership with an animal as its companion and friend.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Beast Master: Ranger's Companion</name>
        <text>You gain a beast companion that accompanies you on your adventures and is trained to fight alongside you. Choose a beast that is no larger than Medium and that has a challenge rating of 1/4 or lower. Add your proficiency bonus to the beast's AC, attack rolls, and damage rolls, as well as to any saving throws and skills it is proficient in. Its hit point maximum equals its normal maximum or four times your ranger level, whichever is higher. Like any creature, the beast can spend Hit Dice during a short rest.</text>
        <text>The beast obeys your commands as best as it can. It takes its turn on your initiative. On your turn, you can verbally command the beast where to move (no action required by you). You can use your action to verbally command it to take the Attack, Dash, Disengage, or Help action. If you don't issue a command, the beast takes the Dodge action. Once you have the Extra Attack feature, you can make one weapon attack yourself when you command the beast to take the Attack action.</text>
        <text>If you are incapacitated or absent, the beast acts on its own, focusing on protecting you and itself. The beast never requires your command to use its reaction, such as when making an opportunity attack.</text>
        <text>While traveling through your favored terrain with only the beast, you can move stealthily at a normal pace.</text>
        <text>If the beast dies, you can obtain another one by spending 8 hours magically bonding with another beast that isn't hostile to you, either the same type of beast as before or a different one.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Hunter</name>
        <text>Emulating the Hunter archetype means accepting your place as a bulwark between civilization and the terrors of the wilderness. As you walk the Hunter's path, you learn specialized techniques for fighting the threats you face, from rampaging ogres and hordes of orcs to towering giants and terrifying dragons.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Horde Breaker</name>
        <text>Once on each of your turns when you make a weapon attack, you can make another attack with the same weapon against a different creature that is within 5 feet of the original target and within range of your weapon.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Hunter's Prey</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain one of the following features of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Colossus Slayer</name>
        <text>Your tenacity can wear down the most potent foes. When you hit a creature with a weapon attack, the creature takes an extra 1d8 damage if it's below its hit point maximum. You can deal this extra damage only once per turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Giant Killer</name>
        <text>When a Large or larger creature within 5 feet of you hits or misses you with an attack, you can use your reaction to attack that creature immediately after its attack, provided that you can see the creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Hunter</name>
        <text>Emulating the Hunter archetype means accepting your place as a bulwark between civilization and the terrors of the wilderness. As you walk the Hunter's path, you learn specialized techniques for fighting the threats you face, from rampaging ogres and hordes of orcs to towering giants and terrifying dragons.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Horde Breaker</name>
        <text>Once on each of your turns when you make a weapon attack, you can make another attack with the same weapon against a different creature that is within 5 feet of the original target and within range of your weapon.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Hunter's Prey</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain one of the following features of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Colossus Slayer</name>
        <text>Your tenacity can wear down the most potent foes. When you hit a creature with a weapon attack, the creature takes an extra 1d8 damage if it's below its hit point maximum. You can deal this extra damage only once per turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Giant Killer</name>
        <text>When a Large or larger creature within 5 feet of you hits or misses you with an attack, you can use your reaction to attack that creature immediately after its attack, provided that you can see the creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Deep Stalker (UA): Deep Stalker</name>
        <text>Many Deep Stalkers are elves, as those folk know all too well the threat posed by the drow. Deep Stalkers scout for new passages into the Underdark, carefully mapping them and working to ensure they remain watched at all times. They venture into the depths on long, dangerous patrols, disappearing for months at a time. Many of them never return. Deep Stalkers master spells useful in navigating the Underdark, and their combat tactics focus on ambush, surprise, and stealth. They fight alone or in small groups in hostile territory, relying on clever tactics to carry the day.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Deep Stalker (UA): Deep Stalker Magic</name>
        <text>From 3rd level, you have darkvision with a range of 90 feet. You also gain access to additional spells at 3rd, 5th, 9th, 13th, and 15th level. You are always able to cast these spells, and they do not count against your number of ranger spells known.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Deep Stalker Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | disguise self</text>
        <text>5th | rope trick</text>
        <text>9th | glyph of warding</text>
        <text>13th | greater invisibility</text>
        <text>17th | seeming</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Deep Stalker (UA): Underdark Scout</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you master the art of the ambush. On your first turn during combat, you gain a +10 bonus to your speed. If you use the attack action on that turn, you can make one additional attack. You gain an additional benefit on all turns after your first turn. At the end of each such turn, you can attempt to hide as a bonus action if you meet the normal requirements for hiding.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Deep Stalker (UA): Deep Stalker</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>Many Deep Stalkers are elves, as those folk know all too well the threat posed by the drow. Deep Stalkers scout for new passages into the Underdark, carefully mapping them and working to ensure they remain watched at all times. They venture into the depths on long, dangerous patrols, disappearing for months at a time. Many of them never return. Deep Stalkers master spells useful in navigating the Underdark, and their combat tactics focus on ambush, surprise, and stealth. They fight alone or in small groups in hostile territory, relying on clever tactics to carry the day.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Deep Stalker (UA): Underdark Scout</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you master the art of the ambush. On your first turn during combat, you gain a +10 bonus to your speed. If you use the attack action on that turn, you can make one additional attack. You gain an additional benefit on all turns after your first turn. At the end of each such turn, you can attempt to hide as a bonus action if you meet the normal requirements for hiding.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Horizon Walker</name>
        <text>Rangers of the Horizon Conclave guard the world against threats that originate from other planes. They seek out planar portals and keep watch over them, venturing to the outer and inner planes as needed to defeat threats.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Planar Magic</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Horizon Walker Spells table. The spell counts as a ranger spell for you, and it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Horizon Walker Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | protection from evil and good</text>
        <text>5th | alter self</text>
        <text>9th | protection from energy</text>
        <text>13th | banishment</text>
        <text>17th | teleportation circle</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Planar Warrior</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn to draw on the energy of the planes to augment your attacks.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of you. Until the end of this turn, your attacks against that creature ignore its damage resistances, and the next time you hit it on this turn, it takes an additional 1d6 force damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Portal Lore</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain the ability to detect the presence of planar portals. As an action, you detect the distance and direction to any planar portals within 1,000 feet of you. You also sense which plane of existence each portal leads to. However, if magic obscures any details of a portal, this feature doesn't reveal them.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest. Alternatively, you can use the feature again if you expend a spell slot of 2nd level or higher.</text>
        <text>See the "Planar Travel" section in chapter 2 of the Dungeon Master's Guide for examples of planar portals.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Horizon Walker</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>Rangers of the Horizon Conclave guard the world against threats that originate from other planes. They seek out planar portals and keep watch over them, venturing to the outer and inner planes as needed to defeat threats.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Planar Warrior</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn to draw on the energy of the planes to augment your attacks.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of you. Until the end of this turn, your attacks against that creature ignore its damage resistances, and the next time you hit it on this turn, it takes an additional 1d6 force damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Portal Lore</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain the ability to detect the presence of planar portals. As an action, you detect the distance and direction to any planar portals within 1,000 feet of you. You also sense which plane of existence each portal leads to. However, if magic obscures any details of a portal, this feature doesn't reveal them.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest. Alternatively, you can use the feature again if you expend a spell slot of 2nd level or higher.</text>
        <text>See the "Planar Travel" section in chapter 2 of the Dungeon Master's Guide for examples of planar portals.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Horizon Walker</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Revised Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>Rangers of the Horizon Conclave guard the world against threats that originate from other planes. They seek out planar portals and keep watch over them, venturing to the outer and inner planes as needed to defeat threats.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Planar Magic</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Horizon Walker Spells table. The spell counts as a ranger spell for you, and it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Horizon Walker Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | protection from evil and good</text>
        <text>5th | alter self</text>
        <text>9th | protection from energy</text>
        <text>13th | banishment</text>
        <text>17th | teleportation circle</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Planar Warrior</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn to draw on the energy of the planes to augment your attacks.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of you. Until the end of this turn, your attacks against that creature ignore its damage resistances, and the next time you hit it on this turn, it takes an additional 1d6 force damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Portal Lore</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain the ability to detect the presence of planar portals. As an action, you detect the distance and direction to any planar portals within 1,000 feet of you. You also sense which plane of existence each portal leads to. However, if magic obscures any details of a portal, this feature doesn't reveal them.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest. Alternatively, you can use the feature again if you expend a spell slot of 2nd level or higher.</text>
        <text>See the "Planar Travel" section in chapter 2 of the Dungeon Master's Guide for examples of planar portals.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Primeval Guardian</name>
        <text>Rangers of the Primeval Guardian Conclave follow an ancient tradition rooted in powerful druidic magic. These rangers learn to become one with nature, allowing them to channel the aspects of various beasts and plants in order to overcome their foes.</text>
        <text>These rangers dwell in the elder forests of the world. They venture out only rarely, as they consider it their sacred duty to protect the druidic groves and ancient trees that saw the earliest days of the world.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Guardian Magic</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Primeval Guardian Spells table. The spell counts as a ranger spell for you, and it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Primeval Guardian Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | entangle</text>
        <text>5th | enhance ability</text>
        <text>9th | conjure animals</text>
        <text>13th | giant insect</text>
        <text>17th | insect plague</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Guardian Soul</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you gain the ability to temporarily grow and take on the appearance of a treelike person, covered with leaves and bark. As a bonus action, you assume this guardian form, which lasts until you end it as a bonus action or until you are incapacitated.</text>
        <text>You undergo the following changes while in your guardian form:</text>
        <text>• Your size becomes Large, unless you were larger.</text>
        <text>• Any speed you have becomes 5 feet, unless the speed was lower.</text>
        <text>• Your reach increases by 5 feet.</text>
        <text>• You gain a number of temporary hit points at the start of each of your turns. The number equals half your ranger level. When the form ends, you lose any temporary hit points you have from it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Piercing Thorns</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, your command of primal magic allows you to enhance your attacks with thorns. Once during each of your turns, you can deal an additional 1d6 piercing damage to one creature you hit with a weapon attack.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Primeval Guardian</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>Rangers of the Primeval Guardian Conclave follow an ancient tradition rooted in powerful druidic magic. These rangers learn to become one with nature, allowing them to channel the aspects of various beasts and plants in order to overcome their foes.</text>
        <text>These rangers dwell in the elder forests of the world. They venture out only rarely, as they consider it their sacred duty to protect the druidic groves and ancient trees that saw the earliest days of the world.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Guardian Soul</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you gain the ability to temporarily grow and take on the appearance of a treelike person, covered with leaves and bark. As a bonus action, you assume this guardian form, which lasts until you end it as a bonus action or until you are incapacitated.</text>
        <text>You undergo the following changes while in your guardian form:</text>
        <text>• Your size becomes Large, unless you were larger.</text>
        <text>• Any speed you have becomes 5 feet, unless the speed was lower.</text>
        <text>• Your reach increases by 5 feet.</text>
        <text>• You gain a number of temporary hit points at the start of each of your turns. The number equals half your ranger level. When the form ends, you lose any temporary hit points you have from it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Piercing Thorns</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, your command of primal magic allows you to enhance your attacks with thorns. Once during each of your turns, you can deal an additional 1d6 piercing damage to one creature you hit with a weapon attack.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Primeval Guardian</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Revised Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>Rangers of the Primeval Guardian Conclave follow an ancient tradition rooted in powerful druidic magic. These rangers learn to become one with nature, allowing them to channel the aspects of various beasts and plants in order to overcome their foes.</text>
        <text>These rangers dwell in the elder forests of the world. They venture out only rarely, as they consider it their sacred duty to protect the druidic groves and ancient trees that saw the earliest days of the world.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Guardian Magic</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Primeval Guardian Spells table. The spell counts as a ranger spell for you, and it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Primeval Guardian Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | entangle</text>
        <text>5th | enhance ability</text>
        <text>9th | conjure animals</text>
        <text>13th | giant insect</text>
        <text>17th | insect plague</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Guardian Soul</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you gain the ability to temporarily grow and take on the appearance of a treelike person, covered with leaves and bark. As a bonus action, you assume this guardian form, which lasts until you end it as a bonus action or until you are incapacitated.</text>
        <text>You undergo the following changes while in your guardian form:</text>
        <text>• Your size becomes Large, unless you were larger.</text>
        <text>• Any speed you have becomes 5 feet, unless the speed was lower.</text>
        <text>• Your reach increases by 5 feet.</text>
        <text>• You gain a number of temporary hit points at the start of each of your turns. The number equals half your ranger level. When the form ends, you lose any temporary hit points you have from it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Piercing Thorns</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, your command of primal magic allows you to enhance your attacks with thorns. Once during each of your turns, you can deal an additional 1d6 piercing damage to one creature you hit with a weapon attack.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer (UA): Monster Slayer</name>
        <text>Rangers of the Slayer Conclave seek out vampires, dragons, evil fey, fiends, and other powerful magical threats. Trained in a variety of arcane and divine techniques to overcome such monsters, slayers are experts at unearthing and defeating mighty foes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer (UA): Slayer's Eye</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you gain the ability to study and unravel a creature's defenses. As a bonus action, choose one creature you can see within 120 feet of you. You immediately learn the target's vulnerabilities, immunities, and resistances. You also learn any special effects triggered when the target takes damage, such as fire damage halting its regeneration.</text>
        <text>In addition, the first time each turn you hit the target with a weapon attack, the target takes an extra 1d6 damage from the weapon.</text>
        <text>This benefit lasts until you target a different creature with this feature or until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer (UA): Slayer's Mysticism</name>
        <text>You learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Slayer Spells table. The spell counts as a ranger spell for you but doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Monster Slayer Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | protection from evil and good</text>
        <text>5th | zone of truth</text>
        <text>9th | magic circle</text>
        <text>13th | banishment</text>
        <text>17th | planar binding</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer (UA): Monster Slayer</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>Rangers of the Slayer Conclave seek out vampires, dragons, evil fey, fiends, and other powerful magical threats. Trained in a variety of arcane and divine techniques to overcome such monsters, slayers are experts at unearthing and defeating mighty foes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer (UA): Slayer's Eye</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you gain the ability to study and unravel a creature's defenses. As a bonus action, choose one creature you can see within 120 feet of you. You immediately learn the target's vulnerabilities, immunities, and resistances. You also learn any special effects triggered when the target takes damage, such as fire damage halting its regeneration.</text>
        <text>In addition, the first time each turn you hit the target with a weapon attack, the target takes an extra 1d6 damage from the weapon.</text>
        <text>This benefit lasts until you target a different creature with this feature or until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer (UA): Monster Slayer</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Revised Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>Rangers of the Slayer Conclave seek out vampires, dragons, evil fey, fiends, and other powerful magical threats. Trained in a variety of arcane and divine techniques to overcome such monsters, slayers are experts at unearthing and defeating mighty foes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer (UA): Slayer's Eye</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you gain the ability to study and unravel a creature's defenses. As a bonus action, choose one creature you can see within 120 feet of you. You immediately learn the target's vulnerabilities, immunities, and resistances. You also learn any special effects triggered when the target takes damage, such as fire damage halting its regeneration.</text>
        <text>In addition, the first time each turn you hit the target with a weapon attack, the target takes an extra 1d6 damage from the weapon.</text>
        <text>This benefit lasts until you target a different creature with this feature or until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer (UA): Slayer's Mysticism</name>
        <text>You learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Slayer Spells table. The spell counts as a ranger spell for you but doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Monster Slayer Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | protection from evil and good</text>
        <text>5th | zone of truth</text>
        <text>9th | magic circle</text>
        <text>13th | banishment</text>
        <text>17th | planar binding</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Gloom Stalker</name>
        <text>Gloom Stalkers are at home in the darkest places: deep under the earth, in gloomy alleyways, in primeval forests, and wherever else the light dims. Most folk enter such places with trepidation, but a Gloom Stalker ventures boldly into the darkness, seeking to ambush threats before they can reach the broader world. Such rangers are often found in the Underdark, but they will go any place where evil lurks in the shadows.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Gloom Stalker: Dread Ambusher</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you master the art of the ambush. You can give yourself a bonus to your initiative rolls equal to your Wisdom modifier.</text>
        <text>At the start of your first turn of each combat, your walking speed increases by 10 feet, which lasts until the end of that turn. If you take the Attack action on that turn, you can make one additional weapon attack as part of that action. If that attack hits, the target takes an extra 1d8 damage of the weapon's damage type.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Gloom Stalker: Gloom Stalker Magic</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Gloom Stalker Spells table. The spell counts as a ranger spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Gloom Stalker Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | disguise self</text>
        <text>5th | rope trick</text>
        <text>9th | fear</text>
        <text>13th | greater invisibility</text>
        <text>17th | seeming</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Gloom Stalker: Umbral Sight</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain darkvision out to a range of 60 feet. If you already have darkvision from your race, its range increases by 30 feet.</text>
        <text>You are also adept at evading creatures that rely on darkvision. While in darkness, you are invisible to any creature that relies on darkvision to see you in that darkness.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Gloom Stalker</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>Gloom Stalkers are at home in the darkest places: deep under the earth, in gloomy alleyways, in primeval forests, and wherever else the light dims. Most folk enter such places with trepidation, but a Gloom Stalker ventures boldly into the darkness, seeking to ambush threats before they can reach the broader world. Such rangers are often found in the Underdark, but they will go any place where evil lurks in the shadows.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Gloom Stalker: Dread Ambusher</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you master the art of the ambush. You can give yourself a bonus to your initiative rolls equal to your Wisdom modifier.</text>
        <text>At the start of your first turn of each combat, your walking speed increases by 10 feet, which lasts until the end of that turn. If you take the Attack action on that turn, you can make one additional weapon attack as part of that action. If that attack hits, the target takes an extra 1d8 damage of the weapon's damage type.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Gloom Stalker: Umbral Sight</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain darkvision out to a range of 60 feet. If you already have darkvision from your race, its range increases by 30 feet.</text>
        <text>You are also adept at evading creatures that rely on darkvision. While in darkness, you are invisible to any creature that relies on darkvision to see you in that darkness.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Gloom Stalker</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Revised Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>Gloom Stalkers are at home in the darkest places: deep under the earth, in gloomy alleyways, in primeval forests, and wherever else the light dims. Most folk enter such places with trepidation, but a Gloom Stalker ventures boldly into the darkness, seeking to ambush threats before they can reach the broader world. Such rangers are often found in the Underdark, but they will go any place where evil lurks in the shadows.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Gloom Stalker: Dread Ambusher</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you master the art of the ambush. You can give yourself a bonus to your initiative rolls equal to your Wisdom modifier.</text>
        <text>At the start of your first turn of each combat, your walking speed increases by 10 feet, which lasts until the end of that turn. If you take the Attack action on that turn, you can make one additional weapon attack as part of that action. If that attack hits, the target takes an extra 1d8 damage of the weapon's damage type.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Gloom Stalker: Gloom Stalker Magic</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Gloom Stalker Spells table. The spell counts as a ranger spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Gloom Stalker Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | disguise self</text>
        <text>5th | rope trick</text>
        <text>9th | fear</text>
        <text>13th | greater invisibility</text>
        <text>17th | seeming</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Gloom Stalker: Umbral Sight</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain darkvision out to a range of 60 feet. If you already have darkvision from your race, its range increases by 30 feet.</text>
        <text>You are also adept at evading creatures that rely on darkvision. While in darkness, you are invisible to any creature that relies on darkvision to see you in that darkness.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Horizon Walker</name>
        <text>Horizon Walkers guard the world against threats that originate from other planes or that seek to ravage the mortal realm with otherworldly magic. They seek out planar portals and keep watch over them, venturing to the Inner Planes and the Outer Planes as needed to pursue their foes. These rangers are also friends to any forces in the multiverse—especially benevolent dragons, fey, and elementals—that work to preserve life and the order of the planes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker: Detect Portal</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain the ability to magically sense the presence of a planar portal. As an action, you detect the distance and direction to the closest planar portal within 1 mile of you.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>See the "Planar Travel" section in chapter 2 of the Dungeon Master's Guide for examples of planar portals.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker: Horizon Walker Magic</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Horizon Walker Spells table. The spell counts as a ranger spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Horizon Walker Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | protection from evil and good</text>
        <text>5th | misty step</text>
        <text>9th | haste</text>
        <text>13th | banishment</text>
        <text>17th | teleportation circle</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker: Planar Warrior</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn to draw on the energy of the multiverse to augment your attacks.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of you. The next time you hit that creature on this turn with a weapon attack, all damage dealt by the attack becomes force damage, and the creature takes an extra 1d8 force damage from the attack. When you reach 11th level in this class, the extra damage increases to 2d8.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Horizon Walker</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>Horizon Walkers guard the world against threats that originate from other planes or that seek to ravage the mortal realm with otherworldly magic. They seek out planar portals and keep watch over them, venturing to the Inner Planes and the Outer Planes as needed to pursue their foes. These rangers are also friends to any forces in the multiverse—especially benevolent dragons, fey, and elementals—that work to preserve life and the order of the planes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker: Detect Portal</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain the ability to magically sense the presence of a planar portal. As an action, you detect the distance and direction to the closest planar portal within 1 mile of you.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>See the "Planar Travel" section in chapter 2 of the Dungeon Master's Guide for examples of planar portals.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker: Planar Warrior</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn to draw on the energy of the multiverse to augment your attacks.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of you. The next time you hit that creature on this turn with a weapon attack, all damage dealt by the attack becomes force damage, and the creature takes an extra 1d8 force damage from the attack. When you reach 11th level in this class, the extra damage increases to 2d8.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Horizon Walker</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Revised Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>Horizon Walkers guard the world against threats that originate from other planes or that seek to ravage the mortal realm with otherworldly magic. They seek out planar portals and keep watch over them, venturing to the Inner Planes and the Outer Planes as needed to pursue their foes. These rangers are also friends to any forces in the multiverse—especially benevolent dragons, fey, and elementals—that work to preserve life and the order of the planes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker: Detect Portal</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain the ability to magically sense the presence of a planar portal. As an action, you detect the distance and direction to the closest planar portal within 1 mile of you.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>See the "Planar Travel" section in chapter 2 of the Dungeon Master's Guide for examples of planar portals.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker: Horizon Walker Magic</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Horizon Walker Spells table. The spell counts as a ranger spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Horizon Walker Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | protection from evil and good</text>
        <text>5th | misty step</text>
        <text>9th | haste</text>
        <text>13th | banishment</text>
        <text>17th | teleportation circle</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker: Planar Warrior</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn to draw on the energy of the multiverse to augment your attacks.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of you. The next time you hit that creature on this turn with a weapon attack, all damage dealt by the attack becomes force damage, and the creature takes an extra 1d8 force damage from the attack. When you reach 11th level in this class, the extra damage increases to 2d8.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Monster Slayer</name>
        <text>You have dedicated yourself to hunting down creatures of the night and wielders of grim magic. A Monster Slayer seeks out vampires, dragons, evil fey, fiends, and other magical threats. Trained in supernatural techniques to overcome such monsters, slayers are experts at unearthing and defeating mighty, mystical foes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer: Hunter's Sense</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain the ability to peer at a creature and magically discern how best to hurt it. As an action, choose one creature you can see within 60 feet of you. You immediately learn whether the creature has any damage immunities, resistances, or vulnerabilities and what they are. If the creature is hidden from divination magic, you sense that it has no damage immunities, resistances, or vulnerabilities.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once). You regain all expended uses of it when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer: Monster Slayer Magic</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Monster Slayer Spells table. The spell counts as a ranger spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Monster Slayer Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | protection from evil and good</text>
        <text>5th | zone of truth</text>
        <text>9th | magic circle</text>
        <text>13th | banishment</text>
        <text>17th | hold monster</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer: Slayer's Prey</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you can focus your ire on one foe, increasing the harm you inflict on it. As a bonus action, you designate one creature you can see within 60 feet of you as the target of this feature. The first time each turn that you hit that target with a weapon attack, it takes an extra 1d6 damage from the weapon.</text>
        <text>This benefit lasts until you finish a short or long rest. It ends early if you designate a different creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Monster Slayer</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>You have dedicated yourself to hunting down creatures of the night and wielders of grim magic. A Monster Slayer seeks out vampires, dragons, evil fey, fiends, and other magical threats. Trained in supernatural techniques to overcome such monsters, slayers are experts at unearthing and defeating mighty, mystical foes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer: Hunter's Sense</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain the ability to peer at a creature and magically discern how best to hurt it. As an action, choose one creature you can see within 60 feet of you. You immediately learn whether the creature has any damage immunities, resistances, or vulnerabilities and what they are. If the creature is hidden from divination magic, you sense that it has no damage immunities, resistances, or vulnerabilities.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once). You regain all expended uses of it when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer: Slayer's Prey</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you can focus your ire on one foe, increasing the harm you inflict on it. As a bonus action, you designate one creature you can see within 60 feet of you as the target of this feature. The first time each turn that you hit that target with a weapon attack, it takes an extra 1d6 damage from the weapon.</text>
        <text>This benefit lasts until you finish a short or long rest. It ends early if you designate a different creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Monster Slayer</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Revised Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>You have dedicated yourself to hunting down creatures of the night and wielders of grim magic. A Monster Slayer seeks out vampires, dragons, evil fey, fiends, and other magical threats. Trained in supernatural techniques to overcome such monsters, slayers are experts at unearthing and defeating mighty, mystical foes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer: Hunter's Sense</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you gain the ability to peer at a creature and magically discern how best to hurt it. As an action, choose one creature you can see within 60 feet of you. You immediately learn whether the creature has any damage immunities, resistances, or vulnerabilities and what they are. If the creature is hidden from divination magic, you sense that it has no damage immunities, resistances, or vulnerabilities.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once). You regain all expended uses of it when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer: Monster Slayer Magic</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Monster Slayer Spells table. The spell counts as a ranger spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Monster Slayer Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | protection from evil and good</text>
        <text>5th | zone of truth</text>
        <text>9th | magic circle</text>
        <text>13th | banishment</text>
        <text>17th | hold monster</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer: Slayer's Prey</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you can focus your ire on one foe, increasing the harm you inflict on it. As a bonus action, you designate one creature you can see within 60 feet of you as the target of this feature. The first time each turn that you hit that target with a weapon attack, it takes an extra 1d6 damage from the weapon.</text>
        <text>This benefit lasts until you finish a short or long rest. It ends early if you designate a different creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Swarmkeeper</name>
        <text>Feeling a deep connection to the world around them, some rangers reach out through their magical connection to nature and gather a host of fey spirits, which take the form of swarming beasts—be they buzzing insects, fluttering birds, slippery squids, or otherwise. The swarm becomes a potent force in battle, as well as helpful—if potentially disturbing—company for the ranger. Some Swarmkeepers are outcasts or hermits, keeping to themselves and their attendant swarms rather than dealing with the discomfort of others. Other Swarmkeepers enjoy building vibrant communities that work for the mutual benefit of all those they consider part of their swarm.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Gathered Swarm</name>
        <text>3rd-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>You magically attract a swarm of fey spirits that look like Tiny beasts of your choice. The swarm remains in your space, crawling on you or through your clothing, or flying and skittering immediately around you within your space.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, you can agitate the swarm for 1 minute. For the duration, some of the swarm clings to your weapons or follows your strikes when you attack: once during each of your turns when you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can deal an extra 1d6 force damage to that creature, and the swarm moves the creature up to 5 feet toward you or away from you (your choice). At 11th level, the extra damage increases to 2d6.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Swarmkeeper Magic</name>
        <text>3rd-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>You learn the mage hand cantrip if you don't already know it. When you cast it, the hand takes the form of swarming nature spirits. You also learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Swarmkeeper Spells table. These spells count as ranger spells for you, but don't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Swarmkeeper Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | faerie fire</text>
        <text>5th | web</text>
        <text>9th | gaseous form</text>
        <text>13th | giant insect</text>
        <text>17th | insect plague</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Swarmkeeper</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>Feeling a deep connection to the world around them, some rangers reach out through their magical connection to nature and gather a host of fey spirits, which take the form of swarming beasts—be they buzzing insects, fluttering birds, slippery squids, or otherwise. The swarm becomes a potent force in battle, as well as helpful—if potentially disturbing—company for the ranger. Some Swarmkeepers are outcasts or hermits, keeping to themselves and their attendant swarms rather than dealing with the discomfort of others. Other Swarmkeepers enjoy building vibrant communities that work for the mutual benefit of all those they consider part of their swarm.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Gathered Swarm</name>
        <text>3rd-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>You magically attract a swarm of fey spirits that look like Tiny beasts of your choice. The swarm remains in your space, crawling on you or through your clothing, or flying and skittering immediately around you within your space.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, you can agitate the swarm for 1 minute. For the duration, some of the swarm clings to your weapons or follows your strikes when you attack: once during each of your turns when you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can deal an extra 1d6 force damage to that creature, and the swarm moves the creature up to 5 feet toward you or away from you (your choice). At 11th level, the extra damage increases to 2d6.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Swarmkeeper</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Revised Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>Feeling a deep connection to the world around them, some rangers reach out through their magical connection to nature and gather a host of fey spirits, which take the form of swarming beasts—be they buzzing insects, fluttering birds, slippery squids, or otherwise. The swarm becomes a potent force in battle, as well as helpful—if potentially disturbing—company for the ranger. Some Swarmkeepers are outcasts or hermits, keeping to themselves and their attendant swarms rather than dealing with the discomfort of others. Other Swarmkeepers enjoy building vibrant communities that work for the mutual benefit of all those they consider part of their swarm.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Gathered Swarm</name>
        <text>3rd-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>You magically attract a swarm of fey spirits that look like Tiny beasts of your choice. The swarm remains in your space, crawling on you or through your clothing, or flying and skittering immediately around you within your space.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, you can agitate the swarm for 1 minute. For the duration, some of the swarm clings to your weapons or follows your strikes when you attack: once during each of your turns when you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can deal an extra 1d6 force damage to that creature, and the swarm moves the creature up to 5 feet toward you or away from you (your choice). At 11th level, the extra damage increases to 2d6.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Swarmkeeper Magic</name>
        <text>3rd-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>You learn the mage hand cantrip if you don't already know it. When you cast it, the hand takes the form of swarming nature spirits. You also learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Swarmkeeper Spells table. These spells count as ranger spells for you, but don't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Swarmkeeper Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | faerie fire</text>
        <text>5th | web</text>
        <text>9th | gaseous form</text>
        <text>13th | giant insect</text>
        <text>17th | insect plague</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Fey Wanderer</name>
        <text>As a Fey Wanderer, you guard the border between the Feywild and the Material Plane, guiding the lost out of the Feywild and preventing dangerous fey from damaging the Material Plane. Your experience with both domains makes you an exceptional negotiator between inhabitants of these worlds, as you understand both humanoid mindsets and the wiles of the fey courts.</text>
        <text>Fey Wanderers possess a preternatural blessing from a fey ally or a place of fey power. Choose your blessing from the Feywild Gifts table or determine it randomly.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Feywild Gifts</text>
        <text>d6 | Gift</text>
        <text>1 | Illusory butterflies flutter around you while you take a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>2 | Fresh, seasonal flowers sprout from your hair each dawn.</text>
        <text>3 | You faintly smell of cinnamon, lavender, nutmeg, or another comforting herb or spice.</text>
        <text>4 | Your shadow dances while no one is looking directly at it.</text>
        <text>5 | Delicate horns or antlers sprout from your head.</text>
        <text>6 | Your skin and hair change color to match the season at each dawn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Cunning Will</name>
        <text>3rd-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>Your experience with the fey has guarded your mind and sharpened your tongue. You have advantage on saving throws against being charmed or frightened.</text>
        <text>In addition, you gain proficiency in one of the following skills of your choice: Deception, Performance, or Persuasion.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Dreadful Strikes</name>
        <text>3rd-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You augment your attacks with mind-scarring magic, drawn from the gloomy hollows of the unseelie fey. You gain a bonus action that you can use to imbue the weapon, or weapons, you're currently holding with magic. Until the end of the turn, the weapons are magical, and they deal an extra 1d6 psychic damage on a hit. A creature can take this extra damage only once per turn.</text>
        <text>When you engage in two-weapon fighting, you can imbue your weapons as part of the same bonus action you use to make the attack.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Fey Wanderer Magic</name>
        <text>3rd-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Fey Wanderer Spells table. The spell counts as a ranger spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Fey Wanderer Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | charm person</text>
        <text>5th | misty step</text>
        <text>9th | dispel magic</text>
        <text>13th | banishment</text>
        <text>17th | mislead</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Fey Wanderer</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>As a Fey Wanderer, you guard the border between the Feywild and the Material Plane, guiding the lost out of the Feywild and preventing dangerous fey from damaging the Material Plane. Your experience with both domains makes you an exceptional negotiator between inhabitants of these worlds, as you understand both humanoid mindsets and the wiles of the fey courts.</text>
        <text>Fey Wanderers possess a preternatural blessing from a fey ally or a place of fey power. Choose your blessing from the Feywild Gifts table or determine it randomly.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Feywild Gifts</text>
        <text>d6 | Gift</text>
        <text>1 | Illusory butterflies flutter around you while you take a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>2 | Fresh, seasonal flowers sprout from your hair each dawn.</text>
        <text>3 | You faintly smell of cinnamon, lavender, nutmeg, or another comforting herb or spice.</text>
        <text>4 | Your shadow dances while no one is looking directly at it.</text>
        <text>5 | Delicate horns or antlers sprout from your head.</text>
        <text>6 | Your skin and hair change color to match the season at each dawn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Cunning Will</name>
        <text>3rd-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>Your experience with the fey has guarded your mind and sharpened your tongue. You have advantage on saving throws against being charmed or frightened.</text>
        <text>In addition, you gain proficiency in one of the following skills of your choice: Deception, Performance, or Persuasion.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Dreadful Strikes</name>
        <text>3rd-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You augment your attacks with mind-scarring magic, drawn from the gloomy hollows of the unseelie fey. You gain a bonus action that you can use to imbue the weapon, or weapons, you're currently holding with magic. Until the end of the turn, the weapons are magical, and they deal an extra 1d6 psychic damage on a hit. A creature can take this extra damage only once per turn.</text>
        <text>When you engage in two-weapon fighting, you can imbue your weapons as part of the same bonus action you use to make the attack.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Fey Wanderer</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Revised Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>As a Fey Wanderer, you guard the border between the Feywild and the Material Plane, guiding the lost out of the Feywild and preventing dangerous fey from damaging the Material Plane. Your experience with both domains makes you an exceptional negotiator between inhabitants of these worlds, as you understand both humanoid mindsets and the wiles of the fey courts.</text>
        <text>Fey Wanderers possess a preternatural blessing from a fey ally or a place of fey power. Choose your blessing from the Feywild Gifts table or determine it randomly.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Feywild Gifts</text>
        <text>d6 | Gift</text>
        <text>1 | Illusory butterflies flutter around you while you take a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>2 | Fresh, seasonal flowers sprout from your hair each dawn.</text>
        <text>3 | You faintly smell of cinnamon, lavender, nutmeg, or another comforting herb or spice.</text>
        <text>4 | Your shadow dances while no one is looking directly at it.</text>
        <text>5 | Delicate horns or antlers sprout from your head.</text>
        <text>6 | Your skin and hair change color to match the season at each dawn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Cunning Will</name>
        <text>3rd-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>Your experience with the fey has guarded your mind and sharpened your tongue. You have advantage on saving throws against being charmed or frightened.</text>
        <text>In addition, you gain proficiency in one of the following skills of your choice: Deception, Performance, or Persuasion.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Dreadful Strikes</name>
        <text>3rd-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You augment your attacks with mind-scarring magic, drawn from the gloomy hollows of the unseelie fey. You gain a bonus action that you can use to imbue the weapon, or weapons, you're currently holding with magic. Until the end of the turn, the weapons are magical, and they deal an extra 1d6 psychic damage on a hit. A creature can take this extra damage only once per turn.</text>
        <text>When you engage in two-weapon fighting, you can imbue your weapons as part of the same bonus action you use to make the attack.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Fey Wanderer Magic</name>
        <text>3rd-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Fey Wanderer Spells table. The spell counts as a ranger spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Fey Wanderer Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | charm person</text>
        <text>5th | misty step</text>
        <text>9th | dispel magic</text>
        <text>13th | banishment</text>
        <text>17th | mislead</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Drakewarden</name>
        <text>Drakewardens are rangers who use their magical connection with nature to form an enduring bond with a minor dragon, a drake. This bond allows the ranger to summon the</text>
        <text>drake to their side and to share in the awe-inspiring power wielded by dragons. Consider how your ranger gained their bond with the drake. The Drakewarden Origin table offers some examples.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text></text>
        <text>d6 | Origin</text>
        <text>1 | You studied a dragon's scale or claw, or a trinket from its hoard, and created your bond through the token's lingering draconic magic.</text>
        <text>2 | A secret order of rangers who collect and guard draconic lore taught you their ways.</text>
        <text>3 | A true dragon gave you a drake egg to care for. When it hatched, the drake bonded to you.</text>
        <text>4 | You drank a few drops of dragon blood, forever infusing your nature magic with draconic power.</text>
        <text>5 | An ancient Draconic inscription on a standing stone empowered you when you read it aloud.</text>
        <text>6 | You had a vivid dream of a mysterious man, accompanied by seven yellow canaries, who warned you of impending doom. When you awoke, your drake was there, watching you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Draconic Gift</name>
        <text>3rd-level Drakewarden feature</text>
        <text>The bond you share with your drake creates a deeper connection to dragon kind, granting you understanding and empowering your presence. You gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• If you can't already, you learn to speak, read, and write Draconic.</text>
        <text>• You learn the thaumaturgy cantrip, which is a ranger spell for you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Drake Companion</name>
        <text>3rd-level Drakewarden feature</text>
        <text>You can magically summon the drake bound to you. As an action, you can summon the drake, which appears in an unoccupied space of your choice that you can see within 30 feet of you.</text>
        <text>The drake is friendly to you and your companions and obeys your commands. See its game statistics in the Drake Companion stat block, which uses your proficiency bonus (PB) in several places. When you summon the drake, choose a damage type listed in its Draconic Essence trait. You can determine the cosmetic characteristics of the drake such as its color, scale texture, or any visible effect of its Draconic Essence; your choice has no effect on its game statistics.</text>
        <text>In combat, the drake shares your initiative count, but it takes its turn immediately after yours. It can move and use its reaction on its own, but the only action it takes on its turn is the Dodge action, unless you take a bonus action on your turn to command it to take another action. That action can be one in its stat block or some other action. If you are incapacitated, the drake can take any action of its choice, not just Dodge.</text>
        <text>Once you summon the drake, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend a spell slot of 1st level or higher to summon it.</text>
        <text>The drake remains for a number of hours equal to your proficiency bonus, until it is reduced to 0 hit points, until you use this feature to summon the drake again, or until you die. Anything the drake was wearing or carrying is left behind when the drake vanishes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Drakewarden</name>
        <text>Drakewardens are rangers who use their magical connection with nature to form an enduring bond with a minor dragon, a drake. This bond allows the ranger to summon the</text>
        <text>drake to their side and to share in the awe-inspiring power wielded by dragons. Consider how your ranger gained their bond with the drake. The Drakewarden Origin table offers some examples.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text></text>
        <text>d6 | Origin</text>
        <text>1 | You studied a dragon's scale or claw, or a trinket from its hoard, and created your bond through the token's lingering draconic magic.</text>
        <text>2 | A secret order of rangers who collect and guard draconic lore taught you their ways.</text>
        <text>3 | A true dragon gave you a drake egg to care for. When it hatched, the drake bonded to you.</text>
        <text>4 | You drank a few drops of dragon blood, forever infusing your nature magic with draconic power.</text>
        <text>5 | An ancient Draconic inscription on a standing stone empowered you when you read it aloud.</text>
        <text>6 | You had a vivid dream of a mysterious man, accompanied by seven yellow canaries, who warned you of impending doom. When you awoke, your drake was there, watching you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Draconic Gift</name>
        <text>3rd-level Drakewarden feature</text>
        <text>The bond you share with your drake creates a deeper connection to dragon kind, granting you understanding and empowering your presence. You gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• If you can't already, you learn to speak, read, and write Draconic.</text>
        <text>• You learn the thaumaturgy cantrip, which is a ranger spell for you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Drake Companion</name>
        <text>3rd-level Drakewarden feature</text>
        <text>You can magically summon the drake bound to you. As an action, you can summon the drake, which appears in an unoccupied space of your choice that you can see within 30 feet of you.</text>
        <text>The drake is friendly to you and your companions and obeys your commands. See its game statistics in the Drake Companion stat block, which uses your proficiency bonus (PB) in several places. When you summon the drake, choose a damage type listed in its Draconic Essence trait. You can determine the cosmetic characteristics of the drake such as its color, scale texture, or any visible effect of its Draconic Essence; your choice has no effect on its game statistics.</text>
        <text>In combat, the drake shares your initiative count, but it takes its turn immediately after yours. It can move and use its reaction on its own, but the only action it takes on its turn is the Dodge action, unless you take a bonus action on your turn to command it to take another action. That action can be one in its stat block or some other action. If you are incapacitated, the drake can take any action of its choice, not just Dodge.</text>
        <text>Once you summon the drake, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend a spell slot of 1st level or higher to summon it.</text>
        <text>The drake remains for a number of hours equal to your proficiency bonus, until it is reduced to 0 hit points, until you use this feature to summon the drake again, or until you die. Anything the drake was wearing or carrying is left behind when the drake vanishes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Drakewarden</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>Drakewardens are rangers who use their magical connection with nature to form an enduring bond with a minor dragon, a drake. This bond allows the ranger to summon the</text>
        <text>drake to their side and to share in the awe-inspiring power wielded by dragons. Consider how your ranger gained their bond with the drake. The Drakewarden Origin table offers some examples.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text></text>
        <text>d6 | Origin</text>
        <text>1 | You studied a dragon's scale or claw, or a trinket from its hoard, and created your bond through the token's lingering draconic magic.</text>
        <text>2 | A secret order of rangers who collect and guard draconic lore taught you their ways.</text>
        <text>3 | A true dragon gave you a drake egg to care for. When it hatched, the drake bonded to you.</text>
        <text>4 | You drank a few drops of dragon blood, forever infusing your nature magic with draconic power.</text>
        <text>5 | An ancient Draconic inscription on a standing stone empowered you when you read it aloud.</text>
        <text>6 | You had a vivid dream of a mysterious man, accompanied by seven yellow canaries, who warned you of impending doom. When you awoke, your drake was there, watching you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Draconic Gift</name>
        <text>3rd-level Drakewarden feature</text>
        <text>The bond you share with your drake creates a deeper connection to dragon kind, granting you understanding and empowering your presence. You gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• If you can't already, you learn to speak, read, and write Draconic.</text>
        <text>• You learn the thaumaturgy cantrip, which is a ranger spell for you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Drake Companion</name>
        <text>3rd-level Drakewarden feature</text>
        <text>You can magically summon the drake bound to you. As an action, you can summon the drake, which appears in an unoccupied space of your choice that you can see within 30 feet of you.</text>
        <text>The drake is friendly to you and your companions and obeys your commands. See its game statistics in the Drake Companion stat block, which uses your proficiency bonus (PB) in several places. When you summon the drake, choose a damage type listed in its Draconic Essence trait. You can determine the cosmetic characteristics of the drake such as its color, scale texture, or any visible effect of its Draconic Essence; your choice has no effect on its game statistics.</text>
        <text>In combat, the drake shares your initiative count, but it takes its turn immediately after yours. It can move and use its reaction on its own, but the only action it takes on its turn is the Dodge action, unless you take a bonus action on your turn to command it to take another action. That action can be one in its stat block or some other action. If you are incapacitated, the drake can take any action of its choice, not just Dodge.</text>
        <text>Once you summon the drake, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend a spell slot of 1st level or higher to summon it.</text>
        <text>The drake remains for a number of hours equal to your proficiency bonus, until it is reduced to 0 hit points, until you use this feature to summon the drake again, or until you die. Anything the drake was wearing or carrying is left behind when the drake vanishes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Fey Wanderer</name>
        <text>A fey mystique surrounds you, thanks to the boon of an archfey, the shining fruit you ate from a talking tree, the magic spring you swam in, or some other auspicious event. However you acquired your fey magic, you are now a Fey Wanderer, a ranger who represents both the mortal and the fey realms. As you wander the multiverse, your joyful laughter brightens the hearts of the downtrodden, and your martial prowess strikes terror in your foes, for great is the mirth of the fey and dreadful is their fury.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Dreadful Strikes</name>
        <text>3rd-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You can augment your weapon strikes with mind-scarring magic, drawn from the gloomy hollows of the Feywild. When you hit a creature with a weapon, you can deal an extra 1d4 psychic damage to the target, which can take this extra damage only once per turn.</text>
        <text>The extra damage increases to 1d6 when you reach 11th level in this class.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Fey Wanderer Magic</name>
        <text>3rd-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Fey Wanderer Spells table. Each spell counts as a ranger spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Fey Wanderer Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | charm person</text>
        <text>5th | misty step</text>
        <text>9th | dispel magic</text>
        <text>13th | dimension door</text>
        <text>17th | mislead</text>
        <text>You also possess a preternatural blessing from a fey ally or a place of fey power. Choose your blessing from the Feywild Gifts table or determine it randomly.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Feywild Gifts</text>
        <text>d6 | Gift</text>
        <text>1 | Illusory butterflies flutter around you while you take a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>2 | Fresh, seasonal flowers sprout from your hair each dawn.</text>
        <text>3 | You faintly smell of cinnamon, lavender, nutmeg, or another comforting herb or spice.</text>
        <text>4 | Your shadow dances while no one is looking directly at it.</text>
        <text>5 | Horns or antlers sprout from your head.</text>
        <text>6 | Your skin and hair change color to match the season at each dawn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Otherworldly Glamour</name>
        <text>3rd-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>Your fey qualities give you a supernatural charm. As a result, whenever you make a Charisma check, you gain a bonus to the check equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of +1).</text>
        <text>In addition, you gain proficiency in one of the following skills of your choice: Deception, Performance, or Persuasion.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Fey Wanderer</name>
        <text>A fey mystique surrounds you, thanks to the boon of an archfey, the shining fruit you ate from a talking tree, the magic spring you swam in, or some other auspicious event. However you acquired your fey magic, you are now a Fey Wanderer, a ranger who represents both the mortal and the fey realms. As you wander the multiverse, your joyful laughter brightens the hearts of the downtrodden, and your martial prowess strikes terror in your foes, for great is the mirth of the fey and dreadful is their fury.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Dreadful Strikes</name>
        <text>3rd-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You can augment your weapon strikes with mind-scarring magic, drawn from the gloomy hollows of the Feywild. When you hit a creature with a weapon, you can deal an extra 1d4 psychic damage to the target, which can take this extra damage only once per turn.</text>
        <text>The extra damage increases to 1d6 when you reach 11th level in this class.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Fey Wanderer Magic</name>
        <text>3rd-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Fey Wanderer Spells table. Each spell counts as a ranger spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Fey Wanderer Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | charm person</text>
        <text>5th | misty step</text>
        <text>9th | dispel magic</text>
        <text>13th | dimension door</text>
        <text>17th | mislead</text>
        <text>You also possess a preternatural blessing from a fey ally or a place of fey power. Choose your blessing from the Feywild Gifts table or determine it randomly.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Feywild Gifts</text>
        <text>d6 | Gift</text>
        <text>1 | Illusory butterflies flutter around you while you take a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>2 | Fresh, seasonal flowers sprout from your hair each dawn.</text>
        <text>3 | You faintly smell of cinnamon, lavender, nutmeg, or another comforting herb or spice.</text>
        <text>4 | Your shadow dances while no one is looking directly at it.</text>
        <text>5 | Horns or antlers sprout from your head.</text>
        <text>6 | Your skin and hair change color to match the season at each dawn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Otherworldly Glamour</name>
        <text>3rd-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>Your fey qualities give you a supernatural charm. As a result, whenever you make a Charisma check, you gain a bonus to the check equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of +1).</text>
        <text>In addition, you gain proficiency in one of the following skills of your choice: Deception, Performance, or Persuasion.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Fey Wanderer</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>A fey mystique surrounds you, thanks to the boon of an archfey, the shining fruit you ate from a talking tree, the magic spring you swam in, or some other auspicious event. However you acquired your fey magic, you are now a Fey Wanderer, a ranger who represents both the mortal and the fey realms. As you wander the multiverse, your joyful laughter brightens the hearts of the downtrodden, and your martial prowess strikes terror in your foes, for great is the mirth of the fey and dreadful is their fury.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Dreadful Strikes</name>
        <text>3rd-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You can augment your weapon strikes with mind-scarring magic, drawn from the gloomy hollows of the Feywild. When you hit a creature with a weapon, you can deal an extra 1d4 psychic damage to the target, which can take this extra damage only once per turn.</text>
        <text>The extra damage increases to 1d6 when you reach 11th level in this class.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Fey Wanderer Magic</name>
        <text>3rd-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You learn an additional spell when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Fey Wanderer Spells table. Each spell counts as a ranger spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Fey Wanderer Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | charm person</text>
        <text>5th | misty step</text>
        <text>9th | dispel magic</text>
        <text>13th | dimension door</text>
        <text>17th | mislead</text>
        <text>You also possess a preternatural blessing from a fey ally or a place of fey power. Choose your blessing from the Feywild Gifts table or determine it randomly.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Feywild Gifts</text>
        <text>d6 | Gift</text>
        <text>1 | Illusory butterflies flutter around you while you take a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>2 | Fresh, seasonal flowers sprout from your hair each dawn.</text>
        <text>3 | You faintly smell of cinnamon, lavender, nutmeg, or another comforting herb or spice.</text>
        <text>4 | Your shadow dances while no one is looking directly at it.</text>
        <text>5 | Horns or antlers sprout from your head.</text>
        <text>6 | Your skin and hair change color to match the season at each dawn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Otherworldly Glamour</name>
        <text>3rd-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>Your fey qualities give you a supernatural charm. As a result, whenever you make a Charisma check, you gain a bonus to the check equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of +1).</text>
        <text>In addition, you gain proficiency in one of the following skills of your choice: Deception, Performance, or Persuasion.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Swarmkeeper</name>
        <text>Feeling a deep connection to the environment around them, some rangers reach out through their magical connection to the world and bond with a swarm of nature spirits. The swarm becomes a potent force in battle, as well as helpful company for the ranger. Some Swarmkeepers are outcasts or hermits, keeping to themselves and their attendant swarms rather than dealing with the discomfort of others. Other Swarmkeepers enjoy building vibrant communities that work for the mutual benefit of all those they consider part of their swarm.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper: Gathered Swarm</name>
        <text>3rd-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>A swarm of intangible nature spirits has bonded itself to you and can assist you in battle. Until you die, the swarm remains in your space, crawling on you or flying and skittering around you within your space. You determine its appearance, or you generate its appearance by rolling on the Swarm Appearance table.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Swarm Appearance</text>
        <text>d4 | Appearance</text>
        <text>1 | Swarming insects</text>
        <text>2 | Miniature twig blights</text>
        <text>3 | Fluttering birds</text>
        <text>4 | Playful pixies</text>
        <text>Once on each of your turns, you can cause the swarm to assist you in one of the following ways, immediately after you hit a creature with an attack:</text>
        <text>• The attack's target takes 1d6 piercing damage from the swarm.</text>
        <text>• The attack's target must succeed on a Strength saving throw against your spell save DC or be moved by the swarm up to 15 feet horizontally in a direction of your choice.</text>
        <text>• You are moved by the swarm 5 feet horizontally in a direction of your choice.</text>
        <name>Swarmkeeper: It's Your Swarm</name>
        <text>   A Swarmkeeper's swarm and spells are reflections of the character's bond with nature spirits. Take the opportunity to describe the swarm and the ranger's magic in play. For example, when your ranger casts gaseous form, they might appear to melt into the swarm, instead of a cloud of mist, or the arcane eye spell could create an extension of your swarm that spies for you. Such descriptions don't change the effects of spells, but they are an exciting opportunity to explore your character's narrative through their class abilities. For more guidance on customizing spells, see the "Personalizing Spells" section in chapter 3.</text>
        <text>   Also, remember that the swarm's appearance is yours to customize, and don't feel confined to a single appearance. Perhaps the spirits' look changes with the ranger's mood or with the seasons. You decide!</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper: Swarmkeeper Magic</name>
        <text>3rd-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>You learn the mage hand cantrip if you don't already know it. When you cast it, the hand takes the form of your swarming nature spirits.</text>
        <text>You also learn an additional spell of 1st level or higher when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Swarmkeeper Spells table. Each spell counts as a ranger spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Swarmkeeper Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | faerie fire</text>
        <text>5th | web</text>
        <text>9th | gaseous form</text>
        <text>13th | arcane eye</text>
        <text>17th | insect plague</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Swarmkeeper</name>
        <text>Feeling a deep connection to the environment around them, some rangers reach out through their magical connection to the world and bond with a swarm of nature spirits. The swarm becomes a potent force in battle, as well as helpful company for the ranger. Some Swarmkeepers are outcasts or hermits, keeping to themselves and their attendant swarms rather than dealing with the discomfort of others. Other Swarmkeepers enjoy building vibrant communities that work for the mutual benefit of all those they consider part of their swarm.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper: Gathered Swarm</name>
        <text>3rd-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>A swarm of intangible nature spirits has bonded itself to you and can assist you in battle. Until you die, the swarm remains in your space, crawling on you or flying and skittering around you within your space. You determine its appearance, or you generate its appearance by rolling on the Swarm Appearance table.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Swarm Appearance</text>
        <text>d4 | Appearance</text>
        <text>1 | Swarming insects</text>
        <text>2 | Miniature twig blights</text>
        <text>3 | Fluttering birds</text>
        <text>4 | Playful pixies</text>
        <text>Once on each of your turns, you can cause the swarm to assist you in one of the following ways, immediately after you hit a creature with an attack:</text>
        <text>• The attack's target takes 1d6 piercing damage from the swarm.</text>
        <text>• The attack's target must succeed on a Strength saving throw against your spell save DC or be moved by the swarm up to 15 feet horizontally in a direction of your choice.</text>
        <text>• You are moved by the swarm 5 feet horizontally in a direction of your choice.</text>
        <name>Swarmkeeper: It's Your Swarm</name>
        <text>   A Swarmkeeper's swarm and spells are reflections of the character's bond with nature spirits. Take the opportunity to describe the swarm and the ranger's magic in play. For example, when your ranger casts gaseous form, they might appear to melt into the swarm, instead of a cloud of mist, or the arcane eye spell could create an extension of your swarm that spies for you. Such descriptions don't change the effects of spells, but they are an exciting opportunity to explore your character's narrative through their class abilities. For more guidance on customizing spells, see the "Personalizing Spells" section in chapter 3.</text>
        <text>   Also, remember that the swarm's appearance is yours to customize, and don't feel confined to a single appearance. Perhaps the spirits' look changes with the ranger's mood or with the seasons. You decide!</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper: Swarmkeeper Magic</name>
        <text>3rd-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>You learn the mage hand cantrip if you don't already know it. When you cast it, the hand takes the form of your swarming nature spirits.</text>
        <text>You also learn an additional spell of 1st level or higher when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Swarmkeeper Spells table. Each spell counts as a ranger spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Swarmkeeper Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | faerie fire</text>
        <text>5th | web</text>
        <text>9th | gaseous form</text>
        <text>13th | arcane eye</text>
        <text>17th | insect plague</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Ranger Archetype: Swarmkeeper</name>
        <text>Note that this subclass is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger subclass.</text>
        <text>Feeling a deep connection to the environment around them, some rangers reach out through their magical connection to the world and bond with a swarm of nature spirits. The swarm becomes a potent force in battle, as well as helpful company for the ranger. Some Swarmkeepers are outcasts or hermits, keeping to themselves and their attendant swarms rather than dealing with the discomfort of others. Other Swarmkeepers enjoy building vibrant communities that work for the mutual benefit of all those they consider part of their swarm.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper: Gathered Swarm</name>
        <text>3rd-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>A swarm of intangible nature spirits has bonded itself to you and can assist you in battle. Until you die, the swarm remains in your space, crawling on you or flying and skittering around you within your space. You determine its appearance, or you generate its appearance by rolling on the Swarm Appearance table.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Swarm Appearance</text>
        <text>d4 | Appearance</text>
        <text>1 | Swarming insects</text>
        <text>2 | Miniature twig blights</text>
        <text>3 | Fluttering birds</text>
        <text>4 | Playful pixies</text>
        <text>Once on each of your turns, you can cause the swarm to assist you in one of the following ways, immediately after you hit a creature with an attack:</text>
        <text>• The attack's target takes 1d6 piercing damage from the swarm.</text>
        <text>• The attack's target must succeed on a Strength saving throw against your spell save DC or be moved by the swarm up to 15 feet horizontally in a direction of your choice.</text>
        <text>• You are moved by the swarm 5 feet horizontally in a direction of your choice.</text>
        <name>Swarmkeeper: It's Your Swarm</name>
        <text>   A Swarmkeeper's swarm and spells are reflections of the character's bond with nature spirits. Take the opportunity to describe the swarm and the ranger's magic in play. For example, when your ranger casts gaseous form, they might appear to melt into the swarm, instead of a cloud of mist, or the arcane eye spell could create an extension of your swarm that spies for you. Such descriptions don't change the effects of spells, but they are an exciting opportunity to explore your character's narrative through their class abilities. For more guidance on customizing spells, see the "Personalizing Spells" section in chapter 3.</text>
        <text>   Also, remember that the swarm's appearance is yours to customize, and don't feel confined to a single appearance. Perhaps the spirits' look changes with the ranger's mood or with the seasons. You decide!</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper: Swarmkeeper Magic</name>
        <text>3rd-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>You learn the mage hand cantrip if you don't already know it. When you cast it, the hand takes the form of your swarming nature spirits.</text>
        <text>You also learn an additional spell of 1st level or higher when you reach certain levels in this class, as shown in the Swarmkeeper Spells table. Each spell counts as a ranger spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Swarmkeeper Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | faerie fire</text>
        <text>5th | web</text>
        <text>9th | gaseous form</text>
        <text>13th | arcane eye</text>
        <text>17th | insect plague</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature>
          <name>Primeval Awareness</name>
        <text>Beginning at 3rd level, you can use your action to focus your awareness on the region around you. For the next minute, you can sense whether the following types of creatures are present within 1 mile of you (or within up to 6 miles if you are in your favored terrain): aberrations, celestials, dragons, elementals, fey, fiends, and undead. This feature doesn't reveal the creatures' location or number.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you must finish a short or long rest before you can use it again</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature>
          <name>Primal Awareness</name>
        <text>3rd-level ranger feature (replaces Primeval Awareness)</text>
        <text>Note that this feature is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger feature.</text>
        <text>You can focus your awareness through the interconnections of nature: you learn additional spells when you reach certain levels in this class if you don't already know them, as shown in the Primal Awareness Spells table. These spells don't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Primal Awareness Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spell</text>
        <text>3rd | detect magic, speak with animals</text>
        <text>5th | beast sense, locate animals or plants</text>
        <text>9th | speak with plants</text>
        <text>13th | locate creature</text>
        <text>17th | commune with nature</text>
        <text>You can cast each of these spells once without expending a spell slot. Once you cast a spell in this way, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 8</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature>
          <name>Primal Awareness</name>
        <text>3rd-level ranger optional class features, which replaces the Primeval Awareness feature</text>
        <text>Note that this feature is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger feature.</text>
        <text>You can focus your awareness through the interconnections of nature: you learn additional spells when you reach certain levels in this class if you don't already know them, as shown in the Primal Awareness Spells table. These spells don't count against the number of ranger spells you know.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Primal Awareness Spells</text>
        <text>Ranger Level | Spell</text>
        <text>3rd | speak with animals</text>
        <text>5th | beast sense</text>
        <text>9th | speak with plants</text>
        <text>13th | locate creature</text>
        <text>17th | commune with nature</text>
        <text>You can cast each of these spells once without expending a spell slot. Once you cast a spell in this way, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature>
          <name>Poultices</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you can create special herbal poultices that have healing power comparable to some potions. You can spend 1 hour gathering herbs and preparing herbal poultices using treated bandages to create a number of such poultices equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum 1). You can carry a number of poultices at one time equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum 1). The poultices you create cannot be applied by anyone but you. After 24 hours, any poultices that you have not used lose their potency.</text>
        <text>If you spend 1 minute applying one of your poultices to a wounded humanoid creature, thereby expending its use, that creature regains 1d6 hit points for every two ranger levels you have (rounded up).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 4th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>4th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>Note that this feature is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger feature.</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4">
        <feature>
          <name>Martial Versatility</name>
        <text>4th-level ranger optional class features</text>
        <text>Note that this feature is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger feature.</text>
        <text>Whenever you reach a level in this class that grants the Ability Score Improvement feature, you can replace a fighting style you know with another fighting style available to rangers. This replacement represents a shift of focus in your martial practice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
        <feature>
          <name>Extra Attack</name>
        <text>Beginning at 5th level, you can attack twice, instead of once, whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="5">
        <feature>
          <name>Additional Maneuvers</name>
        <text>At 5th level, you learn one additional maneuver of your choice, which is chosen from the list of maneuvers available to fighters with the Battle Master archetype.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature>
          <name>Favored Enemy and Natural Explorer improvements</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain an additional favored terrain.</text>
        <text>At 6th level, you choose one additional favored enemy, as well as an associated language. Your choice should reflect the types of monsters you have encountered on your adventures.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature>
          <name>Ranger Archetype feature</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain a feature granted to you by your Ranger Archetype.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Beast Master: Exceptional Training</name>
        <text>Beginning at 7th level, on any of your turns when your beast companion doesn't attack, you can use a bonus action to command the beast to take the Dash, Disengage, or Help action on its turn. In addition, the beast's attacks now count as magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Beast Master: Exceptional Training</name>
        <text>Beginning at 7th level, on any of your turns when your beast companion doesn't attack, you can use a bonus action to command the beast to take the Dash, Disengage, or Help action on its turn. In addition, the beast's attacks now count as magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Defensive Tactics</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain one of the following features of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Escape the Horde</name>
        <text>Opportunity attacks against you are made with disadvantage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Multiattack Defense</name>
        <text>When a creature hits you with an attack, you gain a +4 bonus to AC against all subsequent attacks made by that creature for the rest of the turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Steel Will</name>
        <text>You have advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Defensive Tactics</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain one of the following features of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Escape the Horde</name>
        <text>Opportunity attacks against you are made with disadvantage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Multiattack Defense</name>
        <text>When a creature hits you with an attack, you gain a +4 bonus to AC against all subsequent attacks made by that creature for the rest of the turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Steel Will</name>
        <text>You have advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Deep Stalker (UA): Iron Mind</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain proficiency in Wisdom saving throws.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Deep Stalker (UA): Iron Mind</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain proficiency in Wisdom saving throws.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Ethereal Step</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn to step through the Ethereal Plane. As a bonus action on your turn, you can cast the etherealness spell with this feature, but the spell ends at the end of the current turn. Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Ethereal Step</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn to step through the Ethereal Plane. As a bonus action on your turn, you can cast the etherealness spell with this feature, but the spell ends at the end of the current turn. Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Ethereal Step</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn to step through the Ethereal Plane. As a bonus action on your turn, you can cast the etherealness spell with this feature, but the spell ends at the end of the current turn. Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Ancient Fortitude</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain the endurance of the ancient forests. Your hit point maximum and current hit points increase by 2 per ranger level when you assume your guardian form. This increase lasts until you leave the form; your hit point maximum then returns to normal, but your current hit points remain the same, unless they must decrease to abide by your hit point maximum.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Ancient Fortitude</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain the endurance of the ancient forests. Your hit point maximum and current hit points increase by 2 per ranger level when you assume your guardian form. This increase lasts until you leave the form; your hit point maximum then returns to normal, but your current hit points remain the same, unless they must decrease to abide by your hit point maximum.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Ancient Fortitude</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain the endurance of the ancient forests. Your hit point maximum and current hit points increase by 2 per ranger level when you assume your guardian form. This increase lasts until you leave the form; your hit point maximum then returns to normal, but your current hit points remain the same, unless they must decrease to abide by your hit point maximum.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer (UA): Supernatural Defense</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain extra resilience against your prey's assaults on your mind and body. Whenever the target of your Slayer's Eye forces you to make a saving throw, add 1d6 to your roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer (UA): Supernatural Defense</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain extra resilience against your prey's assaults on your mind and body. Whenever the target of your Slayer's Eye forces you to make a saving throw, add 1d6 to your roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer (UA): Supernatural Defense</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain extra resilience against your prey's assaults on your mind and body. Whenever the target of your Slayer's Eye forces you to make a saving throw, add 1d6 to your roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Gloom Stalker: Iron Mind</name>
        <text>By 7th level, you have honed your ability to resist the mind-altering powers of your prey. You gain proficiency in Wisdom saving throws. If you already have this proficiency, you instead gain proficiency in Intelligence or Charisma saving throws (your choice).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Gloom Stalker: Iron Mind</name>
        <text>By 7th level, you have honed your ability to resist the mind-altering powers of your prey. You gain proficiency in Wisdom saving throws. If you already have this proficiency, you instead gain proficiency in Intelligence or Charisma saving throws (your choice).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Gloom Stalker: Iron Mind</name>
        <text>By 7th level, you have honed your ability to resist the mind-altering powers of your prey. You gain proficiency in Wisdom saving throws. If you already have this proficiency, you instead gain proficiency in Intelligence or Charisma saving throws (your choice).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker: Ethereal Step</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn to step through the Ethereal Plane. As a bonus action, you can cast the etherealness spell with this feature, without expending a spell slot, but the spell ends at the end of the current turn.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker: Ethereal Step</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn to step through the Ethereal Plane. As a bonus action, you can cast the etherealness spell with this feature, without expending a spell slot, but the spell ends at the end of the current turn.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker: Ethereal Step</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn to step through the Ethereal Plane. As a bonus action, you can cast the etherealness spell with this feature, without expending a spell slot, but the spell ends at the end of the current turn.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer: Supernatural Defense</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain extra resilience against your prey's assaults on your mind and body. Whenever the target of your Slayer's Prey forces you to make a saving throw and whenever you make an ability check to escape that target's grapple, add 1d6 to your roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer: Supernatural Defense</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain extra resilience against your prey's assaults on your mind and body. Whenever the target of your Slayer's Prey forces you to make a saving throw and whenever you make an ability check to escape that target's grapple, add 1d6 to your roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer: Supernatural Defense</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you gain extra resilience against your prey's assaults on your mind and body. Whenever the target of your Slayer's Prey forces you to make a saving throw and whenever you make an ability check to escape that target's grapple, add 1d6 to your roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Writhing Tide</name>
        <text>7th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>You can condense part of your swarm into a focused mass that lifts or sweeps you along. Whenever you activate your Gathered Swarm feature, choose one of the following additional benefits:</text>
        <text>• Your walking speed increases by 10 feet, and you can take the Disengage action as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>• You gain a climb speed equal to your walking speed. You can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without making an ability check.</text>
        <text>• You gain a flying speed of 10 feet and can hover.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Writhing Tide</name>
        <text>7th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>You can condense part of your swarm into a focused mass that lifts or sweeps you along. Whenever you activate your Gathered Swarm feature, choose one of the following additional benefits:</text>
        <text>• Your walking speed increases by 10 feet, and you can take the Disengage action as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>• You gain a climb speed equal to your walking speed. You can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without making an ability check.</text>
        <text>• You gain a flying speed of 10 feet and can hover.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Writhing Tide</name>
        <text>7th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>You can condense part of your swarm into a focused mass that lifts or sweeps you along. Whenever you activate your Gathered Swarm feature, choose one of the following additional benefits:</text>
        <text>• Your walking speed increases by 10 feet, and you can take the Disengage action as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>• You gain a climb speed equal to your walking speed. You can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without making an ability check.</text>
        <text>• You gain a flying speed of 10 feet and can hover.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Blessings of the Courts</name>
        <text>7th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You have learned eerie techniques from both the Gloaming Court and the Summer Court of the Feywild. Once during each of your turns, when you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can expend a spell slot to deal extra psychic damage. The extra damage is 3d6 psychic damage and the creature must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC or be frightened of you until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text>In addition, whenever you make a Charisma check, you gain a bonus to the check equal to your Wisdom modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Blessings of the Courts</name>
        <text>7th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You have learned eerie techniques from both the Gloaming Court and the Summer Court of the Feywild. Once during each of your turns, when you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can expend a spell slot to deal extra psychic damage. The extra damage is 3d6 psychic damage and the creature must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC or be frightened of you until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text>In addition, whenever you make a Charisma check, you gain a bonus to the check equal to your Wisdom modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Blessings of the Courts</name>
        <text>7th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You have learned eerie techniques from both the Gloaming Court and the Summer Court of the Feywild. Once during each of your turns, when you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can expend a spell slot to deal extra psychic damage. The extra damage is 3d6 psychic damage and the creature must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC or be frightened of you until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text>In addition, whenever you make a Charisma check, you gain a bonus to the check equal to your Wisdom modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Bond of Fang and Scale</name>
        <text>7th-level Drakewarden feature</text>
        <text>The bond you share with your drake intensifies, protecting you and stoking the drake's fury. While your drake is summoned, you and the drake gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• You gain resistance to the damage type chosen for the drake's Draconic Essence.</text>
        <text>• Choose one of the following: the drake gains a swimming speed of 40 feet and can breathe both air and water, or the drake grows wings and gains a flying speed of 40 feet.</text>
        <text>• The drake's bite attack deals an extra 1d6 damage of the type chosen for its Draconic Essence.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Bond of Fang and Scale</name>
        <text>7th-level Drakewarden feature</text>
        <text>The bond you share with your drake intensifies, protecting you and stoking the drake's fury. While your drake is summoned, you and the drake gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• You gain resistance to the damage type chosen for the drake's Draconic Essence.</text>
        <text>• Choose one of the following: the drake gains a swimming speed of 40 feet and can breathe both air and water, or the drake grows wings and gains a flying speed of 40 feet.</text>
        <text>• The drake's bite attack deals an extra 1d6 damage of the type chosen for its Draconic Essence.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Bond of Fang and Scale</name>
        <text>7th-level Drakewarden feature</text>
        <text>The bond you share with your drake intensifies, protecting you and stoking the drake's fury. While your drake is summoned, you and the drake gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• You gain resistance to the damage type chosen for the drake's Draconic Essence.</text>
        <text>• Choose one of the following: the drake gains a swimming speed of 40 feet and can breathe both air and water, or the drake grows wings and gains a flying speed of 40 feet.</text>
        <text>• The drake's bite attack deals an extra 1d6 damage of the type chosen for its Draconic Essence.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Beguiling Twist</name>
        <text>7th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>The magic of the Feywild guards your mind. You have advantage on saving throws against being charmed or frightened.</text>
        <text>In addition, whenever you or a creature you can see within 120 feet of you succeeds on a saving throw against being charmed or frightened, you can use your reaction to force a different creature you can see within 120 feet of you to make a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC. If the save fails, the target is charmed or frightened by you (your choice) for 1 minute. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a successful save.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Beguiling Twist</name>
        <text>7th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>The magic of the Feywild guards your mind. You have advantage on saving throws against being charmed or frightened.</text>
        <text>In addition, whenever you or a creature you can see within 120 feet of you succeeds on a saving throw against being charmed or frightened, you can use your reaction to force a different creature you can see within 120 feet of you to make a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC. If the save fails, the target is charmed or frightened by you (your choice) for 1 minute. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a successful save.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Beguiling Twist</name>
        <text>7th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>The magic of the Feywild guards your mind. You have advantage on saving throws against being charmed or frightened.</text>
        <text>In addition, whenever you or a creature you can see within 120 feet of you succeeds on a saving throw against being charmed or frightened, you can use your reaction to force a different creature you can see within 120 feet of you to make a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC. If the save fails, the target is charmed or frightened by you (your choice) for 1 minute. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a successful save.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper: Writhing Tide</name>
        <text>7th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>You can condense part of your swarm into a focused mass that lifts you up. As a bonus action, you gain a flying speed of 10 feet and can hover. This effect lasts for 1 minute or until you are incapacitated.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper: Writhing Tide</name>
        <text>7th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>You can condense part of your swarm into a focused mass that lifts you up. As a bonus action, you gain a flying speed of 10 feet and can hover. This effect lasts for 1 minute or until you are incapacitated.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper: Writhing Tide</name>
        <text>7th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>You can condense part of your swarm into a focused mass that lifts you up. As a bonus action, you gain a flying speed of 10 feet and can hover. This effect lasts for 1 minute or until you are incapacitated.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 8th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>8th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>Note that this feature is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger feature.</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
        <feature>
          <name>Land's Stride</name>
        <text>Starting at 8th level, moving through nonmagical difficult terrain costs you no extra movement. You can also pass through nonmagical plants without being slowed by them and without taking damage from them if they have thorns, spines, or a similar hazard.</text>
        <text>In addition, you have advantage on saving throws against plants that are magically created or manipulated to impede movement, such those created by the entangle spell.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
        <feature>
          <name>Natural Antivenom</name>
        <text>Starting at 9th level, you have advantage on saving throws against poison and have resistance to poison damage. Additionally, you can use one of your poultices to cure one poison effect on the creature you are applying it to, in addition to restoring hit points.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
        <feature>
          <name>Additional Maneuvers</name>
        <text>At 9th level, you learn one additional maneuver of your choice, which is chosen from the list of maneuvers available to fighters with the Battle Master archetype.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature>
          <name>Hide in Plain Sight</name>
        <text>Starting at 10th level, you can spend 1 minute creating camouflage for yourself. You must have access to fresh mud, dirt, plants, soot, and other naturally occurring materials with which to create your camouflage.</text>
        <text>Once you are camouflaged in this way, you can try to hide by pressing yourself up against a solid surface, such as a tree or wall, that is at least as tall and wide as you are. You gain a +10 bonus to Dexterity (Stealth) checks as long as you remain there without moving or taking actions. Once you move or take an action or a reaction, you must camouflage yourself again to gain this benefit.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature>
          <name>Fade Away</name>
        <text>10th-level ranger feature (replaces Hide in Plain Sight)</text>
        <text>Note that this feature is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger feature.</text>
        <text>You can use a bonus action to magically become invisible, along with any equipment you are wearing or carrying, until the start of your next turn.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 8</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature>
          <name>Nature's Veil</name>
        <text>10th-level ranger optional class features, which replaces the Hide in Plain Sight feature</text>
        <text>Note that this feature is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger feature.</text>
        <text>You draw on the powers of nature to hide yourself from view briefly. As a bonus action, you can magically become invisible, along with any equipment you are wearing or carrying, until the start of your next turn.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature>
          <name>Natural Explorer improvement</name>
        <text>You gain an additional favored terrain.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature>
          <name>Ranger Archetype feature</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain a feature granted to you by your Ranger Archetype.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Beast Master: Bestial Fury</name>
        <text>Starting at 11th level, when you command your beast companion to take the Attack action, the beast can make two attacks, or it can take the Multiattack action if it has that action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Beast Master: Bestial Fury</name>
        <text>Starting at 11th level, when you command your beast companion to take the Attack action, the beast can make two attacks, or it can take the Multiattack action if it has that action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Multiattack</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain one of the following features of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Volley</name>
        <text>You can use your action to make a ranged attack against any number of creatures within 10 feet of a point you can see within your weapon's range. You must have ammunition for each target, as normal, and you make a separate attack roll for each target.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Whirlwind Attack</name>
        <text>You can use your action to make a melee attack against any number of creatures within 5 feet of you, with a separate attack roll for each target.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Multiattack</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain one of the following features of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Volley</name>
        <text>You can use your action to make a ranged attack against any number of creatures within 10 feet of a point you can see within your weapon's range. You must have ammunition for each target, as normal, and you make a separate attack roll for each target.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Whirlwind Attack</name>
        <text>You can use your action to make a melee attack against any number of creatures within 5 feet of you, with a separate attack roll for each target.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Deep Stalker (UA): Stalker's Flurry</name>
        <text>Starting at 11th level, you have the ability to ensure that your attacks count. If you miss with an attack during your turn, you can immediately make an additional attack. You can gain one additional attack during your turn with this ability.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Deep Stalker (UA): Stalker's Flurry</name>
        <text>Starting at 11th level, you have the ability to ensure that your attacks count. If you miss with an attack during your turn, you can immediately make an additional attack. You can gain one additional attack during your turn with this ability.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Distant Strike</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to step between the planes in a blink of an eye. When you use the Attack action, you can teleport up to 10 feet before each attack. You must be able to see the destination of the teleportation.</text>
        <text>If you attack at least two different creatures with the action, you can make one additional attack with it against a third creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Distant Strike</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to step between the planes in a blink of an eye. When you use the Attack action, you can teleport up to 10 feet before each attack. You must be able to see the destination of the teleportation.</text>
        <text>If you attack at least two different creatures with the action, you can make one additional attack with it against a third creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Distant Strike</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to step between the planes in a blink of an eye. When you use the Attack action, you can teleport up to 10 feet before each attack. You must be able to see the destination of the teleportation.</text>
        <text>If you attack at least two different creatures with the action, you can make one additional attack with it against a third creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Rooted Defense</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to twist and turn the ground beneath you. While you are in your guardian form, the ground within 30 feet of you is difficult terrain for your enemies.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Rooted Defense</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to twist and turn the ground beneath you. While you are in your guardian form, the ground within 30 feet of you is difficult terrain for your enemies.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Rooted Defense</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to twist and turn the ground beneath you. While you are in your guardian form, the ground within 30 feet of you is difficult terrain for your enemies.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer (UA): Relentless Slayer</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to foil your foe's ability to escape. Your study of folklore and arcane knowledge gives you a key insight to keep your prey cornered. If the target of your Slayer's Eye attempts to teleport, change its shape, travel to another plane of existence, or turn gaseous, you can use your reaction to make a Wisdom check contested by a Wisdom check made by the target. To use this ability, you must be able to see the target and need to be within 30 feet of it. If you succeed, you foil its attempt, causing it to waste the action, bonus action, or reaction it used.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer (UA): Relentless Slayer</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to foil your foe's ability to escape. Your study of folklore and arcane knowledge gives you a key insight to keep your prey cornered. If the target of your Slayer's Eye attempts to teleport, change its shape, travel to another plane of existence, or turn gaseous, you can use your reaction to make a Wisdom check contested by a Wisdom check made by the target. To use this ability, you must be able to see the target and need to be within 30 feet of it. If you succeed, you foil its attempt, causing it to waste the action, bonus action, or reaction it used.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer (UA): Relentless Slayer</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to foil your foe's ability to escape. Your study of folklore and arcane knowledge gives you a key insight to keep your prey cornered. If the target of your Slayer's Eye attempts to teleport, change its shape, travel to another plane of existence, or turn gaseous, you can use your reaction to make a Wisdom check contested by a Wisdom check made by the target. To use this ability, you must be able to see the target and need to be within 30 feet of it. If you succeed, you foil its attempt, causing it to waste the action, bonus action, or reaction it used.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Gloom Stalker: Stalker's Flurry</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you learn to attack with such unexpected speed that you can turn a miss into another strike. Once on each of your turns when you miss with a weapon attack, you can make another weapon attack as part of the same action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Gloom Stalker: Stalker's Flurry</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you learn to attack with such unexpected speed that you can turn a miss into another strike. Once on each of your turns when you miss with a weapon attack, you can make another weapon attack as part of the same action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Gloom Stalker: Stalker's Flurry</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you learn to attack with such unexpected speed that you can turn a miss into another strike. Once on each of your turns when you miss with a weapon attack, you can make another weapon attack as part of the same action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker: Distant Strike</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to pass between the planes in the blink of an eye. When you take the Attack action, you can teleport up to 10 feet before each attack to an unoccupied space you can see.</text>
        <text>If you attack at least two different creatures with the action, you can make one additional attack with it against a third creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker: Distant Strike</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to pass between the planes in the blink of an eye. When you take the Attack action, you can teleport up to 10 feet before each attack to an unoccupied space you can see.</text>
        <text>If you attack at least two different creatures with the action, you can make one additional attack with it against a third creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker: Distant Strike</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to pass between the planes in the blink of an eye. When you take the Attack action, you can teleport up to 10 feet before each attack to an unoccupied space you can see.</text>
        <text>If you attack at least two different creatures with the action, you can make one additional attack with it against a third creature.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer: Magic-User's Nemesis</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to thwart someone else's magic. When you see a creature casting a spell or teleporting within 60 feet of you, you can use your reaction to try to magically foil it. The creature must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC, or its spell or teleport fails and is wasted.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer: Magic-User's Nemesis</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to thwart someone else's magic. When you see a creature casting a spell or teleporting within 60 feet of you, you can use your reaction to try to magically foil it. The creature must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC, or its spell or teleport fails and is wasted.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer: Magic-User's Nemesis</name>
        <text>At 11th level, you gain the ability to thwart someone else's magic. When you see a creature casting a spell or teleporting within 60 feet of you, you can use your reaction to try to magically foil it. The creature must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC, or its spell or teleport fails and is wasted.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Gathered Swarm Improvement</name>
        <text>11th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>The extra damage from your swarm increases to 2d6.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Scuttling Eyes</name>
        <text>11th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>As an action, you can magically form one of the spirits of your swarm into the shape of a Tiny beast of your choice. The transformation lasts for 1 hour, at which point the spirit disappears. For the duration, the spirit has a speed of 40 feet, which it can use to walk, climb, fly, or swim. The spirit has your senses and telepathically relays what it sees and hears to you. During your turn, you can speak through the spirit, telepathically command it to move, and it can Hide using your bonus to Dexterity (Stealth) checks. The spirit has AC 18. If it takes damage, you must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw (DC equal to 10, or half the damage dealt, whichever is higher) or the spirit disappears.</text>
        <text>As an action, you can dismiss the spirit early. If you do, you can magically teleport to an unoccupied space within 5 feet of where the spirit disappeared.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest. You can also use it again by expending a spell slot of 3rd level or higher.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Gathered Swarm Improvement</name>
        <text>11th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>The extra damage from your swarm increases to 2d6.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Scuttling Eyes</name>
        <text>11th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>As an action, you can magically form one of the spirits of your swarm into the shape of a Tiny beast of your choice. The transformation lasts for 1 hour, at which point the spirit disappears. For the duration, the spirit has a speed of 40 feet, which it can use to walk, climb, fly, or swim. The spirit has your senses and telepathically relays what it sees and hears to you. During your turn, you can speak through the spirit, telepathically command it to move, and it can Hide using your bonus to Dexterity (Stealth) checks. The spirit has AC 18. If it takes damage, you must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw (DC equal to 10, or half the damage dealt, whichever is higher) or the spirit disappears.</text>
        <text>As an action, you can dismiss the spirit early. If you do, you can magically teleport to an unoccupied space within 5 feet of where the spirit disappeared.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest. You can also use it again by expending a spell slot of 3rd level or higher.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Gathered Swarm Improvement</name>
        <text>11th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>The extra damage from your swarm increases to 2d6.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Scuttling Eyes</name>
        <text>11th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>As an action, you can magically form one of the spirits of your swarm into the shape of a Tiny beast of your choice. The transformation lasts for 1 hour, at which point the spirit disappears. For the duration, the spirit has a speed of 40 feet, which it can use to walk, climb, fly, or swim. The spirit has your senses and telepathically relays what it sees and hears to you. During your turn, you can speak through the spirit, telepathically command it to move, and it can Hide using your bonus to Dexterity (Stealth) checks. The spirit has AC 18. If it takes damage, you must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw (DC equal to 10, or half the damage dealt, whichever is higher) or the spirit disappears.</text>
        <text>As an action, you can dismiss the spirit early. If you do, you can magically teleport to an unoccupied space within 5 feet of where the spirit disappeared.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest. You can also use it again by expending a spell slot of 3rd level or higher.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Beguiling Twist</name>
        <text>11th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You learn how to manipulate mind-altering magic, channeling it from your allies toward others. Whenever a creature you can see within 120 feet of you succeeds on a saving throw against being charmed or frightened, you can use your reaction to force a different creature you can see within 120 feet of you to succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC or suffer your choice of one of the following effects:</text>
        <text>• The creature is charmed or frightened by you (your choice) for 1 minute. The creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a successful save.</text>
        <text>• The creature takes 3d10 psychic damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Beguiling Twist</name>
        <text>11th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You learn how to manipulate mind-altering magic, channeling it from your allies toward others. Whenever a creature you can see within 120 feet of you succeeds on a saving throw against being charmed or frightened, you can use your reaction to force a different creature you can see within 120 feet of you to succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC or suffer your choice of one of the following effects:</text>
        <text>• The creature is charmed or frightened by you (your choice) for 1 minute. The creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a successful save.</text>
        <text>• The creature takes 3d10 psychic damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Beguiling Twist</name>
        <text>11th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You learn how to manipulate mind-altering magic, channeling it from your allies toward others. Whenever a creature you can see within 120 feet of you succeeds on a saving throw against being charmed or frightened, you can use your reaction to force a different creature you can see within 120 feet of you to succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC or suffer your choice of one of the following effects:</text>
        <text>• The creature is charmed or frightened by you (your choice) for 1 minute. The creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a successful save.</text>
        <text>• The creature takes 3d10 psychic damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Drake's Breath</name>
        <text>11th-level Drakewarden feature</text>
        <text>As an action, you can exhale a 30-foot cone of damaging breath or cause your drake to exhale it. Choose acid, cold, fire, lightning, or poison damage. Each creature in the cone must make a Dexterity saving throw against your spell save DC, taking 6d6 damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
        <text>This damage increases to 8d6 when you reach 15th level in this class.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend a spell slot of 3rd level or higher to use it again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Drake's Breath</name>
        <text>11th-level Drakewarden feature</text>
        <text>As an action, you can exhale a 30-foot cone of damaging breath or cause your drake to exhale it. Choose acid, cold, fire, lightning, or poison damage. Each creature in the cone must make a Dexterity saving throw against your spell save DC, taking 6d6 damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
        <text>This damage increases to 8d6 when you reach 15th level in this class.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend a spell slot of 3rd level or higher to use it again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Drake's Breath</name>
        <text>11th-level Drakewarden feature</text>
        <text>As an action, you can exhale a 30-foot cone of damaging breath or cause your drake to exhale it. Choose acid, cold, fire, lightning, or poison damage. Each creature in the cone must make a Dexterity saving throw against your spell save DC, taking 6d6 damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
        <text>This damage increases to 8d6 when you reach 15th level in this class.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend a spell slot of 3rd level or higher to use it again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Fey Reinforcements</name>
        <text>11th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>The royal courts of the Feywild have blessed you with the assistance of fey beings: you know summon fey. It doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know, and you can cast it without a material component. You can also cast it once without a spell slot, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>Whenever you start casting the spell, you can modify it so that it doesn't require concentration. If you do so, the spell's duration becomes 1 minute for that casting.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Fey Reinforcements</name>
        <text>11th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>The royal courts of the Feywild have blessed you with the assistance of fey beings: you know summon fey. It doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know, and you can cast it without a material component. You can also cast it once without a spell slot, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>Whenever you start casting the spell, you can modify it so that it doesn't require concentration. If you do so, the spell's duration becomes 1 minute for that casting.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Fey Reinforcements</name>
        <text>11th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>The royal courts of the Feywild have blessed you with the assistance of fey beings: you know summon fey. It doesn't count against the number of ranger spells you know, and you can cast it without a material component. You can also cast it once without a spell slot, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>Whenever you start casting the spell, you can modify it so that it doesn't require concentration. If you do so, the spell's duration becomes 1 minute for that casting.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper: Mighty Swarm</name>
        <text>11th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>Your Gathered Swarm grows mightier in the following ways:</text>
        <text>• The damage of Gathered Swarm increases to 1d8.</text>
        <text>• If a creature fails its saving throw against being moved by Gathered Swarm, you can also cause the swarm to knock the creature prone.</text>
        <text>• When you are moved by Gathered Swarm, it gives you half cover until the start of your next turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper: Mighty Swarm</name>
        <text>11th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>Your Gathered Swarm grows mightier in the following ways:</text>
        <text>• The damage of Gathered Swarm increases to 1d8.</text>
        <text>• If a creature fails its saving throw against being moved by Gathered Swarm, you can also cause the swarm to knock the creature prone.</text>
        <text>• When you are moved by Gathered Swarm, it gives you half cover until the start of your next turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper: Mighty Swarm</name>
        <text>11th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>Your Gathered Swarm grows mightier in the following ways:</text>
        <text>• The damage of Gathered Swarm increases to 1d8.</text>
        <text>• If a creature fails its saving throw against being moved by Gathered Swarm, you can also cause the swarm to knock the creature prone.</text>
        <text>• When you are moved by Gathered Swarm, it gives you half cover until the start of your next turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 12th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="12">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>12th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>Note that this feature is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger feature.</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
        <feature>
          <name>Call Natural Allies</name>
        <text>Starting at 13th level, when you are in an area of your favored terrain, you can call natural creatures from that terrain to fight on your behalf, using your attunement to the natural world to convince them to aid you. The DM chooses beasts appropriate to the terrain to come to your aid from among those that could hear you and that are within 1 mile of you, in one of the following groups:</text>
        <text>• One beast of challenge rating 2 or lower</text>
        <text>• Two beasts of challenge rating 1 or lower</text>
        <text>• Four beasts of challenge rating 1/2 or lower</text>
        <text>• Eight beasts of challenge rating 1/4 or lower</text>
        <text>These beasts approach you from their current location, and will fight alongside you, attacking any creatures that are hostile to you. They are friendly to you and your comrades, and you roll initiative for the called creatures as a group, which takes its own turns. The DM has the creatures' statistics.</text>
        <text>After 1 hour, these beasts return to their previous location. Once you use this feature, you cannot use it again in the same general area for 24 hours, since the same animals will not repeatedly heed your call.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
        <feature>
          <name>Additional Maneuvers</name>
        <text>At 13th level, you learn one additional maneuver of your choice, which is chosen from the list of maneuvers available to fighters with the Battle Master archetype.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature>
          <name>Vanish</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, you can use the Hide action as a bonus action on your turn. Also, you can't be tracked by nonmagical means, unless you choose to leave a trail.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature>
          <name>Favored Enemy improvement</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you choose one additional favored enemy, as well as an associated language. Your choice should reflect the types of monsters you have encountered on your adventures.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature>
          <name>Ranger Archetype feature</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you gain a feature granted to you by your Ranger Archetype.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Beast Master: Share Spells</name>
        <text>Beginning at 15th level, when you cast a spell targeting yourself, you can also affect your beast companion with the spell if the beast is within 30 feet of you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Beast Master: Beastly Coordination</name>
        <text>Beginning at 15th level, when an attacker that you can see hits your beast companion with an attack, you can call out a warning. If your beast companion can hear you, it can use its reaction to halve the attack's damage against it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Evasion</name>
        <text>You can nimbly dodge out of the way of certain area effects, such as a red dragon's fiery breath or a lightning bolt spell. When you are subjected to an effect that allows you to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, you instead take no damage if you succeed on the saving throw, and only half damage if you fail.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Stand Against the Tide</name>
        <text>When a hostile creature misses you with a melee attack, you can use your reaction to force that creature to repeat the same attack against another creature (other than itself) of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Superior Hunter's Defense</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you gain one of the following features of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Uncanny Dodge</name>
        <text>When an attacker that you can see hits you with an attack, you can use your reaction to halve the attack's damage against you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Evasion</name>
        <text>You can nimbly dodge out of the way of certain area effects, such as a red dragon's fiery breath or a lightning bolt spell. When you are subjected to an effect that allows you to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, you instead take no damage if you succeed on the saving throw, and only half damage if you fail.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Stand Against the Tide</name>
        <text>When a hostile creature misses you with a melee attack, you can use your reaction to force that creature to repeat the same attack against another creature (other than itself) of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Superior Hunter's Defense</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you gain one of the following features of your choice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Hunter: Uncanny Dodge</name>
        <text>When an attacker that you can see hits you with an attack, you can use your reaction to halve the attack's damage against you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Player's Handbook p. 93</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Deep Stalker (UA): Stalker's Dodge</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you master the ability to disrupt an opponent's attacks. If a creature attacks you and does not have advantage on the attack roll, you can use your reaction to grant it disadvantage on the attack roll. You must use this ability before you know the result of the attack.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Deep Stalker (UA): Stalker's Dodge</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you master the ability to disrupt an opponent's attacks. If a creature attacks you and does not have advantage on the attack roll, you can use your reaction to grant it disadvantage on the attack roll. You must use this ability before you know the result of the attack.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Light Dark Underdark p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Spectral Defense</name>
        <text>At 15th level, your ability to move between planes becomes even more finely tuned. As a reaction when you take damage, you can halve that damage against you. For a moment, you slip into the planar boundary to lessen the harm.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Spectral Defense</name>
        <text>At 15th level, your ability to move between planes becomes even more finely tuned. As a reaction when you take damage, you can halve that damage against you. For a moment, you slip into the planar boundary to lessen the harm.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker (UA): Spectral Defense</name>
        <text>At 15th level, your ability to move between planes becomes even more finely tuned. As a reaction when you take damage, you can halve that damage against you. For a moment, you slip into the planar boundary to lessen the harm.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Guardian Aura</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, your guardian form emanates a magical aura that fortifies your injured allies. When any ally starts their turn within 30 feet of your guardian form, that ally regains a number of hit points equal to half your ranger level. This aura has no effect on a creature that has half or more of its hit points, and it has no effect on undead and constructs.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Guardian Aura</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, your guardian form emanates a magical aura that fortifies your injured allies. When any ally starts their turn within 30 feet of your guardian form, that ally regains a number of hit points equal to half your ranger level. This aura has no effect on a creature that has half or more of its hit points, and it has no effect on undead and constructs.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Primeval Guardian (UA): Guardian Aura</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, your guardian form emanates a magical aura that fortifies your injured allies. When any ally starts their turn within 30 feet of your guardian form, that ally regains a number of hit points equal to half your ranger level. This aura has no effect on a creature that has half or more of its hit points, and it has no effect on undead and constructs.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Ranger And Rogue p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer (UA): Slayer's Counter</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you gain the ability to counterattack when your prey tries to sabotage you. If the target of your Slayer's Eye forces you to make a saving throw, you can use your reaction to make one weapon attack against it. You make this attack immediately before making the saving throw. If the attack hits, your save automatically succeeds, in addition to the attack's normal effects.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer (UA): Slayer's Counter</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you gain the ability to counterattack when your prey tries to sabotage you. If the target of your Slayer's Eye forces you to make a saving throw, you can use your reaction to make one weapon attack against it. You make this attack immediately before making the saving throw. If the attack hits, your save automatically succeeds, in addition to the attack's normal effects.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer (UA): Slayer's Counter</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you gain the ability to counterattack when your prey tries to sabotage you. If the target of your Slayer's Eye forces you to make a saving throw, you can use your reaction to make one weapon attack against it. You make this attack immediately before making the saving throw. If the attack hits, your save automatically succeeds, in addition to the attack's normal effects.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: A Trio Of Subclasses p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Gloom Stalker: Shadowy Dodge</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, you can dodge in unforeseen ways, with wisps of supernatural shadow around you. Whenever a creature makes an attack roll against you and doesn't have advantage on the roll, you can use your reaction to impose disadvantage on it. You must use this feature before you know the outcome of the attack roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Gloom Stalker: Shadowy Dodge</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, you can dodge in unforeseen ways, with wisps of supernatural shadow around you. Whenever a creature makes an attack roll against you and doesn't have advantage on the roll, you can use your reaction to impose disadvantage on it. You must use this feature before you know the outcome of the attack roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Gloom Stalker: Shadowy Dodge</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, you can dodge in unforeseen ways, with wisps of supernatural shadow around you. Whenever a creature makes an attack roll against you and doesn't have advantage on the roll, you can use your reaction to impose disadvantage on it. You must use this feature before you know the outcome of the attack roll.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 41</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker: Spectral Defense</name>
        <text>At 15th level, your ability to move between planes enables you to slip through the planar boundaries to lessen the harm done to you during battle. When you take damage from an attack, you can use your reaction to give yourself resistance to all of that attack's damage on this turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker: Spectral Defense</name>
        <text>At 15th level, your ability to move between planes enables you to slip through the planar boundaries to lessen the harm done to you during battle. When you take damage from an attack, you can use your reaction to give yourself resistance to all of that attack's damage on this turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Horizon Walker: Spectral Defense</name>
        <text>At 15th level, your ability to move between planes enables you to slip through the planar boundaries to lessen the harm done to you during battle. When you take damage from an attack, you can use your reaction to give yourself resistance to all of that attack's damage on this turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 42</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer: Slayer's Counter</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you gain the ability to counterattack when your prey tries to sabotage you. If the target of your Slayer's Prey forces you to make a saving throw, you can use your reaction to make one weapon attack against the quarry. You make this attack immediately before making the saving throw. If your attack hits, your save automatically succeeds, in addition to the attack's normal effects.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer: Slayer's Counter</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you gain the ability to counterattack when your prey tries to sabotage you. If the target of your Slayer's Prey forces you to make a saving throw, you can use your reaction to make one weapon attack against the quarry. You make this attack immediately before making the saving throw. If your attack hits, your save automatically succeeds, in addition to the attack's normal effects.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monster Slayer: Slayer's Counter</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you gain the ability to counterattack when your prey tries to sabotage you. If the target of your Slayer's Prey forces you to make a saving throw, you can use your reaction to make one weapon attack against the quarry. You make this attack immediately before making the saving throw. If your attack hits, your save automatically succeeds, in addition to the attack's normal effects.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 43</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Storm of Minions</name>
        <text>15th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>Your swarm can expel a seething storm of spirits that drains life from others. As an action, you create a magical sphere filled with an enraged swarm centered on a point you can see within 120 feet of you. The sphere has a 10-foot-radius and lasts for 1 minute. The sphere is difficult terrain for creatures other than you. A creature other than you that starts its turn in the sphere's area must make a Constitution saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, the creature takes 2d8 necrotic damage and is blinded until the start of its next turn. On a successful save, it takes half as much damage and isn't blinded. At the start of your turn, if any number of Small or larger creatures took necrotic damage from the swarm, you regain 1d8 hit points. On subsequent turns, you can use a bonus action to move the sphere up to 30 feet.</text>
        <text>When you activate this feature, you can choose any number of creatures you can see to be unaffected by it.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest. You can also use it again by expending a spell slot of 4th level or higher.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Storm of Minions</name>
        <text>15th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>Your swarm can expel a seething storm of spirits that drains life from others. As an action, you create a magical sphere filled with an enraged swarm centered on a point you can see within 120 feet of you. The sphere has a 10-foot-radius and lasts for 1 minute. The sphere is difficult terrain for creatures other than you. A creature other than you that starts its turn in the sphere's area must make a Constitution saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, the creature takes 2d8 necrotic damage and is blinded until the start of its next turn. On a successful save, it takes half as much damage and isn't blinded. At the start of your turn, if any number of Small or larger creatures took necrotic damage from the swarm, you regain 1d8 hit points. On subsequent turns, you can use a bonus action to move the sphere up to 30 feet.</text>
        <text>When you activate this feature, you can choose any number of creatures you can see to be unaffected by it.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest. You can also use it again by expending a spell slot of 4th level or higher.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper (UA): Storm of Minions</name>
        <text>15th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>Your swarm can expel a seething storm of spirits that drains life from others. As an action, you create a magical sphere filled with an enraged swarm centered on a point you can see within 120 feet of you. The sphere has a 10-foot-radius and lasts for 1 minute. The sphere is difficult terrain for creatures other than you. A creature other than you that starts its turn in the sphere's area must make a Constitution saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, the creature takes 2d8 necrotic damage and is blinded until the start of its next turn. On a successful save, it takes half as much damage and isn't blinded. At the start of your turn, if any number of Small or larger creatures took necrotic damage from the swarm, you regain 1d8 hit points. On subsequent turns, you can use a bonus action to move the sphere up to 30 feet.</text>
        <text>When you activate this feature, you can choose any number of creatures you can see to be unaffected by it.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest. You can also use it again by expending a spell slot of 4th level or higher.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 3</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Misty Presence</name>
        <text>15th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You can magically remove yourself from one creature's perception: you gain a bonus action that you can use to force a creature you can see within 30 feet of you to make a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, the target can't see or hear you for 24 hours. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of any turn during which you hit it with an attack roll, forced it to make a saving throw, or dealt damage to it. The effect ends early if you use this bonus action again. On a successful save, the target is immune to this feature for 7 days.</text>
        <text>Once you've used this bonus action, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest or until you expend a spell slot of 4th level or higher to use it again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Misty Presence</name>
        <text>15th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You can magically remove yourself from one creature's perception: you gain a bonus action that you can use to force a creature you can see within 30 feet of you to make a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, the target can't see or hear you for 24 hours. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of any turn during which you hit it with an attack roll, forced it to make a saving throw, or dealt damage to it. The effect ends early if you use this bonus action again. On a successful save, the target is immune to this feature for 7 days.</text>
        <text>Once you've used this bonus action, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest or until you expend a spell slot of 4th level or higher to use it again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer (UA): Misty Presence</name>
        <text>15th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You can magically remove yourself from one creature's perception: you gain a bonus action that you can use to force a creature you can see within 30 feet of you to make a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, the target can't see or hear you for 24 hours. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of any turn during which you hit it with an attack roll, forced it to make a saving throw, or dealt damage to it. The effect ends early if you use this bonus action again. On a successful save, the target is immune to this feature for 7 days.</text>
        <text>Once you've used this bonus action, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest or until you expend a spell slot of 4th level or higher to use it again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt3 p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Perfected Bond</name>
        <text>15th-level Drakewarden feature</text>
        <text>Your bond to your drake reaches the pinnacle of its power. While your drake is summoned, you and the drake gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• The drake grows to Large size.</text>
        <text>• The drake's bite attack deals an extra 1d6 damage of the type chosen for its Draconic Essence (for a total of 2d6 extra damage).</text>
        <text>• When either you or the drake takes damage while you're within 30 feet of each other, you can use your reaction to give yourself or the drake resistance to that instance of damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Perfected Bond</name>
        <text>15th-level Drakewarden feature</text>
        <text>Your bond to your drake reaches the pinnacle of its power. While your drake is summoned, you and the drake gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• The drake grows to Large size.</text>
        <text>• The drake's bite attack deals an extra 1d6 damage of the type chosen for its Draconic Essence (for a total of 2d6 extra damage).</text>
        <text>• When either you or the drake takes damage while you're within 30 feet of each other, you can use your reaction to give yourself or the drake resistance to that instance of damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Drakewarden (UA): Perfected Bond</name>
        <text>15th-level Drakewarden feature</text>
        <text>Your bond to your drake reaches the pinnacle of its power. While your drake is summoned, you and the drake gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• The drake grows to Large size.</text>
        <text>• The drake's bite attack deals an extra 1d6 damage of the type chosen for its Draconic Essence (for a total of 2d6 extra damage).</text>
        <text>• When either you or the drake takes damage while you're within 30 feet of each other, you can use your reaction to give yourself or the drake resistance to that instance of damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: 2020 Subclasses Pt5 p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Misty Wanderer</name>
        <text>15th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You can slip in and out of the Feywild to move in a blink of an eye: you can cast misty step without expending a spell slot. You can do so a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>In addition, whenever you cast misty step, you can bring along one willing creature you can see within 5 feet of you. That creature teleports to an unoccupied space of your choice within 5 feet of your destination space.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Misty Wanderer</name>
        <text>15th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You can slip in and out of the Feywild to move in a blink of an eye: you can cast misty step without expending a spell slot. You can do so a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>In addition, whenever you cast misty step, you can bring along one willing creature you can see within 5 feet of you. That creature teleports to an unoccupied space of your choice within 5 feet of your destination space.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Fey Wanderer: Misty Wanderer</name>
        <text>15th-level Fey Wanderer feature</text>
        <text>You can slip in and out of the Feywild to move in a blink of an eye: you can cast misty step without expending a spell slot. You can do so a number of times equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of once), and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>In addition, whenever you cast misty step, you can bring along one willing creature you can see within 5 feet of you. That creature teleports to an unoccupied space of your choice within 5 feet of your destination space.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper: Swarming Dispersal</name>
        <text>15th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>You can discorporate into your swarm, avoiding danger. When you take damage, you can use your reaction to give yourself resistance to that damage. You vanish into your swarm and then teleport to an unoccupied space that you can see within 30 feet of you, where you reappear with the swarm.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper: Swarming Dispersal</name>
        <text>15th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>You can discorporate into your swarm, avoiding danger. When you take damage, you can use your reaction to give yourself resistance to that damage. You vanish into your swarm and then teleport to an unoccupied space that you can see within 30 feet of you, where you reappear with the swarm.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Swarmkeeper: Swarming Dispersal</name>
        <text>15th-level Swarmkeeper feature</text>
        <text>You can discorporate into your swarm, avoiding danger. When you take damage, you can use your reaction to give yourself resistance to that damage. You vanish into your swarm and then teleport to an unoccupied space that you can see within 30 feet of you, where you reappear with the swarm.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 16th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="16">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>16th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>Note that this feature is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger feature.</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature>
          <name>Relentless</name>
        <text>Starting at 17th level, when you roll initiative and have no superiority dice remaining, you regain 1 superiority die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature>
          <name>Additional Maneuvers</name>
        <text>At 17th level, you learn one additional maneuver of your choice, which is chosen from the list of maneuvers available to fighters with the Battle Master archetype.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature>
          <name>Feral Senses</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you gain preternatural senses that help you fight creatures you can't see. When you attack a creature you can't see, your inability to see it doesn't impose disadvantage on your attack rolls against it. You are also aware of the location of any invisible creature within 30 feet of you, provided that the creature isn't hidden from you and you aren't blinded or deafened.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19" scoreImprovement="YES">
        <feature>
          <name>Ability Score Improvement</name>
        <text>When you reach 19th level, you can increase one ability score of your choice by 2, or you can increase two ability scores of your choice by 1. As normal, you can't increase an ability score above 20 using this feature.</text>
        <text>If your DM allows the use of feats, you may instead take a feat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="19">
        <feature>
          <name>Proficiency Versatility</name>
        <text>19th-level feature (enhances Ability Score Improvement)</text>
        <text>Note that this feature is intended for use with the Ranger class presented in the Player's Handbook. It is presented here for convenience, and may be unsuitable for use as a Spell-less Ranger feature.</text>
        <text>When you gain the Ability Score Improvement feature from your class, you can also replace one of your skill proficiencies with a skill proficiency offered by your class at 1st level (the proficiency you replace needn't be from the class).</text>
        <text>This change represents one of your skills atrophying as you focus on a different skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Class Feature Variants p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
        <feature>
          <name>Foe Slayer</name>
        <text>At 20th level, you become an unparalleled hunter of your enemies. Once on each of your turns, you can add your Wisdom modifier to the attack roll or the damage roll of an attack you make against one of your favored enemies. You can choose to use this feature before or after the roll, but before any effects of the roll are applied.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modifying Classes p. 5</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
