<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Bard</name>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Swords v2 (UA): College of Swords v2</name>
        <text>Bards of the College of Swords are called blades, and they entertain through daring feats of weapon prowess. Blades perform stunts such as sword swallowing, knife throwing and juggling, and mock combats. But though they use their weapons to entertain, they are also highly trained and skilled warriors in their own right.</text>
        <text>Their talent with weapons inspires many blades to lead double lives. One blade might use a circus troupe as cover for nefarious deeds such as assassination, robbery, and blackmail. Other blades strike at the wicked, bringing justice to bear against the cruel and powerful. Most troupes are happy to accept a blade's talent for the excitement it adds to a performance, but few entertainers fully trust them.</text>
        <text>Blades who abandon lives as entertainers have often run into trouble that makes maintaining their secret activities impossible. A blade caught stealing or engaging in vigilante justice is too great a liability for most performer troupes. With their weapon skills as their greatest asset, these blades either take up work as enforcers for thieves' guilds or strike out on their own as adventurers.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Swords v2 (UA): Blade Flourish</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn to conduct impressive displays of skill with your weapons. As a standard action, you can make a standard melee attack and increase your walking speed by 10 feet until the end of the current turn. Whenever you use this option, you can also use one of the following Blade Flourish options with it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Defensive Flourish</text>
        <text>   You spin your weapon around you in swift circles, creating a hypnotic display. You can expend one of your uses of Bardic Inspiration, rolling a Bardic Inspiration die and applying the number rolled as a bonus to your AC until the start of your next turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Slashing Flourish</text>
        <text>   If the attack hits its target, you can expend one of your uses of Bardic Inspiration to cause the weapon to damage each creature of your choice, other than the target, that you can see within 5 feet of you. The damage equals the number you roll on the Bardic Inspiration die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Mobile Flourish</text>
        <text>   If the attack hits its target, you can expend one of your uses of Bardic Inspiration to push the target up to 5 feet away from you, plus a number of feet equal to the number you roll on the Bardic Inspiration die. You can then immediately use your reaction to move up to your speed to an unoccupied space within 5 feet of the target.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Swords v2 (UA): Bonus Proficiencies</name>
        <text>When you join the College of Blades at 3rd level, you gain proficiency with medium armor and with scimitars. If you are proficient with a simple or martial melee weapon, you can use it as a spellcasting focus for your Bard spells.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Swords v2 (UA): Fighting Style</name>
        <text>The College of Blades emphasizes mastery with weapons, granting you access to either the dueling or two-weapon fighting option for the Fighting Style class feature, which are as follows.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Swords v2 (UA): Cunning Flourish</name>
        <text>Beginning at 6th level, you can attack twice, instead of once, whenever you take the Blade Flourish action on your turn. You can, nevertheless, only use one Blade Flourish option when you take that action.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Swords v2 (UA): Master's Flourish</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, whenever you use a Blade Flourish option, you can roll a d6 and use it instead of expending a Bardic Inspiration die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 1</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
