<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Fighter</name>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Arcane Archer v2</name>
        <text>An Arcane Archer studies a unique elven method of archery that weaves magic into attacks to produce supernatural effects. Among elves, Arcane Archers are some of their most elite warriors. These archers stand watch over the fringes of elven domains, keeping a keen eye out for trespassers and using magic-infused arrows to defeat monsters and invaders before they can reach elven settlements. Over the centuries, the methods of these elf archers have been learned by members of other races who can also balance arcane aptitude with archery.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Arcane Arrow</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn to unleash special magical effects with some of your shots. When you gain this feature, you learn two Arcane Shot options of your choice (see the "Arcane Shot Options" section below).</text>
        <text>Once per turn when you fire a magic arrow from a shortbow or longbow as part of the Attack action, you can apply one of your Arcane Shot options to that arrow. You decide to use the option when the arrow hits, unless the option doesn't involve an attack roll. You have two uses of this ability, and you regain all expended uses of it when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>You gain an additional Arcane Shot option of your choice when you reach certain levels in this class: 7th, 10th, 15th, and 18th level. Each option also improves when you become an 18th-level fighter.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Arcane Shot</name>
        <text>The Arcane Shot feature lets you choose options for it at certain levels. The options are presented here in alphabetical order. They are all magical effects, and each one is associated with one of the schools of magic.</text>
        <text>If an option requires a saving throw, your Arcane Shot save DC equals 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Intelligence modifier.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Archer's Lore</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn magical theory or some of the secrets of nature—typical for practitioners of this elven martial tradition. You gain proficiency in either the Arcana or Nature skill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Magic Arrow</name>
        <text>When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you gain the ability to infuse arrows with magic. Whenever you fire a nonmagical arrow from a shortbow or longbow, you can make it a magic arrow, with a +1 bonus to the attack and damage rolls. The magic fades from the arrow immediately after it hits or misses its target.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Curving Shot</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn how to direct an errant arrow toward a new target. When you make an attack roll with a magic arrow and miss, you can use a bonus action to reroll the attack roll against a different target within 60 feet of the original target.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Extra Arcane Shot</name>
        <text>At 7th level, you learn an additional Arcane Shot option.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Extra Arcane Shot</name>
        <text>At 10th level, you learn an additional Arcane Shot option.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Ever-Ready Shot</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, your magical archery is ever available to you when you need it most. If you roll initiative and have no uses of Arcane Shot remaining, you regain one use of it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Extra Arcane Shot</name>
        <text>At 15th level, you learn an additional Arcane Shot option.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="18">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Archer v2 (UA): Extra Arcane Shot</name>
        <text>At 18th level, you learn an additional Arcane Shot option.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Subclasses p. 2</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
