<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Aspect of the Moon (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Pact of the Tome</prerequisite>
    <text>You no longer need to sleep and can't be forced to sleep by any means. To gain the benefits of a long rest, you can spend all 8 hours doing light activity, such as reading your Book of Shadows and keeping watch.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Cloak of Flies (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>5th level</prerequisite>
    <text>As a bonus action, you can surround yourself with a magical aura that looks like buzzing flies. The aura includes your space, extends 5 feet from you in every direction, and is blocked by total cover. It lasts until you're incapacitated or you dismiss it with a bonus action.
The aura grants you advantage on Charisma (Intimidation) checks but disadvantage on all other Charisma checks. Any other creature that starts its turn in the aura takes poison damage equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of 0 damage).
Once you use this invocation, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 5</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Maneuver: Control Mount (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Maneuver: Cavalier V2 (UA)
When you make a Wisdom (Animal Handling) check to influence a creature that you or an ally is riding, you can expend one superiority die, roll it, and add the number rolled to the check. You can do this before or after rolling the d20, but before applying the results of the check.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 3</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Eldritch Smite (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>5th level, Pact of the Blade</prerequisite>
    <text>Once per turn when you hit a creature with your pact weapon, you can expend a warlock spell slot to deal an extra 1d8 force damage to the target, plus another 1d8 per level of the spell slot. If the target takes any of this damage, you can knock the target prone if it is Huge or smaller.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 6</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Frost Lance (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Eldritch Blast cantrip</prerequisite>
    <text>Once on each of your turns when you hit a creature with your eldritch blast, you can reduce that creature's speed by 10 feet until the end of your next turn.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 6</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Ghostly Gaze (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>7th level</prerequisite>
    <text>As an action, you gain the ability to see through solid objects to a range of 30 feet. Within that range, you have darkvision if you don't already have it. This special sight lasts until the end of the current turn. During that time, you perceive objects as ghostly, transparent images. Once you use this invocation, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 6</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Gift of the Depths (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>5th level</prerequisite>
    <text>You can breathe underwater, and you gain a swimming speed equal to your walking speed. You can also cast water breathing without expending a spell slot. Once you cast it using this invocation, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 6</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Gift of the Ever-Living Ones (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Pact of the Chain</prerequisite>
    <text>Whenever you regain hit points while your familiar is within 100 feet of you, treat any dice rolled to determine the hit points you regain as having rolled their maximum value for you.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 6</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Grasp of Hadar (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Eldritch Blast cantrip</prerequisite>
    <text>Once on each of your turns when you hit a creature with your eldritch blast cantrip, you can move that creature in a straight line 10 feet closer to yourself.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 6</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Improved Pact Weapon (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Pact of the Blade</prerequisite>
    <text>You can use any weapon you summon with your Pact of the Blade feature as a spellcasting focus for your warlock spells. In addition, the weapon counts as a magic weapon with a +1 bonus to its attack and damage rolls, unless it is already a magic weapon that you transformed into your pact weapon.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 6</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Kiss of Mephistopheles (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>Eldritch Blast cantrip, 5th level</prerequisite>
    <text>When you hit a creature with your eldritch blast, you can cast fireball as a bonus action using a warlock spell slot. The spell must be centered on the creature you hit with eldritch blast.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 6</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Maddening Hex (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>5th level</prerequisite>
    <text>As a bonus action, you cause a psychic disturbance around the target cursed by your hex spell or by a warlock feature of yours, such as Hexblade's Curse and Sign of Ill Omen. When you do so, you deal psychic damage to the target and each creature of your choice within 5 feet of it. The psychic damage equals your Charisma modifier (minimum of 0 damage).
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 6</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Maneuver: Precision Attack (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Maneuver: Cavalier V2 (UA)
When you make a weapon attack against a creature, you can expend one superiority die, roll it, and add it to the attack roll. You can use this ability before or after rolling the d20, but before any of the effects of the attack are applied.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 3</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Relentless Hex (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>7th level</prerequisite>
    <text>Your curse creates a temporary bond between you and your target. As a bonus action, you can magically teleport up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space you can see within 5 feet of the target cursed by your hex spell or by a warlock feature of yours, such as Hexblade's Curse and Sign of Ill Omen. To teleport in this way, you must be able to see the cursed target.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 6</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Shroud of Shadow (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>15th level</prerequisite>
    <text>You can cast invisibility at will, without expending a spell slot.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 6</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Tomb of Levistus (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>5th level</prerequisite>
    <text>As a reaction when you take damage, you can entomb yourself in ice, which melts away at the end of your next turn. You gain 10 temporary hit points per warlock level, which take as much of the triggering damage as possible. You also gain vulnerability to fire damage, your speed is reduced to 0, and you are incapacitated. These effects all end when the ice melts.
Once you use this invocation, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 6</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Invocation: Trickster's Escape (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite>7th level</prerequisite>
    <text>You can cast freedom of movement once on yourself without expending a spell slot. You regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 7</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Maneuver: Trip Attack (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Maneuver: Cavalier V2 (UA)
When you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can expend one superiority die to attempt to knock the target down. Roll the die, and add it to the attack's damage roll. If the target is Large or smaller, it must also succeed on a Strength saving throw (DC 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Strength modifier) or be knocked prone.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 3</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Maneuver: Warding Maneuver (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Maneuver: Cavalier V2 (UA)
If you or a creature within 5 feet of you is hit by an attack, you can expend one superiority die as a reaction if you're wielding a weapon or a shield. Roll the die, and add the number rolled to the target's AC against that attack. If the attack still hits, the target has resistance against the attack's damage.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Revised Class Options p. 3</text>
    </feat>
  </compendium>
