<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <feat>
      <name>Rune: Haug (Hill Rune) (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>This rune's magic bestows a resilience reminiscent of a hill giant. While wearing or carrying an object inscribed with this rune, you have advantage on saving throws against being poisoned, and you have resistance against poison damage.
In addition, you can invoke the rune as a bonus action, gaining resistance to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage for 1 minute. Once you invoke the rune, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 1</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Rune: Ild (Fire Rune) (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>This rune's magic channels the masterful craftsmanship of fire giant smiths. While wearing or carrying an object inscribed with this rune, your proficiency bonus is doubled for any ability check you make that uses your proficiency with a tool.
In addition, when you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can invoke the rune to summon fiery shackles: the target must succeed on a Strength saving throw or be restrained for 1 minute. While restrained by the shackles, the target takes  2d6 fire damage at the start of each of its turns. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, banishing the shackles on a success. Once you invoke the rune, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 1</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Rune: Ise (Frost Rune) (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>This rune's magic evokes a frost giant's stoic calm. While wearing or carrying an object inscribed with this rune, you have advantage on Wisdom (Animal Handling) checks and Charisma (Intimidation) checks.
In addition, you can invoke the rune as a bonus action to increase your Strength score by 2 for 10 minutes. This increase can cause your score to exceed 20, but not 30. Once you invoke the rune, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 1</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Rune: Skye (Cloud Rune) (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>This rune's magic emulates the deceptiveness of a cloud giant. While wearing or carrying an object inscribed with this rune, you have advantage on Dexterity (Sleight of Hand) checks and Charisma (Deception) checks.
In addition, when you or a creature you can see within 30 feet of you is hit by an attack roll, you can use your reaction to invoke the rune and cause that attack to target a different creature within 30 feet of you (other than the attacker), using the same roll. This magic can transfer the attack regardless of the attack's range. Once you invoke the rune, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 2</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Rune: Stein (Stone Rune) (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>This rune's magic channels the insightfulness of a stone giant. While wearing or carrying an object inscribed with this rune, you have advantage on Wisdom (Insight) checks, and you have darkvision out to a range of 60 feet. If you already have darkvision, its range increases by 30 feet.
In addition, when a creature you can see ends its turn within 30 feet of you, you can use your reaction to invoke the rune and force the creature to make a Wisdom saving throw. Unless the save succeeds, the creature is charmed by you for 1 minute. While charmed in this way, the creature has a speed of 0 and is incapacitated, descending into a dreamy stupor. The effect ends if the charmed creature takes any damage or if someone else uses an action to shake the creature out of its haze. Once you invoke the rune, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 2</text>
    </feat>
  <feat>
      <name>Rune: Uvar (Storm Rune) (UA)</name>
    <prerequisite></prerequisite>
    <text>Using this rune, you can glimpse the future like a storm giant. While wearing or carrying an object inscribed with this rune, you have advantage on Intelligence (Arcana) checks, and you can't be surprised as long as you are not incapacitated.
In addition, you can invoke the rune as a bonus action to enter a prophetic state for 1 minute or until you're incapacitated. Until the state ends, when you or another creature you can see within 60 feet of you makes an attack roll, a saving throw, or an ability check, you can use your reaction to cause the roll to have advantage or disadvantage. Once you invoke the rune, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Fighter Ranger Rogue p. 2</text>
    </feat>
  </compendium>
