<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <race>
      <name>Gith (UA) (Githyanki)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Int 1, Str 2</ability>
    <proficiency></proficiency>
    <spellAbility>Intelligence</spellAbility>
    <trait>
        <name>Description</name>
      <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eladrin And Gith (UA) (Githyanki) p. 2</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Gith (UA) (Githyanki)yanki tend toward lawful evil. They are self-centered, violent, and arrogant, yet they remain the faithful servants of their lich-queen, Vlaakith. Renegade Gith (UA) (Githyanki)yanki tend toward chaos as they have forsaken her will.
</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Decadent Mastery</name>
      <text>You learn one language of your choice, and you are proficient with one skill or tool of your choice. In the timeless city of Tu'narath, Gith (UA) (Githyanki)yanki have bountiful time to master odd bits of knowledge.
</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Martial Prodigy</name>
      <text>You are proficient with light and medium armor. Your people are ever ready for war.
</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Githyanki Psionics</name>
      <text>You know the mage hand cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast jump once with this trait, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest. When you reach 5th level, you can cast the misty step spell once with this trait, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest.
Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for these spells. You can cast all of them without components.
</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Age</name>
      <text>Gith (UA) (Githyanki) reach adulthood in their late teens and live for about a century.
</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Size</name>
      <text>Gith (UA) (Githyanki) are taller and leaner than humans, with most a slender 6 feet in height.
</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Gith (UA) (Githyanki).
</text>
      </trait>
    </race>
  <race>
      <name>Gith (UA) (Githzerai)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <speed>30</speed>
    <ability>Int 1, Wis 2</ability>
    <proficiency></proficiency>
    <spellAbility>Wisdom</spellAbility>
    <trait>
        <name>Description</name>
      <text>Source: Unearthed Arcana: Eladrin And Gith (UA) (Githzerai) p. 3</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Alignment</name>
      <text>Gith (UA) (Githzerai)zerai tend toward lawful neutral. Their rigorous training in psychic abilities requires an implacable mental discipline.
</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Monastic Training</name>
      <text>You gain a +1 bonus to AC while you aren't wearing medium or heavy armor and aren't using a shield. All Gith (UA) (Githzerai)zerai receive basic training from monks, and the monks among them are unmatched in their defensive abilities.
</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Githzerai Psionics</name>
      <text>You know the mage hand cantrip. When you reach 3rd level, you can cast shield once with this trait, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest. When you reach 5th level, you can cast the detect thoughts spell once with this trait, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest.
Wisdom is your spellcasting ability for these spells. You can cast all of them without components.
</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Age</name>
      <text>Gith (UA) (Githzerai) reach adulthood in their late teens and live for about a century.
</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Size</name>
      <text>Gith (UA) (Githzerai) are taller and leaner than humans, with most a slender 6 feet in height.
</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Languages</name>
      <text>You can speak, read, and write Common and Gith (UA) (Githzerai).
</text>
      </trait>
    </race>
  </compendium>
