<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <spell>
      <name>Arcane Hacking (UA)</name>
    <classes>Warlock, Sorcerer, Wizard, Warlock (Ghost in the Machine (UA))</classes>
    <level>2</level>
    <school>T</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Self</range>
    <components>V, S, M (hacking tools)</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 1 hour</duration>
    <text>You gain advantage on all Intelligence checks using hacking tools to break software encryption or online security when using a foreign system. This spell also allows you to break 2nd-level and lower protective spells such as arcane lock or glyph of warding by making an Intelligence check using hacking tools against the spell save DC of the spell's caster.
At Higher Levels:
When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, you can attempt to counteract a spell set to secure the foreign system if the spell's level is equal to or less than the level of the spell slot you used.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 5</text>
    </spell>
  <spell>
      <name>Commune with City (UA)</name>
    <classes>Warlock, Sorcerer, Wizard, Cleric (City (UA))</classes>
    <level>5</level>
    <school>D</school>
    <ritual>YES</ritual>
    <time>1 minute</time>
    <range>Self</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <text>You briefly become one with the city and gain knowledge of the surrounding area. Aboveground, this spell gives you knowledge of the area within 1 mile of you. In sewers and other underground settings, you gain knowledge of the area within 600 feet of you.
You instantly gain knowledge of up to three facts of your choice about any of the following subjects as they relate to the area:
• Terrain and bodies of water
• Prevalent buildings, plants, animals, or intelligent creatures
• Powerful (CR 1 or higher) celestials, fey, fiends, elementals, or undead
• Influences from other planes of existence
• Electrical currents, wireless signals, and active transit lines and tracks
For example, you could determine the location of powerful undead in the area, the location of major sources of electrical power or interference, and the location of any nearby parks. 
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 5</text>
    </spell>
  <spell>
      <name>Conjure Knowbot (UA)</name>
    <classes>Warlock, Sorcerer, Wizard, Warlock (Ghost in the Machine (UA))</classes>
    <level>4</level>
    <school>C</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Touch</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>10 minutes</duration>
    <text>You touch a single computerized device or computer system to conjure a knowbot—a partially sentient piece of software imprinted with vestiges of your own skills and computer abilities. For the duration of the spell, you can use a bonus action to have the knowbot execute a computer-related task that would normally require an action. The knowbot makes Intelligence ability checks using your ability score and proficiency bonuses (including your proficiency with hacking tools, if applicable).
You have a limited telepathic bond with the knowbot, out to a range of 500 feet from the device or system where the knowbot was conjured. If you move beyond this range, the knowbot disappears in 2d4 rounds, as if the duration of the spell had expired. Moving within range again immediately reestablishes the bond.
The knowbot is bound to the system in which it was created, and it stays there until it is dismissed or the spell's duration expires.
At Higher Levels:
When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, the spell's duration increases to 1 hour. Additionally, your telepathic bond with the knowbot is effective out to a range of 1,000 feet, and if you leave the range of the bond, the knowbot continues performing its last directed task until the spell expires.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 5</text>
    <roll>2d4</roll>
    </spell>
  <spell>
      <name>Digital Phantom (UA)</name>
    <classes>Warlock, Sorcerer, Wizard, Warlock (Ghost in the Machine (UA))</classes>
    <level>2</level>
    <school>A</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Self</range>
    <components>V, S, M (a small piece of copper wire)</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 1 hour</duration>
    <text>This spell works to actively hide your presence within a computer system. For the spell's duration, you and any other users you choose on your local network gain a +10 bonus to Intelligence checks to avoid detection by administrators, knowbots, tracking software, and the like. Whenever you and your chosen users leave any computer system you are working in while this spell is in effect, all trace of your previous presence in that system is erased.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 6</text>
    </spell>
  <spell>
      <name>Find Vehicle (UA)</name>
    <classes>Warlock, Sorcerer, Wizard, Cleric (City (UA))</classes>
    <level>2</level>
    <school>C</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>10 minutes</time>
    <range>30 feet</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>8 hours</duration>
    <text>You summon a spirit that assumes the form of a nonmilitary land vehicle of your choice, appearing in an unoccupied space within range. The vehicle has the statistics of a normal vehicle of its sort, though it is celestial, fey, or fiendish (your choice in origin). The physical characteristics of the vehicle reflect its origin to some degree. For example, a fiendish SUV might be jet black in color, with tinted windows and a sinister-looking front grille.
You have a supernatural bond with the conjured vehicle that allows you to drive beyond your normal ability. While driving the conjured vehicle, you are considered proficient with vehicles of its type, and you add double your proficiency bonus to ability checks related to driving the vehicle. While driving the vehicle, you can make any spell you cast that targets only you also target the vehicle.
If the vehicle drops to 0 hit points, it disappears, leaving behind no physical form. You can also dismiss the vehicle at any time as an action, causing it to disappear.
You can't have more than one vehicle bonded by this spell at a time. As an action, you can release the vehicle from its bond at any time, causing it to disappear.
At Higher Levels:
When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 3rd level or higher, you can conjure a nonmilitary water vehicle large enough to carry six Medium creatures. When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, you can conjure a nonmilitary air vehicle large enough to carry ten Medium creatures. When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 7th level or higher, you can conjure any type of vehicle, subject to the DM's approval.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 6</text>
    </spell>
  <spell>
      <name>Haywire (UA)</name>
    <classes>Warlock, Sorcerer, Wizard, Warlock (Ghost in the Machine (UA))</classes>
    <level>3</level>
    <school>EN</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>90 feet</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
    <text>This spell plays havoc with electronic devices, making the use of such devices all but impossible. Each electronic device in a 10-foot-radius sphere centered on a point you choose within range is subject to random behavior while it remains within the area. A device not held by a creature is automatically affected. If an electronic device is held by a creature, that creature must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or have the device affected by the spell.
At the start of each of your turns, roll a d6 for each affected device to determine its behavior. Except where otherwise indicated, that behavior lasts until the start of your next turn while this spell is in effect.
d6 | Effect
1 | The device shuts down and must be restarted. Do not roll again for this device until it is restarted.
2-4 | The device does not function.
5 | The device experiences a power surge, causing an electric shock to the wielder (if any) and one random creature within 5 feet of the device. Each affected creature must make a Dexterity saving throw against your spell save DC, taking 6d6 lightning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.
6 | The device is usable as normal.
At Higher Levels:
When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 4th level or higher, the radius of the sphere affected by the spell increases by 5 feet for each slot level above 3rd.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 7</text>
    <roll>6d6</roll>
    </spell>
  <spell>
      <name>Infallible Relay (UA)</name>
    <classes>Warlock, Sorcerer, Wizard, Warlock (Ghost in the Machine (UA))</classes>
    <level>1</level>
    <school>D</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 minute</time>
    <range>Self</range>
    <components>V, S, M (a mobile phone)</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 10 minutes</duration>
    <text>With this spell, you can target any creature with whom you have spoken previously, as long as the two of you are on the same plane of existence. When you cast the spell, the nearest functioning telephone or similar communications device within 100 feet of the target begins to ring. If there is no suitable device close enough to the target, the spell fails.
The target must make a successful Charisma saving throw or be compelled to answer your call. Once the connection is established, the call is crystal clear and cannot be dropped until the conversation has ended or the spell's duration ends. You can end the conversation at any time, but a target must succeed on a Charisma saving throw to end the conversation.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 7</text>
    </spell>
  <spell>
      <name>Invisibility to Cameras (UA)</name>
    <classes>Warlock, Sorcerer, Wizard, Warlock (Ghost in the Machine (UA))</classes>
    <level>3</level>
    <school>I</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>10 feet</range>
    <components>V, S, M (a scrap of black paper)</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
    <text>Four creatures of your choice within range become undetectable to electronic sensors and cameras for the duration of the spell. Anything a target is wearing or carrying is likewise undetectable as long as it is on the target's person. The targets remain visible to vision.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 7</text>
    </spell>
  <spell>
      <name>On/Off (UA)</name>
    <classes>Warlock, Sorcerer, Wizard</classes>
    <level>0</level>
    <school>T</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>60 feet</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <text>This cantrip allows you to activate or deactivate any electronic device within range, as long as the device has a clearly defined on or off function that can be easily accessed from the outside of the device. Any device that requires a software-based shutdown sequence to activate or deactivate cannot be affected by on/off.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 7</text>
    </spell>
  <spell>
      <name>Protection from Ballistics (UA)</name>
    <classes>Warlock, Sorcerer, Wizard, Cleric (City (UA))</classes>
    <level>3</level>
    <school>A</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Touch</range>
    <components>V, S, M (a shell casing)</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 10 minutes</duration>
    <text>This spell enchants the flesh of the target against the impact of bullets. Until the spell ends, the target has resistance to nonmagical ballistic damage.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 8</text>
    </spell>
  <spell>
      <name>Remote Access (UA)</name>
    <classes>Warlock, Sorcerer, Wizard, Cleric (City (UA)), Warlock (Ghost in the Machine (UA))</classes>
    <level>1</level>
    <school>T</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>120 feet</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>10 minutes</duration>
    <text>You can use any electronic device within range as if it were in your hands. This is not a telekinesis effect. Rather, this spell allows you to simulate a device's mechanical functions electronically. You are able to access only functions that a person using the device manually would be able to access. You can use remote access with only one device at a time.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 8</text>
    </spell>
  <spell>
      <name>Shutdown (UA)</name>
    <classes>Warlock, Sorcerer, Wizard, Cleric (City (UA)), Warlock (Ghost in the Machine (UA))</classes>
    <level>5</level>
    <school>T</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>120 feet</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 1 minute</duration>
    <text>This spell shuts down all electronic devices within range that are not wielded by or under the direct control of a creature. If an electronic device within range is used by a creature, that creature must succeed on a Constitution saving throw to prevent the device from being shut down. While the spell remains active, no electronic device within range can be started or restarted.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 8</text>
    </spell>
  <spell>
      <name>Synchronicity (UA)</name>
    <classes>Warlock, Sorcerer, Wizard, Cleric (City (UA)), Warlock (Ghost in the Machine (UA))</classes>
    <level>4</level>
    <school>EN</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>Touch</range>
    <components>V, S</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 1 hour</duration>
    <text>The creature you touch feels reality subtly shifted to its favor while this spell is in effect. The target isn't inconvenienced by mundane delays of any sort. Traffic lights are always green, there's always a waiting elevator, and a taxi is always around the corner. The target can run at full speed through dense crowds, and attacks of opportunity provoked by the target's movement are made with disadvantage.
Synchronicity grants advantage to Dexterity (Stealth) checks, since the target always finds a handy piece of cover available. Additionally, the target has advantage on all ability checks made to drive a vehicle.
In the event that two or more creatures under the effect of synchronicity are attempting to avoid being inconvenienced by each other, the creatures engage in a contest of Charisma each time the effects of the spells would oppose each other.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 8</text>
    </spell>
  <spell>
      <name>System Backdoor (UA)</name>
    <classes>Warlock, Sorcerer, Wizard, Warlock (Ghost in the Machine (UA))</classes>
    <level>4</level>
    <school>T</school>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 minute</time>
    <range>Self</range>
    <components>V, S, M (hacking tools)</components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 1 hour</duration>
    <text>This spell allows you to bypass system security in order to create a secure login on a foreign system. The login you create allows you administrator-level privileges in any computer system not enhanced through technomagic. The login defeats any technomagic spells of 3rd level or lower.
Once the duration of the spell expires, the login and all privileges are wiped from the system. System logs still show the activity of the user, but the user identification cannot be found or traced.
At Higher Levels:
When you cast this spell using a spell slot of 5th level or higher, you are able to bypass technomagic spells if the spell's level is equal to or less than the level of the spell slot you used.
Source: Unearthed Arcana: Modern Magic p. 8</text>
    </spell>
  </compendium>
