<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <monster>
      <name>Al'chaia</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (gith)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>91 (14d8+28)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Con +5, Int +5, Wis +5</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Gith</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Al'chaia makes two silver greatsword attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Silver Greatsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d6 + 6) slashing damage plus 10 (3d6) psychic damage. This is a magic weapon attack. On a critical hit against a target in an astral body (as with the astral projection spell), Al'chaia can cut the silvery cord that tethers the target to its material body, instead of dealing damage.</text>
      <attack>Silver Greatsword|+9|2d6+6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting (Psionics)</name>
      <text>Al'chaia's innate spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no components:</text>
      <text>At will: mage hand (the hand is invisible)</text>
      <text>3/day each: jump, misty step, nondetection (self only), tongues</text>
      <text>1/day each: plane shift, telekinesis</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>mage hand, jump, misty step, nondetection, tongues, plane shift, telekinesis</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 218</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Animated Ballista</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>50 (50d1)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>3</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>6</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 120 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <action>
        <name>Magic Bolt</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. 16 (3d10) fire damage</text>
      <attack>Magic Bolt|+6|3d10</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Each animated ballista is a Large wood-and-iron construct.
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 39</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Animated Jade Serpent</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>14</ac>
    <hp>11 (2d8+2)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 10 ft.</senses>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 6 (1d4 + 4) piercing damage, and the target must make a DC 11 Constitution saving throw, taking 10 (3d6) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+6|1d4+4</attack>
      <attack>Bite||3d6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 92</description>
    <environment>underdark, grassland, forest, swamp, urban, desert</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Animated Staff</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>40</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>18</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist>cold</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>40</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Wielder Domination</name>
      <text>A creature can grab the staff out of the air with a successful grapple check against the staff, and grappling the staff does not reduce the creature's speed. Any creature that successfully grapples the staff must succeed on a DC 12 Charisma saving throw or be charmed by the staff until the staff is no longer in its grasp. While the creature is charmed, the staff can issue commands to it, which the creature does its best to obey. The creature can repeat the saving throw each time it takes damage, ending the effect on itself on a success. A creature that successfully resists the staff's control can't be charmed by it for 24 hours.</text>
      <text>A creature holding the staff that isn't charmed by it can use an action to attempt to break the staff over a knee or against a solid surface, doing so with a successful DC 17 Strength (Athletics) check. Breaking the staff in this manner destroys it.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Staff of Frost</name>
      <text>The staff has 10 charges. It can expend 1 or more of its charges to cast one of the following spells (save DC 12): cone of cold (5 charges), fog cloud (1 charge), ice storm (4 charges), or wall of ice (4 charges). It regains 1d6 + 4 expended charges daily at dawn. If the staff expends its last charge, roll a d20. On a 1, the staff turns to water and is destroyed.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Staff</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (2d6) bludgeoning damage plus 1 cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Staff|+5|2d6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 262</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Animated Statue of Lolth</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>230 (20d12+100)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>22</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't adamantine</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The statue is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The statue has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Weapons</name>
      <text>The statue's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Spider Climb</name>
      <text>The statue can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without needing to make an ability check.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The statue makes two slam attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 19 (3d8 + 6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+10|3d8+6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slow (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The statue targets one or more creatures it can see within 10 feet of it. Each target must make a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw against this magic. On a failed save, a target can't use reactions, its speed is halved, and it can't make more than one attack on its turn. In addition, the target can take either an action or a bonus action on its turn, not both. These effects last for 1 minute. A target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 142</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Animated Stove</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>17</ac>
    <hp>50 (50d1)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>3</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>6</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 30 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (2d8 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+6|2d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Belch Fire (Recharge 4-6)</name>
      <text>The stove belches fire in a 15-foot cone. Each creature in the area must make a DC 10 Dexterity saving throw, taking 22 (4d10) fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Belch Fire (Recharge 4-6)||4d10</attack>
      </action>
    <description>The stove was given a semblance of life through an animate objects spell made permanent by a wish spell.
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 186</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Animated Wand</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>20 (20d1)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>4</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>3</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>6</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 30 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Animated</name>
      <text>If the wand lacks legs or other appendages it can use for locomotion, it instead has a flying speed of 30 feet and can hover. If the wand is securely attached to a surface or larger wand, such as a chain bolted to a wall, its speed is 0.</text>
      <text>When the animated wand drops to 0 hit points, it reverts to its original wand form, and any remaining damage carries over to its original wand form.</text>
      <text>The DM might rule that a specific wands slam attack inflicts slashing or piercing damage based on its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Wand of Wonder</name>
      <text>The animated wand can expend 1 of its charges and target a random creature with one of its wand of wonder. Any such effect that would target the wand's user targets the wand instead. If reduced to 0 hit points, the wand crumbles into dust and is destroyed.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d4 + 4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+8|1d4+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 299</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Arcturia</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Any Evil Alignment</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>135 (18d8+54)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Con +10, Int +12, Wis +9</save>
    <skill>Arcana +19, History +12, Insight +9, Perception +9</skill>
    <passive>19</passive>
    <languages>Common plus up to five other languages</languages>
    <cr>21</cr>
    <resist>cold, lightning, necrotic</resist>
    <immune>poison; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If Arcturia fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Rejuvenation</name>
      <text>If it has a phylactery, a destroyed lich gains a new body in 1d10 days, regaining all its hit points and becoming active again. The new body appears within 5 feet of the phylactery.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Turn Resistance</name>
      <text>Arcturia has advantage on saving throws against any effect that turns undead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Paralyzing Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +12 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 10 (3d6) cold damage. The target must succeed on a DC 18 Constitution saving throw or be paralyzed for 1 minute. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <attack>Paralyzing Touch|+12|3d6</attack>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>The undead can take 4 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The undead regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Cantrip</name>
      <text>Arcturia casts a cantrip.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Paralyzing Touch (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Arcturia uses its Paralyzing Touch.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Frightening Gaze (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Arcturia fixes its gaze on one creature it can see within 10 feet of it. The target must succeed on a DC 18 Wisdom saving throw against this magic or become frightened for 1 minute. The frightened target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. If a target's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the target is immune to Arcturia's gaze for the next 24 hours.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Disrupt Life (Costs 3 Actions)</name>
      <text>Each non-undead creature within 20 feet of Arcturia must make a DC 18 Constitution saving throw against this magic, taking 21 (6d6) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Lair Actions</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>On initiative count 20 (losing initiative ties), the lich can take a lair action to cause one of the following magical effects; the lich can't use the same effect two rounds in a row:</text>
      <text>• The lich rolls a d8 and regains a spell slot of that level or lower. If it has no spent spell slots of that level or lower, nothing happens.</text>
      <text>• The lich targets one creature it can see within 30 feet of it. A crackling cord of negative energy tethers the lich to the target. Whenever the lich takes damage, the target must make a DC 18 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the lich takes half the damage (rounded down), and the target takes the remaining damage. This tether lasts until initiative count 20 on the next round or until the lich or the target is no longer in the lich's lair.</text>
      <text>• The lich calls forth the spirits of creatures that died in its lair. These apparitions materialize and attack one creature that the lich can see within 60 feet of it. The target must succeed on a DC 18 Constitution saving throw, taking 52 (15d6) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a success. The apparitions then disappear.</text>
      </legendary>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Arcturia is an 18th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 20, +12 to hit with spell attacks). Arcturia has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): mage hand, prestidigitation, ray of frost</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, magic missile, shield, thunderwave</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, invisibility, Melf's acid arrow, mirror image</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): animate dead, counterspell, dispel magic, fireball</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): blight, dimension door</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): cloudkill, scrying</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): disintegrate, globe of invulnerability</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): finger of death, plane shift</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): dominate monster, power word stun</text>
      <text>• 9th level (1 slots): power word kill</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>mage hand, prestidigitation, ray of frost, detect magic, magic missile, shield, thunderwave, detect thoughts, invisibility, Melf's acid arrow, mirror image, animate dead, counterspell, dispel magic, fireball, blight, dimension door, cloudkill, scrying, disintegrate, globe of invulnerability, finger of death, plane shift, dominate monster, power word stun, power word kill</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 296</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Ashtyrranthor</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>dragon</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>256 (19d12+133)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., climb 40 ft., fly 80 ft.</speed>
    <str>27</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>25</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>21</cha>
    <save>Dex +6, Con +13, Wis +7, Cha +11</save>
    <skill>Perception +13, Stealth +6</skill>
    <passive>23</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>17</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft., darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If Ashtyrranthor fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Ashtyrranthor can use its Frightful Presence. It then makes three attacks: one with its bite and two with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 19 (2d10 + 8) piercing damage plus 7 (2d6) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+14|2d10+8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 15 (2d6 + 8) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+14|2d6+8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. 17 (2d8 + 8) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Tail|+14|2d8+8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Frightful Presence</name>
      <text>Each creature of Ashtyrranthor's choice that is within 120 feet of Ashtyrranthor and aware of it must succeed on a DC 19 Wisdom saving throw or become frightened for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. If a creature's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the creature is immune to Ashtyrranthor's Frightful Presence for the next 24 hours.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Fire Breath (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>Ashtyrranthor exhales fire in a 60-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 21 Dexterity saving throw, taking 63 (18d6) fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Fire Breath (Recharge 5-6)||18d6</attack>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>The dragon can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The dragon regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Detect</name>
      <text>Ashtyrranthor makes a Wisdom (Perception) check.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Tail Attack</name>
      <text>Ashtyrranthor makes a tail attack.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Wing Attack (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Ashtyrranthor beats its wings. Each creature within 10 feet of Ashtyrranthor must succeed on a DC 22 Dexterity saving throw or take 15 (2d6 + 8) bludgeoning damage and be knocked prone. Ashtyrranthor can then fly up to half its flying speed.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Lair Actions</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>On initiative count 20 (losing initiative ties), the dragon takes a lair action to cause one of the following effects; the dragon can't use the same effect two rounds in a row:</text>
      <text>• Magma erupts from a point on the ground the dragon can see within 120 feet of it, creating a 20-foot-high, 5-foot-radius geyser. Each creature in the geyser's area must make a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw, taking 21 (6d6) fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <text>• A tremor shakes the lair in a 60-foot radius around the dragon. Each creature other than the dragon on the ground in that area must succeed on a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      <text>• Volcanic gases form a cloud in a 20-foot-radius sphere centered on a point the dragon can see within 120 feet of it. The sphere spreads a round corners, and its area is lightly obscured. It lasts until initiative count 20 on the next round. Each creature that starts its turn in the cloud must succeed on a DC 13 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned until the end of its turn. While poisoned in this way, a creature is incapacitated.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Regional Effects</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>The region containing a legendary red dragon's lair is warped by the dragon's magic, which creates one or more of the following effects:</text>
      <text>• Small earthquakes are common within 6 miles of the dragon's lair.</text>
      <text>• Water sources within 1 mile of the lair are supernaturally warm and tainted by sulfur.</text>
      <text>• Rocky fissures within 1 mile of the dragon's lair form portals to the Elemental Plane of Fire, allowing creatures of elemental fire into the world to dwell nearby.</text>
      <text>If the dragon dies, these effects fade over the course of 1d10 days.</text>
      </legendary>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 210</description>
    <environment>mountain, hill</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Awakened Brown Bear</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>11 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>34 (4d10+12)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>one language known by its creator</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>The bear has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The bear makes two attacks: one with its bite and one with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (1d8 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+6|1d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+6|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 72</description>
    <environment>forest, hill, arctic</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Awakened Elk</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>13 (2d10+2)</hp>
    <speed>walk 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>one language known by its creator</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Charge</name>
      <text>If the elk moves at least 20 feet straight toward a target and then hits it with a ram attack on the same turn, the target takes an extra 7 (2d6) damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 13 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Ram</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Ram|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hooves</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one prone creature. 8 (2d4 + 3) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Hooves|+5|2d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 72</description>
    <environment>grassland, forest, hill</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Awakened Giant Wasp</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>13 (3d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 10 ft., fly 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>one language known by its creator</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Sting</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage, and the target must make a DC 11 Constitution saving throw, taking 10 (3d6) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. If the poison damage reduces the target to 0 hit points, the target is stable but poisoned for 1 hour, even after regaining hit points, and is paralyzed while poisoned in this way.</text>
      <attack>Sting|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      <attack>Sting||3d6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 72</description>
    <environment>grassland, forest, urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Berlain Shadowdusk</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>99 (18d8+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Int +9, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +13, History +13</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>any six languages</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <resist>damage from spells; nonmagical bludgeoning, piercing, slashing (from stoneskin)</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Berlain has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Extra Parts</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Berlain can use her extra mouth and arms to cast any cantrip she has prepared.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+6|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Familiars</name>
      <text>Any spellcaster that can cast the find familiar spell (such as an archmage or mage) is likely to have a familiar. The familiar can be one of the creatures described in the spell (see the Player's Handbook) or some other Tiny monster, such as a crawling claw, imp, pseudodragon, or quasit.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Berlain is an 18th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks). Berlain can cast disguise self and invisibility at will and has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>At will: disguise self, invisibility</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, identify, mage armor*, magic missile</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fly, lightning bolt</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): banishment, fire shield, stoneskin*</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): cone of cold, scrying, wall of force</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): globe of invulnerability</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): teleport</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): mind blank*</text>
      <text>• 9th level (1 slots): time stop</text>
      <text>*Berlain casts these spells on itself before combat.</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>disguise self, invisibility, fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp, detect magic, identify, mage armor, magic missile, detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step, counterspell, fly, lightning bolt, banishment, fire shield, stoneskin, cone of cold, scrying, wall of force, globe of invulnerability, teleport, mind blank, time stop</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 283</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Big Xorn</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>103 (9d10+54)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., burrow 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>17</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>22</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +6, Stealth +3</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Terran</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist>piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't adamantine</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft., tremorsense 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Earth Glide</name>
      <text>The xorn can burrow through nonmagical, unworked earth and stone. While doing so, the xorn doesn't disturb the material it moves through.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Stone Camouflage</name>
      <text>The xorn has advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks made to hide in rocky terrain.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Treasure Sense</name>
      <text>The xorn can pinpoint, by scent, the location of precious metals and stones, such as coins and gems, within 60 feet of it.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The xorn makes three claw attacks and one bite attack.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (3d6 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+6|3d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+6|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 51</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Bore Worm</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>247 (15d20+90)</hp>
    <speed>walk 50 ft., burrow 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>28</str>
    <dex>7</dex>
    <con>22</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>8</wis>
    <cha>4</cha>
    <save>Con +11, Wis +4</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>16</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire, poison, psychic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't adamantine</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 30 ft., tremorsense 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Tunneler</name>
      <text>The worm can burrow through solid rock at half its burrow speed and leaves a 10-foot-diameter tunnel in its wake.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Regeneration</name>
      <text>The worm regains 10 hit points at the start of each of its turns if it has at least 1 hit point.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The worm makes two attacks: one with its grinding jaws and one with its stinger.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Grinding Jaws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 22 (3d8 + 9) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Grinding Jaws|+9|3d8+9</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Tail Stinger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 10 ft., one creature. 19 (3d6 + 9) piercing damage, and the target must make a DC 19 Constitution saving throw, taking 42 (12d6) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Tail Stinger|+9|3d6+9</attack>
      <attack>Tail Stinger||12d6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Trobriand modeled this 100-foot-long, 15-foot-diameter drilling machine after a purple worm. Unless Trobriand commands it to do otherwise, the worm tirelessly moves through well-worn tunnels and trenches. It mindlessly attacks anything that gets in its way, and occasionally ventures up to level 12 or down to level 14. Characters hear it long before they see it.
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 171</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Captain N'ghathrod</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (breastplate)</ac>
    <hp>111 (13d8+13)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>19</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save>Int +7, Wis +6, Cha +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +7, Deception +6, Insight +6, Perception +6, Persuasion +6, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Deep Speech, Undercommon, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Captain N'ghathrod has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Tentacles</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 15 (2d10 + 4) psychic damage. If the target is Medium or smaller, it is grappled (escape DC 15) and must succeed on a DC 15 Intelligence saving throw or be stunned until this grapple ends.</text>
      <attack>Tentacles|+7|2d10+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Extract Brain</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one incapacitated humanoid grappled by Captain N'ghathrod. The target takes 55 (10d10) piercing damage. If this damage reduces the target to 0 hit points, Captain N'ghathrod kills the target by extracting and devouring its brain.</text>
      <attack>Extract Brain|+7|10d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Mind Blast (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>Captain N'ghathrod magically emits psychic energy in a 60-foot cone. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 15 Intelligence saving throw or take 22 (4d8 + 4) psychic damage and be stunned for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <attack>Mind Blast (Recharge 5-6)||4d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting (Psionics)</name>
      <text>Captain N'ghathrod's innate spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 15). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no components:</text>
      <text>At will: detect thoughts, levitate</text>
      <text>1/day each: dominate monster, plane shift (self only)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Captain N'ghathrod is a 10th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (save DC 15, +7 to hit with spell attacks). Captain N'ghathrod has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): blade ward, dancing lights, mage hand, shocking grasp</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, disguise self, shield, sleep</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): blur, invisibility, ray of enfeeblement</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): clairvoyance, lightning bolt, sending</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): confusion, hallucinatory terrain</text>
      <text>• 5th level (2 slots): telekinesis, wall of force</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>detect thoughts, levitate, dominate monster, plane shift, blade ward, dancing lights, mage hand, shocking grasp, detect magic, disguise self, shield, sleep, blur, invisibility, ray of enfeeblement, clairvoyance, lightning bolt, sending, confusion, hallucinatory terrain, telekinesis, wall of force</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 250</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Carrion Ogre</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>11 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>59 (7d10+21)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>5</int>
    <wis>7</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>8</passive>
    <languages>Common, Giant</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Tied Down</name>
      <text>While lashed to the floor, the creature is prone and restrained. It also suffers from two levels of exhaustion.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Greatclub</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Greatclub|+6|2d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Javelin</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 30/120 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Javelin|+6|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 189</description>
    <environment>grassland, forest, swamp, hill, desert, coastal, arctic, underdark, mountain</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Cassiok Shadowdusk</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>99 (18d8+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Int +9, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +13, History +13</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>any six languages</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <resist>damage from spells; nonmagical bludgeoning, piercing, slashing (from stoneskin)</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Cassiok has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Cassiok carries a staff of power that grants him a +2 bonus to Armor Class, spell attack rolls, and saving throws. His insectoid physiology prevents him from making melee attacks with the staff. If reduced to 20 hit points or fewer, Cassiok uses his next action to break his staff in a retributive strike.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Familiars</name>
      <text>Any spellcaster that can cast the find familiar spell (such as an archmage or mage) is likely to have a familiar. The familiar can be one of the creatures described in the spell (see the Player's Handbook) or some other Tiny monster, such as a crawling claw, imp, pseudodragon, or quasit.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Cassiok is an 18th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks). Cassiok can cast disguise self and invisibility at will and has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>At will: disguise self, invisibility</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, identify, mage armor*, magic missile</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fly, lightning bolt</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): banishment, fire shield, stoneskin*</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): cone of cold, scrying, wall of force</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): globe of invulnerability</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): teleport</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): mind blank*</text>
      <text>• 9th level (1 slots): time stop</text>
      <text>*Cassiok casts these spells on itself before combat.</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>disguise self, invisibility, fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp, detect magic, identify, mage armor, magic missile, detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step, counterspell, fly, lightning bolt, banishment, fire shield, stoneskin, cone of cold, scrying, wall of force, globe of invulnerability, teleport, mind blank, time stop</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 287</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Copper Stormforge</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>16 (3d8+3)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Nature +4, Perception +5, Stealth +6, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common), Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Hearing and Sight</name>
      <text>Copper has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing or sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; has advantage on saving throws against poison, and has resistance against poison damage.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Copper makes two melee attacks or two ranged attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Longbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, ranged 150/600 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Longbow|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 30</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Crow</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>1 (1d4-1)</hp>
    <speed>walk 10 ft., fly 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>2</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>8</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Mimicry</name>
      <text>The crow can mimic simple sounds it has heard, such as a person whispering, a baby crying, or an animal chittering. A creature that hears the sounds can tell they are imitations with a successful DC 10 Wisdom (Insight) check.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Beak</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 1 piercing damage.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 302</description>
    <environment>swamp, hill, urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Crystal Battleaxe</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>17 (5d6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>5</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save>Dex +4</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>7</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Antimagic Susceptibility</name>
      <text>The battleaxe is incapacitated while in the area of an antimagic field. If targeted by dispel magic, the battleaxe must succeed on a Constitution saving throw against the caster's spell save DC or fall unconscious for 1 minute.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>False Appearance</name>
      <text>While the battleaxe remains motionless and isn't flying, it is indistinguishable from a normal battleaxe.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Longbattleaxe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d8 + 1) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Longbattleaxe|+3|1d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 89</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Crystal Golem</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>178 (17d10+85)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>22</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't adamantine</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The golem is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The golem has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Weapons</name>
      <text>The golem's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Illumination</name>
      <text>The golem magically sheds bright light in a 30-foot radius and dim light for an additional 30 feet. This light goes out when the golem is destroyed.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Light Intensity</name>
      <text>Any creature that starts its turn within 10 feet of the illuminated golem and can see the golem must succeed on a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw or be blinded until the start of the creature's next turn.</text>
      <text>A creature can avert its eyes to avoid the saving throw at the start of its turn. If the creature does so, it can't see the golem until the start of its next turn, when it can avert its eyes again. If the creature looks at the golem in the meantime, it must immediately make the save.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The golem makes two slam attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 19 (3d8 + 6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+10|3d8+6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slow (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The golem targets one or more creatures it can see within 10 feet of it. Each target must make a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw against this magic. On a failed save, a target can't use reactions, its speed is halved, and it can't make more than one attack on its turn. In addition, the target can take either an action or a bonus action on its turn, not both. These effects last for 1 minute. A target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 210</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Deformed Duergar</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (scale mail, shield)</ac>
    <hp>40 (4d8+4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Dwarvish, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Third Arm</name>
      <text>The duergar can make an attack with its javelin as a bonus action.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Merged Heads</name>
      <text>The duergar has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks and on saving throws against being charmed, frightened, stunned, and knocked unconscious.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Duergar Resilience</name>
      <text>The duergar has advantage on saving throws against poison, spells, and illusions, as well as to resist being charmed or paralyzed.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, the duergar has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Enlarge (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>For 1 minute, the duergar magically increases in size, along with anything it is wearing or carrying. While enlarged, the duergar is Large, doubles its damage dice on Strength-based weapon attacks (included in the attacks), and makes Strength checks and Strength saving throws with advantage. If the duergar lacks the room to become Large, it attains the maximum size possible in the space available.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>War Pick</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage, or 11 (2d8 + 2) piercing damage while enlarged.</text>
      <attack>War Pick|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Javelin</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 30/120 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage, or 9 (2d6 + 2) piercing damage while enlarged.</text>
      <attack>Javelin|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Invisibility (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>The duergar magically turns invisible until it attacks, casts a spell, or uses its Enlarge, or until its concentration is broken, up to 1 hour (as if concentrating on a spell). Any equipment the duergar wears or carries is invisible with it.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 180</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Dezmyr Shadowdusk</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>20 (plate armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>180 (19d8+95)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Dex +6, Wis +9, Cha +10</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common</languages>
    <cr>17</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>necrotic, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Warp Reality</name>
      <text>As a bonus action on her turn, Dezmyr can warp reality, undoing damage dealt to herself or another creature that she can see within 20 feet of her. The beneficiary of this warped reality instantly regains 10 hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Dezmyr has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Marshal Undead</name>
      <text>Unless Dezmyr is incapacitated, it and undead creatures of its choice within 60 feet of it have advantage on saving throws against features that turn undead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Dezmyr makes three longsword attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Longsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (1d8 + 5) slashing damage, or 10 (1d10 + 5) slashing damage if used with two hands, plus 18 (4d8) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Longsword|+11|1d8+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hellfire Orb (1/Day)</name>
      <text>Dezmyr hurls a magical ball of fire that explodes at a point it can see within 120 feet of it. Each creature in a 20-foot-radius sphere centered on that point must make a DC 18 Dexterity saving throw. The sphere spreads around corners. A creature takes 35 (10d6) fire damage and 35 (10d6) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Hellfire Orb (1/Day)||10d6</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Dezmyr adds 6 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, Dezmyr must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Dezmyr is a 19th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 18, +10 to hit with spell attacks). It has the following paladin spells prepared:</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): command, compelled duel, searing smite</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): hold person, magic weapon</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): dispel magic, elemental weapon</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): banishment, staggering smite</text>
      <text>• 5th level (2 slots): destructive wave (necrotic)</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>command, compelled duel, searing smite, hold person, magic weapon, dispel magic, elemental weapon, banishment, staggering smite, destructive wave</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 287</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Drivvin Freth</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (elf)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>99 (18d8+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Int +9, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +13, History +13, Perception +1</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>any six languages, Elvish</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <resist>damage from spells; nonmagical bludgeoning, piercing, slashing (from stoneskin)</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Drivvin has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put Drivvin to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, Drivvin has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+6|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Summon Demon (1/Day)</name>
      <text>Drivvin magically summons a demon of challenge rating 6 or lower. The summoned demon appears in an unoccupied space within 60 feet of him, acts as his ally, and can't summon other demons. The summoned demon remains until Drivvin dismisses it as an action or until the demon is reduced to 0 hit points.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Familiars</name>
      <text>Any spellcaster that can cast the find familiar spell (such as an archmage or mage) is likely to have a familiar. The familiar can be one of the creatures described in the spell (see the Player's Handbook) or some other Tiny monster, such as a crawling claw, imp, pseudodragon, or quasit.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Drivvin is an 18th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks). Drivvin can cast disguise self and invisibility at will and has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>At will: disguise self, invisibility</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, identify, mage armor*, magic missile</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fly, lightning bolt</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): banishment, fire shield, stoneskin*</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): cone of cold, scrying, wall of force</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): globe of invulnerability</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): teleport</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): mind blank*</text>
      <text>• 9th level (1 slots): time stop</text>
      <text>*Drivvin casts these spells on itself before combat.</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt;'s innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 15). &lt;$title_short_name$&gt; can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: dancing lights</text>
      <text>1/day each: darkness, faerie fire</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>disguise self, invisibility, fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp, detect magic, identify, mage armor, magic missile, detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step, counterspell, fly, lightning bolt, banishment, fire shield, stoneskin, cone of cold, scrying, wall of force, globe of invulnerability, teleport, mind blank, time stop, dancing lights, darkness, faerie fire</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 169</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Emberosa</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>162 (13d12+78)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>25</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>23</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save>Dex +3, Con +10, Cha +5</save>
    <skill>Athletics +11, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Giant</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Emberosa makes two greatsword attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Greatsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 28 (6d6 + 7) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Greatsword|+11|6d6+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hurl Fire</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, range 60/240 ft., one target. 29 (4d10 + 7) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Hurl Fire|+11|4d10+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: New Giant Options</name>
      <text>Some adult fire giants are trained to lay siege to strongholds and break through enemy lines. These abilities are represented by the following traits.</text>
      <text>Siege Monster. Emberosa deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
      <text>Tackle. When Emberosa enters any enemy's space for the first time on a turn, the enemy must succeed on a DC 19 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 185</description>
    <environment>underdark, mountain</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Ezzat</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Any Evil Alignment</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>135 (18d8+54)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Con +10, Int +12, Wis +9</save>
    <skill>Arcana +19, History +12, Insight +9, Perception +9</skill>
    <passive>19</passive>
    <languages>Common plus up to five other languages</languages>
    <cr>21</cr>
    <resist>cold, lightning, necrotic</resist>
    <immune>poison; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Ezzat wears an amulet of proof against detection and location.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If Ezzat fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Rejuvenation</name>
      <text>If it has a phylactery, a destroyed lich gains a new body in 1d10 days, regaining all its hit points and becoming active again. The new body appears within 5 feet of the phylactery.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Turn Resistance</name>
      <text>Ezzat has advantage on saving throws against any effect that turns undead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Paralyzing Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +12 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 10 (3d6) cold damage. The target must succeed on a DC 18 Constitution saving throw or be paralyzed for 1 minute. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <attack>Paralyzing Touch|+12|3d6</attack>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>The undead can take 4 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The undead regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Cantrip</name>
      <text>Ezzat casts a cantrip.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Paralyzing Touch (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Ezzat uses its Paralyzing Touch.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Frightening Gaze (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Ezzat fixes its gaze on one creature it can see within 10 feet of it. The target must succeed on a DC 18 Wisdom saving throw against this magic or become frightened for 1 minute. The frightened target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. If a target's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the target is immune to Ezzat's gaze for the next 24 hours.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Disrupt Life (Costs 3 Actions)</name>
      <text>Each non-undead creature within 20 feet of Ezzat must make a DC 18 Constitution saving throw against this magic, taking 21 (6d6) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Lair Actions</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>On initiative count 20 (losing initiative ties), the lich can take a lair action to cause one of the following magical effects; the lich can't use the same effect two rounds in a row:</text>
      <text>• The lich rolls a d8 and regains a spell slot of that level or lower. If it has no spent spell slots of that level or lower, nothing happens.</text>
      <text>• The lich targets one creature it can see within 30 feet of it. A crackling cord of negative energy tethers the lich to the target. Whenever the lich takes damage, the target must make a DC 18 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the lich takes half the damage (rounded down), and the target takes the remaining damage. This tether lasts until initiative count 20 on the next round or until the lich or the target is no longer in the lich's lair.</text>
      <text>• The lich calls forth the spirits of creatures that died in its lair. These apparitions materialize and attack one creature that the lich can see within 60 feet of it. The target must succeed on a DC 18 Constitution saving throw, taking 52 (15d6) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a success. The apparitions then disappear.</text>
      </legendary>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Ezzat is an 18th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 20, +12 to hit with spell attacks). Ezzat has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): mage hand, prestidigitation, ray of frost</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, magic missile, shield, thunderwave</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, invisibility, Melf's acid arrow, mirror image</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): animate dead, counterspell, dispel magic, fireball</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): blight, dimension door</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): cloudkill, scrying</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): disintegrate, globe of invulnerability</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): finger of death, plane shift</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): dominate monster, power word stun</text>
      <text>• 9th level (1 slots): power word kill</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>mage hand, prestidigitation, ray of frost, detect magic, magic missile, shield, thunderwave, detect thoughts, invisibility, Melf's acid arrow, mirror image, animate dead, counterspell, dispel magic, fireball, blight, dimension door, cloudkill, scrying, disintegrate, globe of invulnerability, finger of death, plane shift, dominate monster, power word stun, power word kill</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 262</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Fazrian</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>200 (16d10+112)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., fly 120 ft.</speed>
    <str>24</str>
    <dex>20</dex>
    <con>24</con>
    <int>19</int>
    <wis>22</wis>
    <cha>25</cha>
    <save>Con +12, Wis +11, Cha +12</save>
    <skill>Perception +11</skill>
    <passive>21</passive>
    <languages>all, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>16</cr>
    <resist>radiant; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Angelic Weapons</name>
      <text>Fazrian's weapon attacks are magical. When Fazrian hits with any weapon, the weapon deals an extra 5d8 radiant damage (included in the attack).</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Divine Awareness</name>
      <text>Fazrian knows if it hears a lie.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Fazrian has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Fazrian makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Greatsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 21 (4d6 + 7) slashing damage plus 22 (5d8) radiant damage.</text>
      <attack>Greatsword|+12|4d6+7</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Fazrian's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 20). Fazrian can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: detect evil and good, invisibility (self only)</text>
      <text>3/day each: blade barrier, dispel evil and good, flame strike, raise dead</text>
      <text>1/day each: commune, control weather, insect plague</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>detect evil and good, invisibility, blade barrier, dispel evil and good, flame strike, raise dead, commune, control weather, insect plague</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 275</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Fidelio</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>80 (10d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>7</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>any languages it knew in life</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist>acid, fire, lightning, thunder; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>cold, necrotic, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Ethereal Sight</name>
      <text>Fidelio can see 60 feet into the Ethereal Plane when it is on the Material Plane, and vice versa.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Incorporeal Movement</name>
      <text>Fidelio can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain. It takes 5 (1d10) force damage if it ends its turn inside an object.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Withering Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 17 (4d6 + 3) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Withering Touch|+5|4d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Etherealness</name>
      <text>Fidelio enters the Ethereal Plane from the Material Plane, or vice versa. It is visible on the Material Plane while it is in the Border Ethereal, and vice versa, yet it can't affect or be affected by anything on the other plane.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Horrifying Visage</name>
      <text>Each non-undead creature within 60 feet of Fidelio that can see it must succeed on a DC 13 Wisdom saving throw or be frightened for 1 minute. If the save fails by 5 or more, the target also ages 1d4 x 10 years. A frightened target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the frightened condition on itself on a success. If a target's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the target is immune to this ghost's Horrifying Visage for the next 24 hours. The aging effect can be reversed with a  greater restoration spell, but only within 24 hours of it occurring.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Possession (Recharge 6)</name>
      <text>One humanoid that Fidelio can see within 5 feet of it must succeed on a DC 13 Charisma saving throw or be possessed by Fidelio; Fidelio then disappears, and the target is incapacitated and loses control of its body. Fidelio now controls the body but doesn't deprive the target of awareness. Fidelio can't be targeted by any attack, spell, or other effect, except ones that turn undead, and it retains its alignment, Intelligence, Wisdom, Charisma, and immunity to being charmed and frightened. It otherwise uses the possessed target's statistics, but doesn't gain access to the target's knowledge, class features, or proficiencies.</text>
      <text>The possession lasts until the body drops to 0 hit points, Fidelio ends it as a bonus action, or Fidelio is turned or forced out by an effect like the dispel evil and good spell. When the possession ends, Fidelio reappears in an unoccupied space within 5 feet of the body. The target is immune to this ghost's Possession for 24 hours after succeeding on the saving throw or after the possession ends.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 197</description>
    <environment>underdark, urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Five-Armed Troll</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>84 (8d10+40)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>7</int>
    <wis>9</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Giant</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>The troll has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Regeneration</name>
      <text>The troll regains 10 hit points at the start of its turn. If the troll takes acid or fire damage, this trait doesn't function at the start of the troll's next turn. The troll dies only if it starts its turn with 0 hit points and doesn't regenerate.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The troll makes six attacks: one with its bite and five with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+7|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+7|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Loathsome Limbs</name>
      <text>Whenever the troll takes at least 15 slashing damage at one time, roll a d20 to determine what else happens to it:</text>
      <text>• 1–10: Nothing else happens.</text>
      <text>• 11–14: One leg is severed from the troll if it has any legs left.</text>
      <text>• 15–18: One arm is severed from the troll if it has any arms left.</text>
      <text>• 19–20: The troll is decapitated, but the troll dies only if it can't regenerate. If it dies, so does the severed head.</text>
      <text>If the troll finishes a short or long rest without reattaching a severed limb or head, the part regrows. At that point, the severed part dies. Until then, a severed part acts on the troll's initiative and has its own action and movement. A severed part has AC 13, 10 hit points, and the troll's Regeneration trait.</text>
      <text>A severed leg is unable to attack and has a speed of 5 feet.</text>
      <text>A severed arm has a speed of 5 feet and can make one claw attack on its turn, with disadvantage on the attack roll unless the troll can see the arm and its target. Each time the troll loses an arm, it loses a claw attack.</text>
      <text>If its head is severed, the troll loses its bite attack and its body is blinded unless the head can see it. The severed head has a speed of 0 feet and the troll's Keen Smell trait. It can make a bite attack but only against a target in its space.</text>
      <text>The troll's speed is halved if it's missing a leg. If it loses both legs, it falls prone. If it has both arms, it can crawl. With only one arm, it can still crawl, but its speed is halved. With no arms or legs, its speed is 0, and it can't benefit from bonuses to speed.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 154</description>
    <environment>underdark, mountain, forest, swamp, hill, arctic</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Flying Trident</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>17 (5d6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>5</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save>Dex +4</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>7</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Antimagic Susceptibility</name>
      <text>The trident is incapacitated while in the area of an antimagic field. If targeted by dispel magic, the trident must succeed on a Constitution saving throw against the caster's spell save DC or fall unconscious for 1 minute.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>False Appearance</name>
      <text>While the trident remains motionless and isn't flying, it is indistinguishable from a normal trident.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Longtrident</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d8 + 1) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Longtrident|+3|1d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 106</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Giant Flying Spider</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>26 (4d10+4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>4</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Stealth +7</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 10 ft., darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Spider Climb</name>
      <text>The spider can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without needing to make an ability check.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Web Sense</name>
      <text>While in contact with a web, the spider knows the exact location of any other creature in contact with the same web.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Web Walker</name>
      <text>The spider ignores movement restrictions caused by webbing.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage, and the target must make a DC 11 Constitution saving throw, taking 9 (2d8) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. If the poison damage reduces the target to 0 hit points, the target is stable but poisoned for 1 hour, even after regaining hit points, and is paralyzed while poisoned in this way.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      <attack>Bite||2d8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Web (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 30/60 ft., one creature. The target is restrained by webbing. As an action, the restrained target can make a DC 12 Strength check, bursting the webbing on a success. The webbing can also be attacked and destroyed (AC 10; hp 5; vulnerability to fire damage; immunity to bludgeoning, poison, and psychic damage).</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 150</description>
    <environment>underdark, forest, swamp, urban, desert</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>drow Mutated Drow</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>humanoid (elf)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Good (50%) Neutral Evil (50%)</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>200 (16d12+96)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>27</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>22</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Con +10, Wis +7, Cha +7</save>
    <skill>Insight +7, Perception +1</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Common, drow, Elvish</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>The drow has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put drow Mutated Drow to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, drow Mutated Drow has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The drow makes two morningstar attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Morningstar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 21 (3d8 + 8) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Morningstar|+12|3d8+8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Rock</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, range 60/240 ft., one target. 30 (4d10 + 8) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Rock|+12|4d10+8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: New drow Options</name>
      <text>Some adult cloud drows have the magical ability to create barriers of gale-force wind around themselves that can deflect incoming missiles. Others like to fling enemies through the air. These abilities are represented by the following action options.</text>
      <text>Fling. The drow tries to throw a Small or Medium creature within 10 feet of it. The target must succeed on a DC 20 Dexterity saving throw or be hurled up to 60 feet horizontally in a direction of the drow's choice and land prone, taking 4 (1d8) bludgeoning damage for every 10 feet it was thrown.</text>
      <text>Wind Aura. A magical aura of wind surrounds the drow. The aura is a 10-foot-radius sphere that lasts as long as the drow maintains concentration on it (as if concentrating on a spell). While the aura is in effect, the drow gains a +2 bonus to its AC against ranged weapon attacks, and all open flames within the aura are extinguished unless they are magical.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The drow's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma. It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: detect magic, fog cloud, light</text>
      <text>3/day each: feather fall, fly, misty step, telekinesis</text>
      <text>1/day each: control weather, gaseous form</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt;'s innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 15). &lt;$title_short_name$&gt; can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: dancing lights</text>
      <text>1/day each: darkness, faerie fire</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>detect magic, fog cloud, light, feather fall, fly, misty step, telekinesis, control weather, gaseous form, dancing lights, darkness, faerie fire</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 143</description>
    <environment>mountain</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Glyster</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>dragon</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>212 (17d12+102)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., fly 80 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>25</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>23</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>19</cha>
    <save>Dex +5, Con +11, Wis +7, Cha +9</save>
    <skill>Insight +7, Perception +12, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>22</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>15</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>lightning</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft., darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>Glyster can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If Glyster fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Glyster can use its Frightful Presence. It then makes three attacks: one with its bite and two with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 18 (2d10 + 7) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+12|2d10+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 14 (2d6 + 7) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+12|2d6+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. 16 (2d8 + 7) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Tail|+12|2d8+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Frightful Presence</name>
      <text>Each creature of Glyster's choice that is within 120 feet of Glyster and aware of it must succeed on a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw or become frightened for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. If a creature's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the creature is immune to Glyster's Frightful Presence for the next 24 hours.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Breath Weapons (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>Glyster uses one of the following breath weapons.</text>
      <text>• Lightning Breath. Glyster exhales lightning in a 90-foot line that is 5 feet wide. Each creature in that line must make a DC 19 Dexterity saving throw, taking 66 (12d10) lightning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Breath Weapons (Recharge 5-6)||12d10</attack>
      <text>• Repulsion Breath. Glyster exhales repulsion energy in a 30-foot cone. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 19 Strength saving throw. On a failed save, the creature is pushed 60 feet away from Glyster.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Change Shape</name>
      <text>Glyster magically polymorphs into a humanoid or beast that has a challenge rating no higher than its own, or back into its true form. It reverts to its true form if it dies. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying is absorbed or borne by the new form (Glyster's choice).</text>
      <text>In a new form, Glyster retains its alignment, hit points, Hit Dice, ability to speak, proficiencies, Legendary Resistance, lair actions, and Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma scores, as well as this action. Its statistics and capabilities are otherwise replaced by those of the new form, except any class features or legendary actions of that form.</text>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>The dragon can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The dragon regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Detect</name>
      <text>Glyster makes a Wisdom (Perception) check.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Tail Attack</name>
      <text>Glyster makes a tail attack.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Wing Attack (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Glyster beats its wings. Each creature within 10 feet of Glyster must succeed on a DC 20 Dexterity saving throw or take 14 (2d6 + 7) bludgeoning damage and be knocked prone. Glyster can then fly up to half its flying speed.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Lair Actions</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>On initiative count 20 (losing initiative ties), the dragon takes a lair action to cause one of the following effects:</text>
      <text>• The dragon creates fog as though it had cast the fog cloud spell. The fog lasts until initiative count 20 on the next round.</text>
      <text>• A thunderclap originates at a point the dragon can see within 120 feet of it. Each creature within a 20-foot radius centered on that point must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw or take 5 (1d10) thunder damage and be deafened until the end of its next turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Regional Effects</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>The region containing a legendary bronze dragon's lair is warped by the dragon's magic.</text>
      <text>• Once per day, the dragon can alter the weather in a 6-mile radius centered on its lair. The dragon doesn't need to be outdoors; otherwise the effect is identical to the control weather spell.</text>
      <text>• Underwater plants within 6 miles of the dragon's lair take on dazzlingly brilliant hues.</text>
      <text>• Within its lair, the dragon can set illusory sounds, such as soft music and strange echoes, so that they can be heard in various parts of the lair.</text>
      <text>If the dragon dies, changed weather reverts to normal, as described in the spell, and the other effects fade in 1d10 days.</text>
      </legendary>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 241</description>
    <environment>coastal</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Gorka Tharn</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>97 (13d8+39)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>18</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Con +8, Int +5, Wis +9, Cha +8</save>
    <skill>History +5, Religion +5</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>the languages it knew in life</languages>
    <cr>15</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>necrotic, poison; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</immune>
    <vulnerable>fire</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The mummy lord has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Rejuvenation</name>
      <text>A destroyed mummy lord gains a new body in 24 hours if its heart is intact, regaining all its hit points and becoming active again. The new body appears within 5 feet of the mummy lord's heart.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The mummy can use its Dreadful Glare and makes one attack with its rotting fist.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Rotting Fist</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 14 (3d6 + 4) bludgeoning damage plus 21 (6d6) necrotic damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 16 Constitution saving throw or be cursed with mummy rot. The cursed target can't regain hit points, and its hit point maximum decreases by 10 (3d6) for every 24 hours that elapse. If the curse reduces the target's hit point maximum to 0, the target dies, and its body turns to dust. The curse lasts until removed by the remove curse spell or other magic.</text>
      <attack>Rotting Fist|+9|3d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dreadful Glare</name>
      <text>The mummy lord targets one creature it can see within 60 feet of it. If the target can see the mummy lord, it must succeed on a DC 16 Wisdom saving throw against this magic or become frightened until the end of the mummy's next turn. If the target fails the saving throw by 5 or more, it is also paralyzed for the same duration. A target that succeeds on the saving throw is immune to the Dreadful Glare of all mummies and mummy lords for the next 24 hours.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Enlarge (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>For 1 minute, the mummy lord magically increases in size, along with anything it is wearing or carrying. While enlarged, the mummy lord is Large, doubles its damage dice with its Rotting Fist attack, and makes Strength checks and Strength saving throws with advantage. If the mummy lord lacks the room to become Large, it attains the maximum size possible in the space available.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Invisibility (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>The mummy lord magically turns invisible for up to 1 hour or until it attacks, it casts a spell, it uses its Enlarge, or its concentration is broken (as if concentrating on a spell). Any equipment the mummy lord wears or carries is invisible with it.</text>
      <text>The stalagmite in the northwest alcove is hollow and serves as Gorka Tharn's sarcophagus. The mummy lord is lodged inside the stalagmite's funnel-shaped interior. When it awakens, the mummy lord uses a stone shape spell to create an opening large enough for it to emerge. It destroys any intruders in its lair, then returns to its sarcophagus and its slumber.</text>
      <text>At the bottom of the stalagmite's hollow cavity, four 1-foot-tall clay urns contain Gorka Tharn's preserved internal organs, including the mummy lord's shriveled heart. Only by destroying the heart can the characters prevent the mummy lord from rejuvenating. The heart is a Tiny object with AC 5, 25 hit points, and immunity to all damage except fire.</text>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>The undead can take 5 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The undead regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Attack</name>
      <text>The mummy lord makes one attack with its rotting fist or uses its Dreadful Glare.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Blinding Dust</name>
      <text>Blinding dust and sand swirls magically around the mummy lord. Each creature within 5 feet of the mummy lord must succeed on a DC 16 Constitution saving throw or be blinded until the end of the creature's next turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Blasphemous Word (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>The mummy lord utters a blasphemous word. Each non-undead creature within 10 feet of the mummy lord that can hear the magical utterance must succeed on a DC 16 Constitution saving throw or be stunned until the end of the mummy lord's next turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Channel Negative Energy (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>The mummy lord magically unleashes negative energy. Creatures within 60 feet of the mummy lord, including ones behind barriers and around corners, can't regain hit points until the end of the mummy lord's next turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Whirlwind of Sand (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>The mummy lord magically transforms into a whirlwind of sand, moves up to 60 feet, and reverts to its normal form. While in whirlwind form, the mummy lord is immune to all damage, and it can't be grappled, petrified, knocked prone, restrained, or stunned. Equipment worn or carried by the mummy lord remain in its possession.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Lair Actions</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>On initiative count 20 (losing initiative ties), the mummy lord takes a lair action to cause one of the following effects; the mummy lord can't use the same effect two rounds in a row:</text>
      <text>• Each undead creature in the lair can pinpoint the location of each living creature within 120 feet of it until initiative count 20 on the next round.</text>
      <text>• Each undead in the lair has advantage on saving throws against effects that turn undead until initiative count 20 on the next round.</text>
      <text>• Until initiative count 20 on the next round, any non-undead creature that tries to cast a spell of 4th level or lower in the mummy lord's lair is wracked with pain. The creature can choose another action, but if it tries to cast the spell, it must make a DC 16 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, it takes 1d6 necrotic damage per level of the spell, and the spell has no effect and is wasted.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Regional Effects</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>A mummy lord's temple or tomb is warped in any of the following ways by the creature's dark presence:</text>
      <text>• Food instantly molders and water instantly evaporates when brought into the lair. Other non magical drinks are spoiled - wine turning to vinegar, for instance.</text>
      <text>• Divination spells cast within the lair by creatures other than the mummy lord have a 25 percent chance to provide misleading results, as determined by the DM. If a divination spell already has a chance to fail or become unreliable when cast multiple times, that chance increases by 25 percent.</text>
      <text>• A creature that takes treasure from the lair is cursed until the treasure is returned. The cursed target has disadvantage on all saving throws. The curse lasts until removed by a remove curse spell or other magic.</text>
      <text>If the mummy lord is destroyed, these regional effects end immediately.</text>
      </legendary>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The mummy lord is a 10th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks). The mummy lord has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): sacred flame, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): command, guiding bolt, shield of faith</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): hold person, silence, spiritual weapon</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): animate dead, dispel magic</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): divination, guardian of faith</text>
      <text>• 5th level (2 slots): contagion, insect plague</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): harm</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1</slots>
    <spells>sacred flame, thaumaturgy, command, guiding bolt, shield of faith, hold person, silence, spiritual weapon, animate dead, dispel magic, divination, guardian of faith, contagion, insect plague, harm</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 257</description>
    <environment>desert</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Gorzil's Gang Troglodyte</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (troglodyte)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>11 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>13 (2d8+4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Stealth +2</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Troglodyte</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Chameleon Skin</name>
      <text>The troglodyte has advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks made to hide.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Stench</name>
      <text>Any creature other than a troglodyte that starts its turn within 5 feet of the troglodyte must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned until the start of the creature's next turn. On a successful saving throw, the creature is immune to the stench of all troglodytes for 1 hour.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, the troglodyte has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The troglodyte makes three attacks: one with its bite and two with its longsword.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Longsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) slashing damage, or 7 (1d10 + 2) slashing damage if used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Longsword|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 150</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Halaster Blackcloak</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (17 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>246 (29d8+116)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>24</int>
    <wis>18</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Int +14, Wis +11</save>
    <skill>Arcana +21, History +21, Perception +11</skill>
    <passive>21</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Celestial, Common, Draconic, Dwarvish, Elvish, Infernal, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>23</cr>
    <resist>fire; lightning (granted by the blast scepter, see "Special Equipment" below)</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Halaster wears a robe of eyes that lets him see in all directions, gives him darkvision out to a range of 120 feet, grants advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight, and allows him to see invisible creatures and objects, as well as into the Ethereal Plane, out to a range of 120 feet.</text>
      <text>Halaster wields a blast scepter (a very rare magic item that requires attunement). It can be used as an arcane focus. Whoever is attuned to the blast scepter gains resistance to fire and lightning damage and can, as an action, use it to cast thunderwave as a 4th-level spell (save DC 16) without expending a spell slot.</text>
      <text>Halaster also wears a horned ring (a very rare magic item that requires attunement), which allows an attuned wearer to ignore Undermountain's magical restrictions (see "Alterations to Magic").</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Arcane Recovery (1/Day)</name>
      <text>When he finishes a short rest, Halaster recovers all his spell slots of 5th level and lower.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If Halaster fails a saving throw, he can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Rejuvenation</name>
      <text>If Halaster dies in Undermountain, he revives after 1d10 days, with all his hit points and any missing body parts restored. His new body appears in a random safe location in Undermountain.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Blast Scepter</name>
      <text>Halaster uses his blast scepter to cast thunderwave as a 4th-level spell. Each creature in a 15-foot cube originating from him must make a DC 16 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, a creature takes 5d8 thunder damage and is pushed 10 feet away. On a successful save, the creature takes half as much damage and isn't pushed</text>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>Halaster can take 2 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Halaster regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Cast Spell</name>
      <text>Halaster casts a spell of 3rd level or lower.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Spell Ward (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Halaster expends a spell slot of 4th level or lower and gains 5 temporary hit points per level of the slot.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Lair Actions</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>On initiative count 20 (losing initiative ties), Halaster takes a lair action to cause one of the following effects:</text>
      <text>• Halaster targets a volume of unoccupied space or solid stone no larger than four 10-foot cubes within 30 feet of him, turning the open space to solid, worked stone or vice versa.</text>
      <text>• Halaster causes one door or archway within 30 feet of him to disappear and be replaced by a blank wall, or he restores a door or an archway previously removed in this way.</text>
      <text>• Halaster deactivates or reactivates one of Undermountain's magic gates. The gate must be within 120 feet of him.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Regional Effects</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>When Halaster is in Undermountain, the following effects can occur in any location within the dungeon or in any extraplanar extension of the dungeon:</text>
      <text>• A magical scrying sensor appears, taking the form of a ghostly, 1-foot-diameter humanoid eye surrounded by motes of light. The sensor is stationary, though Halaster can reorient the eye to face in any direction. Halaster can see through the eye as though he was in its space. The eye can't be harmed or dispelled, but it winks out within an antimagic field. A scrying eye lasts until Halaster ends the effect (no action required).</text>
      <text>• A minor illusory effect is triggered, as though Halaster had cast minor illusion in an area. Common illusions include the echo of rattling chains, the distant sound of explosive spells being cast, a dusty cloak or a rusty helm floating as though worn by an invisible figure, and illusory footprints appearing on a dusty floor.</text>
      <text>• Silent apparitions of dead adventurers drift through halls and rooms as though they are lost. An apparition can't be harmed, and it doesn't acknowledge creatures or objects in any way. It can't be dispelled but is suppressed within an antimagic field.</text>
      </legendary>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Halaster is a 20th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 22, +14 to hit with spell attacks). He can cast disguise self and invisibility at will. He can cast fly and lightning bolt once each without expending a spell slot, but can't do so again until he finishes a short or long rest. Halaster has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>At will: disguise self, invisibility</text>
      <text>1/day: fly, lightning bolt</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): dancing lights, fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): mage armor, magic missile, shield, silent image</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): arcane lock, cloud of daggers, darkvision, knock</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, dispel magic, fireball</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): confusion, hallucinatory terrain, polymorph</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): Bigby's hand, geas, wall of force</text>
      <text>• 6th level (2 slots): chain lightning, globe of invulnerability, programmed illusion</text>
      <text>• 7th level (2 slots): finger of death, symbol, teleport</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): maze, mind blank</text>
      <text>• 9th level (1 slots): meteor swarm, wish</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 2, 2, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>disguise self, invisibility, fly, lightning bolt, dancing lights, fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, mage armor, magic missile, shield, silent image, arcane lock, cloud of daggers, darkvision, knock, counterspell, dispel magic, fireball, confusion, hallucinatory terrain, polymorph, Bigby's hand, geas, wall of force, chain lightning, globe of invulnerability, programmed illusion, finger of death, symbol, teleport, maze, mind blank, meteor swarm, wish</spells>
    <description>As the master of Undermountain, Halaster can alter the entire dungeon to some extent. His lair actions and regional effects don't extend beyond Undermountain.
Halaster, the Mad Mage of Undermountain, is the deranged individual behind most of the traps and horrors found in the great dungeon under Waterdeep. Undermountain is his home, an amusement gallery in which others perform to entertain him.
The Mad Mage knows the ever-changing ways of Undermountain as no one else does, for he is the one who controls those changes. He prefers to remain unseen, skulking about invisibly or peering through scrying sensors that resemble wide-open eyes surrounded by sparkling motes of light.
Halaster's abilities far exceed those of most mortal wizards. His expertise with magic gates allows him to travel far and wide to engage in magical research. He spends much of his time creating gates, moving them around, and casting elder runes on them. Halaster's gates connect the different levels of Undermountain, thus enabling him to bring new monsters into the dungeon to replenish those that die or escape. Even as groups of adventurers try to gain decisive control of just a small section of Undermountain's halls, Halaster constantly alters the dungeon's perils to thwart them.
Halaster's true form is that of a tall, gaunt, male human, but he uses magic to take on many other visages and shapes. No matter what form he wears, the Mad Mage giggles and mutters incessantly. Contrary to appearances, however, Halaster is alert and attentive to the activities and preparations of all beings near him. He never willingly enters combat without first casting mage armor and mind blank on himself.
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 310</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Halaster Horror</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>20 (plate armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>60 (8d8+24)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't adamantine</resist>
    <immune>force, necrotic, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, stunned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The Halaster horror has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Spell Immunity</name>
      <text>The Halaster horror is immune to the cone of cold, disintegrate, and fireball spells.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The Halaster horror makes two longsword attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Longsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (1d8 + 4) slashing damage, or 9 (1d10 + 4) slashing damage if used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Longsword|+6|1d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 129</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Halaster Puppet</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>8</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>frightened, exhaustion</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>8</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Antimagic Susceptibility</name>
      <text>The puppet is destroyed if a successful dispel magic spell (DC 15) is cast on it</text>
      </trait>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 31</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Haungharassk</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>6</ac>
    <hp>52 (7d12+7)</hp>
    <speed>walk 10 ft., climb 10 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>3</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Salt Sensitivity</name>
      <text>A pound of salt thrown onto the snail's skin deals 1d6 acid damage to the creature.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magical Properties</name>
      <text>A creature that uses an action to touch the living snail gains 6 temporary hit points that last for 24 hours. Any creature or object that touches the living snail also gains the benefit of a remove curse spell. The snail loses these magical properties if it dies.</text>
      </trait>
    <description>Haungharassk is a magical snail as large as an elephant, with a shell of gleaming gold.
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 258</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Horned Sister</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (tiefling)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with horned sister armor)</ac>
    <hp>40 (9d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Int +6, Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, History +6</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>any four languages, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist>fire</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (sister 1d4 + 2) piercing dahorned sister.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Familiars</name>
      <text>Any spellcaster that can cast the find familiar spell (such as an archhorned sister or horned sister) is likely to have a familiar. The familiar can be one of the creatures described in the spell (see the Player's Handbook) or some other Tiny monster, such as a crawling claw, imp, pseudodragon, or quasit.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The horned sister is a 9th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks). The horned sister has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, horned sister hand, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, horned sister armor, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): misty step, suggestion</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fireball, fly</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): greater invisibility, ice storm</text>
      <text>• 5th level (1 slots): cone of cold</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt;'s innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 11). &lt;$title_short_name$&gt; can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>1/day each: darkness, hellish rebuke</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>fire bolt, light, horned sister hand, prestidigitation, detect magic, horned sister armor, magic missile, shield, misty step, suggestion, counterspell, fireball, fly, greater invisibility, ice storm, cone of cold, thaumaturgy, darkness, hellish rebuke</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 118</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Huge Gray Ooze</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>ooze</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>8</ac>
    <hp>152 (16d12+48)</hp>
    <speed>walk 10 ft., climb 10 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>6</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>6</wis>
    <cha>2</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Stealth +2</skill>
    <passive>8</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist>acid, cold, fire</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amorphous</name>
      <text>The ooze can move through a space as narrow as 1 inch wide without squeezing.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Corrode Metal</name>
      <text>Any nonmagical weapon made of metal that hits the ooze corrodes. After dealing damage, the weapon takes a permanent and cumulative −1 penalty to damage rolls. If its penalty drops to −5, the weapon is destroyed. Nonmagical ammunition made of metal that hits the ooze is destroyed after dealing damage.</text>
      <text>The ooze can eat through 2-inch-thick, nonmagical metal in 1 round.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>False Appearance</name>
      <text>While the ooze remains motionless, it is indistinguishable from an oily pool or wet rock.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Pseudopod</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) bludgeoning damage plus 7 (2d6) acid damage, and if the target is wearing nonmagical metal armor, its armor is partly corroded and takes a permanent and cumulative −1 penalty to the AC it offers. The armor is destroyed if the penalty reduces its AC to 10.</text>
      <attack>Pseudopod|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Psychic Gray Ooze</name>
      <text>A gray ooze that lives a long time can evolve to become more intelligent and develop limited psionic ability. Such occurrences are more common in gray oozes that live near psioncic creatures such as mind flayer, suggesting that the ooze can sense and mimic psionic ability.</text>
      <text>A psionic gray ooze has an intelligence score of 6 (-2), as well as the following additional action.</text>
      <text>Psychic Crush (Recharge 5-6). The ooze targets one creature that it can sense within 60 feet of it. The target must make a DC 10 Intelligence saving throw, taking 10 (3d6) psychic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 243</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Intelligent Black Pudding</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>ooze</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>7</ac>
    <hp>85 (10d10+30)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., climb 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>5</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>6</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>8</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>acid, cold, lightning, slashing</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amorphous</name>
      <text>The pudding can move through a space as narrow as 1 inch wide without squeezing.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Corrosive Form</name>
      <text>A creature that touches the pudding or hits it with a melee attack while within 5 feet of it takes 4 (1d8) acid damage. Any nonmagical weapon made of metal or wood that hits the pudding corrodes. After dealing damage, the weapon takes a permanent and cumulative −1 penalty to damage rolls. If its penalty drops to −5, the weapon is destroyed. Nonmagical ammunition made of metal or wood that hits the pudding is destroyed after dealing damage. The pudding can eat through 2-inch-thick, nonmagical wood or metal in 1 round.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Spider Climb</name>
      <text>The pudding can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without needing to make an ability check.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Pseudopod</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) bludgeoning damage plus 18 (4d8) acid damage. In addition, nonmagical armor worn by the target is partly dissolved and takes a permanent and cumulative −1 penalty to the AC it offers. The armor is destroyed if the penalty reduces its AC to 10.</text>
      <attack>Pseudopod|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Split</name>
      <text>When a pudding that is Medium or larger is subjected to lightning or slashing damage, it splits into two new puddings if it has at least 10 hit points. Each new pudding has hit points equal to half the original pudding's, rounded down. New puddings are one size smaller than the original pudding.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 244</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Iron Spider</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>19</ac>
    <hp>80</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>3</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>6</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>80</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Web Cable</name>
      <text>The iron spider shoots out a 6-inch-thick web cable up to 50 feet long, attaching the far end of the cable to a solid surface up to 50 feet away from it. As a bonus action, it can detach the other end of the cable from itself and attach it to a solid surface within 10 feet of it. Once it creates 200 feet of web cable, the spider can't produce any more cable until the next dawn.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 165</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Junior Drow Priestess of Lolth</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (elf)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (chain shirt)</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Medicine +7, Persuasion +3, Religion +5, Perception +1</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>any two languages, Elvish</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Divine Eminence</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, the priestess can expend a spell slot to cause its melee weapon attacks to magically deal an extra 10 (3d6) radiant damage to a target on a hit. This benefit lasts until the end of the turn. If the priestess expends a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the extra damage increases by 1d6 for each level above 1st.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put Junior Drow Priestess of Lolth to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, Junior Drow Priestess of Lolth has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Mace</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Mace|+2|1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The priestess is a 5th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). The priestess has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): cure wounds, guiding bolt, sanctuary</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): lesser restoration, spiritual weapon</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (2 slots): dispel magic, spirit guardians</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 2</slots>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt;'s innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 11). &lt;$title_short_name$&gt; can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: dancing lights</text>
      <text>1/day each: darkness, faerie fire</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy, cure wounds, guiding bolt, sanctuary, lesser restoration, spiritual weapon, dispel magic, spirit guardians, dancing lights, darkness, faerie fire</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 149</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Kavil</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>40 (9d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Int +6, Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, History +6</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>any four languages</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Familiars</name>
      <text>Any spellcaster that can cast the find familiar spell (such as an archmage or mage) is likely to have a familiar. The familiar can be one of the creatures described in the spell (see the Player's Handbook) or some other Tiny monster, such as a crawling claw, imp, pseudodragon, or quasit.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Kavil is a 9th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks). Kavil has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): misty step, suggestion</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fireball, fly</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): greater invisibility, ice storm</text>
      <text>• 5th level (1 slots): cone of cold</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield, misty step, suggestion, counterspell, fireball, fly, greater invisibility, ice storm, cone of cold</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 205</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Keresta Delvingstone</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead (shapechanger)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>144 (17d8+68)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Dex +9, Wis +7, Cha +9</save>
    <skill>Perception +7, Stealth +9</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>the languages it knew in life</languages>
    <cr>13</cr>
    <resist>necrotic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>If Keresta isn't in sunlight or running water, it can use its action to polymorph into a Tiny bat or a Medium cloud of mist, or back into its true form.</text>
      <text>While in bat form, Keresta can't speak, its walking speed is 5 feet, and it has a flying speed of 30 feet. Its statistics, other than its size and speed, are unchanged. Anything it is wearing transforms with it, but nothing it is carrying does. It reverts to its true form if it dies.</text>
      <text>While in mist form, Keresta can't take any actions, speak, or manipulate objects. It is weightless, has a flying speed of 20 feet, can hover, and can enter a hostile creature's space and stop there. In addition, if air can pass through a space, the mist can do so without squeezing, and it can't pass through water. It has advantage on Strength, Dexterity, and Constitution saving throws, and it is immune to all nonmagical damage, except the damage it takes from sunlight.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If Keresta fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Misty Escape</name>
      <text>When it drops to 0 hit points outside its resting place, Keresta transforms into a cloud of mist (as in the Shapechanger trait) instead of falling unconscious, provided that it isn't in sunlight or running water. If it can't transform, it is destroyed.</text>
      <text>While it has 0 hit points in mist form, it can't revert to its vampire form, and it must reach its resting place within 2 hours or be destroyed. Once in its resting place, it reverts to its vampire form. It is then paralyzed until it regains at least 1 hit point. After spending 1 hour in its resting place with 0 hit points, it regains 1 hit point.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Regeneration</name>
      <text>Keresta regains 20 hit points at the start of its turn if it has at least 1 hit point and isn't in sunlight or running water. If Keresta takes radiant damage or damage from holy water, this trait doesn't function at the start of Keresta's next turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Spider Climb</name>
      <text>Keresta can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without needing to make an ability check.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Vampire Weaknesses</name>
      <text>Keresta has the following flaws:</text>
      <text>Forbiddance. Keresta can't enter a residence without an invitation from one of the occupants.</text>
      <text>Harmed by Running Water. Keresta takes 20 acid damage if it ends its turn in running water.</text>
      <text>Stake to the Heart. If a piercing weapon made of wood is driven into Keresta's heart while Keresta is incapacitated in its resting place, Keresta is paralyzed until the stake is removed.</text>
      <text>Sunlight Hypersensitivity. Keresta takes 20 radiant damage when it starts its turn in sunlight. While in sunlight, it has disadvantage on attack rolls and ability checks.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack (Vampire Form Only)</name>
      <text>Keresta makes two attacks, only one of which can be a bite attack.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Unarmed Strike (Vampire Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 8 (1d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage. Instead of dealing damage, Keresta can grapple the target (escape DC 18).</text>
      <attack>Unarmed Strike (Vampire Form Only)|+9|1d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite (Bat or Vampire Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one willing creature, or a creature that is grappled by Keresta, incapacitated, or restrained. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage plus 10 (3d6) necrotic damage. The target's hit point maximum is reduced by an amount equal to the necrotic damage taken, and Keresta regains hit points equal to that amount. The reduction lasts until the target finishes a long rest. The target dies if this effect reduces its hit point maximum to 0. A humanoid slain in this way and then buried in the ground rises the following night as a vampire spawn under Keresta's control.</text>
      <attack>Bite (Bat or Vampire Form Only)|+9|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Charm</name>
      <text>Keresta targets one humanoid it can see within 30 feet of it. If the target can see Keresta, the target must succeed on a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw against this magic or be charmed by Keresta. The charmed target regards Keresta as a trusted friend to be heeded and protected. Although the target isn't under Keresta's control, it takes Keresta's requests or actions in the most favorable way it can, and it is a willing target for Keresta's bite attack.</text>
      <text>Each time Keresta or Keresta's companions do anything harmful to the target, it can repeat the saving throw, ending the effect on itself on a success. Otherwise, the effect lasts 24 hours or until Keresta is destroyed, is on a different plane of existence than the target, or takes a bonus action to end the effect.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Children of the Night (1/Day)</name>
      <text>The vampire magically calls 2d4 swarms of swarm of bats or swarm of rats, provided that the sun isn't up. While outdoors, the vampire can call 3d6 giant centipede instead. The called creatures arrive in 1d4 rounds, acting as allies of the vampire and obeying its spoken commands. The beasts remain for 1 hour, until the vampire dies, or until the vampire dismisses them as a bonus action.</text>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>The undead (shapechanger) can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The undead (shapechanger) regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Move</name>
      <text>Keresta moves up to its speed without provoking opportunity attacks.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Unarmed Strike</name>
      <text>Keresta makes one unarmed strike.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Bite (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Keresta makes one bite attack.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Regional Effects</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>The region surrounding a vampire's lair is warped by the creature's unnatural presence, creating any of the following effects:</text>
      <text>• There's a noticeable increase in the populations of bats, rats, and wolves in the region.</text>
      <text>• Plants within 500 feet of the lair wither, and their stems and branches become twisted and thorny.</text>
      <text>• Shadows cast within 500 feet of the lair seem abnormally gaunt and sometimes move as though alive.</text>
      <text>• A creeping fog clings to the ground within 500 feet of the vampire's lair. The fog occasionally takes eerie forms, such as grasping claws and writhing serpents.</text>
      <text>If the vampire is destroyed, these effects end after 2d6 days.</text>
      </legendary>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 232</description>
    <environment>urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Kol'daan</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (troglodyte)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>11 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>20 (2d8+4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Stealth +2</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Troglodyte</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Chameleon Skin</name>
      <text>Kol'daan has advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks made to hide.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Stench</name>
      <text>Any creature other than a troglodyte that starts its turn within 5 feet of Kol'daan must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned until the start of the creature's next turn. On a successful saving throw, the creature is immune to the stench of all troglodytes for 1 hour.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, Kol'daan has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Kol'daan makes three attacks: one with its bite and two with its claws or sparring sword.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Sparring Sword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d4 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Sparring Sword|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 155</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Large Mimic</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity (shapechanger)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>12 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>67 (9d10+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 15 ft.</speed>
    <str>17</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>5</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>acid</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>The mimic can use its action to polymorph into an object or back into its true, amorphous form. Its statistics are the same in each form. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying isn't transformed. It reverts to its true form if it dies.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Adhesive (Object Form Only)</name>
      <text>The mimic adheres to anything that touches it. A Huge or smaller creature adhered to the mimic is also grappled by it (escape DC 13). Ability checks made to escape this grapple have disadvantage.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>False Appearance (Object Form Only)</name>
      <text>While the mimic remains motionless, it is indistinguishable from an ordinary object.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Grappler</name>
      <text>The mimic has advantage on attack rolls against any creature grappled by it.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Pseudopod</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) bludgeoning damage. If the mimic is in object form, the target is subjected to its Adhesive trait.</text>
      <attack>Pseudopod|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage plus 4 (1d8) acid damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 76</description>
    <environment>underdark, urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Lava Child</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (lava child)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>60 (8d8+24)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft., climb 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +6, Survival +2</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Ignan</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from metal weapons</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Metal Immunity</name>
      <text>The lava child can move through metal without hindrance, and it has advantage on attack rolls against any creature wearing metal armor or using a metal shield.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The lava child makes two attacks: one with its bite and one with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+6|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+7|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Physically identical to one another, lava children have muscular builds and childish, perpetually grinning faces. Most are born in the Fountains of Creation, also known as the Plane of Magma, which is wedged between the Elemental Planes of Earth and Fire. Within volcanic caverns, lava children form communities, serving primordial beings out of fear or worshiping gods of earth and fire.
Though they're not violent by nature, lava children fiercely defend territory they claim as their own. Many intruders have been fooled by a lava child's smile, believing themselves welcome when in fact they're about to be torn limb from limb. Lava children typically stick close to their lairs, but actively hunt when food grows scarce.
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 313</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Living Unseen Servant</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>4 (1d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>2</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +2, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>understands one language (usually Common) but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Invisibility</name>
      <text>The unseen servant is invisible.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 1 bludgeoning damage.</text>
      </action>
    <description>Constructed Nature. A living spell doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.
Magical Essence. The process that creates a living spell changes the nature of its magic. A living spell isn't subject to dispel magic and isn't affected by an antimagic field.
Like an overzealous butler or maid, a living unseen servant spell busies itself with tasks in hopes of pleasing its creator. It can wield simple weapons but prefers not to. See invisibility, true seeing, and similar effects reveal that the servant has a shape similar to that of a slender humanoid adult.
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 313</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Mad Golem</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>264 (23d12+115)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>22</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't adamantine</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The golem is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The golem has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Weapons</name>
      <text>The golem's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The golem makes two slam attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 24 (4d8 + 6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+10|4d8+6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slow (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The golem targets one or more creatures it can see within 10 feet of it. Each target must make a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw against this magic. On a failed save, a target can't use reactions, its speed is halved, and it can't make more than one attack on its turn. In addition, the target can take either an action or a bonus action on its turn, not both. These effects last for 1 minute. A target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 254</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Maddgoth's Homunculus</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>55 (10d10)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>4</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Telepathic Bond</name>
      <text>While the homunculus is on the same plane of existence as its master, it can magically convey what it senses to its master, and the two can communicate telepathically.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 2d6 + 2 piercing damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 10 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned for 1 minute. If the saving throw fails by 5 or more, the target is instead poisoned for 5 (1d10) minutes and unconscious while poisoned in this way.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 96</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Marta Moonshadow</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (elf)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>40 (9d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Int +6, Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, History +6, Perception +1</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>any four languages, Elvish</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>Marta has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put her to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put &lt;$title_short_name$&gt; to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Familiars</name>
      <text>Any spellcaster that can cast the find familiar spell (such as an archmage or mage) is likely to have a familiar. The familiar can be one of the creatures described in the spell (see the Player's Handbook) or some other Tiny monster, such as a crawling claw, imp, pseudodragon, or quasit.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Marta is a 9th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks). Marta has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, ray of frost</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): misty step, suggestion</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fireball, fly</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): greater invisibility, ice storm</text>
      <text>• 5th level (1 slots): cone of cold</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, ray of frost, detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield, misty step, suggestion, counterspell, fireball, fly, greater invisibility, ice storm, cone of cold</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 46</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Melissara Shadowdusk</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>99 (18d8+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Int +9, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +13, History +13</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>any six languages</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <resist>damage from spells; nonmagical bludgeoning, piercing, slashing (from stoneskin)</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Melissara has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+6|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Familiars</name>
      <text>Any spellcaster that can cast the find familiar spell (such as an archmage or mage) is likely to have a familiar. The familiar can be one of the creatures described in the spell (see the Player's Handbook) or some other Tiny monster, such as a crawling claw, imp, pseudodragon, or quasit.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Melissara is an 18th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks). Melissara can cast disguise self and invisibility at will and has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>At will: disguise self, invisibility</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, identify, mage armor*, magic missile</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fly, lightning bolt</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): dimension door, fire shield, stoneskin*</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): cone of cold, scrying, wall of force</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): globe of invulnerability</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): teleport</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): mind blank*</text>
      <text>• 9th level (1 slots): time stop</text>
      <text>*Melissara casts these spells on itself before combat.</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>disguise self, invisibility, fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp, detect magic, identify, mage armor, magic missile, detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step, counterspell, fly, lightning bolt, dimension door, fire shield, stoneskin, cone of cold, scrying, wall of force, globe of invulnerability, teleport, mind blank, time stop</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 281</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Metal Wasp</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>13 (3d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 10 ft., fly 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Sting</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage, and the target must make a DC 11 Constitution saving throw, taking 10 (3d6) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. If the poison damage reduces the target to 0 hit points, the target is stable but poisoned for 1 hour, even after regaining hit points, and is paralyzed while poisoned in this way.</text>
      <attack>Sting|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      <attack>Sting||3d6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 174</description>
    <environment>grassland, forest, urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Mobar</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (goblin, shapechanger)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>42 (7d6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>8</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +3, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Goblin (can't speak in bat form)</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't silvered</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>Mobar can use its action to polymorph into a Medium bat-humanoid hybrid, or into a Large giant bat, or back into its true form, which is humanoid. Its statistics, other than its size, are the same in each form. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying isn't transformed. It reverts to its true form if it dies.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Echolocation (Bat or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Mobar has blindsight out to a range of 60 feet as long as it's not deafened.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Hearing</name>
      <text>Mobar has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Nimble Escape (Humanoid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Mobar can take the Disengage or Hide action as a bonus action on each of its turns.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, Mobar has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Blind Eye</name>
      <text>Due to poor depth perception, Mobar has disadvantage on any attack roll against a target more than 30 feet away.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>In humanoid form, Mobar makes two scimitar attacks or two shortbow attacks. In hybrid form, it can make one bite attack and one scimitar attack.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite (Bat or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage, and Mobar gains temporary hit points equal to the damage dealt. If the target is a humanoid, it must succeed on a DC 10 Constitution saving throw or be cursed with werebat lycanthropy.</text>
      <attack>Bite (Bat or Hybrid Form Only)|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Scimitar (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Scimitar (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortbow (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 77</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Muiral</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>195 (23d10+69)</hp>
    <speed>walk 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>18</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Con +8, Int +9</save>
    <skill>Arcana +9, Athletics +9, Perception +6, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish, Elvish, Goblin, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>13</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If Muiral fails a saving throw, he can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Muiral makes three attacks: two with his longsword and one with his sting.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Longsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d8 + 4) slashing damage, or 15 (2d10 + 4) slashing damage if used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Longsword|+9|2d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Sting</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 10 ft., one creature. 9 (1d10 + 4) piercing damage. The target must make a DC 16 Constitution saving throw, taking 27 (6d8) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Sting|+9|1d10+4</attack>
      <attack>Sting||6d8</attack>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>Muiral can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Muiral regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Cast Cantrip</name>
      <text>Muiral casts a cantrip.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Lunging Attack (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Muiral makes one longsword attack that has a reach of 10 feet.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Retreating Strike (Costs 3 Actions)</name>
      <text>Muiral moves up to his speed without provoking opportunity attacks. Before the move, he can make one longsword attack.</text>
      </legendary>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Muiral is a 13th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks). He has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): dancing lights, mage hand, prestidigitation, ray of frost, shocking grasp</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): expeditious retreat, fog cloud, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): darkness, knock, see invisibility, spider climb</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): animate dead, counterspell, lightning bolt</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): greater invisibility, polymorph</text>
      <text>• 5th level (2 slots): animate objects, wall of force</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): create undead, flesh to stone</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): finger of death</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>dancing lights, mage hand, prestidigitation, ray of frost, shocking grasp, expeditious retreat, fog cloud, magic missile, shield, darkness, knock, see invisibility, spider climb, animate dead, counterspell, lightning bolt, greater invisibility, polymorph, animate objects, wall of force, create undead, flesh to stone, finger of death</spells>
    <description>Muiral was an accomplished human warrior who long served as Halaster's bodyguard. His descent into madness began when he asked the Mad Mage to tutor him in the wizardly arts. Muiral learned enough magic to transform himself into a half-scorpion monstrosity, becoming known as Muiral the Misshapen. He then retired to the level of Undermountain that would later be called Muiral's Gauntlet, driving out and slaying its original drow denizens. Muiral now spends his days hunting adventurers and other interlopers for fun. Long years alone—and Halaster's influence—have rendered him utterly insane.
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 314</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Nerozar the Defeated</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>93 (11d10+33)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>8</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save>Wis +2</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages>understands Deep Speech and Undercommon but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned, prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Undead Fortitude</name>
      <text>If damage reduces Nerozar to 0 hit points, it must make a Constitution saving throw with a DC of 5 + the damage taken, unless the damage is radiant or from a critical hit. On a success, Nerozar drops to 1 hit point instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 14 (4d6) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+3|4d6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Eye Ray</name>
      <text>The zombie uses a random magical eye ray, choosing a target that it can see within 60 feet of it.</text>
      <text>1. Paralyzing Ray. The targeted creature must succeed on a DC 14 Constitution saving throw or be paralyzed for 1 minute. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <text>2. Fear Ray. The targeted creature must succeed on a DC 14 Wisdom saving throw or be frightened for 1 minute. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <text>3. Enervation Ray. The targeted creature must make a DC 14 Constitution saving throw, taking 36 (8d8) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Eye Ray||8d8</attack>
      <text>4. Telekinetic Ray. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 14 Strength saving throw, or the zombie moves it up to 30 feet in any direction. It is restrained by the ray's telekinetic grip until the start of the zombie's next turn or until the zombie is incapacitated. If the target is an object weighing 300 pounds or less that isn't being worn or carried, it is moved up to 30 feet in any direction. The zombie can also exert fine control on objects with this ray, such as manipulating a simple tool or opening a door or container.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 52</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Nester</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>99 (18d8+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Int +9, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +13, History +13</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>any six languages</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <resist>damage from spells; nonmagical bludgeoning, piercing, slashing (from stoneskin)</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Nester has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+6|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Familiars</name>
      <text>Any spellcaster that can cast the find familiar spell (such as an archmage or mage) is likely to have a familiar. The familiar can be one of the creatures described in the spell (see the Player's Handbook) or some other Tiny monster, such as a crawling claw, imp, pseudodragon, or quasit.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Nester is an 18th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks). Nester can cast disguise self and invisibility at will and has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>At will: disguise self, invisibility</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, identify, mage armor*, magic missile</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, animate dead, lightning bolt</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): blight, fire shield, stoneskin*</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): cone of cold, Rary's telepathic bond, wall of force</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): globe of invulnerability</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): teleport</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): mind blank*</text>
      <text>• 9th level (1 slots): time stop</text>
      <text>*Nester casts these spells on itself before combat.</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>disguise self, invisibility, fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp, detect magic, identify, mage armor, magic missile, detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step, counterspell, animate dead, lightning bolt, blight, fire shield, stoneskin, cone of cold, Rary's telepathic bond, wall of force, globe of invulnerability, teleport, mind blank, time stop</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 131</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Old Troglodyte</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (troglodyte)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>11 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>13 (2d8+4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Stealth +2</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Troglodyte</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Chameleon Skin</name>
      <text>The troglodyte has advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks made to hide.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Stench</name>
      <text>Any creature other than a troglodyte that starts its turn within 5 feet of the troglodyte must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned until the start of the creature's next turn. On a successful saving throw, the creature is immune to the stench of all troglodytes for 1 hour.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, the troglodyte has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The troglodyte makes two claw attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 155</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Otto</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>dragon</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Good</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>104 (16d10+16)</hp>
    <speed>walk 10 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>3</str>
    <dex>20</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Arcana +4, Perception +3, Stealth +7</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Draconic, Sylvan</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>The Colors of Age</name>
      <text>A faerie dragon's scales change hue as it ages, moving through all the colors of the rainbow. All faerie dragons have innate spellcasting ability, gaining new spells as they mature.</text>
      <text>Red—5 years or less</text>
      <text>Orange—6–10 years</text>
      <text>Yellow—11–20 years</text>
      <text>Green—21–30 years</text>
      <text>Blue—31–40 years</text>
      <text>Indigo—41–50 years</text>
      <text>Violet—51 years or more</text>
      <text>A green or older faerie dragon's CR increases to 2.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Superior Invisibility</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, the dragon can magically turn invisible until its concentration ends (as if concentrating on a spell). Any equipment the dragon wears or carries is invisible with it.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Limited Telepathy</name>
      <text>Using telepathy, the dragon can magically communicate with any other faerie dragon within 60 feet of it.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The faerie dragon has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 2d6 + 4 piercing damage.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Euphoria Breath (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The dragon exhales a puff of euphoria gas at one creature within 5 feet of it. The target must succeed on a DC 11 Wisdom saving throw, or for 1 minute, the target can't take reactions and must roll a d6 at the start of each of its turns to determine its behavior during the turn:</text>
      <text>1–4. The target takes no action or bonus action and uses all of its movement to move in a random direction.</text>
      <text>5–6. The target doesn't move, and the only thing it can do on its turn is make a DC 11 Wisdom saving throw, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The dragon's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 13). It can innately cast a number of spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>1/day each: color spray, dancing lights, hallucinatory terrain, mage hand, major image, minor illusion, mirror image, polymorph, suggestion</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>color spray, dancing lights, hallucinatory terrain, mage hand, major image, minor illusion, mirror image, polymorph, suggestion</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 96</description>
    <environment>forest</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Play-by-Play Generator</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>22 (4d8+4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Modron</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Axiomatic Mind</name>
      <text>the generator can't be compelled to act in a manner contrary to its nature or its instructions.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Disintegration</name>
      <text>If the generator dies, its body disintegrates into dust, leaving behind its weapons and anything else it was carrying.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The generator makes two fist attacks or four dart attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Fist</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d4 + 1) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Fist|+3|1d4+1</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Magic Dart</name>
      <text>The generator hurls a magic dart at a target it can see up to 60 feet away from it. The dart hits its target automatically (no attack roll required) for 5 (2d4) force damage.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Rogue Modrons</name>
      <text>A modron unit sometimes becomes defective, either through natural decay or exposure to chaotic forces. Rogue modrons don't act in accordance with Primus's wishes and directives, breaking laws, disobeying orders, and even engaging in violence. Other modrons hunt down such rogues.</text>
      <text>A rogue modron loses the Axiomatic Mind trait and can have any alignment other than lawful neutral. Otherwise, it has the same statistics as a regular modron of its rank.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 205</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Poison Weird</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>58 (9d10+9)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., swim 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>17</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands Aquan but doesn't speak</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist>fire; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, grappled, paralyzed, poisoned, restrained, prone, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Invisible in Water</name>
      <text>The poison weird is invisible while fully immersed in water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Water Bound</name>
      <text>The poison weird dies if it leaves the water to which it is bound or if that water is destroyed.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Constrict</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 10 ft., one creature. 13 (3d6 + 3) bludgeoning damage. If the target is Medium or smaller, it is grappled (escape DC 13) and pulled 5 feet toward the poison weird. Until this grapple ends, the target is restrained, the poison weird tries to drown it, and the poison weird can't constrict another target.</text>
      <attack>Constrict|+5|3d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 127</description>
    <environment>underdark, urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Portia Dzuth</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>143 (22d8+44)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Str +9, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +9, Intimidation +5, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Indomitable (2/Day)</name>
      <text>Portia rerolls a failed saving throw.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Second Wind (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Portia can regain 20 hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Shadowfell Despair</name>
      <text>Portia suffers from Shadowfell despair manifesting as unshakable dread. Until the despair ends, she has disadvantage on all saving throws and gains the following flaw: "I'm convinced that I'm going to die in Vanrakdoom." Portia can attempt to end her despair each time she finishes a long rest, doing so with a successful DC 15 Wisdom saving throw. A calm emotions spell also ends her despair, as does any spell or other magical effect that removes a curse.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Portia makes three attacks with its greatsword or its shortbow.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Greatsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 12 (2d6 + 5) slashing damage, plus 7 (2d6) slashing damage if Portia has more than half of its total hit points remaining.</text>
      <attack>Greatsword|+9|2d6+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage, plus 7 (2d6) piercing damage if Portia has more than half of its total hit points remaining.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow|+6|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 239</description>
    <environment>desert, urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Preeta Kreepa</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>40 (9d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Int +6, Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, History +6</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>any four languages</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Familiars</name>
      <text>Any spellcaster that can cast the find familiar spell (such as an archmage or mage) is likely to have a familiar. The familiar can be one of the creatures described in the spell (see the Player's Handbook) or some other Tiny monster, such as a crawling claw, imp, pseudodragon, or quasit.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Preeta is a 9th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks). Preeta has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): misty step, suggestion</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fireball, fly</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): greater invisibility, ice storm</text>
      <text>• 5th level (1 slots): cone of cold</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield, misty step, suggestion, counterspell, fireball, fly, greater invisibility, ice storm, cone of cold</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 56</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Rabbithead</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>4 (1d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Club</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Club|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 295</description>
    <environment>arctic, desert, coastal, grassland, hill, urban, forest</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Rowboat Mimic</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity (shapechanger)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>12 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>67 (9d10+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 15 ft.</speed>
    <str>17</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>5</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>acid</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>The mimic can use its action to polymorph into an object or back into its true, amorphous form. Its statistics are the same in each form. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying isn't transformed. It reverts to its true form if it dies.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Adhesive (Object Form Only)</name>
      <text>The mimic adheres to anything that touches it. A Huge or smaller creature adhered to the mimic is also grappled by it (escape DC 13). Ability checks made to escape this grapple have disadvantage.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>False Appearance (Object Form Only)</name>
      <text>While the mimic remains motionless, it is indistinguishable from an ordinary object.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Grappler</name>
      <text>The mimic has advantage on attack rolls against any creature grappled by it.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Pseudopod</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) bludgeoning damage. If the mimic is in object form, the target is subjected to its Adhesive trait.</text>
      <attack>Pseudopod|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage plus 4 (1d8) acid damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 76</description>
    <environment>underdark, urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Runed Behir</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>168 (16d12+64)</hp>
    <speed>walk 50 ft., climb 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>7</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +6, Stealth +7</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Draconic</languages>
    <cr>11</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>lightning</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 90 ft.</senses>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The behir makes two attacks: one with its bite and one to constrict.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 22 (3d10 + 6) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+10|3d10+6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Constrict</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 5 ft., one Large or smaller creature. 17 (2d10 + 6) bludgeoning damage plus 17 (2d10 + 6) slashing damage. The target is grappled (escape DC 16) if the behir isn't already constricting a creature, and the target is restrained until this grapple ends.</text>
      <attack>Constrict|+10|2d10+6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Lightning Breath (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The behir exhales a line of lightning that is 20 feet long and 5 feet wide. Each creature in that line must make a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw, taking 66 (12d10) lightning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Lightning Breath (Recharge 5-6)||12d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Swallow</name>
      <text>The behir makes one bite attack against a Medium or smaller target it is grappling. If the attack hits, the target is also swallowed, and the grapple ends. While swallowed, the target is blinded and restrained, it has total cover against attacks and other effects outside the behir, and it takes 21 (6d6) acid damage at the start of each of the behir's turns. A behir can have only one creature swallowed at a time.</text>
      <text>If the behir takes 30 damage or more on a single turn from the swallowed creature, the behir must succeed on a DC 14 Constitution saving throw at the end of that turn or regurgitate the creature, which falls prone in a space within 10 feet of the behir. If the behir dies, a swallowed creature is no longer restrained by it and can escape from the corpse by using 15 feet of movement, exiting prone.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 158</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Scaladar</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>94 (7d12+49)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>25</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist>fire; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>force, lightning, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, paralyzed, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Lightning Absorption</name>
      <text>Whenever the scaladar is subjected to lightning damage, it takes no damage, and its sting deals an extra 11 (2d10) lightning damage until the end of its next turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Scaladar Link</name>
      <text>The scaladar knows the location of other scaladar within 100 feet of it, and it can sense when any of them take damage.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The scaladar makes three attacks: two with its claws and one with its sting.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 10 (1d12 + 4) bludgeoning damage, and the target is grappled (escape DC 15). The scaladar has two claws, each of which can grapple one target.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+7|1d12+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Sting</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 9 (1d10 + 4) piercing damage plus 11 (2d10) lightning damage.</text>
      <attack>Sting|+7|1d10+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Scaladar are constructs created by Trobriand, one of Halaster's apprentices. They move and attack like giant scorpions, grabbing prey with two large pincer claws and delivering a deadly pulse of lightning with their metal stinger tails.
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 315</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Shadow Assassin</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14</ac>
    <hp>78 (12d8+24)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>6</str>
    <dex>19</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Dex +8, Int +5</save>
    <skill>Perception +9, Stealth +12</skill>
    <passive>19</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages it knew in life but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist>acid, cold, fire, lightning, thunder; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>necrotic, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable>radiant</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, frightened, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, restrained</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amorphous</name>
      <text>The assassin can move through a space as narrow as 1 inch wide without squeezing.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Shadow Stealth</name>
      <text>While in dim light or darkness, the assassin can take the Hide action as a bonus action.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Weakness</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, the assassin has disadvantage on attack rolls, ability checks, and saving throws.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The assassin makes two Shadow Blade attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shadow Blade</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage plus 10 (3d6) necrotic damage. Unless the target is immune to necrotic damage, the target's Strength score is reduced by 1d4 each time it is hit by this attack. The target dies if its Strength is reduced to 0. The reduction lasts until the target finishes a short or long rest. If a non-evil humanoid dies from this attack, a shadow (see the Monster Manual) rises from the corpse 1d4 hours later.</text>
      <attack>Shadow Blade|+8|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>A shadow assassin looks like an undead shadow (as described in theMonster Manual) that wields shortswords also made of shadow. It exists only to slay the living.
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 316</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Shapechanged Roper</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>20 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>93 (11d10+33)</hp>
    <speed>walk 10 ft., climb 10 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>7</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +6, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>False Appearance</name>
      <text>While the roper remains motionless, it is indistinguishable from a normal cave formation, such as a stalagmite.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Grasping Tendrils</name>
      <text>The roper can have up to six tendrils at a time. Each tendril can be attacked (AC 20; 10 hit points; immunity to poison and psychic damage). Destroying a tendril deals no damage to the roper, which can extrude a replacement tendril on its next turn. A tendril can also be broken if a creature takes an action and succeeds on a DC 15 Strength check against it.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Spider Climb</name>
      <text>The roper can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without needing to make an ability check.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>The roper can use its action to polymorph into a stone object or back to its true form. Its statistics are the same in each form. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying isn't transformed. It reverts to its true form if it dies.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The roper makes four attacks with its tendrils, uses Reel, and makes one attack with its bite.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 22 (4d8 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+7|4d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Tendril</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 50 ft., one creature. The target is grappled (escape DC 15). Until the grapple ends, the target is restrained and has disadvantage on Strength checks and Strength saving throws, and the roper can't use the same tendril on another target.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Reel</name>
      <text>The roper pulls each creature grappled by it up to 25 feet straight toward it.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 106</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Shockerstomper</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>18</ac>
    <hp>300 (300d1)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>1</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>5</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>14</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, deafened, charmed, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Disable</name>
      <text>When a leg drops to 0 hit points, it is disabled, and Shockerstomper can use a reaction to detach it from its main body. Whenever one of its legs is disabled, Shockerstomper's walking speed is reduced by 10 feet. The whole contraption topples over and shuts down if four of its seven legs are disabled.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Electrified Surface</name>
      <text>A creature that ends its turn in contact with Shockerstomper's body (saucer or turrets) must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw, taking 22 (4d10) lightning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>Shockerstomper is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Control Module</name>
      <text>A creature atop or above Shockerstomper's platform can locate its control module with a successful DC 15 Intelligence (Investigation) check or Wisdom (Perception) check. As an action, a character can try to open the control module's access panel, either by tearing it off with a successful DC 25 Strength (Athletics) check or by dislodging it with thieves' tools and a successful DC 25 Dexterity check. Behind the panel, embedded in the floor of the control module, is a 5-foot-diameter pulsating crystal hemisphere with AC 10, 25 hit points, and immunity to poison and psychic damage. Destroying the crystal hemisphere shuts down Shockerstomper.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Lightning Turret</name>
      <text>A character can try to plug the nozzle of a lightning turret with a 10-pound rock or similar object, doing so with a successful DC 15 Strength (Athletics) check. A plugged turret can't shoot lightning until a creature uses an action to try to clear the obstruction, which requires another successful DC 15 Strength (Athletics) check. Shockerstomper has no ability to clear an obstruction itself.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Shockerstomper makes three Lightning Turret attacks and two Stomp attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Lightning Turret</name>
      <text>The turret shoots a magical lightning bolt at one creature within 60 feet of Shockerstomper. The target must make a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw, taking 44 (8d10) lightning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Lightning Turret||8d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Stomp</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one creature. 22 (3d10 + 6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Stomp|+8|3d10+6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 174</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Shunn Shurreth</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (elf)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>18 (studded leather armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>71 (11d8+22)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Dex +7, Con +5, Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Perception +4, Stealth +10</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Elvish, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Spider Features</name>
      <text>While cursed with spider features, Shunn can climb difficult surfaces, even across ceilings, without needing to make an ability check.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>Shunn has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put Shunn to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, Shunn has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Shunn makes two shortsword attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage plus 10 (3d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+7|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hand Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 13 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned for 1 hour. If the saving throw fails by 5 or more, the target is also unconscious while poisoned in this way. The target wakes up if it takes damage or if another creature takes an action to shake it awake.</text>
      <attack>Hand Crossbow|+7|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Shunn adds 3 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, Shunn must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Drow Magic Armor and Weapons</name>
      <text>Drow often wear magic armor and carry magic weapons that lose their enhancement bonuses permanently if they are exposed to sunlight for 1 hour or longer.</text>
      <text>A drow elite warrior wearing +2 Studded Leather Armor and carrying a +2 shortsword has AC 20 and a +2 bonus on attack and damage rolls with shortsword attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Shunn's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 12). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: dancing lights</text>
      <text>1/day each: darkness, faerie fire, levitate (self only)</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>dancing lights, darkness, faerie fire, levitate</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 33</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sing-Along</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (halfling)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>4 (1d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common), Halfling</languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Halfling Nimbleness</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; can move through a space of a Medium or larger creature.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Brave</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; has advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Club</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Club|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 148</description>
    <environment>arctic, desert, coastal, grassland, hill, urban, forest</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Space Hamster</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>1 (1d4-1)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>2</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>9</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>4</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>the hamster has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +0 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 1 piercing damage.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 251</description>
    <environment>swamp, urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Stalagma Steelshadow</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>dragon</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>243 (18d12+126)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., fly 80 ft.</speed>
    <str>27</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>25</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>21</cha>
    <save>Dex +5, Con +12, Wis +6, Cha +10</save>
    <skill>Arcana +8, History +8, Perception +11, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>21</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>16</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>cold</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft., darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If the dragon fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The dragon can use its Frightful Presence. It then makes three attacks: one with its bite and two with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 19 (2d10 + 8) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+13|2d10+8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 15 (2d6 + 8) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+13|2d6+8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. 17 (2d8 + 8) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Tail|+13|2d8+8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Frightful Presence</name>
      <text>Each creature of the dragon's choice that is within 120 feet of the dragon and aware of it must succeed on a DC 18 Wisdom saving throw or become frightened for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. If a creature's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the creature is immune to the dragon's Frightful Presence for the next 24 hours.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Breath Weapons (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The dragon uses one of the following breath weapons.</text>
      <text>• Acid Breath. The dragon exhales acid in a 60-foot line that is 5 feet wide. Each creature in that line must make a DC 18 Dexterity saving throw, taking 58 (13d8) acid damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Breath Weapons (Recharge 5-6)||13d8</attack>
      <text>• Paralyzing Breath. The dragon exhales paralyzing gas in a 60-foot cone. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 20 Constitution saving throw or be paralyzed for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Change Shape</name>
      <text>The dragon magically polymorphs into a humanoid or beast that has a challenge rating no higher than its own, or back into its true form. It reverts to its true form if it dies. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying is absorbed or borne by the new form (the dragon's choice).</text>
      <text>In a new form, the dragon retains its alignment, hit points, Hit Dice, ability to speak, proficiencies, Legendary Resistance, lair actions, and Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma scores, as well as this action. Its statistics and capabilities are otherwise replaced by those of the new form, except any class features or legendary actions of that form.</text>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>The dragon can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The dragon regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Detect</name>
      <text>The dragon makes a Wisdom (Perception) check.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Tail Attack</name>
      <text>The dragon makes a tail attack.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Wing Attack (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>The dragon beats its wings. Each creature within 10 feet of the dragon must succeed on a DC 22 Dexterity saving throw or take 15 (2d6 + 8) bludgeoning damage and be knocked prone. The dragon can then fly up to half its flying speed.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Lair Actions</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>On initiative count 20 (losing initiative ties), the dragon takes a lair action to cause one of the following effects:</text>
      <text>• The dragon creates fog as if it had cast the fog cloud spell. The fog lasts until initiative count 20 on the next round.</text>
      <text>• A blisteringly cold wind blows through the lair near the dragon. Each creature within 120 feet of the dragon must succeed on a DC 15 Constitution saving throw or take 5 (1d10) cold damage. Gases and vapors are dispersed by the wind, and unprotected flames are extinguished. Protected flames, such as lanterns, have a 50 percent chance of being extinguished.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Regional Effects</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>The region containing a legendary silver dragon's lair is warped by the dragon's magic, which creates one or more of the following effects.</text>
      <text>• Once per day, the dragon can alter the weather in a 6-mile radius centered on its lair. The dragon doesn't need to be outdoors; otherwise the effect is identical to the control weather spell.</text>
      <text>• Within 1 mile of the lair, winds buoy non-evil creatures that fall due to no act of the dragon's or its allies. Such creatures descend at a rate of 60 feet per round and take no falling damage.</text>
      <text>• Given days or longer to work, the dragon can make clouds and fog within its lair as solid as stone, forming structures and other objects as it wishes.</text>
      <text>If the dragon dies, changed weather reverts to normal, as described in the spell, and the other effects fade in 1d10 days.</text>
      </legendary>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 273</description>
    <environment>mountain, urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Statue of Vergadain</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>178 (17d10+85)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>22</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't adamantine</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The statue is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The statue has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Weapons</name>
      <text>The statue's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Theft</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, the golem targets one creature it can see within 30 feet of it. The target must succeed on a DC 17 Charisma saving throw, or all magic items in its possession are teleported to the bottom of the pit in area 31.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The statue makes two slam attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 19 (3d8 + 6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+10|3d8+6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slow (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The statue targets one or more creatures it can see within 10 feet of it. Each target must make a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw against this magic. On a failed save, a target can't use reactions, its speed is halved, and it can't make more than one attack on its turn. In addition, the target can take either an action or a bonus action on its turn, not both. These effects last for 1 minute. A target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 202</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Stonecloak</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>178 (17d10+85)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>22</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't adamantine</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The stonecloak is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The stonecloak has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Weapons</name>
      <text>The stonecloak's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The stonecloak makes two slam attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 19 (3d8 + 6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+10|3d8+6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slow (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The stonecloak targets one or more creatures it can see within 10 feet of it. Each target must make a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw against this magic. On a failed save, a target can't use reactions, its speed is halved, and it can't make more than one attack on its turn. In addition, the target can take either an action or a bonus action on its turn, not both. These effects last for 1 minute. A target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 253</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sundeth</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>143 (22d8+44)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Str +9, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +9, Intimidation +5, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Indomitable (2/Day)</name>
      <text>Sundeth rerolls a failed saving throw.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Second Wind (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Sundeth can regain 20 hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Sundeth makes three attacks with its greatsword or its shortbow.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Greatsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 12 (2d6 + 5) slashing damage, plus 7 (2d6) slashing damage if Sundeth has more than half of its total hit points remaining.</text>
      <attack>Greatsword|+9|2d6+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage, plus 7 (2d6) piercing damage if Sundeth has more than half of its total hit points remaining.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow|+6|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 304</description>
    <environment>desert, urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Thwad Underbrew</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>143 (22d8+44)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Str +9, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +9, Intimidation +5, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common), Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Indomitable (2/Day)</name>
      <text>Thwad rerolls a failed saving throw.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Second Wind (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Thwad can regain 20 hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; has advantage on saving throws against poison, and has resistance against poison damage.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Thwad makes three attacks with his maul or his shortbow.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Maul</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 12 (2d6 + 5) bludgeoning damage, plus 7 (2d6) bludgeoning damage if Thwad has more than half of his total hit points remaining.</text>
      <attack>Maul|+9|2d6+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage, plus 7 (2d6) piercing damage if Thwad has more than half of its total hit points remaining.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow|+6|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 204</description>
    <environment>desert, urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Torbit</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (bullywug)</type>
    <alignment>Any Non-Good Alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (studded leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>78 (12d8+24)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Dex +6, Int +4</save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +6, Deception +3, Perception +3, Stealth +9</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Thieves' cant plus any two languages, Bullywug</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Assassinate</name>
      <text>During its first turn, Torbit has advantage on attack rolls against any creature that hasn't taken a turn. Any hit Torbit scores against a surprised creature is a critical hit.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Evasion</name>
      <text>If Torbit is subjected to an effect that allows it to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, Torbit instead takes no damage if it succeeds on the saving throw, and only half damage if it fails.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sneak Attack (1/Turn)</name>
      <text>Torbit deals an extra 14 (4d6) damage when it hits a target with a weapon attack and has advantage on the attack roll, or when the target is within 5 feet of an ally of Torbit that isn't incapacitated and Torbit doesn't have disadvantage on the attack roll.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Swamp Camouflage</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; has advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks made to hide in swampy terrain.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Standing Leap</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt;'s long jump is up to 20 feet and their high jump is up to 10 feet, with or without a running start.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Torbit makes two shortsword attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage, and the target must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw, taking 24 (7d6) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+6|1d6+3</attack>
      <attack>Shortsword||7d6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Light Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage, and the target must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw, taking 24 (7d6) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Light Crossbow|+6|1d8+3</attack>
      <attack>Light Crossbow||7d6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 115</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Trenzia</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>40 (9d4+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>1</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Arcana +5, Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist>lightning, necrotic, piercing</resist>
    <immune>cold, fire, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned, prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Illumination</name>
      <text>Trenzia sheds either dim light in a 15-foot radius, or bright light in a 15-foot radius and dim light for an additional 15 feet. It can switch between the options as an action.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Trenzia has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Rejuvenation</name>
      <text>If Trenzia is destroyed, it regains all its hit points in 1 hour unless holy water is sprinkled on its remains or a dispel magic or remove curse spell is cast on them.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Trenzia uses Fire Ray twice.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Fire Ray</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +5 to hit, range 30 ft., one target. 10 (3d6) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Fire Ray|+5|3d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Trenzia is a 5th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). It requires no somatic or material components to cast its spells. Trenzia has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): mage hand</text>
      <text>• 1st level (3 slots): magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (2 slots): blur, flaming sphere</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (1 slots): fireball</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>3, 2, 1</slots>
    <spells>mage hand, magic missile, shield, blur, flaming sphere, fireball</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 32</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Trobriand</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>20 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>210 (20d10+100)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>24</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>16</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire, poison, psychic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't adamantine</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fire Absorption</name>
      <text>Whenever Trobriand is subjected to fire damage, it takes no damage and instead regains a number of hit points equal to the fire damage dealt.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>Trobriand is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Trobriand has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Weapons</name>
      <text>Trobriand's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Trobriand makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 20 (3d8 + 7) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+13|3d8+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Sword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 23 (3d10 + 7) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Sword|+13|3d10+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Poison Breath (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>Trobriand exhales poisonous gas in a 15-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 19 Constitution saving throw, taking 45 (10d8) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Poison Breath (Recharge 5-6)||10d8</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 294</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Umbraxakar</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>dragon</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>212 (17d12+102)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., fly 80 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>25</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>23</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>19</cha>
    <save>Dex +5, Con +11, Wis +7, Cha +9</save>
    <skill>Insight +7, Perception +12, Stealth +2</skill>
    <passive>22</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>15</cr>
    <resist>necrotic</resist>
    <immune>lightning</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft., darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The dragon can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If the dragon fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Living Shadow</name>
      <text>While in dim light or darkness, the dragon has resistance to damage that isn't force, psychic, or radiant.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Shadow Stealth</name>
      <text>While in dim light or darkness, the dragon can take the Hide action as a bonus action.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, the dragon has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The dragon can use its Frightful Presence. It then makes three attacks: one with its bite and two with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 18 (2d10 + 7) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+12|2d10+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 14 (2d6 + 7) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+12|2d6+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. 16 (2d8 + 7) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Tail|+12|2d8+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Frightful Presence</name>
      <text>Each creature of the dragon's choice that is within 120 feet of the dragon and aware of it must succeed on a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw or become frightened for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. If a creature's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the creature is immune to the dragon's Frightful Presence for the next 24 hours.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Breath Weapons (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The dragon uses one of the following breath weapons.</text>
      <text>• Necrotic Breath. The dragon exhales necrotic in a 90-foot line that is 5 feet wide. Each creature in that line must make a DC 19 Dexterity saving throw, taking 66 (12d10) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Breath Weapons (Recharge 5-6)||12d10</attack>
      <text>• Repulsion Breath. The dragon exhales repulsion energy in a 30-foot cone. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 19 Strength saving throw. On a failed save, the creature is pushed 60 feet away from the dragon.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Change Shape</name>
      <text>The dragon magically polymorphs into a humanoid or beast that has a challenge rating no higher than its own, or back into its true form. It reverts to its true form if it dies. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying is absorbed or borne by the new form (the dragon's choice).</text>
      <text>In a new form, the dragon retains its alignment, hit points, Hit Dice, ability to speak, proficiencies, Legendary Resistance, lair actions, and Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma scores, as well as this action. Its statistics and capabilities are otherwise replaced by those of the new form, except any class features or legendary actions of that form.</text>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>The dragon can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The dragon regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Detect</name>
      <text>The dragon makes a Wisdom (Perception) check.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Tail Attack</name>
      <text>The dragon makes a tail attack.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Wing Attack (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>The dragon beats its wings. Each creature within 10 feet of the dragon must succeed on a DC 20 Dexterity saving throw or take 14 (2d6 + 7) bludgeoning damage and be knocked prone. The dragon can then fly up to half its flying speed.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Lair Actions</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>On initiative count 20 (losing initiative ties), the dragon takes a lair action to cause one of the following effects:</text>
      <text>• The dragon creates fog as though it had cast the fog cloud spell. The fog lasts until initiative count 20 on the next round.</text>
      <text>• A thunderclap originates at a point the dragon can see within 120 feet of it. Each creature within a 20-foot radius centered on that point must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw or take 5 (1d10) thunder damage and be deafened until the end of its next turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Regional Effects</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>The region containing a legendary bronze dragon's lair is warped by the dragon's magic.</text>
      <text>• Once per day, the dragon can alter the weather in a 6-mile radius centered on its lair. The dragon doesn't need to be outdoors; otherwise the effect is identical to the control weather spell.</text>
      <text>• Underwater plants within 6 miles of the dragon's lair take on dazzlingly brilliant hues.</text>
      <text>• Within its lair, the dragon can set illusory sounds, such as soft music and strange echoes, so that they can be heard in various parts of the lair.</text>
      <text>If the dragon dies, changed weather reverts to normal, as described in the spell, and the other effects fade in 1d10 days.</text>
      </legendary>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 241</description>
    <environment>coastal</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Undead Bulette</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>125 (9d10+45)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., burrow 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft., tremorsense 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Standing Leap</name>
      <text>The bulette's long jump is up to 30 feet and its high jump is up to 15 feet, with or without a running start.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 30 (4d12 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+7|4d12+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Deadly Leap</name>
      <text>If the bulette jumps at least 15 feet as part of its movement, it can then use this action to land on its feet in a space that contains one or more other creatures. Each of those creatures must succeed on a DC 16 Strength or Dexterity saving throw (target's choice) or be knocked prone and take 14 (3d6 + 4) bludgeoning damage plus 14 (3d6 + 4) slashing damage. On a successful save, the creature takes only half the damage, isn't knocked prone, and is pushed 5 feet out of the bulette's space into an unoccupied space of the creature's choice. If no unoccupied space is within range, the creature instead falls prone in the bulette's space.</text>
      <attack>Deadly Leap||3d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 90</description>
    <environment>mountain, grassland, hill</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Undead Shambling Mound</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>plant</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>136 (16d10+48)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., swim 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>5</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Stealth +2</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist>cold, fire</resist>
    <immune>lightning</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, deafened, exhaustion</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Lightning Absorption</name>
      <text>Whenever the shambling mound is subjected to lightning damage, it takes no damage and regains a number of hit points equal to the lightning damage dealt.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The shambling mound makes two slam attacks. If both attacks hit a Medium or smaller target, the target is grappled (escape DC 14), and the shambling mound uses its Engulf on it.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+7|2d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Engulf</name>
      <text>The shambling mound engulfs a Medium or smaller creature grappled by it. The engulfed target is blinded, restrained, and unable to breathe, and it must succeed on a DC 14 Constitution saving throw at the start of each of the mound's turns or take 13 (2d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage. If the mound moves, the engulfed target moves with it. The mound can have only one creature engulfed at a time.</text>
      <attack>Engulf||2d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 142</description>
    <environment>forest, swamp</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Valtagar Steelshadow</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>99 (18d8+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Int +9, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +13, History +13</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>any six languages, Dwarvish, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <resist>damage from spells; nonmagical bludgeoning, piercing, slashing (from stoneskin), poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Valtagar has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; has advantage on saving throws against poison, and has resistance against poison damage.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Enlarge (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>For 1 minute, Valtagar magically increases in size, along with anything they are wearing or carrying. While enlarged, Valtagar is Large, doubles their damage dice on Strength-based weapon attacks (included in the attacks), and makes Strength checks and Strength saving throws with advantage. If Valtagar lacks the room to become Large, they attain the maximum size possible in the space available.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Invisibility (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; magically turns invisible until they attack, cast a spell, or use their Enlarge, or until their concentration is broken, up to 1 hour (as if concentrating on a spell). Any equipment Valtagar wears or carries is invisible with them.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+6|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Familiars</name>
      <text>Any spellcaster that can cast the find familiar spell (such as an archmage or mage) is likely to have a familiar. The familiar can be one of the creatures described in the spell (see the Player's Handbook) or some other Tiny monster, such as a crawling claw, imp, pseudodragon, or quasit.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Valtagar is an 18th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks). Valtagar can cast disguise self and invisibility at will and has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>At will: disguise self, invisibility</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, identify, mage armor*, magic missile</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fly, lightning bolt</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): Otiluke's Resilient Sphere, fire shield, stoneskin*</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): cone of cold, scrying, wall of force</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): globe of invulnerability</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): teleport</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): mind blank*</text>
      <text>• 9th level (1 slots): time stop</text>
      <text>*Valtagar casts these spells on itself before combat.</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>disguise self, invisibility, fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp, detect magic, identify, mage armor, magic missile, detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step, counterspell, fly, lightning bolt, Otiluke's Resilient Sphere, fire shield, stoneskin, cone of cold, scrying, wall of force, globe of invulnerability, teleport, mind blank, time stop</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 271</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Vertrand Shadowdusk</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>99 (18d8+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Int +9, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +13, History +13</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>any six languages</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <resist>damage from spells; nonmagical bludgeoning, piercing, slashing (from stoneskin)</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Vertrand has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+6|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Familiars</name>
      <text>Any spellcaster that can cast the find familiar spell (such as an archmage or mage) is likely to have a familiar. The familiar can be one of the creatures described in the spell (see the Player's Handbook) or some other Tiny monster, such as a crawling claw, imp, pseudodragon, or quasit.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Vertrand is an 18th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks). Vertrand can cast disguise self and invisibility at will and has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>At will: disguise self, invisibility</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, identify, mage armor*, magic missile</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fly, lightning bolt</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): confusion, fire shield, stoneskin*</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): cone of cold, scrying, wall of force</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): globe of invulnerability</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): teleport</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): mind blank*</text>
      <text>• 9th level (1 slots): time stop</text>
      <text>*Vertrand casts these spells on itself before combat.</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>disguise self, invisibility, fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp, detect magic, identify, mage armor, magic missile, detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step, counterspell, fly, lightning bolt, confusion, fire shield, stoneskin, cone of cold, scrying, wall of force, globe of invulnerability, teleport, mind blank, time stop</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 282</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Werebat</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (goblin, shapechanger)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>24 (7d6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>8</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +3, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Goblin (can't speak in bat form)</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't silvered</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>The werebat can use its action to polymorph into a Medium bat-humanoid hybrid, or into a Large giant bat, or back into its true form, which is humanoid. Its statistics, other than its size, are the same in each form. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying isn't transformed. It reverts to its true form if it dies.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Echolocation (Bat or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>The werebat has blindsight out to a range of 60 feet as long as it's not deafened.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Hearing</name>
      <text>The werebat has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Nimble Escape (Humanoid Form Only)</name>
      <text>The werebat can take the Disengage or Hide action as a bonus action on each of its turns.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, the werebat has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>In humanoid form, the werebat makes two scimitar attacks or two shortbow attacks. In hybrid form, it can make one bite attack and one scimitar attack.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite (Bat or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage, and the werebat gains temporary hit points equal to the damage dealt. If the target is a humanoid, it must succeed on a DC 10 Constitution saving throw or be cursed with werebat lycanthropy.</text>
      <attack>Bite (Bat or Hybrid Form Only)|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Scimitar (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Scimitar (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortbow (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>A werebat is a humanoid afflicted with a rare form of lycanthropy that enables it to transform into a giant bat or a bat-humanoid hybrid. (See the Monster Manual for more information onlycanthropy.) Most werebats are of goblin stock.
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 317</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Wooden Donkey</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>11 (2d8+2)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Beast of Burden</name>
      <text>The donkey is considered to be a Large animal for the purpose of determining its carrying capacity.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sure-Footed</name>
      <text>The donkey has advantage on Strength and Dexterity saving throws made against effects that would knock it prone.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Hooves</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Hooves|+2|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 84</description>
    <environment>hill, urban, desert</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Wyllow</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (elf)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>16 (hide armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>132 (24d8+24)</hp>
    <speed>walk 35 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>20</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Int +5, Wis +9</save>
    <skill>Medicine +9, Nature +5, Perception +1</skill>
    <passive>19</passive>
    <languages>Druidic plus any two languages, Elvish</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put Wyllow to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Mask of the Wild</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; can attempt to hide even when they are only lightly obscured by foliage, heavy rain, falling snow, mist, and other natural phenomena.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Scimitar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Scimitar|+6|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Change Shape (2/Day)</name>
      <text>Wyllow magically polymorphs into a beast or elemental with a challenge rating of 6 or less, and can remain in this form for up to 9 hours. Wyllow can choose whether its equipment falls to the ground, melds with its new form, or is worn by the new form. Wyllow reverts to its true form if it dies or falls unconscious. Wyllow can revert to its true form using a bonus action on its turn.</text>
      <text>While in a new form, Wyllow retains its game statistics and ability to speak, but its AC, movement modes, Strength, and Dexterity are replaced by those of the new form, and it gains any special senses, proficiencies, traits, actions, and reactions (except class features, legendary actions, and lair actions) that the new form has but that it lacks. It can cast its spells with verbal or somatic components in its new form.</text>
      <text>The new form's attacks count as magical for the purpose of overcoming resistances and immunity to nonmagical attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Wyllow is an 18th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks). It has the following druid spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): druidcraft, mending, poison spray, produce flame</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): cure wounds, entangle, faerie fire, speak with animals</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): animal messenger, beast sense, hold person</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): conjure animals, meld into stone, water breathing</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): dominate beast, locate creature, stoneskin, wall of fire</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): commune with nature, mass cure wounds, tree stride</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): heal, heroes' feast, sunbeam</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): fire storm</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): animal shapes</text>
      <text>• 9th level (1 slots): foresight</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>druidcraft, mending, poison spray, produce flame, cure wounds, entangle, faerie fire, speak with animals, animal messenger, beast sense, hold person, conjure animals, meld into stone, water breathing, dominate beast, locate creature, stoneskin, wall of fire, commune with nature, mass cure wounds, tree stride, heal, heroes' feast, sunbeam, fire storm, animal shapes, foresight</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 70</description>
    <environment>forest, mountain, swamp</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Zalthar Shadowdusk</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>20 (plate armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>180 (19d8+95)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Dex +6, Wis +9, Cha +10</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common</languages>
    <cr>17</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>necrotic, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Zalthar wields a nine lives stealer longsword with 5 charges remaining.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Zalthar has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Marshal Undead</name>
      <text>Unless Zalthar is incapacitated, it and undead creatures of its choice within 60 feet of it have advantage on saving throws against features that turn undead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Zalthar makes three longsword attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Nine Lives Stealer Longsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +13 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (1d8 + 7) slashing damage, or 12 (1d10 + 7) slashing damage if used with two hands, plus 18 (4d8) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Nine Lives Stealer Longsword|+13|1d8+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hellfire Orb (1/Day)</name>
      <text>Zalthar hurls a magical ball of fire that explodes at a point it can see within 120 feet of it. Each creature in a 20-foot-radius sphere centered on that point must make a DC 18 Dexterity saving throw. The sphere spreads around corners. A creature takes 35 (10d6) fire damage and 35 (10d6) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Hellfire Orb (1/Day)||10d6</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Zalthar adds 6 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, Zalthar must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Zalthar is a 19th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 18, +10 to hit with spell attacks). It has the following paladin spells prepared:</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): command, compelled duel, searing smite</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): hold person, magic weapon</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): dispel magic, elemental weapon</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): locate creature, staggering smite</text>
      <text>• 5th level (2 slots): destructive wave (necrotic)</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>command, compelled duel, searing smite, hold person, magic weapon, dispel magic, elemental weapon, locate creature, staggering smite, destructive wave</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 286</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Zorak Lightdrinker</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead (shapechanger)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>144 (17d8+68)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Dex +9, Wis +7, Cha +9</save>
    <skill>Perception +7, Stealth +9</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>13</cr>
    <resist>necrotic, poison; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
      <text>Augrek has advantage on saving throws against poison.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>If Zorak isn't in sunlight or running water, he can use his action to polymorph into a Tiny bat or a Medium cloud of mist, or back into his true form.</text>
      <text>While in bat form, Zorak can't speak, his walking speed is 5 feet, and he has a flying speed of 30 feet. His statistics, other than his size and speed, are unchanged. Anything he is wearing transforms with it, but nothing he is carrying does. He reverts to his true form if he dies.</text>
      <text>While in mist form, Zorak can't take any actions, speak, or manipulate objects. He is weightless, has a flying speed of 20 feet, can hover, and can enter a hostile creature's space and stop there. In addition, if air can pass through a space, the mist can do so without squeezing, and he can't pass through water. He has advantage on Strength, Dexterity, and Constitution saving throws, and he is immune to all nonmagical damage, except the damage he takes from sunlight.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If Zorak fails a saving throw, he can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Misty Escape</name>
      <text>When he drops to 0 hit points outside his resting place, Zorak transforms into a cloud of mist (as in the Shapechanger trait) instead of falling unconscious, provided that he isn't in sunlight or running water. If he can't transform, he is destroyed.</text>
      <text>While he has 0 hit points in mist form, he can't revert to his vampire form, and he must reach his resting place within 2 hours or be destroyed. Once in his resting place, he reverts to his vampire form. He is then paralyzed until he regains at least 1 hit point. After spending 1 hour in his resting place with 0 hit points, he regains 1 hit point.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Regeneration</name>
      <text>Zorak regains 20 hit points at the start of his turn if he has at least 1 hit point and isn't in sunlight or running water. If Zorak takes radiant damage or damage from holy water, this trait doesn't function at the start of Zorak's next turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Spider Climb</name>
      <text>Zorak can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without needing to make an ability check.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Vampire Weaknesses</name>
      <text>Zorak has the following flaws:</text>
      <text>Forbiddance. Zorak can't enter a residence without an invitation from one of the occupants.</text>
      <text>Harmed by Running Water. Zorak takes 20 acid damage if he ends his turn in running water.</text>
      <text>Stake to the Heart. If a piercing weapon made of wood is driven into Zorak's heart while Zorak is incapacitated in his resting place, Zorak is paralyzed until the stake is removed.</text>
      <text>Sunlight Hypersensitivity. Zorak takes 20 radiant damage when he starts his turn in sunlight. While in sunlight, he has disadvantage on attack rolls and ability checks.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Zorak makes two attacks with his dwarven thrower, only one of which can be a ranged attack.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dwarven Thrower</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 11 (1d8 + 7) bludgeoning damage, or 12 (1d10 + 7) bludgeoning damage when used with two hands to make a melee attack. On a ranged attack that hits, the hammer deals an extra 1d8 bludgeoning damage (2d8 if the target is a giant). Hit or Miss: If thrown, the weapon flies back to Zorak's hand after the attack.</text>
      <attack>Dwarven Thrower|+12|1d8+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack (Vampire Form Only)</name>
      <text>Zorak makes two attacks, only one of which can be a bite attack.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Unarmed Strike (Vampire Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 8 (1d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage. Instead of dealing damage, Zorak can grapple the target (escape DC 18).</text>
      <attack>Unarmed Strike (Vampire Form Only)|+9|1d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite (Bat or Vampire Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one willing creature, or a creature that is grappled by Zorak, incapacitated, or restrained. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage plus 10 (3d6) necrotic damage. The target's hit point maximum is reduced by an amount equal to the necrotic damage taken, and Zorak regains hit points equal to that amount. The reduction lasts until the target finishes a long rest. The target dies if this effect reduces his hit point maximum to 0. A humanoid slain in this way and then buried in the ground rises the following night as a vampire spawn under Zorak's control.</text>
      <attack>Bite (Bat or Vampire Form Only)|+9|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Charm</name>
      <text>Zorak targets one humanoid he can see within 30 feet of it. If the target can see Zorak, the target must succeed on a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw against this magic or be charmed by Zorak. The charmed target regards Zorak as a trusted friend to be heeded and protected. Although the target isn't under Zorak's control, it takes Zorak's requests or actions in the most favorable way it can, and it is a willing target for Zorak's bite attack.</text>
      <text>Each time Zorak or Zorak's companions do anything harmful to the target, it can repeat the saving throw, ending the effect on itself on a success. Otherwise, the effect lasts 24 hours or until Zorak is destroyed, is on a different plane of existence than the target, or takes a bonus action to end the effect.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Children of the Night (1/Day)</name>
      <text>Zorak magically calls 2d4 swarms of swarm of bats or swarm of rats, provided that the sun isn't up. While outdoors, Zorak can call 3d6 wolf instead. The called creatures arrive in 1d4 rounds, acting as allies of Zorak and obeying his spoken commands. The beasts remain for 1 hour, until Zorak dies, or until Zorak dismisses them as a bonus action.</text>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>Zorak can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Zorak regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Move</name>
      <text>Zorak moves up to his speed without provoking opportunity attacks.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Unarmed Strike</name>
      <text>Zorak makes one unarmed strike.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Bite (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Zorak makes one bite attack.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Regional Effects</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>The region surrounding a vampire's lair is warped by the creature's unnatural presence, creating any of the following effects:</text>
      <text>• There's a noticeable increase in the populations of bats, rats, and wolves in the region.</text>
      <text>• Plants within 500 feet of the lair wither, and their stems and branches become twisted and thorny.</text>
      <text>• Shadows cast within 500 feet of the lair seem abnormally gaunt and sometimes move as though alive.</text>
      <text>• A creeping fog clings to the ground within 500 feet of the vampire's lair. The fog occasionally takes eerie forms, such as grasping claws and writhing serpents.</text>
      <text>If the vampire is destroyed, these effects end after 2d6 days.</text>
      </legendary>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 204</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Zox Clammersham</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (gnome)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>99 (18d8+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Int +9, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +13, History +13</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>any six languages, Gnomish</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <resist>damage from spells; nonmagical bludgeoning, piercing, slashing (from stoneskin)</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Zox has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Gnome Cunning</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; has advantage on all Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saving throws against magic.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+6|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Familiars</name>
      <text>Any spellcaster that can cast the find familiar spell (such as an archmage or mage) is likely to have a familiar. The familiar can be one of the creatures described in the spell (see the Player's Handbook) or some other Tiny monster, such as a crawling claw, imp, pseudodragon, or quasit.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Zox is an 18th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks). Zox can cast disguise self and invisibility at will and has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>At will: disguise self, invisibility</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, identify, mage armor*, magic missile</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fly, lightning bolt</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): confusion, fire shield, stoneskin*</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): cone of cold, scrying, wall of force</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): globe of invulnerability</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): teleport</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): mind blank*</text>
      <text>• 9th level (1 slots): time stop</text>
      <text>*Zox casts these spells on itself before combat.</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>disguise self, invisibility, fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp, detect magic, identify, mage armor, magic missile, detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step, counterspell, fly, lightning bolt, confusion, fire shield, stoneskin, cone of cold, scrying, wall of force, globe of invulnerability, teleport, mind blank, time stop</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 176</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Zress Orlezziir</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (elf)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (chain mail)</ac>
    <hp>162 (25d8+50)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>19</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save>Dex +8, Con +6, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Perception +6, Stealth +8</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Elvish, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Battle Command</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Zress targets one ally he can see within 30 feet of him. If the target can see or hear Zress, the target can use its reaction to make one melee attack or to take the Dodge or Hide action.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>Zress has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put Zress to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, Zress has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Zress makes three attacks: two with his scimitar and one with his whip or his hand crossbow.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Scimitar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) slashing damage plus 14 (4d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Scimitar|+8|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Whip</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 6 (1d4 + 4) slashing damage. If the target is an ally, it has advantage on attack rolls until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Whip|+8|1d4+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hand Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 13 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned for 1 hour. If the saving throw fails by 5 or more, the target is also unconscious while poisoned in this way. The target regains consciousness if it takes damage or if another creature takes an action to shake it.</text>
      <attack>Hand Crossbow|+8|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Zress adds 3 to his AC against one melee attack that would hit him. To do so, Zress must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Zress's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 13). He can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: dancing lights</text>
      <text>1/day each: darkness, faerie fire, levitate (self only)</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>dancing lights, darkness, faerie fire, levitate</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dungeon of the Mad Mage p. 136</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  </compendium>
