<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <item>
        <name>Bad News</name>
        <type>R</type>
        <weight>25</weight>
        <text>A ranged weapon similar to a sniper rifle.</text>
        <text>Two-Handed, Reload 1, Misfire 3</text>
        <text>Proficiency: firearms</text>
        <text>Ammunition: 10g (5)</text>
        <value></value>
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger 1.3 p. 3</text>
        <dmg1>2d12</dmg1>
        <dmg2></dmg2>
        <dmgType>P</dmgType>
        <property>M,A,LD,2H</property>
        <range>200/800</range>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Blunderbuss</name>
        <type>R</type>
        <weight>10</weight>
        <text>A ranged weapon that is powerful at short range.</text>
        <text>Reload 1, Misfire 2</text>
        <text>Proficiency: firearms</text>
        <text>Ammunition: 5g (20)</text>
        <value></value>
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger 1.3 p. 3</text>
        <dmg1>2d8</dmg1>
        <dmg2></dmg2>
        <dmgType>P</dmgType>
        <property>M,A,LD</property>
        <range>15/60</range>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Hand Mortar</name>
        <type>R</type>
        <weight>10</weight>
        <text>A thrown weapon that explodes on impact, can be volatile.  Deals Fire damage on hit.</text>
        <text>Reload 1, Misfire 2, Explosive</text>
        <text>Proficiency: firearms</text>
        <text>Ammunition: 10g (1)</text>
        <value></value>
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger 1.3 p. 3</text>
        <dmg1>2d8</dmg1>
        <dmg2></dmg2>
        <dmgType>B</dmgType>
        <property>M,T</property>
        <range>30/60</range>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Musket</name>
        <type>R</type>
        <weight>10</weight>
        <text>A two handed ranged weapon that fires at long range.</text>
        <text>Two-Handed, Reload 1, Misfire 2</text>
        <text>Proficiency: firearms</text>
        <text>Ammunition: 5g (20)</text>
        <value></value>
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger 1.3 p. 3</text>
        <dmg1>1d12</dmg1>
        <dmg2></dmg2>
        <dmgType>P</dmgType>
        <property>M,A,LD,2H</property>
        <range>120/480</range>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Palm Pistol</name>
        <type>R</type>
        <weight>1</weight>
        <text>A ranged weapon that fits in the palm of your hand.</text>
        <text>Light, Reload 1, Misfire 1</text>
        <text>Proficiency: firearms</text>
        <text>Ammunition: 2g (20)</text>
        <value>50</value>
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger 1.3 p. 3</text>
        <dmg1>1d8</dmg1>
        <dmg2></dmg2>
        <dmgType>P</dmgType>
        <property>M,A,L,LD</property>
        <range>40/160</range>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Pistol</name>
        <type>R</type>
        <weight>3</weight>
        <text>A ranged weapon that fires bullets.</text>
        <text>Reload 4, Misfire 1</text>
        <text>Proficiency: firearms</text>
        <text>Ammunition: 4g (20)</text>
        <value>150</value>
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger 1.3 p. 3</text>
        <dmg1>1d10</dmg1>
        <dmg2></dmg2>
        <dmgType>P</dmgType>
        <property>M,A,LD</property>
        <range>60/240</range>
    </item>
    <item>
        <name>Pepperbox</name>
        <type>R</type>
        <weight>5</weight>
        <text>A special, complex one handed ranged weapon that fires quickly.</text>
        <text>Reload 6, Misfire 2</text>
        <text>Proficiency: firearms</text>
        <text>Ammunition: 4g (20)</text>
        <value>250</value>
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger 1.3 p. 3</text>
        <dmg1>1d10</dmg1>
        <dmg2></dmg2>
        <dmgType>P</dmgType>
        <property>M,A,LD</property>
        <range>80/320</range>
    </item>

    <class>
        <name>Blood Hunter</name>
        <hd>10</hd>
        <proficiency>Dexterity, Intelligence, Acrobatics, Arcana, Athletics, History, Insight, Religion, Survival</proficiency>
        <spellAbility>Intelligence</spellAbility>
        <numSkills>3</numSkills>
        <armor>Light armor, medium armor, shields</armor>
        <weapons>Simple weapons, martial weapons</weapons>
        <tools>Alchemist&#39;s supplies</tools>
        <wealth>4d4x10</wealth>

        <autolevel level="1">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Starting Blood Hunter</name>
                <text>You start with the following equipment, in addition to the equipment granted by your background:</text>
                <text>• (a) a martial weapon or (b) two simple weapons</text>
                <text>• (a) a light crossbow and 20 bolts or (b) hand crossbow and 20 bolts</text>
                <text>• (a) studded leather armor or (b) scale mail armor</text>
                <text>• an explorer’s pack</text>
                <text>Alternatively, you could begin with starting wealth of 4d4x10 gp and purchase starting items of your choice.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="1">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Multiclass Blood Hunter</name>
                <text>Blood Hunter Multiclassing Prerequisites:</text>
                <text>Ability Score Minimum: Strength 13 or Dexterity 13, and Intelligence 13</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Blood Hunter Multiclassing Proficiencies:</text>
                <text>Proficiencies Gained:</text>
                <text>Light armor, medium armor, shields, simple weapons, martial weapons, alchemical supplies.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Blood Hunter Multiclassing with Warlock:</text>
                <text>If multiclassing Order of the Profane Soul with Warlock levels, add a third of your blood hunter levels (rounded down) to your Warlock level and consult the Warlock progression table in the Player’s Handbook for total Spell Slots, Cantrips known, and Spell Slot Level.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="1">
            <feature>
                <name>Hunter's Bane</name>
                <text>Beginning at 1st level,you have survived theHunter’s Bane, a dangerous, long-guarded ritual that alters your life’s blood, forever binding you to the darkness and honing your senses against it. You have advantage on Wisdom (Survival) checks to track fey, fiends, or undead, as well as on Inteligence ability checks to recall information about them.</text>
                <text>The Hunter’s Bane also empowers your body to control and shape hemocraft magic, using your own blood and life essence to fuel your abilities. Some of your features require your target to make a saving throw to resist the feature’s effects. The saving throw DC is calculated as folows:</text>
                <text>Hemocraft save DC = 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Inteligence modifier.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="1">
            <feature>
                <name>Blood Maledict</name>
                <text>At 1st level, you gain the ability to channel, and sometimes sacrifice, a part of your vital essence to curse and manipulate creatures through hemocraft magic. You gain one blood curse of your choice, detailed in the “Blood Curses” section at the end of the class description. You learn one blood curse of your choice, and you can choose one of the blood curses you know and replace it with another blood curse, at 6th, 10th, 14th, and 18th level.</text>
                <text>When you use your Blood Maledict, you choose which curse to invoke. While invoking a Blood Curse, but before it affects the target, you can amplify the curse by losing a number of hit points equal to one roll of your hemocraft die, as shown in the hemocraft die column of the Blood Hunter table. An amplified curse gains an additional effect, noted In the curse’s description. Creatures that do not have blood in their bodies are immune to blood curses, unless you have amplified the curse.</text>
                <text>You can use this feature once. The amount of times you can use it increases at 6th, 13th, and 17th level. You regain all expended uses when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
            </feature>
            <counter>
                <name>Blood Maledict</name>
                <value>1</value>
                <reset>S</reset>
            </counter>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="1">
            <feature>
                <name>List of Blood Curses</name>
                <text>Blood Curse of the Anxious</text>
                <text>As a bonus action, you magnify the adrenaline in the body of a creature within 30 feet of you, making them susceptible to forceful influence. Until the end of your next turn, all creatures have advantage on Charisma (Intimidation) checks directed at the target creature.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Amplify: The next Wisdom saving throw the target has to make before this curse ends has disadvantage.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Blood Curse of Binding</text>
                <text>As a bonus action, you can attempt to bind a creature you can see within 30 feet of you that is no more than one size larger than you. The target must succeed on a Strength saving throw or have their speed be reduced to 0 and they can’t use reactions until the end of your next turn.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Amplify: This curse lasts for 1 minute and can affect a creature regardless of their size category. At the end of each of its turns, the cursed creature can make another Strength saving throw. On a success, this curse ends.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Blood Curse of Bloated Agony</text>
                <text>As a bonus action, you curse a creature that you can see within 30 feet of you to painfully swell until the end of your next turn. For the duration of this curse, the creature has disadvantage on Strength and Dexterity ability checks, and suffers 1d8 necrotic damage if it makes more than one melee or ranged attack during its turn.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Amplify: This curse lasts for 1 minute. At the end of each of its turns, the cursed creature can make a Constitution saving throw. On a success, this curse ends.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Blood Curse of Corrosion</text>
                <text>Prerequisite: 15th level, Order of the Mutant</text>
                <text>As a bonus action, a creature within 30 feet of you must make a Constitution saving throw or become poisoned. At the end of each of its turns, the target can make another Constitution saving throw. On a success, the curse ends.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Amplify: The cursed creature suffers 4d6 necrotic damage, and suffers this damage again every time it fails its Constitution saving throw to end this curse at the end of its turn.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Blood Curse of Exposure</text>
                <text>When a creature you can see within 30 feet is hit by an attack or spell, you can use your reaction to temporarily weaken their resilience against it. Until the end of the turn, the target loses resistance to the damage types of the triggering attack or spell.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Amplify: The target instead loses invulnerability to the damage types of the triggering attack or spell, having resistance to them until the end of the turn.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Blood Curse of the Exorcist</text>
                <text>Prerequisite: 15th level, Order of the Ghostslayer</text>
                <text>As a bonus action, you can choose one creature you can see within 30 feet of you that is charmed, frightened, or possessed. The target creature is no longer charmed, frightened, or possessed.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Amplify: The creature that charmed, frightened, or possessed the target of your curse suffers 3d6 psychic damage and must make a Wisdom saving throw or be stunned until the end of your next turn.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Blood Curse of the Eyeless</text>
                <text>When a creature you can see within 30 feet of you makes an attack roll, you can use your reaction to roll one hemocraft die and subtract the number rolled from the creature’s attack roll. You can choose to use this feature after the creature’s roll, but before the DM determines whether the attack roll succeeds. The creature is immune if it is immune to blindness.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Amplify: You apply this curse to all of the creature’s attack rolls until the end of the turn. You roll a new hemocraft die for each affected attack.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Blood Curse of the Fallen Puppet</text>
                <text>When a creature you can see within 30 feet drops to 0 hit points, you can use your reaction to make that creature immediately makes a single weapon attack against a target of your choice within its attack range.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Amplify: You can first move the cursed creature up to half their speed, and you grant a bonus to the cursed creature’s attack roll equal to your Intelligence modifier (minimum of 1).</text>
                <text></text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Blood Curse of the Howl</text>
                <text>Prerequisite: 18th level, Order of the Lycan</text>
                <text>As an action, you unleash a blood-curdling howl. Each creature within 30 feet of you that can hear you must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or become frightened of you until the end of your next turn. If they fail their saving throw by 5 or more, they are stunned while frightened in this way. A creature that succeeds on this saving throw is immune to this blood curse for the next 24 hours. You can choose any number of creatures you can see to be unaffected by this howl.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Amplify: The range of this curse increases to 60 feet.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Blood Curse of the Marked</text>
                <text>As a bonus action, you can mark a creature within 30 feet of you. Until the end of your turn, you roll an additional hemocraft die whenever you deal rite damage to the target.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Amplify: The next attack roll you make against the target before the end of your turn has advantage.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Blood Curse of the Muddled Mind</text>
                <text>As a bonus action, you curse a creature that you can see within 30 feet of you that is concentrating on a spell. That creature has disadvantage on the next Constitution saving throw it must make to maintain concentration before the end of your next turn.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Amplify: The cursed creature has disadvantage on all Constitution saving throws made to maintain concentration of spells until the end of your next turn.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Blood Curse of the Souleater</text>
                <text>Prerequisite: 18th level, Order of the Profane Soul</text>
                <text>When a creature that isn’t a construct or undead is reduced to 0 hit points within 30 feet of you, you can use your reaction to usher their soul to your patron in exchange for power. Until the end of your next turn, your weapon attacks have advantage.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Amplify: In addition, you regain an expended warlock spell slot. Once you’ve amplified this blood curse, you must finish a long rest before you can amplify it again.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="2">
            <feature>
                <name>Fighting Style</name>
                <text>At 2nd level, you adopt a style of fighting as your specialty. Choose one of the following options. You can’t take a fighting style more than once, even if you later get to choose again.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="2">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Fighting Style: Archery</name>
                <text>You gain a +2 bonus to attack rolls you make with ranged weapons.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Player's Handbook, p. 72</text>
                <special>fighting style archery</special>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="2">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Fighting Style: Dueling</name>
                <text>When you are wielding a melee weapon in one hand and no other weapons, you gain a +2 bonus to damage rolls with that weapon.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Player's Handbook, p. 72</text>
                <special>fighting style dueling</special>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="2">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Fighting Style: Great Weapon Fighting</name>
                <text>When you roll a 1 or 2 on a damage die for an attack you make with a melee weapon that you are wielding with two hands, you can reroll the die and must use the new roll, even if the new roll is a 1 or a 2. The weapon must have the two-handed or versatile property for you to gain this benefit.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Player's Handbook, p. 72</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="2">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Fighting Style: Two-Weapon Fighting</name>
                <text>When you engage in two-weapon fighting, you can add your ability modifier to the damage of the second attack.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Player's Handbook, p. 72</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="2">
            <feature>
                <name>Crimson Rite</name>
                <text>At 2nd level, you learn to invoke a rite of hemocraft within your weapon at the cost of your own vitality. Choose one rite from the Primal Rites list below to learn.</text>
                <text>As a bonus action, you can activate a crimson rite on a single weapon with the elemental energy of a known rite of your choice that lasts until you finish a short or long rest, or if you aren’t holding the weapon at the end of your turn. When you activate a rite, you lose a number of hit points equal to one roll of your hemocraft die, as shown in the hemocraft die column of the Blood Hunter table.</text>
                <text>While active, attacks from this weapon deal an additional 1d4 damage of the chosen rite’s type. This damage is magical, and increases as you gain levels as a blood hunter, as showin in the hemocraft die column of the Blood Hunter table.</text>
                <text>You learn an additional Primal Rite of your choice at 7th level, and choose an Esoteric Rite to learn at 14th level.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Primal Rites</text>
                <text>Choose from the following:</text>
                <text>Rite of the Flame. Your rite damage is fire damage.</text>
                <text>Rite of the Frozen. Your rite damage is cold damage.</text>
                <text>Rite of the Storm. Your rite damage is lightning damage.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Esoteric Rites</text>
                <text>Choose from the following:</text>
                <text>Rite of the Dead. Your rite damage is necrotic damage.</text>
                <text>Rite of the Oracle. Your rite damage is psychic damage.</text>
                <text>Rite of the Roar. Your rite damage is thunder damage.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature>
                <name>Blood Hunter Order</name>
                <text>There are a handful of secretive orders of blood hunters that guard their cryptic techniques and rituals. One must adhere to one of these orders to even be granted acess to the Hunter’s Bane rite that starts their journey, and only once they’ve proven their dedication and ability will the secrets of the order begin to be revealed. It’s within these small, enigmatic sects that the real power of a blood hunter is learned.</text>
                <text>At 3rd level, you commit to an order of blood hunter martial focus. Choose Order of the Ghostslayer, Order of the Profane Soul, Order of the Mutant, or Order of the Lycan. The order you choose grants you features at 3rd level, and again at 7th, 11th, 15th, and 18th level.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>

        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Blood Hunter Order: Order of the Ghostslayer</name>
                <text>The Order of the Ghostslayer is the oldest of the orders, having originally rediscovered the secrets of blood magic and refined them for combat against the scourge of undeath. Ghostslayers seek out and study the moment of death, obsessing over the mysteries of the transition and how it can become corrupted by unholy powers to rise once more. Tuning their abilities to annihilate such abominations, these zealous blood hunters seek out the sources of such necromantic energies, intent to destroy them wherever they arise.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Rite of the Dawn (Ghostslayer)</name>
                <text>When you join this order at 3rd level, you learn the Rite of the Dawn esoteric rite, detailed below.</text>
                <text>Rite of the Dawn: Your rite damage is radiant damage. While the rite is active, you gain the following benefits:</text>
                <text>• Your weapon sheds bright light out to a radius of 20 feet.</text>
                <text>• You have resistance to necrotic damage.</text>
                <text>• Your weapon deals one additional hemocraft die when you hit an undead.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Curse Specialist (Ghostslayer)</name>
                <text>Beginning at 3rd level, your ancient order teaches advanced mastery over blood curses. You gain an additional use of your blood maledict feature. In addition, your blood curses can target any creature, whether it has blood or not.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>

        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Blood Hunter Order: Order of the Profane Soul</name>
                <text>Those who have taken to the Order of the Profane Soul have seen the limits of hemocraft against some of the most ancient and cruel fiends and terrors of the world. Unable to pursue beings of such power, creatures able to vanish amongst the nobles without a trace, or bend the mind of the most stalwart warrior with but a glance, this order trusted in their resilience and delved into this same well of corrupting arcane knowledge, making pacts with lesser evils to better combat the greater. While they may have traded a part of themselves, members of this order believe the power gained far outweighs the price, for even devils now quake when they know they’ve drawn the attention of the Order of the Profane Soul.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Otherworldly Patron (Profane Soul)</name>
                <text>When you reach 3rd level, you strike a bargain with an otherworldly being of your choice: the Archfey, the Fiend, or the Great Old One, each detailed in the Player’s Handbook, the Undying within the Sword Coast Adventurer’s Guide, and the Celestial or Hexblade in Xanathar’s Guide to Everything. Your choice augments some of your order features.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="3">
            <slots optional="YES">2, 1</slots>
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Pact Magic (Profane Soul)</name>
                <text>When you reach 3rd level, you can augment your combat techniques with the ability to cast spells. See chapter 10 of the Player’s Handbook for the general rules of spellcasting and chapter 11 of the Player’s Handbook for the Warlock spell list.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Cantrips:</text>
                <text>You learn two cantrips of your choice from the warlock spell list. You learn an additional warlock cantrip of your choice at 10th level.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Spell Slots:</text>
                <text>The Profane Soul Spellcasting table shows how many spell slots you have. The table also shows what the level of those slots is; all of your spell slots are the same level. To cast one of your warlock spells of 1st level or higher, you must expend a spell slot. You regain all expended spell slots when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
                <text>For example, when you are 8th level, you have two 2nd-level spell slots. To cast the 1st-level spell witch bolt, you must spend one of those slots, and you cast it as a 2nd-level spell.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Spells Known of 1st Level and Higher:</text>
                <text>At 3rd level, you know two 1st-level spells of your choice from the warlock spell list.</text>
                <text>The Spells Known column of the Profane Soul table shows when you learn more warlock spells of your choice of 1st level and higher. A spell you choose must be of a level no higher than what’s shown in the table’s Slot Level column for your level. When you reach 11th level, for example, you learn a new warlock spell, which can be 1st, 2nd, or 3rd level.</text>
                <text>Additionally, when you gain a level in this class and order, you can choose one of the warlock spells you know and replace it with another spell from the warlock spell list, which also must be of a level for which you have spell slots.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Spellcasting Ability:</text>
                <text>Intelligence is your spellcasting ability for your warlock spells, so you use your Intelligence whenever a spell refers to your spellcasting ability. In addition, you use your Intelligence modifier when setting the saving throw DC for a warlock spell you cast and when making an attack roll with one.</text>
                <text>Spell save DC = 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Intelligence modifier.</text>
                <text>Spell attack modifier = your proficiency bonus + your Intelligence modifier.</text>
                <text></text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Rite Focus (Profane Soul)</name>
                <text>Beginning at 3rd level, your weapon becomes a core to your pact with your chosen dark patron. While you have an active Crimson Rite, you can use your weapon as a spellcasting focus (found in chapter 5 of the Player’s Handbook) for your warlock spells, and you gain a specific benefit based on your chosen pact (outlined below).</text>
                <text>The Archfey: When you deal rite damage to a creature, it glows with faint light until the end of your next turn. For the duration, the creature can’t benefit from half cover, three-quarters cover, or being invisible.</text>
                <text>The Fiend: When you hit a creature with your Rite of the Flame, if you roll a 1 or 2 on your hemocraft die, you can reroll the die. If you do so, you must use the new roll.</text>
                <text>The Great Old One: When you score a critical hit against a creature while using the weapon, that creature is frightened of you until the end of your next turn.</text>
                <text>The Undying: Whenever you reduce a hostile creature to 0 hit points using a weapon, you regain a number of hit points equal to one roll of your hemocraft die.</text>
                <text>The Celestial: You can expend a use of your Blood Maledict feature as a bonus action to heal one creature that you can see within 60 feet of you. They regain a number of hit points equal to one roll of your hemocraft die + your Intelligence modifier (minimum of 1).</text>
                <text>The Hexblade: Whenever you target a creature with a blood curse, your next attack against the cursed creature deals additional damage equal to your proficiency modifier.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="3">
            <slots optional="YES">2, 1</slots>
        </autolevel>

        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Blood Hunter Order: Order of the Mutant</name>
                <text>The process of the Hunter’s Bane is a painful, scarring, and sometimes fatal experience. Those that survive find themselves irrevocably changed, enhanced. Some found this experience exalting, embracing the ability to alter one’s own physiology through a combination of hemocraft and corrupted alchemy. Over generations of experimentation, a splinter order of blood hunters began to emerge, one that focused on brewing toxic elixirs to modify their capabilities in battle, altering their blood and, over time, become something beyond what they once were. They called themselves the Order of the Mutant. Researching their targets to know their strengths and weaknesses, these blood hunters can alter their biology to be best prepared for the coming conflict.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Formulas (Mutant)</name>
                <text>You begin to uncover forbidden alchemical formulas that temporarily alter your mental and physical abilities.</text>
                <text>Beginning at 3rd level, you choose to learn four mutagen formulas. Your formula options are detailed at the end of this order description. You gain an additional formula at 7th level, 11th level, 15th level, and 18th level.</text>
                <text>Additionally, when you gain a new mutagen formula, you can choose one of the formulas you already know and replace it with a new mutagen formula.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Mutagencraft (Mutant)</name>
                <text>At 3rd level, you can concoct a single mutagen when you finish a short or long rest. Starting at 7th level, the number of mutagens you can create when you finish a rest increases to two, and you can create three mutagens at 15th level.</text>
                <text>As a bonus action you can consume a single mutagen, and the effects and side effects last until you finish a short or long rest, unless otherwise specified. While one or more mutagens are affecting you, you can use an action to focus and flush the toxins from your system, ending the effects and side effects of all mutagens.</text>
                <text>Mutagens are designed for your biology and have no effect on other creatures. They are also unstable by nature, losing their potency over time and becoming inert if not used before you finish your next short or long rest.</text>
            </feature>
            <counter>
                <name>Mutagencraft</name>
                <value>1</value>
                <reset>S</reset>
            </counter>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Mutagen List (Mutant)</name>
                <text>Aether (11th Level Required)</text>
                <text>You gain a flying speed of 20 feet for 1 hour. As a side effect, you gain disadvantage on Strength and Dexterity ability checks for 1 hour.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Alluring</text>
                <text>Your skin and voice become malleable, allowing you to slightly enhance your appearance and presence. You have advantage on Charisma ability checks. As a side effect, you gain disadvantage on initiative rolls.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Celerity</text>
                <text>Your Dexterity score increases by 3, as does your Dexterity maximum. This bonus increases by 1 at 11th level (+4) and 18th level (+5). As a side effect, you gain disadvantage on Wisdom saving throws.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Conversant</text>
                <text>You gain advantage on Intelligence ability checks. As a side effect, you gain disadvantage on Wisdom ability checks.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Cruelty (11th level required)</text>
                <text>When you use the Attack action, you can make an additional weapon attack as a bonus action. As a side effect, you gain disadvantage on Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saving throws.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Deftness</text>
                <text>You gain advantage on Dexterity ability checks. As a side effect, you gain disadvantage on Wisdom ability checks.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Embers</text>
                <text>You gain resistance to fire damage. As a side effect, you gain vulnerability to cold damage.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Gelid</text>
                <text>You gain resistance to cold damage. As a side effect, you gain vulnerability to fire damage.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Impermeable</text>
                <text>You gain resistance to piercing damage. As a side effect, you gain vulnerability to slashing damage.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Mobile</text>
                <text>You are immune to the grappled and restrained conditions. At 11th level, you also are immune to the paralyzed condition. As a side effect, you gain disadvantage on Strength ability checks.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Nighteye</text>
                <text>You gain darkvision for up to 60 feet. If you already have darkvision, this increases its range by 60 additional feet. As a side effect, you gain sunlight sensitivity (detailed in the Dark Elf section on page 24 in the Player’s Handbook).</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Percipient</text>
                <text>You gain advantage on Wisdom ability checks. As a side effect, you gain disadvantage on Charisma ability checks.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Potency</text>
                <text>Your Strength score increases by 3, as does your Strength maximum. This bonus increases by 1 at 11th level (+4) and 18th level (+5). As a side effect, you have disadvantage on Dexterity saving throws.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Precision (11th level required)</text>
                <text>Your weapon attacks score a critical hit on a roll of 19-20. As a side effect, you gain disadvantage on Strength saving throws.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Rapidity</text>
                <text>Your speed increases by 10 feet. At 15th level, your speed increases by 15 feet instead. As a side effect, you gain disadvantage on Intelligence ability checks.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Reconstruction (7th level required)</text>
                <text>For 1 hour, at the start of each of your turns, you regain hit points equal to your proficiency bonus if you have at least 1 hit point but no more than half of your hit points left. As a side effect, your speed decreases by 10 ft for 1 hour.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Sagacity</text>
                <text>Your Intelligence score increases by 3, as does your Intelligence maximum. This bonus increases by 1 at 11th level (+4) and 18th level (+5). As a side effect, you gain disadvantage on Charisma saving throws.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Shielded</text>
                <text>You gain resistance to slashing damage. As a side effect, you gain vulnerability to bludgeoning damage. Unbreakable. You gain resistance to bludgeoning damage. As a side effect, you gain vulnerability to piercing damage.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Vermillion</text>
                <text>You gain an additional use of your Blood Maledict feature. As a side effect, you gain disadvantage on death saving throws.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>

        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Blood Hunter Order: Order of the Lycan</name>
                <text>Of the many terrible curses that plague the realm, few are as ancient or as feared as Lycanthropy. Passed through blood, this affliction seeds a host with the savage strength and hunger for violence of a wicked beast. The Order of the Lycan is a proud order of blood hunters who undergo “The Taming,” a ceremonial inflicting of lycanthropy from a senior member. These hunters then use their abilities to harness the power of the monster they harbor without losing themselves to it. Through intense honing of one’s own willpower, combined with the secrets of the order’s blood magic rituals, members learn to control and unleash their hybrid form for short periods of time. Enhanced physical prowess, unnatural resilience, and razor sharp claws make these warriors a terrible foe to any evil that crosses their path. Yet, no training is perfect, and without care and complete focus, even the greatest of blood hunters can temporarily lose themselves to the bloodlust.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Heightened Senses (Lycan)</name>
                <text>Starting when you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you begin to adopt the improved abilities of a natural predator. You gain advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing or smell.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Hybrid Transformation (Lycan)</name>
                <text>Upon choosing this archetype at 3rd level, you begin to learn to control the lycanthropic curse that now lives in your blood. As a bonus action, you can transform into your hybrid form for up to 1 hour. You can speak, use equipment, and wear armor in this form. You can revert to your normal form earlier as a bonus action. You automatically revert to your normal form if you fall unconscious, drop to 0 hit points, or die. This feature replaces the rules for Lycanthropy within the Monster’s Manual.</text>
                <text>Once you use this feature, you must finish a short or long rest before you can use it again. While you are transformed, you gain the following features:</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Feral Might</text>
                <text>You gain a +1 to melee damage rolls. This bonus increases by 1 at 11th level (+2) and 18th level (+3). You also have advantage on Strength checks and Strength saving throws.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Resilient Hide</text>
                <text>You have resistance to bludgeoning, piercing, and slashing damage from nonmagical attacks not made with silver weapons. While you are not wearing heavy armor, you gain a +1 bonus to your AC.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Predatory Strikes</text>
                <text>Your can apply your Crimson Rite feature to your unarmed strikes. You can use Dexterity instead of Strength for the attack and damage rolIs of your unarmed strikes. When you use the Attack action with an unarmed strike, you can make one unarmed strike as a bonus action.</text>
                <text>Your unarmed strikes deal 1d6 slashing damage. The damage increases to 1d8 at 11th level.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Bloodlust</text>
                <text>If you begin your turn with no more than half of your maximum hit points, you must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw (DC is equal to 8 + 1/3 of your blood hunter level) or move directly towards the nearest creature to you and use the Attack action against that creature. You can choose whether or not to use your Extra Attack feature for this frenzied attack. If there is more than one possible target, roll to randomly determine the target. You then regain control for the remainder of your turn.</text>
                <text>If you are under an effect that prevents you from concentrating (like the barbarian’s Rage feature), you automatically fail this saving throw.</text>
            </feature>
            <counter>
                <name>Hybrid Transformation</name>
                <value>1</value>
                <reset>S</reset>
            </counter>
        </autolevel>

        <autolevel level="4" scoreImprovement="YES">
        </autolevel>

        <autolevel level="5">
            <feature>
                <name>Extra Attack</name>
                <text>Beginning at 5th level, you can attack twice, instead of once, whenever you take the attack action.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="6">
            <slots optional="YES">2, 2</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="6">
            <feature>
                <name>Brand of Castigation</name>
                <text>At 6th level, whenever you damage a creature with your Crimson Rite feature, you can choose to sear an arcane brand of hemocraft magic into it (requires no action). You always know the direction to the branded creature, and each time the branded creature deals damage to you or a creature you can see within 5 feet of you, the branded creature suffers psychic damage equal to your intelligence modifier (minimum of 1 damage).</text>
                <text>Your brand lasts until you dismiss it, or you apply a brand to another creature. Your brand counts as a spell for the purposes of dispel magic, and the spell level is equal to half your blood hunter level (maximum of 9th level spell).</text>
                <text>Once you use this feature, you can’t use it again until you finish a rest.</text>
            </feature>
            <counter>
                <name>Brand of Castigation</name>
                <value>1</value>
                <reset>S</reset>
            </counter>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="6">
            <counter>
                <name>Blood Maledict</name>
                <value>2</value>
                <reset>S</reset>
            </counter>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="7">
            <feature>
                <name>Primal Rite</name>
                <text>You learn an additional Primal Rite of your choice at 7th level.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Primal Rites</text>
                <text>Choose from the following:</text>
                <text>Rite of the Flame. Your rite damage is fire damage.</text>
                <text>Rite of the Frozen. Your rite damage is cold damage.</text>
                <text>Rite of the Storm. Your rite damage is lightning damage.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="7">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Ethereal Step (Ghostslayer)</name>
                <text>Upon reaching 7th level, at the start of your turn, if you aren’t incapacitated, you can choose to magically step into the veil between planes. You can move through other creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain, as well as see and affect objects on the Ethereal Plane. You take 1d10 force damage if you end your turn inside an object. If you are inside an object when this feature ends, you are immediately shunted to the nearest unoccupied space that you can occupy and take force damage equal to twice the number of feet you moved. This feature lasts for a number of rounds equal to your Intelligence modifier (minimum of one round).</text>
                <text>You can use this feature once. Beginning at 15th level, you can use your Ethereal step feature twice between rests. You regain all expended uses when you finish a short or long rest.</text>
            </feature>
            <counter>
                <name>Ethereal Step</name>
                <value>1</value>
                <reset>S</reset>
            </counter>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="7">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Mystic Frenzy (Profane Soul)</name>
                <text>Starting at 7th level, when you use your action to cast a cantrip, you can immediately make one weapon attack as a bonus action.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Revealed Arcana (Profane Soul)</name>
                <text>At 7th level, your dark patron grants you the rare use of a dangerous arcane spell based on your pact.</text>
                <text>The Archfey: You can cast blur once using a pact magic spell slot. You can’t do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
                <text>The Fiend: You can cast scorching ray once using a pact magic spell slot. You can’t do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
                <text>The Great Old One: You can cast detect thoughts once using a pact magic spell slot. You can’t do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
                <text>The Undying: You can cast blindness/deafness once using a pact magic spell slot. You can’t do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
                <text>The Celestial: You can cast lesser restoration once using a pact magic spell slot. You can’t do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
                <text>The Hexblade: You can cast branding smite once using a pact magic spell slot. You can’t do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="7">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Strange Metabolism (Mutant)</name>
                <text>Beginning at 7th level, your body has begun to adapt to toxins and venoms, ignoring their corroding effects. You gain immunity to poison damage and the poisoned condition.</text>
                <text>In addition, you can instill a burst of adrenaline to temporarily resist the negative effects of a mutagen. As a bonus action, you can choose to ignore the side effect of a mutagen affecting you for 1 minute.</text>
                <text>Once you use this feature to resist side effects, you can’t do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
            </feature>
            <counter>
                <name>Strange Metabolism</name>
                <value>1</value>
                <reset>L</reset>
            </counter>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="7">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Stalker&#39;s Prowess (Lycan)</name>
                <text>At 7th level, your speed increases by 10 feet. You also can add 10 feet to your long jump distance and 3 feet to your high jump distance. In addition, your hybrid form gains the Improved Predatory Strikes feature.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Improved Predatory Strikes</text>
                <text>You gain a +1 bonus to attack rolls made with your unarmed strikes. This bonus increases by 1 at 11th level (+2) and 18th level (+3). In addition, when you have an active Crimson Rite while in your hybrid form, your unarmed strikes are considered magical for the purpose of overcoming resistance and immunity to nonmagical attacks and damage.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="8" scoreImprovement="YES">
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="9">
            <feature>
                <name>Grim Psychometry</name>
                <text>When you reach 9th level, you have a supernatural talent for discerning the history surrounding mysterious objects or places touched by evil. When making an Intelligence (History) check to recall information about a darker past surrounding an object you are touching, or a location you are present in, you have advantage on the roll. The information gleaned often leans towards the more sinister influences of the past, and sometimes conveys visions of things previously unknown to the character on higher rolls.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="10">
            <slots optional="YES">3, 0, 2</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="10">
            <feature>
                <name>Dark Augmentation</name>
                <text>Upon reaching 10th level, arcane blood magic suffuses your body, permanently reinforcing your resilience. Your speed increases by 5 feet, and whenever you make a Strength, Dexterity, or Constitution saving throw, you gain a bonus equal to your Intelligence modifier (minimum of one).</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="11">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Brand of Sundering (Ghostslayer)</name>
                <text>Beginning at 11th level, your Brand of Castigation now exposes a fragment of your foe’s essence, leaving them vulnerable to your Crimson Rite. Whenever you damage a branded creature with your Crimson Rite, you reroll one additional hemocraft die. In addition, the branded creature can’t move through creatures or objects.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="11">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Brand of the Sapping Scar (Profane Soul)</name>
                <text>Upon reaching 11th level, your Brand of Castigation feature now digs dark, arcane scars into your target, leaving them vulnerable to your magic. A creature branded by you has disadvantage on their saving throws against your warlock spells.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="11">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Brand of Axiom (Mutant)</name>
                <text>At 11th level, your hemocraft has altered your Brand of Castigation to enforce a foe’s true nature. Any illusions disguising or making a creature invisible when you brand them end, and they can’t benefit from such illusions while branded. If a creature branded by you is polymorphed or has changed shape, they must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or revert to their true form and be stunned until the end of your next turn. Whenever a branded creature attempts to polymorph or change shape, they must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or the attempt fails, and they are stunned until the end of your next turn.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="11">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Advanced Transformation (Lycan)</name>
                <text>Starting at 11th level, you learn to unleash and control more of the beast within. You can use your Hybrid Transformation feature twice, regaining all expended uses when you finish a short or long rest. In addition, your hybrid form gains the Lycan Regeneration feature.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Lycan Regeneration</text>
                <text>At the start of each of your turns, you regain hit points equal to 1 + your Constitution modifier (minimum of 1) if you have at least 1 hit point and no more than half of your hit points left.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Improved Predatory Strikes (Lycan)</name>
                <text>You gain a +2 bonus to attack rolls made with your unarmed strikes.</text>
            </feature>
            <counter>
                <name>Hybrid Transformation</name>
                <value>2</value>
                <reset>S</reset>
            </counter>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="12" scoreImprovement="YES">
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="13">
            <counter>
                <name>Blood Maledict</name>
                <value>3</value>
                <reset>S</reset>
            </counter>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="13">
            <slots optional="YES">3, 0, 0, 2</slots>
            <feature>
                <name>Brand of Tethering</name>
                <text>Starting at 13th level, the psychic damage from your Brand of Castigation feature increases to twice your Intelligence modifier (minimum of 2).</text>
                <text>In addition, a branded creature can’t take the dash action, and if a creature branded to you attempts to teleport or leave their current plane via ability, spell, or portal, they take 4d6 psychic damage and must make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failure, the teleport or plane shift fails.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="14">
            <feature>
                <name>Esoteric Rite</name>
                <text>Choose an Esoteric Rite to learn at 14th level.</text>
                <text></text>
                <text>Esoteric Rites</text>
                <text>Choose from the following:</text>
                <text>Rite of the Dead. Your rite damage is necrotic damage.</text>
                <text>Rite of the Oracle. Your rite damage is psychic damage.</text>
                <text>Rite of the Roar. Your rite damage is thunder damage.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="14">
            <feature><name>Hardened Soul</name>
                <text>When you reach 14th level, you have advantage on saving throws against being charmed and frightened.</text>
            </feature>
            <counter>
                <name>Blood Maledict</name>
                <value>3</value>
                <reset>S</reset>
            </counter>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="15">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Curse of the Exorcist (Ghostslayer)</name>
                <text>At 15th level, you’ve honed your hemocraft to tear wicked influence from your allies, punishing those who would infiltrate their body and mind. You gain the Blood Curse of the Exorcist for your Blood Maledict feature. This doesn’t count against your number of curses known.</text>
            </feature>
            <counter>
                <name>Ethereal Step</name>
                <value>1</value>
                <reset>S</reset>
            </counter>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="15">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Unsealed Arcana (Profane Soul)</name>
                <text>At 15th level, your patron grants you the rare use of an additional arcane spell based on your pact.</text>
                <text>The Archfey. You can cast slow once without expending a spell slot.</text>
                <text>You can’t do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
                <text>The Fiend. You can cast fireball once without expending a spell slot. You can’t do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
                <text>The Great Old One. You can cast haste once without expending a spell slot. You can’t do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
                <text>The Undying. You can cast bestow curse once without expending a spell slot. You can’t do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
                <text>The Celestial. You can cast revivify once without expending a spell slot. You can’t do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
                <text>The Hexblade. You can cast blink once without expending a spell slot. You can’t do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="15">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Blood Curse of Corrosion (Mutant)</name>
                <text>Starting at 15th level, your blood curse can wrack a creature’s body with terrible toxins. You gain the Blood Curse of Corrosion for your Blood Maledict feature. This does not count against your number of blood curses known.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="15">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Brand of the Voracious (Lycan)</name>
                <text>At 15th level, you have advantage on your Wisdom saving throws to maintain control of your bloodlust in hybrid form. In addition, your Brand of Castigation now binds your foe to your hunter’s thirst for savagery. While in your hybrid form, your attacks have advantage against a creature branded by you.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="16" scoreImprovement="YES">
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="17">
            <counter>
                <name>Blood Maledict</name>
                <value>4</value>
                <reset>S</reset>
            </counter>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="18">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Rite Revival (Ghostslayer)</name>
                <text>Upon reaching 18th level, you learn to protect your fading life by absorbing your blood rite. When you are reduced to 0 hit points while you have an active crimson rite, but don’t die outright, the rite ends and you drop to 1 hit point instead. If you have multiple rites active, you choose which one ends.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="18">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Blood Curse of the Souleater (Profane Soul)</name>
                <text>Starting at 18th level, you’ve learned to siphon the soul from your fallen prey. You gain the Blood Curse of the Souleater for your Blood Maledict feature. This does not count against your number of blood curses known.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="18">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Exalted Mutation (Mutant)</name>
                <text>At 18th level, your body has adapted to produce your toxins naturally in a moment of need. As a reaction, you can choose one mutagen currently affecting you to flush from your system and end, then immediately have a mutagen you know the formula for take effect in its place.</text>
                <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Intelligence modifier (minimum of 1). You regain all uses of this feature after you finish a long rest.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
         <autolevel level="18">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Hybrid Transformation Mastery (Lycan)</name>
                <text>At 18th level, you have wrestled your inner predator and mastered it. You can use your Hybrid Transformation feature an unlimited number of times, and your hybrid form can now last indefinitely.</text>
                <text>You also gain the Blood Curse of the Howl for your Blood Maledict feature. This does not count against your number of blood curses known.</text>
            </feature>
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Improved Predatory Strikes (Lycan)</name>
                <text>You gain a +3 bonus to attack rolls made with your unarmed strikes.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="19" scoreImprovement="YES">
            <slots optional="YES">3, 0, 0, 0, 2</slots>
        </autolevel>
        <autolevel level="20">
            <feature>
                <name>Sanguine Mastery</name>
                <text>Upon becoming 20th level, you honed your control over blood magic, mitigating your sacrifice and empowering your capability. Once per turn, whenever a blood hunter feature requires you to roll a hemocraft die, you can choose to reroll the die and choose which result to use.</text>
                <text>In addition, whenever you score a critical hit with a weapon empowered by your Crimson Rite, you regain one expended use of your blood maledict feature.</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
    </class>

    <class>
        <name>Fighter</name>

        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Martial Archetype: Gunslinger</name>
                <text>Most warriors and combat specialists spend their years perfecting the classic arts of swordplay, archery, or polearm tactics.  Whether the duelist of infantry martial weapons were seemingly perfected long ago, and the true challenge is to master them.</text>
                <text>    However, some minds couldn’t stop with the innovation of the crossbow.  Experimentation with alchemical components and rare metals have unlocked the secrets of controlled explosive force.  The few who survive these trials of ingenuity may become the first to create, and deftly wield, the first firearms.</text>
                <text>    This archetype focuses on the ability to design, craft and utilize powerful, yet dangerous ranged weapons.  Through creative innovation and immaculate aim, you become a distant force of death on the battlefield.  However, not being a perfect science, firearms carry an inherent instability that can occasionally leave you without a functional means of attack.  This is the danger of new, untested technologies in a world where the arcane energies that rule the elements are ever present.</text>
                <text>    Should this path of powder, fire and metal call to you, keep your wits about you, hold onto your convictions as a fighter, and let skill meet luck to guide your bullets to strike true.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.3 p. 1</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>

        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Firearm Proficiency (Gunslinger)</name>
                <text>Starting from when you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you gain proficiency in firearms, allowing you to add your proficiency bonus to attacks made with firearms.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.3 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>

        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Gunsmith (Gunslinger)</name>
                <text>Upon choosing this archetype at 3rd level, you gain proficiency in Tinker’s Tools.  You may use them to craft ammunition, repair damaged firearms, or even draft and create new ones (DM’s discretion). Some extremely intricate and experimental features are only available through crafting.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>

        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Firearm Properties</name>
                <text>Firearms are a new and volatile technology, and as such bring their own unique set of weapon properties.  Some properties are followed by a number, and this number signifies an element of their property.  These properties replace the optional ones presented in the DM guide.  Firearms are ranged weapons.</text>
                <text>    RELOAD.  The weapon can be fired a number of times equal to its Reload score before you must spend 1 attack or 1 action to reload.  You must have one free hand to reload a firearm.</text>
                <text>    MISFIRE.  Whenever you make an attack roll with a firearm, and the dice roll is equal to or lower than weapon’s Misfire score, the weapon misfires.  The attack misses, and the weapon cannot be used again until you spend an action to try and repair it.  To repair your firearm, you must make a successful Tinker’s Tools check (DC equal to 8 + Misfire score).  If your check fails, the weapon is broken and must be repaired out of combat at half the cost of the firearm.</text>
                <text>    SCATTER.  An attack is made against each creature within a 30 ft. cone.  These attacks are simultaneous.  If an affected creature is adjacent to you, they suffer double damage on a hit.  This attack cannot be affected by any of your shot features.</text>
                <text>    EXPLOSIVE.  Upon a hit, everything within 5 ft. of the target must make a Dexterity saving throw (DC equal to 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Dexterity modifier) or suffer 1d8 fire damage.  If the weapon misses, the ammunition fails to detonate, or bounces away harmlessly before doing so.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>

        <autolevel level="3">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Adept Marksman (Gunslinger)</name>
                <text>When you choose this archetype at 3rd level, you learn to perform powerful trick shots to disable or damage your opponents using your firearms.</text>
                <text>    Trick Shots: You learn two trick shots of your choice.  Many maneuvers enhance an attack in some way.  Each use of a trick shot must be declared before the attack roll is made.  You can use only one trick shot per attack.</text>
                <text>    You learn an additional trick shot of your choice at 7th, 10th, 15th, and 18th level.  Each time you learn a trick shot, you can also replace one trick shot you know with a different one.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Grit: You gain a number of grit points equal to your Wisdom modifier (minimum of 1).  You regain 1 expended grit point each time you roll a 20 on the d20 roll with a firearm, or deal a killing blow with a firearm to a creature of significant threat (DM’s discretion).  You gain all expended grit points after a short or long rest.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Saving Throws: Some of your trick shots require your targets to make a saving throw to resist the trick shot’s effect.  The saving throw DC is calculated as follows:
                    Trick Shot save DC = 8 + your proficiency bonus + Dexterity Modifier</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.3 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>

        <autolevel level="7">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Quickdraw (Gunslinger)</name>
                <text>When you reach 7th level, you add your proficiency to your initiative.  You can also stow a firearm, then draw another firearm as a single object interaction on your turn</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.3 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>

        <autolevel level="10">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Rapid Repair (Gunslinger)</name>
                <text>Upon reaching 10th level, you learn how to quickly attempt to fix a jammed gun.  You can spend a grit point to attempt to repair a misfired (but not broken) firearm as a bonus action.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>

        <autolevel level="15">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Lightning Reload (Gunslinger)</name>
                <text>Starting at 15th level, you can reload any firearm as a bonus action.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>

        <autolevel level="18">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Vicious Intent (Gunslinger)</name>
                <text>At 18th level, your firearm attacks score a critical hit on a roll of 19-20, and you regain a grit point on a roll of 19 or 20 on a d20 attack roll with a firearm.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>

        <autolevel level="10">
            <feature optional="YES">
                <name>Hemorrrhaging Critical (Gunslinger)</name>
                <text>Upon reaching 18th level, whenever you score a critical hit on an attack with a firearm, the target additionally suffers half of the damage from the attack at the end of its next turn.</text>
                <text>    </text>
                <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
            </feature>
        </autolevel>
    </class>

    <spell>
        <name>Bullying Shot</name>
        <level>1</level>
        <ritual>NO</ritual>
        <time></time>
        <range></range>
        <components>None</components>
        <duration></duration>
        <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger)</classes>
        <text>You can use the powerful blast and thundering sound of your firearm to shake the resolve of a creature.  When making a Charisma (Intimidation) check, you can expend one grit point to gain advantage on the roll.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
    </spell>
    <spell>
        <name>Dazing Shot</name>
        <level>1</level>
        <ritual>NO</ritual>
        <time></time>
        <range></range>
        <components>None</components>
        <duration></duration>
        <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger)</classes>
        <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to attempt to dizzy your opponent.  On a hit, the creature suffers normal damage and must make a Constiution saving throw or suffer disadvantage on attacks until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
    </spell>
    <spell>
        <name>Deadeye Shot</name>
        <level>1</level>
        <ritual>NO</ritual>
        <time></time>
        <range></range>
        <components>None</components>
        <duration></duration>
        <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger)</classes>
        <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to gain advantage on the attack roll.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
    </spell>
    <spell>
        <name>Disarming Shot</name>
        <level>1</level>
        <ritual>NO</ritual>
        <time></time>
        <range></range>
        <components>None</components>
        <duration></duration>
        <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger)</classes>
        <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to attempt to shoot an object from their hands.  On a hit, the creature suffers normal damage and must succeed on a Strength saving throw or drop 1 held object of your choice and have that object pushed 10 feet away from you.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
    </spell>
    <spell>
        <name>Forceful Shot</name>
        <level>1</level>
        <ritual>NO</ritual>
        <time></time>
        <range></range>
        <components>None</components>
        <duration></duration>
        <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger)</classes>
        <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to attempt to trip them up and force them back.  On a hit, the creature suffers normal damage and must succeed on a Strength saving throw or be pushed 15 feet away from you.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
    </spell>
    <spell>
        <name>Piercing Shot</name>
        <level>1</level>
        <ritual>NO</ritual>
        <time></time>
        <range></range>
        <components>None</components>
        <duration></duration>
        <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger)</classes>
        <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to attempt to fire through multiple opponents.  The initial attack gains a +1 to the firearm’s misfire score.  On a hit, the creature suffers normal damage and you make an attack roll with disadvantage against every creature in a line directly behind the target within your first range increment.  Only the initial attack can misfire.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
    </spell>
    <spell>
        <name>Violent Shot</name>
        <level>1</level>
        <ritual>NO</ritual>
        <time></time>
        <range></range>
        <components>None</components>
        <duration></duration>
        <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger)</classes>
        <text>When you make a fireman attack against a creature, you can expend one or more grit points to enhance the volatility of the attack.  For each grit point expended, the attack gains a +2 to the firearm’s misfire score.  If the attack hits, you can roll one additional weapon damage per grit point spent when determining the damage.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 3</text>
    </spell>
    <spell>
        <name>Winging Shot</name>
        <level>1</level>
        <ritual>NO</ritual>
        <time></time>
        <range></range>
        <components>None</components>
        <duration></duration>
        <classes>Fighter (Gunslinger)</classes>
        <text>When you make a firearm attack against a creature, you can expend one grit point to attempt to topple a moving target.  On a hit, the creature suffers normal damage and must make a Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
        <text />
        <text>Source: Matthew Mercer - Gunslinger Martial Archetype 1.2 p. 2</text>
    </spell>
</compendium>
