<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Rogue</name>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Roguish Archetype: Phantom</name>
        <text>Many rogues walk a fine line between life and death, risking their own lives and taking the lives of others. While adventuring on that line, some rogues discover a mystical connection to death itself. These rogues take knowledge from the dead and become immersed in negative energy, eventually becoming like ghosts. Thieves' guilds value them as highly effective information gatherers and spies.</text>
        <text>Many shadar-kai of the Shadowfell are masters of these macabre techniques, and some are willing to teach this path. In places like Thay in the Forgotten Realms and Karrnath in Eberron, where many necromancers practice their craft, a Phantom can become a wizard's confidant and right hand. In temples of gods of death, the Phantom might work as an agent to track down those who try to cheat death and to recover knowledge that might otherwise be lost to the grave.</text>
        <text>How did you discover this grim power? Did you sleep in a graveyard and awaken to your new abilities? Or did you cultivate them in a temple or thieves' guild dedicated to a deity of death?</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 62</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Phantom: Wails from the Grave</name>
        <text>3rd-level Phantom feature</text>
        <text>As you nudge someone closer to the grave, you can channel the power of death to harm someone else as well. Immediately after you deal your Sneak Attack damage to a creature on your turn, you can target a second creature that you can see within 30 feet of the first creature. Roll half the number of Sneak Attack dice for your level (round up), and the second creature takes necrotic damage equal to the roll's total, as wails of the dead sound around them for a moment.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 62</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Phantom: Whispers of the Dead</name>
        <text>3rd-level Phantom feature</text>
        <text>Echoes of those who have died cling to you. Whenever you finish a short or long rest, you can choose one skill or tool proficiency that you lack and gain it, as a ghostly presence shares its knowledge with you. You lose this proficiency when you use this feature to choose a different proficiency that you lack.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 62</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Roguish Archetype: Soulknife</name>
        <text>Most assassins strike with physical weapons, and many burglars and spies use thieves' tools to infiltrate secure locations. In contrast, a Soulknife strikes and infiltrates with the mind, cutting through barriers both physical and psychic. These rogues discover psionic power within themselves and channel it to do their roguish work. They find easy employment as members of thieves' guilds, though they are often mistrusted by rogues who are leery of anyone using strange mind powers to conduct their business. Most governments would also be happy to employ a Soulknife as a spy.</text>
        <text>Amid the trees of ancient forests on the Material Plane and in the Feywild, some wood elves walk the path of the Soulknife, serving as silent, lethal guardians of their woods. In the endless war among the gith, a githzerai is encouraged to become a Soulknife when stealth is required against the githyanki foe.</text>
        <text>As a Soulknife, your psionic abilities might have haunted you since you were a child, only revealing their full potential as you experienced the stress of adventure. Or you might have sought out a reclusive order of psychic adepts and spent years learning how to manifest your power.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 63</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Soulknife: Psionic Power</name>
        <text>3rd-level Soulknife feature</text>
        <text>You harbor a wellspring of psionic energy within yourself. This energy is represented by your Psionic Energy dice, which are each a d6. You have a number of these dice equal to twice your proficiency bonus, and they fuel various psionic powers you have, which are detailed below.</text>
        <text>Some of your powers expend the Psionic Energy die they use, as specified in a power's description, and you can't use a power if it requires you to use a die when your dice are all expended. You regain all your expended Psionic Energy dice when you finish a long rest. In addition, as a bonus action, you can regain one expended Psionic Energy die, but you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text>When you reach certain levels in this class, the size of your Psionic Energy dice increases: at 5th level (d8), 11th level (d10), and 17th level (d12).</text>
        <text>The powers below use your Psionic Energy dice.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 63</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Soulknife: Psychic Blades</name>
        <text>3rd-level Soulknife feature</text>
        <text>You can manifest your psionic power as shimmering blades of psychic energy. Whenever you take the Attack action, you can manifest a psychic blade from your free hand and make the attack with that blade. This magic blade is a simple melee weapon with the finesse and thrown properties. It has a normal range of 60 feet and no long range, and on a hit, it deals psychic damage equal to 1d6 plus the ability modifier you used for the attack roll. The blade vanishes immediately after it hits or misses its target, and it leaves no mark on its target if it deals damage.</text>
        <text>After you attack with the blade, you can make a melee or ranged weapon attack with a second psychic blade as a bonus action on the same turn, provided your other hand is free to create it. The damage die of this bonus attack is 1d4, instead of 1d6.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 63</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Soulknife: Psi-Bolstered Knack</name>
        <text>When your nonpsionic training fails you, your psionic power can help: if you fail an ability check using a skill or tool with which you have proficiency, you can roll one Psionic Energy die and add the number rolled to the check, potentially turning failure into success. You expend the die only if the roll succeeds.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 63</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Soulknife: Psychic Whispers</name>
        <text>You can establish telepathic communication between yourself and others-perfect for quiet infiltration. As an action, choose one or more creatures you can see, up to a number of creatures equal to your proficiency bonus, and then roll one Psionic Energy die. For a number of hours equal to the number rolled, the chosen creatures can speak telepathically with you, and you can speak telepathically with them. To send or receive a message (no action required), you and the other creature must be within 1 mile of each other. A creature can't use this telepathy if it can't speak any languages, and a creature can end the telepathic connection at any time (no action required). You and the creature don't need to speak a common language to understand each other.</text>
        <text>The first time you use this power after each long rest, you don't expend the Psionic Energy die. All other times you use the power, you expend the die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 63</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature>
          <name>Steady Aim</name>
        <text>3rd-level rogue optional class features</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, you give yourself advantage on your next attack roll on the current turn. You can use this bonus action only if you haven't moved during this turn, and after you use the bonus action, your speed is 0 until the end of the current turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 62</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Phantom: Tokens of the Departed</name>
        <text>9th-level Phantom feature</text>
        <text>When a life ends in your presence, you're able to snatch a token from the departing soul, a sliver of its life essence that takes physical form: as a reaction when a creature you can see dies within 30 feet of you, you can open your free hand and cause a Tiny trinket to appear there, a soul trinket. The DM determines the trinket's form or has you roll on the Trinket table in the Player's Handbook to generate it. You can have a maximum number of soul trinkets equal to your proficiency bonus, and you can't create one while at your maximum.</text>
        <text>You can use soul trinkets in the following ways:</text>
        <text>• While a soul trinket is on your person, you have advantage on death saving throws and Constitution saving throws, for your vitality is enhanced by the life essence within the object.</text>
        <text>• When you deal Sneak Attack damage on your turn, you can destroy one of your soul trinkets that's on your person and then immediately use Wails from the Grave, without expending a use of that feature.</text>
        <text>• As an action, you can destroy one of your soul trinkets, no matter where it's located. When you do so, you can ask the spirit associated with the trinket one question. The spirit appears to you and answers in a language it knew in life. It's under no obligation to be truthful, and it answers as concisely as possible, eager to be free. The spirit knows only what it knew in life, as determined by the DM.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 62</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Soulknife: Soul Blades</name>
        <text>9th-level Soulknife feature</text>
        <text>Your Psychic Blades are now an expression of your psi-suffused soul, giving you these powers that use your Psionic Energy dice:</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 63</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Soulknife: Homing Strikes</name>
        <text>If you make an attack roll with your Psychic Blades and miss the target, you can roll one Psionic Energy die and add the number rolled to the attack roll. If this causes the attack to hit, you expend the Psionic Energy die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 63</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="9">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Soulknife: Psychic Teleportation</name>
        <text>As a bonus action, you manifest one of your Psychic Blades, expend one Psionic Energy die and roll it, and throw the blade at an unoccupied space you can see, up to a number of feet away equal to 10 times the number rolled. You then teleport to that space, and the blade vanishes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 63</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Phantom: Ghost Walk</name>
        <text>13th-level Phantom feature</text>
        <text>You can phase partially into the realm of the dead, becoming like a ghost. As a bonus action, you assume a spectral form. While in this form, you have a flying speed of 10 feet, you can hover, and attack rolls have disadvantage against you. You can also move through creatures and objects as if they were difficult terrain, but you take 1d10 force damage if you end your turn inside a creature or an object.</text>
        <text>You stay in this form for 10 minutes or until you end it as a bonus action. To use this feature again, you must finish a long rest or destroy one of your soul trinkets as part of the bonus action you use to activate Ghost Walk.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 62</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="13">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Soulknife: Psychic Veil</name>
        <text>13th-level Soulknife feature</text>
        <text>You can weave a veil of psychic static to mask yourself. As an action, you can magically become invisible, along with anything you are wearing or carrying, for 1 hour or until you dismiss this effect (no action required). This invisibility ends early immediately after you deal damage to a creature or you force a creature to make a saving throw.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend a Psionic Energy die to use this feature again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 63</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Phantom: Death's Friend</name>
        <text>17th-level Phantom feature</text>
        <text>Your association with death has become so close that you gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• When you use your Wails from the Grave, you can deal the necrotic damage to both the first and the second creature.</text>
        <text>• At the end of a long rest, a soul trinket appears in your hand if you don't have any soul trinkets, as the spirits of the dead are drawn to you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 62</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Soulknife: Rend Mind</name>
        <text>17th-level Soulknife feature</text>
        <text>You can sweep your Psychic Blades directly through a creature's mind. When you use your Psychic Blades to deal Sneak Attack damage to a creature, you can force that target to make a Wisdom saving throw (DC equal to 8 + your proficiency bonus + your Dexterity modifier). If the save fails, the target is stunned for 1 minute. The stunned target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend three Psionic Energy dice to use it again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 63</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
