<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Warlock</name>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Otherworldly Patron: The Fathomless</name>
        <text>You have plunged into a pact with the deeps. An entity of the ocean, the Elemental Plane of Water, or another otherworldly sea now allows you to draw on its thalassic power. Is it merely using you to learn about terrestrial realms, or does it want you to open cosmic floodgates and drown the world?</text>
        <text>Perhaps you were born into a generational cult that venerates the Fathomless and its spawn. Or you might have been shipwrecked and on the brink of drowning when your patron's grasp offered you a chance at life. Whatever the reason for your pact, the sea and its unknown depths call to you.</text>
        <text>Entities of the deep that might empower a warlock include krakens, ancient water elementals, godlike hallucinations dreamed into being by kuo-toa, merfolk demigods, and sea hag covens.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Expanded Spell List</text>
        <text>   1st-level Fathomless feature</text>
        <text>   The Fathomless lets you choose from an expanded list of spells when you learn a warlock spell. The following spells are added to the warlock spell list for you.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Fathomless Expanded Spells</text>
        <text>Spell Level | Spells</text>
        <text>1st | create or destroy water, thunderwave</text>
        <text>2nd | gust of wind, silence</text>
        <text>3rd | lightning bolt, sleet storm</text>
        <text>4th | control water, summon elemental (water only)</text>
        <text>5th | Bigby's hand (appears as a tentacle), cone of cold</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Fathomless: Gift of the Sea</name>
        <text>1st-level Fathomless feature</text>
        <text>You gain a swimming speed of 40 feet, and you can breathe underwater.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Fathomless: Tentacle of the Deeps</name>
        <text>1st-level Fathomless feature</text>
        <text>You can magically summon a spectral tentacle that strikes at your foes. As a bonus action, you create a 10-foot-long tentacle at a point you can see within 60 feet of you. The tentacle lasts for 1 minute or until you use this feature to create another tentacle.</text>
        <text>When you create the tentacle, you can make a melee spell attack against one creature within 10 feet of it. On a hit, the target takes 1d8 cold damage, and its speed is reduced by 10 feet until the start of your next turn. When you reach 10th level in this class, the damage increases to 2d8.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action on your turn, you can move the tentacle up to 30 feet and repeat the attack.</text>
        <text>You can summon the tentacle a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Otherworldly Patron: The Genie</name>
        <text>You have made a pact with one of the rarest kinds of genie, a noble genie. Such entities rule vast fiefs on the Elemental Planes and have great influence over lesser genies and elemental creatures. Noble genies are varied in their motivations, but most are arrogant and wield power that rivals that of lesser deities. They delight in turning the table on mortals, who often bind genies into servitude, and readily enter into pacts that expand their reach.</text>
        <text>You choose your patron's kind or determine it randomly, using the Genie Kind table.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Genie Kind</text>
        <text>d4 | Kind | Element</text>
        <text>1 | Dao | Earth</text>
        <text>2 | Djinni | Air</text>
        <text>3 | Efreeti | Fire</text>
        <text>4 | Marid | Water</text>
        <name>The Genie: Expanded Spell List</name>
        <text>   1st-level Genie feature</text>
        <text>   The Genie lets you choose from an expanded list of spells when you learn a warlock spell. The Genie Expanded Spells table shows the genie spells that are added to the warlock spell list for you, along with the spells associated in the table with your patron's kind: dao, djinni, efreeti, or marid.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Genie Expanded Spells</text>
        <text>Spell Level | Genie Spells | Dao Spells | Djinni Spells | Efreeti Spells | Marid Spells</text>
        <text>1st | detect evil and good | sanctuary | thunderwave | burning hands | fog cloud</text>
        <text>2nd | phantasmal force | spike growth | gust of wind | scorching ray | blur</text>
        <text>3rd | create food and water | meld into stone | wind wall | fireball | sleet storm</text>
        <text>4th | phantasmal killer | stone shape | greater invisibility | fire shield | control water</text>
        <text>5th | creation | wall of stone | seeming | flame strike | cone of cold</text>
        <text>9th | wish | — | — | — | —</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Genie: Genie's Vessel</name>
        <text>1st-level Genie feature</text>
        <text>Your patron gifts you a magical vessel that grants you a measure of the genie's power. The vessel is a Tiny object, and you can use it as a spellcasting focus for your warlock spells. You decide what the object is, or you can determine what it is randomly by rolling on the Genie's Vessel table.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Genie's Vessel</text>
        <text>d6 | Vessel</text>
        <text>1 | Oil lamp</text>
        <text>2 | Urn</text>
        <text>3 | Ring with a compartment</text>
        <text>4 | Stoppered bottle</text>
        <text>5 | Hollow statuette</text>
        <text>6 | Ornate lantern</text>
        <text>While you are touching the vessel, you can use it in the following ways:</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Genie: Bottled Respite</name>
        <text>As an action, you can magically vanish and enter your vessel, which remains in the space you left. The interior of the vessel is an extradimensional space in the shape of a 20-foot-radius cylinder, 20 feet high, and resembles your vessel. The interior is appointed with cushions and low tables and is a comfortable temperature. While inside, you can hear the area around your vessel as if you were in its space. You can remain inside the vessel up to a number of hours equal to twice your proficiency bonus. You exit the vessel early if you use a bonus action to leave, if you die, or if the vessel is destroyed. When you exit the vessel, you appear in the unoccupied space closest to it. Any objects left in the vessel remain there until carried out, and if the vessel is destroyed, every object stored there harmlessly appears in the unoccupied spaces closest to the vessel's former space. Once you enter the vessel, you can't enter again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Genie: Genie's Wrath</name>
        <text>Once during each of your turns when you hit with an attack roll, you can deal extra damage to the target equal to your proficiency bonus. The type of this damage is determined by your patron: bludgeoning (dao), thunder (djinni), fire (efreeti), or cold (marid).</text>
        <text>The vessel's AC equals your spell save DC. Its hit points equal your warlock level plus your proficiency bonus, and it is immune to poison and psychic damage.</text>
        <text>If the vessel is destroyed or you lose it, you can perform a 1-hour ceremony to receive a replacement from your patron. This ceremony can be performed during a short or long rest, and the previous vessel is destroyed if it still exists. The vessel vanishes in a flare of elemental power when you die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Pact Boon: Pact of the Talisman</name>
        <text>Your patron gives you an amulet, a talisman that can aid the wearer when the need is great. When the wearer fails an ability check, they can add a d4 to the roll, potentially turning the roll into a success. This benefit can be used a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and all expended uses are restored when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>If you lose the talisman, you can perform a 1-hour ceremony to receive a replacement from your patron. This ceremony can be performed during a short or long rest, and it destroys the previous amulet. The talisman turns to ash when you die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 105</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="4">
        <feature>
          <name>Eldritch Versatility</name>
        <text>4th-level warlock optional class features</text>
        <text>Whenever you reach a level in this class that grants the Ability Score Improvement feature, you can do one of the following, representing a change of focus in your occult studies:</text>
        <text>• Replace one cantrip you learned from this class's Pact Magic feature with another cantrip from the warlock spell list.</text>
        <text>• Replace the option you chose for the Pact Boon feature with one of that feature's other options.</text>
        <text>• If you're 12th level or higher, replace one spell from your Mystic Arcanum feature with another warlock spell of the same level. If this change makes you ineligible for any of your Eldritch Invocations, you must also replace them now, choosing invocations for which you qualify.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 70</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Fathomless: Guardian Coil</name>
        <text>6th-level Fathomless feature</text>
        <text>Your Tentacle of the Deeps can defend you and others, interposing itself between them and harm. When you or a creature you can see takes damage while within 10 feet of the tentacle, you can use your reaction to choose one of those creatures and reduce the damage to that creature by 1d8. When you reach 10th level in this class, the damage reduced by the tentacle increases to 2d8.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Fathomless: Oceanic Soul</name>
        <text>6th-level Fathomless feature</text>
        <text>You are now even more at home in the depths. You gain resistance to cold damage. In addition, when you are fully submerged, any creature that is also fully submerged can understand your speech, and you can understand theirs.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Genie: Elemental Gift</name>
        <text>6th-level Genie feature</text>
        <text>You begin to take on characteristics of your patron's kind. You now have resistance to a damage type determined by your patron's kind: bludgeoning (dao), thunder (djinni), fire (efreeti), or cold (marid).</text>
        <text>In addition, as a bonus action, you can give yourself a flying speed of 30 feet that lasts for 10 minutes, during which you can hover. You can use this bonus action a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Fathomless: Grasping Tentacles</name>
        <text>10th-level Fathomless feature</text>
        <text>You learn the spell Evard's black tentacles. It counts as a warlock spell for you, but it doesn't count against the number of spells you know. You can also cast it once without a spell slot, and you regain the ability to do so when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>Whenever you cast this spell, your patron's magic bolsters you, granting you a number of temporary hit points equal to your warlock level. Moreover, damage can't break your concentration on this spell.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Genie: Sanctuary Vessel</name>
        <text>10th-level Genie feature</text>
        <text>When you enter your Genie's Vessel via the Bottled Respite feature, you can now choose up to five willing creatures that you can see within 30 feet of you, and the chosen creatures are drawn into the vessel with you.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, you can eject any number of creatures from the vessel, and everyone is ejected if you leave or die or if the vessel is destroyed.</text>
        <text>In addition, anyone (including you) who remains within the vessel for at least 10 minutes gains the benefit of finishing a short rest, and anyone can add your proficiency bonus to the number of hit points they regain if they spend any Hit Dice as part of a short rest there.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Fathomless: Fathomless Plunge</name>
        <text>14th-level Fathomless feature</text>
        <text>You can magically open temporary conduits to watery destinations. As an action, you can teleport yourself and up to five other willing creatures that you can see within 30 feet of you. Amid a whirl of tentacles, you all vanish and then reappear up to 1 mile away in a body of water you've seen (pond size or larger) or within 30 feet of it, each of you appearing in an unoccupied space within 30 feet of the others.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 72</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>The Genie: Limited Wish</name>
        <text>14th-level Genie feature</text>
        <text>You entreat your patron to grant you a small wish. As an action, you can speak your desire to your Genie's Vessel, requesting the effect of one spell that is 6th level or lower and has a casting time of 1 action. The spell can be from any class's spell list, and you don't need to meet the requirements in that spell, including costly components; the spell simply takes effect as part of this action.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish 1d4 long rests.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 73</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
