<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Bard</name>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Bard College: College of Glamour</name>
        <text>The College of Glamour is the home of bards who mastered their craft in the vibrant realm of the Feywild or under the tutelage of someone who dwelled there. Tutored by satyrs, eladrin, and other fey, these bards learn to use their magic to delight and captivate others.</text>
        <text>The bards of this college are regarded with a mixture of awe and fear. Their performances are the stuff of legend. These bards are so eloquent that a speech or song that one of them performs can cause captors to release the bard unharmed and can lull a furious dragon into complacency. The same magic that allows them to quell beasts can also bend minds. Villainous bards of this college can leech off a community for weeks, misusing their magic to turn their hosts into thralls. Heroic bards of this college instead use this power to gladden the downtrodden and undermine oppressors.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 14</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Glamour: Enthralling Performance</name>
        <text>Starting at 3rd level, you can charge your performance with seductive, fey magic.</text>
        <text>If you perform for at least 1 minute, you can attempt to inspire wonder in your audience by singing, reciting a poem, or dancing. At the end of the performance, choose a number of humanoids within 60 feet of you who watched and listened to all of it, up to a number equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of one). Each target must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC or be charmed by you. While charmed in this way, the target idolizes you, it speaks glowingly of you to anyone who talks to it, and it hinders anyone who opposes you, although it avoids violence unless it was already inclined to fight on your behalf. This effect ends on a target after 1 hour, if it takes any damage, if you attack it, or if it witnesses you attacking or damaging any of its allies.</text>
        <text>If a target succeeds on its saving throw, the target has no hint that you tried to charm it.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 14</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Glamour: Mantle of Inspiration</name>
        <text>When you join the College of Glamour at 3rd level, you gain the ability to weave a song of fey magic that imbues your allies with vigor and speed.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, you can expend one use of your Bardic Inspiration to grant yourself a wondrous appearance. When you do so, choose a number of creatures you can see and that can see you within 60 feet of you, up to a number equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of one). Each of them gains 5 temporary hit points. When a creature gains these temporary hit points, it can immediately use its reaction to move up to its speed, without provoking opportunity attacks.</text>
        <text>The number of temporary hit points increases when you reach certain levels in this class, increasing to 8 at 5th level, 11 at 10th level, and 14 at 15th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 14</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Bard College: College of Swords</name>
        <text>Bards of the College of Swords are called blades, and they entertain through daring feats of weapon prowess. Blades perform stunts such as sword swallowing, knife throwing and juggling, and mock combats. Though they use their weapons to entertain, they are also highly trained and skilled warriors in their own right.</text>
        <text>Their talent with weapons inspires many blades to lead double lives. One blade might use a circus troupe as cover for nefarious deeds such as assassination, robbery, and blackmail. Other blades strike at the wicked, bringing justice to bear against the cruel and powerful. Most troupes are happy to accept a blade's talent for the excitement it adds to a performance, but few entertainers fully trust a blade in their ranks.</text>
        <text>Blades who abandon their lives as entertainers have often run into trouble that makes maintaining their secret activities impossible. A blade caught stealing or engaging in vigilante justice is too great a liability for most troupes. With their weapon skills and magic, these blades either take up work as enforcers for thieves' guilds or strike out on their own as adventurers.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 15</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Swords: Blade Flourish</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn to perform impressive displays of martial prowess and speed.</text>
        <text>Whenever you take the Attack action on your turn, your walking speed increases by 10 feet until the end of the turn, and if a weapon attack that you make as part of this action hits a creature, you can use one of the following Blade Flourish options of your choice. You can use only one Blade Flourish option per turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 15</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Swords: Bonus Proficiencies</name>
        <text>When you join the College of Swords at 3rd level, you gain proficiency with medium armor and the scimitar.</text>
        <text>If you're proficient with a simple or martial melee weapon, you can use it as a spellcasting focus for your bard spells.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 15</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Swords: Fighting Style</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you adopt a style of fighting as your specialty. Choose one of the following options. You can't take a Fighting Style option more than once, even if something in the game lets you choose again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 15</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Swords: Defensive Flourish</name>
        <text>You can expend one use of your Bardic Inspiration to cause the weapon to deal extra damage to the target you hit. The damage equals the number you roll on the Bardic Inspiration die. You also add the number rolled to your AC until the start of your next turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 15</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Swords: Mobile Flourish</name>
        <text>You can expend one use of your Bardic Inspiration to cause the weapon to deal extra damage to the target you hit. The damage equals the number you roll on the Bardic Inspiration die. You can also push the target up to 5 feet away from you, plus a number of feet equal to the number you roll on that die. You can then immediately use your reaction to move up to your walking speed to an unoccupied space within 5 feet of the target.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 15</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Swords: Slashing Flourish</name>
        <text>You can expend one use of your Bardic Inspiration to cause the weapon to deal extra damage to the target you hit and to any other creature of your choice that you can see within 5 feet of you. The damage equals the number you roll on the Bardic Inspiration die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 15</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Bard College: College of Whispers</name>
        <text>Most folk are happy to welcome a bard into their midst. Bards of the College of Whispers use this to their advantage. They appear to be like other bards, sharing news, singing songs, and telling tales to the audiences they gather. In truth, the College of Whispers teaches its students that they are wolves among sheep. These bards use their knowledge and magic to uncover secrets and turn them against others through extortion and threats.</text>
        <text>Many other bards hate the College of Whispers, viewing it as a parasite that uses a bard's reputation to acquire wealth and power. For this reason, members of this college rarely reveal their true nature. They typically claim to follow some other college, or they keep their actual calling secret in order to infiltrate and exploit royal courts and other settings of power.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 16</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Whispers: Psychic Blades</name>
        <text>When you join the College of Whispers at 3rd level, you gain the ability to make your weapon attacks magically toxic to a creature's mind.</text>
        <text>When you hit a creature with a weapon attack, you can expend one use of your Bardic Inspiration to deal an extra 2d6 psychic damage to that target. You can do so only once per round on your turn.</text>
        <text>The psychic damage increases when you reach certain levels in this class, increasing to 3d6 at 5th level, 5d6 at 10th level, and 8d6 at 15th level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 16</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Whispers: Words of Terror</name>
        <text>At 3rd level, you learn to infuse innocent-seeming words with an insidious magic that can inspire terror.</text>
        <text>If you speak to a humanoid alone for at least 1 minute, you can attempt to seed paranoia in its mind. At the end of the conversation, the target must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC or be frightened of you or another creature of your choice. The target is frightened in this way for 1 hour, until it is attacked or damaged, or until it witnesses its allies being attacked or damaged.</text>
        <text>If the target succeeds on its saving throw, the target has no hint that you tried to frighten it.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 16</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Glamour: Mantle of Majesty</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to cloak yourself in a fey magic that makes others want to serve you. As a bonus action, you cast command, without expending a spell slot, and you take on an appearance of unearthly beauty for 1 minute or until your concentration ends (as if you were concentrating on a spell). During this time, you can cast command as a bonus action on each of your turns, without expending a spell slot.</text>
        <text>Any creature charmed by you automatically fails its saving throw against the command you cast with this feature.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 14</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Swords: Extra Attack</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you can attack twice, instead of once, whenever you take the Attack action on your turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 15</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Whispers: Mantle of Whispers</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to adopt a humanoid's persona. When a humanoid dies within 30 feet of you, you can magically capture its shadow using your reaction. You retain this shadow until you use it or you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>You can use the shadow as an action. When you do so, it vanishes, magically transforming into a disguise that appears on you. You now look like the dead person, but healthy and alive. This disguise lasts for 1 hour or until you end it as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>While you're in the disguise, you gain access to all information that the humanoid would freely share with a casual acquaintance. Such information includes general details on its background and personal life, but doesn't include secrets. The information is enough that you can pass yourself off as the person by drawing on its memories.</text>
        <text>Another creature can see through this disguise by succeeding on a Wisdom (Insight) check contested by your Charisma (Deception) check. You gain a +5 bonus to your check.</text>
        <text>Once you capture a shadow with this feature, you can't capture another one with it until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 16</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Glamour: Unbreakable Majesty</name>
        <text>At 14th level, your appearance permanently gains an otherworldly aspect that makes you look more lovely and fierce.</text>
        <text>In addition, as a bonus action, you can assume a magically majestic presence for 1 minute or until you are incapacitated. For the duration, whenever any creature tries to attack you for the first time on a turn, the attacker must make a Charisma saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, it can't attack you on this turn, and it must choose a new target for its attack or the attack is wasted. On a successful save, it can attack you on this turn, but it has disadvantage on any saving throw it makes against your spells on your next turn.</text>
        <text>Once you assume this majestic presence, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 14</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Swords: Master's Flourish</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, whenever you use a Blade Flourish option, you can roll a d6 and use it instead of expending a Bardic Inspiration die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 15</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>College of Whispers: Shadow Lore</name>
        <text>At 14th level, you gain the ability to weave dark magic into your words and tap into a creature's deepest fears.</text>
        <text>As an action, you magically whisper a phrase that only one creature of your choice within 30 feet of you can hear. The target must make a Wisdom saving throw against your spell save DC. It automatically succeeds if it doesn't share a language with you or if it can't hear you. On a successful saving throw, your whisper sounds like unintelligible mumbling and has no effect.</text>
        <text>On a failed saving throw, the target is charmed by you for the next 8 hours or until you or your allies attack it, damage it, or force it to make a saving throw. It interprets the whispers as a description of its most mortifying secret. You gain no knowledge of this secret, but the target is convinced you know it.</text>
        <text>The charmed creature obeys your commands for fear that you will reveal its secret. It won't risk its life for you or fight for you, unless it was already inclined to do so. It grants you favors and gifts it would offer to a close friend.</text>
        <text>When the effect ends, the creature has no understanding of why it held you in such fear.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 16</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
