<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Paladin</name>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sacred Oath: Oath of Conquest</name>
        <text>The Oath of Conquest calls to paladins who seek glory in battle and the subjugation of their enemies. It isn't enough for these paladins to establish order. They must crush the forces of chaos. Sometimes called knight tyrants or iron mongers, those who swear this oath gather into grim orders that serve gods or philosophies of war and well-ordered might.</text>
        <text>Some of these paladins go so far as to consort with the powers of the Nine Hells, valuing the rule of law over the balm of mercy. The archdevil Bel, warlord of Avernus, counts many of these paladins—called hell knights—as his most ardent supporters. Hell knights cover their armor with trophies taken from fallen enemies, a grim warning to any who dare oppose them and the decrees of their lords. These knights are often most fiercely resisted by other paladins of this oath, who believe that the hell knights have wandered too far into darkness.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 37</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Conquest: Channel Divinity: Conquering Presence</name>
        <text>You can use your Channel Divinity to exude a terrifying presence. As an action, you force each creature of your choice that you can see within 30 feet of you to make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, a creature becomes frightened of you for 1 minute. The frightened creature can repeat this saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 37</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Conquest: Channel Divinity: Guided Strike</name>
        <text>You can use your Channel Divinity to strike with supernatural accuracy. When you make an attack roll, you can use your Channel Divinity to gain a +10 bonus to the roll. You make this choice after you see the roll, but before the DM says whether the attack hits or misses.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 37</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Conquest: Oath Spells</name>
        <text>You gain oath spells at the paladin levels listed.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Oath of Conquest Spells</text>
        <text>Paladin Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | armor of Agathys, command</text>
        <text>5th | hold person, spiritual weapon</text>
        <text>9th | bestow curse, fear</text>
        <text>13th | dominate beast, stoneskin</text>
        <text>17th | cloudkill, dominate person</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 37</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Conquest: Tenets of Conquest</name>
        <text>A paladin who takes this oath has the tenets of conquest seared on the upper arm.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Douse the Flame of Hope</text>
        <text>   It is not enough to merely defeat an enemy in battle. Your victory must be so overwhelming that your enemies' will to fight is shattered forever. A blade can end a life. Fear can end an empire.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Rule with an Iron Fist</text>
        <text>   Once you have conquered, tolerate no dissent. Your word is law. Those who obey it shall be favored. Those who defy it shall be punished as an example to all who might follow.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Strength Above All</text>
        <text>   You shall rule until a stronger one arises. Then you must grow mightier and meet the challenge, or fall to your own ruin.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 37</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Sacred Oath: Oath of Redemption</name>
        <text>The Oath of Redemption sets a paladin on a difficult path, one that requires a holy warrior to use violence only as a last resort. Paladins who dedicate themselves to this oath believe that any person can be redeemed and that the path of benevolence and justice is one that anyone can walk. These paladins face evil creatures in the hope of turning their foes to the light, and they slay their enemies only when such a deed will clearly save other lives. Paladins who follow this path are known as redeemers.</text>
        <text>While redeemers are idealists, they are no fools. Redeemers know that undead, demons, devils, and other supernatural threats can be inherently evil. Against such foes, paladins who swear this oath bring the full wrath of their weapons and spells to bear. Yet the redeemers still pray that, one day, even creatures of wickedness will invite their own redemption.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 38</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Redemption: Channel Divinity: Emissary of Peace</name>
        <text>You can use your Channel Divinity to augment your presence with divine power. As a bonus action, you grant yourself a +5 bonus to Charisma (Persuasion) checks for the next 10 minutes.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 38</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Redemption: Channel Divinity: Rebuke the Violent</name>
        <text>You can use your Channel Divinity to rebuke those who use violence. Immediately after an attacker within 30 feet of you deals damage with an attack against a creature other than you, you can use your reaction to force the attacker to make a Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the attacker takes radiant damage equal to the damage it just dealt. On a successful save, it takes half as much damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 38</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Redemption: Oath Spells</name>
        <text>You gain oath spells at the paladin levels listed.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Oath of Redemption Spells</text>
        <text>Paladin Level | Spells</text>
        <text>3rd | sanctuary, sleep</text>
        <text>5th | calm emotions, hold person</text>
        <text>9th | counterspell, hypnotic pattern</text>
        <text>13th | Otiluke's resilient sphere, stoneskin</text>
        <text>17th | hold monster, wall of force</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 38</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Redemption: Tenets of Redemption</name>
        <text>The tenets of the Oath of Redemption hold a paladin to a high standard of peace and justice.</text>
        <name>Oath of Redemption: Peace</name>
        <text>   Violence is a weapon of last resort. Diplomacy and understanding are the paths to long-lasting peace.</text>
        <name>Oath of Redemption: Innocence</name>
        <text>   All people begin life in an innocent state, and it is their environment or the influence of dark forces that drives them to evil. By setting the proper example, and working to heal the wounds of a deeply flawed world, you can set anyone on a righteous path.</text>
        <name>Oath of Redemption: Patience</name>
        <text>   Change takes time. Those who have walked the path of the wicked must be given reminders to keep them honest and true. Once you have planted the seed of righteousness in a creature, you must work day after day to allow that seed to survive and flourish.</text>
        <name>Oath of Redemption: Wisdom</name>
        <text>   Your heart and mind must stay clear, for eventually you will be forced to admit defeat. While every creature can be redeemed, some are so far along the path of evil that you have no choice but to end their lives for the greater good. Any such action must be carefully weighed and the consequences fully understood, but once you have made the decision, follow through with it knowing your path is just.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 38</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Conquest: Aura of Conquest</name>
        <text>Starting at 7th level, you constantly emanate a menacing aura while you're not incapacitated. The aura extends 10 feet from you in every direction, but not through total cover.</text>
        <text>If a creature is frightened of you, its speed is reduced to 0 while in the aura, and that creature takes psychic damage equal to half your paladin level if it starts its turn there.</text>
        <text>At 18th level, the range of this aura increases to 30 feet.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 37</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="7">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Redemption: Aura of the Guardian</name>
        <text>Starting at 7th level, you can shield others from harm at the cost of your own health. When a creature within 10 feet of you takes damage, you can use your reaction to magically take that damage, instead of that creature taking it. This feature doesn't transfer any other effects that might accompany the damage, and this damage can't be reduced in any way.</text>
        <text>At 18th level, the range of this aura increases to 30 feet.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 38</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Conquest: Scornful Rebuke</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, those who dare to strike you are psychically punished for their audacity. Whenever a creature hits you with an attack, that creature takes psychic damage equal to your Charisma modifier (minimum of 1) if you're not incapacitated.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 37</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="15">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Redemption: Protective Spirit</name>
        <text>Starting at 15th level, a holy presence mends your wounds in battle. You regain hit points equal to 1d6 + half your paladin level if you end your turn in combat with fewer than half of your hit points remaining and you aren't incapacitated.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 38</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Conquest: Invincible Conqueror</name>
        <text>At 20th level, you gain the ability to harness extraordinary martial prowess. As an action, you can magically become an avatar of conquest, gaining the following benefits for 1 minute:</text>
        <text>• You have resistance to all damage.</text>
        <text>• When you take the Attack action on your turn, you can make one additional attack as part of that action.</text>
        <text>• Your melee weapon attacks score a critical hit on a roll of 19 or 20 on the d20.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't use it again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 37</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="20">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Oath of Redemption: Emissary of Redemption</name>
        <text>At 20th level, you become an avatar of peace, which gives you two benefits:</text>
        <text>• You have resistance to all damage dealt by other creatures (their attacks, spells, and other effects).</text>
        <text>• Whenever a creature hits you with an attack, it takes radiant damage equal to half the damage you take from the attack.</text>
        <text>If you attack a creature, cast a spell on it, or deal damage to it by any means but this feature, neither benefit works against that creature until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Xanathar's Guide to Everything p. 38</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
