<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <monster>
      <name>Amphisbaena (monstrosity)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>14</ac>
    <hp>11 (2d8+2)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 10 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Two Heads</name>
      <text>The Amphisbaena (monstrosity) has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks and on saving throws against being blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, stunned, and knocked unconscious.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The Amphisbaena (monstrosity) makes two bite attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d4 + 4) piercing damage, and the target must make a DC 11 Constitution saving throw, taking 3 (1d6) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+6|1d4+4</attack>
      <attack>Bite||1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 230, Mythic Odysseys of Theros</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Barnacle Bess</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>13 (3d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>9</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>Bess can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) bludgeoning damage, and the target is grappled (escape DC 11). Bess has two claws, each of which can grapple only one target.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 220</description>
    <environment>coastal</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Bullywug Croaker</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (bullywug)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (hide armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>33 (6d8+6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>7</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Con +3</save>
    <skill>Perception +4, Stealth +3</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Bullywug</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The croaker can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Speak with Frogs and Toads</name>
      <text>The croaker can communicate simple concepts to frogs and toads when it speaks in Bullywug.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Standing Leap</name>
      <text>The croaker's long jump is up to 20 feet and its high jump is up to 10 feet, with or without a running start.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Swamp Camouflage</name>
      <text>The croaker has advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks made to hide in swampy terrain.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage, or 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Spear|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Glaaar-pat (3/Day)</name>
      <text>The croaker sings a song of marshy doom. Each chosen creature within 30 feet of the croaker that can hear the song must make a DC 12 Wisdom saving throw, taking 9 (2d8) psychic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. A creature that fails this saving throw also has disadvantage on Constitution saving throws until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Glaaar-pat (3/Day)||2d8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Rooooo-glog (1/Day)</name>
      <text>The croaker sings an ode to an elder froghemoth. Each bullywug within 30 feet of the croaker that can hear the song gains 10 temporary hit points.</text>
      </action>
    <description>Some bullywugs are born with the ability to weave magic into their songs. These rare specimens are raised in protected enclaves where they are taught to use their magic to both heal and harm. As demonstrated in Danger at Dunwater, they are among the most pompous of bullywugs.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 232</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Bullywug Royal</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (bullywug)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (hide armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>52 (8d8+16)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Str +5, Dex +3</save>
    <skill>Athletics +5, Intimidation +4, Stealth +3</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Bullywug</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The royal can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Brute</name>
      <text>A melee weapon deals one extra die of its damage when the royal hits with it (included in the attack).</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Frog Rider</name>
      <text>The royal has advantage on melee attacks made while riding a frog mount.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Speak with Frogs and Toads</name>
      <text>The royal can communicate simple concepts to frogs and toads when it speaks in Bullywug.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Standing Leap</name>
      <text>The royal's long jump is up to 20 feet and its high jump is up to 10 feet, with or without a running start.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Swamp Camouflage</name>
      <text>The royal has advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks made to hide in swampy terrain.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The royal makes two attacks: one with its royal spear and one with its bite.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Royal Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 10 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 10 (2d6 + 3) piercing damage, or 12 (2d8 + 3) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack. If the target is a Medium or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 13 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Royal Spear|+5|2d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Croaked Decree (1/Day)</name>
      <text>The royal makes a loud pronouncement. Each bullywug within 60 feet of the royal that can hear the pronouncement has advantage on its next attack roll.</text>
      </action>
    <description>The largest and most intelligent bullywugs invariably end up leading their kind. These sneering specimens dress in robes made from leather, rough cloth, and bits of marsh plants. As seen in Danger at Dunwater, a bullywug royal is often accompanied by and mounted astride a giant toad.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 232</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Captain Xendros</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (tiefling)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (chain shirt)</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Medicine +7, Persuasion +3, Religion +5</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>any two languages, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist>fire</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Divine Eminence</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Xendros can expend a spell slot to cause its melee weapon attacks to magically deal an extra 10 (3d6) radiant damage to a target on a hit. This benefit lasts until the end of the turn. If Xendros expends a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the extra damage increases by 1d6 for each level above 1st.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Mace</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Mace|+2|1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Xendros is a 5th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). Xendros has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): cure wounds, guiding bolt, sanctuary</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): lesser restoration, spiritual weapon</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (2 slots): dispel magic, spirit guardians</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 2</slots>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt;'s innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 11). &lt;$title_short_name$&gt; can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>1/day each: darkness, hellish rebuke</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy, cure wounds, guiding bolt, sanctuary, lesser restoration, spiritual weapon, dispel magic, spirit guardians, thaumaturgy, darkness, hellish rebuke</spells>
    <description>
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 14</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Drowned Ascetic</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>75 (10d8+30)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>9</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save>Dex +5</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages it knew in life but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Bottom Treader</name>
      <text>The drowned ascetic cannot swim, and it sinks to the bottom of any body of water. It takes no penalties to its movement or attacks underwater. It is immune to the effects of being underwater at a depth greater than 100 feet.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Bound Together</name>
      <text>The drowned ascetic shares its mind with every other drowned one within 1 mile of it, and can communicate its thoughts and observations to them instantaneously and without limitation.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Undead Fortitude</name>
      <text>If damage reduces the drowned ascetic to 0 hit points, it must make a Constitution saving throw with a DC of 5 + the damage taken, unless the damage is radiant or from a critical hit. On a success, the drowned ascetic drops to 1 hit point instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The drowned ascetic makes three unarmed strikes.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Unarmed Strike</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) bludgeoning damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or contract bluerot (see the "Bluerot" in notes).</text>
      <attack>Unarmed Strike|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Dexterous Target</name>
      <text>The drowned ascetic adds 3 to its AC against one ranged attack that would hit it. To do so, the drowned ascetic must see the attacker.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>Dressed in tattered robes, its fists wrapped in long rib bons of rotting cloth, the drowned ascetic moves with alarming speed for an undead creature. This martial artist, rising from the ocean in Tammeraut's Fate, retains its fighting reflexes despite its rotting flesh.
Bluerot. This disease targets humanoids. While afflicted with bluerot, a victim grows grotesque blue boils on their face and back. This disease is carried by undead (including the drowned ones in Tammeraut's Fate), and victims most often acquire it through wounds caused by infected creatures. The disease's boils manifest in 1d4 hours, causing the victim's Constitution and Charisma scores to decrease by 1d4 each, to a minimum of 3. This is quickly followed by a fever and tingling in the extremities. An infected creature is vulnerable to radiant damage and gains the ability to breathe underwater.
At the end of each long rest, an infected creature makes a DC 12 Constitution saving throw. On a success, the victim regains 1 point of Constitution and 1 point of Charisma lost to the disease. If the infected creature regains all the points lost to the disease, it is cured. Other effects that raise the victim's ability scores do not cure the disease. On a failed saving throw, the victim takes 18 (4d8) necrotic damage as the boils burst and spread. A creature reduced to 0 hit points by this damage cannot regain hit points until the disease is cured, though it can be stabilized as normal.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 233, Locathah Rising</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Drowned Assassin</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>67 (9d8+27)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>9</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Dex +5, Con +5</save>
    <skill>Intimidation +5, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages it knew in life but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Bottom Treader</name>
      <text>The drowned assassin cannot swim, and it sinks to the bottom of any body of water. It takes no penalties to its movement or attacks underwater. It is immune to the effects of being underwater at a depth greater than 100 feet.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Bound Together</name>
      <text>The drowned assassin shares its mind with every other drowned one within 1 mile of it, and can communicate its thoughts and observations to them instantaneously and without limitation.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Undead Fortitude</name>
      <text>If damage reduces the drowned assassin to 0 hit points, it must make a Constitution saving throw with a DC of 5 + the damage taken, unless the damage is radiant or from a critical hit. On a success, the drowned assassin drops to 1 hit point instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The drowned assassin makes two hand crossbow attacks or two dagger attacks. It can then take the Dash, Disengage, or Hide action.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hand Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage plus 3 (1d6) poison damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or contract bluerot (see the "Bluerot" in notes).</text>
      <attack>Hand Crossbow|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage plus 9 (2d8) poison damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or contract bluerot (see the "Bluerot" in notes).</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Reveal (1/Day)</name>
      <text>The drowned assassin removes its mask, revealing its rotting face. Each creature of the assassin's choice within 30 feet of it that can see the assassin must succeed on a DC 13 Wisdom saving throw or be frightened until the end of its next turn.</text>
      </action>
    <description>The drowned assassin stalks and kills in a grim pantomime of its former occupation. Sneaking from shadow to shadow, and appearing in the undead assault of Tammeraut's Fate, it aims its barnacle-encrusted hand crossbow with deadly precision. Hidden behind a simple driftwood mask, this creature's face causes terror in mortal hearts when exposed.
Bluerot. This disease targets humanoids. While afflicted with bluerot, a victim grows grotesque blue boils on their face and back. This disease is carried by undead (including the drowned ones in Tammeraut's Fate), and victims most often acquire it through wounds caused by infected creatures. The disease's boils manifest in 1d4 hours, causing the victim's Constitution and Charisma scores to decrease by 1d4 each, to a minimum of 3. This is quickly followed by a fever and tingling in the extremities. An infected creature is vulnerable to radiant damage and gains the ability to breathe underwater.
At the end of each long rest, an infected creature makes a DC 12 Constitution saving throw. On a success, the victim regains 1 point of Constitution and 1 point of Charisma lost to the disease. If the infected creature regains all the points lost to the disease, it is cured. Other effects that raise the victim's ability scores do not cure the disease. On a failed saving throw, the victim takes 18 (4d8) necrotic damage as the boils burst and spread. A creature reduced to 0 hit points by this damage cannot regain hit points until the disease is cured, though it can be stabilized as normal.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 234, Locathah Rising</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Drowned Blade</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>10 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>45 (6d8+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>9</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages it knew in life but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Bottom Treader</name>
      <text>The drowned blade cannot swim, and it sinks to the bottom of any body of water. It takes no penalties to its movement or attacks underwater. It is immune to the effects of being underwater at a depth greater than 100 feet.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Bound Together</name>
      <text>The drowned blade shares its mind with every other drowned one within 1 mile of it, and can communicate its thoughts and observations to them instantaneously and without limitation.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Undead Fortitude</name>
      <text>If damage reduces the drowned blade to 0 hit points, it must make a Constitution saving throw with a DC of 5 + the damage taken, unless the damage is radiant or from a critical hit. On a success, the drowned blade drops to 1 hit point instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The drowned blade makes two rusted longsword attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Rusted Longsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) slashing damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or contract bluerot (see the "Bluerot" in notes).</text>
      <attack>Rusted Longsword|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Assaulting the hermitage in Tammeraut's Fate, this barnacle-encrusted undead warrior fights with surprising cunning. Starfish cling to its wispy beard, and its evil rage is visible in its bloated gray eyes.
Bluerot. This disease targets humanoids. While afflicted with bluerot, a victim grows grotesque blue boils on their face and back. This disease is carried by undead (including the drowned ones in Tammeraut's Fate), and victims most often acquire it through wounds caused by infected creatures. The disease's boils manifest in 1d4 hours, causing the victim's Constitution and Charisma scores to decrease by 1d4 each, to a minimum of 3. This is quickly followed by a fever and tingling in the extremities. An infected creature is vulnerable to radiant damage and gains the ability to breathe underwater.
At the end of each long rest, an infected creature makes a DC 12 Constitution saving throw. On a success, the victim regains 1 point of Constitution and 1 point of Charisma lost to the disease. If the infected creature regains all the points lost to the disease, it is cured. Other effects that raise the victim's ability scores do not cure the disease. On a failed saving throw, the victim takes 18 (4d8) necrotic damage as the boils burst and spread. A creature reduced to 0 hit points by this damage cannot regain hit points until the disease is cured, though it can be stabilized as normal.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 235, Locathah Rising</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Drowned Master</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>157 (21d8+63)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>17</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Con +7, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Perception +10</skill>
    <passive>20</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages it knew in life but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Bound Together</name>
      <text>The drowned master shares its mind with every other drowned one within 1 mile of it, and can communicate its thoughts and observations to them instantaneously and without limitation.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Cold Aura</name>
      <text>At the start of each of the drowned master's turns, each creature within 5 feet of it takes 5 (1d10) cold damage. A creature that touches the drowned master or hits it with a melee attack while within 5 feet of it takes 5 (1d10) cold damage.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Undead Fortitude</name>
      <text>If damage reduces the drowned master to 0 hit points, it must make a Constitution saving throw with a DC of 5 + the damage taken, unless the damage is radiant or from a critical hit. On a success, the drowned master drops to 1 hit point instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The drowned master makes two attacks: one with its greatsword and one with its Life-Draining Tentacle.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Greatsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (2d6 + 3) slashing damage plus 14 (4d6) cold damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or contract bluerot (see the "Bluerot" in notes).</text>
      <attack>Greatsword|+7|2d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Life-Draining Tentacle</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. 10 (2d6 + 3) necrotic damage. The target must succeed on a DC 15 Constitution saving throw or have its hit point maximum reduced by an amount equal to the damage taken. The target dies if this effect reduces its hit point maximum to 0. This reduction lasts until the target finishes a long rest. On a failed save, the target also contracts bluerot (see the "Bluerot" in notes).</text>
      <attack>Life-Draining Tentacle|+7|2d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Necrotic Ink (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The drowned master discharges foul ink in front of itself in a 30-foot cone. Each creature caught in the ink must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw, taking 27 (6d8) necrotic damage on a failed save or half as much damage on a successful one. A creature that fails this saving throw is blinded until the end of its next turn and contracts bluerot (see the "Bluerot" in notes).</text>
      <attack>Necrotic Ink (Recharge 5-6)||6d8</attack>
      </action>
    <description>This waterlogged undead, bound to the Pit of Hatred in Tammeraut's Fate, hovers menacingly over the bones of its victims. Its torso, arms, and head retain their former shapes, but its legs have split into shadowy tentacles. The drowned master is tethered to a source of powerful magic that prevents it from traveling far. It commands other drowned ones, compelling them to serve as agents in its dark plots.
Bluerot. This disease targets humanoids. While afflicted with bluerot, a victim grows grotesque blue boils on their face and back. This disease is carried by undead (including the drowned ones in Tammeraut's Fate), and victims most often acquire it through wounds caused by infected creatures. The disease's boils manifest in 1d4 hours, causing the victim's Constitution and Charisma scores to decrease by 1d4 each, to a minimum of 3. This is quickly followed by a fever and tingling in the extremities. An infected creature is vulnerable to radiant damage and gains the ability to breathe underwater.
At the end of each long rest, an infected creature makes a DC 12 Constitution saving throw. On a success, the victim regains 1 point of Constitution and 1 point of Charisma lost to the disease. If the infected creature regains all the points lost to the disease, it is cured. Other effects that raise the victim's ability scores do not cure the disease. On a failed saving throw, the victim takes 18 (4d8) necrotic damage as the boils burst and spread. A creature reduced to 0 hit points by this damage cannot regain hit points until the disease is cured, though it can be stabilized as normal.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 235, Locathah Rising</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Fish</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>1 (1d4-1)</hp>
    <speed>swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>2</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>9</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>7</wis>
    <cha>2</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>8</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Water Breathing</name>
      <text>The fish can breathe only underwater.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 1 piercing damage.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 224</description>
    <environment>underwater</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Giant Coral Snake</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>90 (12d10+24)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 10 ft.</senses>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (2d4 + 3) piercing damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or be stunned until the end of its next turn. On a failed save, the target begins to hallucinate and is afflicted with a dmg|8|madness). The effect lasts 10 minutes.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+5|2d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Comfortable on land or in water, these brilliantly colored snakes are renowned for their potent and hallucinogenic venom. They are most often found in coastal caves. In the abandoned chambers of the hermitage in Tammeraut's Fate, these giant serpents feed on any creature that crosses their path.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 236</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Giant Sea Eel</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>19 (3d10+3)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>7</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save>Dex +4</save>
    <skill>Perception +2, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Water Breathing</name>
      <text>The eel can breathe only underwater.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d10 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+4|2d10+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Snaking predators lurking in the dark waters of the ocean, these kelp-colored beasts serve as guards and mounts for the locathah (including those found in Danger at Dunwater).
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 237</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Giant White Moray Eel</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>60 (8d12+8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 10 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Water Breathing</name>
      <text>The eel can breathe only underwater.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 10 ft., one creature. 11 (2d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+6|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 216</description>
    <environment>underwater, underdark, forest, swamp, desert</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Harpy Matriarch</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>88 (16d8+16)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Dex +6, Cha +6</save>
    <skill>Perception +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Luring Maestro</name>
      <text>While within 60 feet of the matriarch, creatures have disadvantage on saving throws against the matriarch's Luring Song.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The matriarch has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The matriarch makes two claws attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (3d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+6|3d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Fleeting Form</name>
      <text>The matriarch can magically disguise itself to resemble a humanoid of roughly similar size and shape for up to 1 hour. It can revert to its true form as a bonus action. This illusion does not hold up to close scrutiny.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Luring Song</name>
      <text>The matriarch sings a magical melody. Every humanoid and giant within 300 feet of the matriarch that can hear the song must succeed on a DC 14 Wisdom saving throw or be charmed until the song ends. The matriarch must take a bonus action on its subsequent turns to continue singing. It can stop singing at any time. The song ends if the matriarch is incapacitated.</text>
      <text>While charmed by the matriarch, a target is incapacitated and ignores the songs of other harpies. If the charmed target is more than 5 feet away from the matriarch, the target must move on its turn toward the matriarch by the most direct route, trying to get within 5 feet. It doesn't avoid opportunity attacks, but before moving into damaging terrain, such as lava or a pit, and whenever it takes damage from a source other than the matriarch, the target can repeat the saving throw. A charmed target can also repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns. If the saving throw is successful, the effect ends on it.</text>
      <text>A target that successfully saves is immune to this matriarch's song for the next 24 hours.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Visage of Desire (1/Day)</name>
      <text>The matriarch projects a vision into the minds of creatures within 30 feet of it that aren't constructs or undead, showing each creature achieving whatever it most desires. An affected creature must succeed on a DC 14 Wisdom saving throw or drop whatever it is holding and become paralyzed until the end of its next turn.</text>
      </action>
    <description>Happy to watch its flock squabble over carrion in Tammeraut's Fate, this gray-feathered matron of the harpies is surrounded by a cloud of magical spirits resembling skeletal seabirds.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 237</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Juvenile Kraken</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>monstrosity (titan)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>207 (18d12+90)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., swim 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>24</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>19</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save>Str +12, Dex +5, Con +10, Int +9, Wis +7</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Celestial, Infernal, Primordial, telepathy 60 ft. but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>14</cr>
    <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>lightning</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>frightened, paralyzed</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The kraken can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Freedom of Movement</name>
      <text>The kraken ignores difficult terrain, and magical effects can't reduce its speed or cause it to be restrained. It can spend 5 feet of movement to escape from nonmagical restraints or being grappled.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The kraken makes two tentacle attacks, each of which it can replace with a use of Fling.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 20 (3d8 + 7) piercing damage. If the target is a Medium or smaller creature grappled by the kraken, that creature is swallowed and the grapple ends. While swallowed, the creature is blinded and restrained, it has total cover against attacks and other effects outside the kraken, and it takes 21 (6d6) acid damage at the start of each of the kraken's turns. One Medium or two smaller creatures can be swallowed at the same time.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+12|3d8+7</attack>
      <text>If the kraken takes 35 damage or more on a single turn from a creature inside it, the kraken must succeed on a DC 23 Constitution saving throw at the end of that turn or regurgitate all swallowed creatures, which fall prone in spaces within 10 feet of the kraken. If the kraken dies, a swallowed creature is no longer restrained by it and can escape from the corpse using 10 feet of movement, exiting prone.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Tentacle</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 20 ft., one target. 17 (3d6 + 7) bludgeoning damage, and the target is grappled (escape DC 20). Until the grapple ends, the target is restrained. The kraken has ten tentacles, each of which can grapple one target.</text>
      <attack>Tentacle|+12|3d6+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Fling</name>
      <text>One Medium or smaller object held or creature grappled by the kraken is thrown up to 40 feet in a random direction and knocked prone. If a thrown target strikes a solid surface, the target takes 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage for every 10 feet it was thrown. If the target is thrown at another creature, that creature must succeed on a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw or take the same damage and be knocked prone.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Lightning Strike</name>
      <text>The kraken magically create a bolt of lightning, which can strike a target the kraken can see within 90 feet of it. The target must make a DC 18 Dexterity saving throw, taking 22 (4d10) lightning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Lightning Strike||4d10</attack>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>The monstrosity (titan) can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The monstrosity (titan) regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Tentacle Attack (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>The kraken makes one tentacle attack.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Fling</name>
      <text>The kraken uses Fling.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Ink Cloud (Costs 3 Actions)</name>
      <text>While underwater, the kraken expels an ink cloud in a 40-foot radius. The cloud spreads around corners, and that area is heavily obscured to creatures other than the kraken. Each creature other than the kraken that ends its turn there must succeed on a DC 18 Constitution saving throw, taking 11 (2d10) poison damage on a failed save or half as much damage on a successful one. A strong current disperses the cloud, which otherwise disappears at the end of the kraken's next turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <description>Hidden in a deep, dark underwater pit near the Styes, this creature bears the mark of the dark god Tharizdun's madness. Becoming more independent every day, it dreams of freeing itself from its aboleth tenders and wreaking its own foul will upon the seas.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 238</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Koalinth</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (goblinoid)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (scale mail)</ac>
    <hp>16 (3d8+3)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Dex +2</save>
    <skill>Athletics +3, Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Goblin</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The koalinth can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Martial Advantage</name>
      <text>Once per turn, the koalinth can deal an extra 7 (2d6) damage to a creature it hits with a weapon attack if that creature is within 5 feet of an ally of the koalinth that isn't incapacitated.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Trident</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) piercing damage, or 5 (1d8 + 1) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Trident|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>The koalinth, found in Danger at Dunwater, are martial and aggressive aquatic hobgoblins, with brightly colored faces and functional gills. They are known for their ferocity, and for their hatred of elves.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 239</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Koalinth Sergeant</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (goblinoid)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (scale mail)</ac>
    <hp>33 (6d8+6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Dex +2, Wis +2</save>
    <skill>Athletics +4, Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Goblin</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The koalinth can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Martial Advantage</name>
      <text>Once per turn, the sergeant can deal an extra 7 (2d6) damage to a creature it hits with a weapon attack if that creature is within 5 feet of an ally of the sergeant that isn't incapacitated.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The sergeant makes two melee attacks with its trident.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Trident</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage, or 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Trident|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hooked Net</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 10/30 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage, and the target is restrained. A creature can use its action to make a DC 12 Strength check to free itself or another creature in a hooked net, ending the effect on a success. Dealing 5 slashing damage to the net (AC 12) frees the target without harming it and destroys the net.</text>
      <attack>Hooked Net|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Spear the Helpless (2/Day)</name>
      <text>Whenever a creature within 30 feet of the sergeant becomes restrained, the sergeant can move its speed toward the restrained creature. If the sergeant ends its move within reach of the restrained creature, it can make a melee attack against it.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>These fierce koalinths lead special missions for their people, such as the diplomatic envoy encountered in Danger at Dunwater. A koalinth sergeant focuses its ire on the most significant threats on the battlefield, then eliminates those threats one by one.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 239</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Krell Grohlg</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (half-orc)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>11 (16 with barkskin)</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Medicine +4, Nature +3, Perception +4, Intimidation +1</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Druidic plus any two languages, Orc</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Relentless Endurance</name>
      <text>When reduced to 0 hit points, &lt;$title_short_name$&gt; drops to 1 hit point instead (but can't do this again until they finish a long rest).</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Savage Attacks</name>
      <text>When they score a critical hit, &lt;$title_short_name$&gt; can roll one of the weapon's damage dice and add it to the extra damage of the critical hit.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Quarterstaff</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit (+4 to hit with shillelagh), reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage, or 6 (1d8 + 2) bludgeoning damage with shillelagh or if wielded with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Quarterstaff|+2|1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Krell is a 4th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 12, +4 to hit with spell attacks). It has the following druid spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): druidcraft, produce flame, shillelagh</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): entangle, longstrider, speak with animals, thunderwave</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): flaming sphere, barkskin</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3</slots>
    <spells>druidcraft, produce flame, shillelagh, entangle, longstrider, speak with animals, thunderwave, flaming sphere, barkskin</spells>
    <description>
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 92</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Kysh</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (triton)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Persuasion +4, Survival +3</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>Kysh can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Emissary of the Sea</name>
      <text>Kysh can communicate simple ideas with amphibious and water-breathing beasts. They understand the meaning of his words, but he cannot understand them in return.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Kysh makes two melee attacks with his spear.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft, one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage, or 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Spear|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Kysh's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 12, +4 to hit with spell attacks). He can cast the following spell, requiring only verbal components:</text>
      <text>1/day: fog cloud</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>fog cloud</spells>
    <description>A prisoner of the sahuagin in The Final Enemy, Kysh is a defender of the deep sea realms who is ready to join the party in their struggle. Tritons are folk of the Elemental Plane of Water who journeyed to the Material Plane to watch over the dark places of the ocean depths. They stand guard over portals, deep sea chasms, and other places where foul monsters might emerge. When such threats appear, the tritons take up arms to drive them from the world.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 240</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Living Iron Statue</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>102 (12d8+48)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>lightning, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable>acid</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The statue is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The statue makes two attacks: one with its blade and one with its hammer.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Blade</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (2d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Blade|+6|2d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hammer</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (2d6 + 3) bludgeoning damage, and the target is knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Hammer|+6|2d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Whirl (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The statue can use its action to spin at the waist, targeting creatures of its choice within 10 feet of it. Each target must make a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw, taking 19 (3d10 + 3) bludgeoning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Whirl (Recharge 5-6)||3d10+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>This squat, solid-looking statue, currently guarding the evil cult's treasure in Isle of the Abbey, is made from pure iron. Its hands are shaped into deadly weapons.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 241</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Lizardfolk Commoner</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (lizardfolk)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>16 (3d8+3)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>7</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +3, Stealth +2, Survival +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Draconic</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>The lizardfolk can hold its breath for 15 minutes.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>These lizardfolk, found wandering the halls in Danger at Dunwater, are just as fierce as their armed kin, and can equip themselves with weapons and shields if such are available.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 241</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Lizardfolk Render</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>humanoid (lizardfolk)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>52 (7d10+14)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>7</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +5, Perception +3, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Draconic</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Blood Frenzy</name>
      <text>The render has advantage on melee attack rolls against any creature that doesn't have all its hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>The render can hold its breath for 15 minutes.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The render makes two attacks: one with its claws and one with its bite.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 12 (2d8 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+5|2d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (1d10 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+5|1d10+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Rend the Field (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The render makes a claw attack against each creature of its choice within 10 feet of it. A creature hit by this attack must succeed on a DC 13 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      </action>
    <description>Filled with the primal magic of Semuanya, the lizardfolk render undergoes terrifying changes during a dayslong ritual performed by a shaman. As seen in Danger at Dunwater, the render's claws grow long and hard as steel, its frame enlarges, and its temperament becomes even more ferocious.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 241, Essentials Kit: Storm Lord's Wrath, Infernal Machine Rebuild</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Lizardfolk Scaleshield</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (lizardfolk)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>16 (scale mail, shield)</ac>
    <hp>32 (5d8+10)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>7</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +4, Perception +3, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Draconic</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>The scaleshield can hold its breath for 15 minutes.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The scaleshield makes two melee attacks, each one with a different weapon.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Morningstar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Morningstar|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spiked Shield</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Spiked Shield|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Shield Block</name>
      <text>If an ally within 5 feet of the scaleshield is hit by an attack, the scaleshield can reduce that attack's damage by half.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>Serving as the elite warriors and officers of a lizardfolk clan, these robust creatures wear thick armor made from crocodile scales and metal. Trained in martial weapons and advanced combat tactics, they are found protecting lizardfolk lairs such as the one in Danger at Dunwater.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 242</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Lizardfolk Subchief</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (lizardfolk)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>52 (8d8+16)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Wis +5</save>
    <skill>Athletics +4, Perception +5, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Draconic</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>The subchief can hold its breath for 15 minutes.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Tooth Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Tooth Dagger|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Jaws of Semuanya (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The subchief invokes the primal magic of Semuanya, summoning a spectral maw around a target it can see within 60 feet of it. The target must make a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw, taking 22 (5d8) piercing damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. A creature that fails this saving throw is also frightened until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Jaws of Semuanya (Recharge 5-6)||5d8</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The subchief is a 5th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). It has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light, sacred flame, spare the dying, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): command, guiding bolt, purify food and drink</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): hold person, lesser restoration, silence</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (2 slots): bestow curse, dispel magic</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>light, sacred flame, spare the dying, thaumaturgy, command, guiding bolt, purify food and drink, hold person, lesser restoration, silence, bestow curse, dispel magic</spells>
    <description>The lizardfolk subchief (seen in Danger at Dunwater) is a devout priest of Semuanya, pursuing the worship of its god in a manner similar to a cleric. It wields a dagger crafted of a massive crocodile tooth blessed by Semuanya, representing the subchief's prowess in both battle and piety.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 242, Essentials Kit: Storm Lord's Wrath</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Locathah</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (locathah)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>22 (4d8+4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Dex +3</save>
    <skill>Athletics +3, Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Aquan, Common</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Leviathan Will</name>
      <text>The locathah has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned, stunned, or put to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Limited Amphibiousness</name>
      <text>The locathah can breathe air and water, but it needs to be submerged at least once every 4 hours to avoid suffocating.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The locathah makes two melee attacks with its spear.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) piercing damage, or 5 (1d8 + 1) piercing damage if used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Spear|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>These resilient and proud fish-folk (found in Danger at Dunwater) have endured war, slavery, and mistreatment at the hands of other aquatic creatures. They dwell in submerged tribal communities along seacoasts, and hunt both above and below the water.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 243, Infernal Machine Rebuild</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Locathah Hunter</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (locathah)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>33 (6d8+6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Dex +4, Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Athletics +3, Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Aquan, Common</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Leviathan Will</name>
      <text>The hunter has advantage on saving throws against spells and effects that control its actions.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Limited Amphibiousness</name>
      <text>The hunter can breathe air and water, but it needs to be submerged at least once every 4 hours to avoid suffocating.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The hunter makes two attacks with its envenomed crossbow.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Envenomed Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 11 (2d8 + 2) piercing damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Envenomed Crossbow|+4|2d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Club</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Club|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>The far-ranging locathah hunter is trained in tracking and stalking prey on land and in water. They often serve as leaders to small bands of locathah or emissaries for their people (such as the hunter found in Danger at Dunwater). Their colorful, poisoned, and fast-loading crossbows rarely miss a target.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 243</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Master Refrum</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (chain shirt)</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Medicine +7, Persuasion +3, Religion +5</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>any two languages</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Divine Eminence</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Refrum can expend a spell slot to cause its melee weapon attacks to magically deal an extra 10 (3d6) radiant damage to a target on a hit. This benefit lasts until the end of the turn. If Refrum expends a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the extra damage increases by 1d6 for each level above 1st.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Mace</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Mace|+2|1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Refrum is a 5th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). Refrum has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): cure wounds, guiding bolt, sanctuary</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): lesser restoration, spiritual weapon</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (2 slots): dispel magic, spirit guardians</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy, cure wounds, guiding bolt, sanctuary, lesser restoration, spiritual weapon, dispel magic, spirit guardians</spells>
    <description>
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 165</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Maw of Sekolah</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>114 (12d12+36)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., swim 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>21</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save>Str +8, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +8, Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Sahuagin, telepathy 100 ft.</languages>
    <cr>7</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (2/Day)</name>
      <text>If the maw of Sekolah fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Water Breathing</name>
      <text>The maw of Sekolah can breathe only underwater.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The maw of Sekolah makes one attack with its bite and one attack with its tail smash.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 16 (2d10 + 5) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+8|2d10+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Tail Smash</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 9 (1d8 + 5) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Tail Smash|+8|1d8+5</attack>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>The monstrosity can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The monstrosity regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Detect</name>
      <text>The maw of Sekolah makes a Wisdom (Perception) check.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Speed of Sekolah</name>
      <text>The maw of Sekolah moves up to its speed.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Feed (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>The ferocious spirit of Sekolah flashes through the water, tearing through the foes of the maw of Sekolah. Each creature of the maw's choosing within 60 feet of it must make a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw, taking 7 (2d6) slashing damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      </legendary>
    <description>Summoned from the shadowy depths of the ocean through ritual and tidal magic, the Maw of Sekolah appears in The Final Enemy as the avatar of the hungry sahuagin god. This huge, two-headed shark is fed a steady diet of sentient creatures, captured by the sahuagin and offered up as tribute. Sahuagin priestesses adorn the fins of the maw of Sekolah with gemmed bands and polished skulls.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 244</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Merfolk Salvager</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (merfolk)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>22 (4d8+4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 10 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save>Dex +4</save>
    <skill>Athletics +3, Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Aquan, Common</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The salvager can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The salvager makes two attacks with its coral rapier.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Coral Rapier</name>
      <text>Melee Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Coral Rapier|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Inject Toxin (2/Day)</name>
      <text>Melee Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage, and the creature must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or be paralyzed until the end of its next turn.</text>
      <attack>Inject Toxin (2/Day)|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Veterans of scouring the wrecks and ruins found in the deepest waters, these skilled warriors help defend their kin with rapier-like weapons of living coral. The salvagers escort other merfolk on scavenging missions, using their keen senses to detect danger. They are found allying with the lizardfolk in Danger at Dunwater.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 244</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Merfolk Scout</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (merfolk)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>16 (3d8+3)</hp>
    <speed>walk 10 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Nature +4, Perception +5, Stealth +6, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common), Aquan</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Hearing and Sight</name>
      <text>The scout has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing or sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The scout makes two melee attacks or two ranged attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 216</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Minotaur Living Crystal Statue</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>136 (16d10+48)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>lightning, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable>force</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The statue is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The statue makes two attacks: one with its greataxe and one gore attack.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Greataxe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 17 (2d12 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Greataxe|+7|2d12+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Gore</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (1d8 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Gore|+7|1d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Flying Shards</name>
      <text>In response to a creature hitting the statue with a melee weapon attack, the statue deals 11 (2d10) piercing damage to the attacker.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>Given life through powerful magic, a large, crudely carved crystal minotaur guards the tunnels in Isle of the Abbey.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 245</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Monstrous Peryton</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>144 (17d10+51)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Str +8, Dex +6, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>understands Common and Elvish but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>11</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Flyby</name>
      <text>The peryton doesn't provoke opportunity attacks when it flies out of an enemy's reach.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Sight and Smell</name>
      <text>The peryton has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight or smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If the peryton fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The peryton makes two attacks: one with its gore and one with its talons.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Gore</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 12 (2d6 + 5) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Gore|+9|2d6+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Talons</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 16 (2d10 + 5) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Talons|+9|2d10+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Warp Shadow</name>
      <text>The peryton chooses up to three creatures within 60 feet of it that it can see. Each creature must succeed on a DC 14 Wisdom saving throw or become cursed. While cursed, whenever the creature makes an attack roll, an ability check, or a saving throw, it must roll a d4 and subtract that number from the roll. A cursed creature can repeat this saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself with a success. A creature that succeeds on this saving throw is immune to this peryton's Warp Shadow for 24 hours.</text>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>The monstrosity can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The monstrosity regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Detect</name>
      <text>The peryton makes a Wisdom (Perception) check.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Talons Attack</name>
      <text>The peryton makes one attack with its talons.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Dive Attack (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>The peryton moves up to its speed toward one target of its choosing. It then makes a gore attack that deals an extra 9 (2d8) piercing damage on a hit.</text>
      </legendary>
    <description>The terror of the coast and the recent scourge of Firewatch Island in Tammeraut's Fate, this large peryton preys on ships and coastal communities alike. It has built numerous nests to mark its territory.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 245</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Mr. Dory</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>18 (studded leather armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>170 (20d8+80)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>20</dex>
    <con>19</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Con +8, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +5, Perception +6, Stealth +9</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Deep Speech, telepathy 60 ft.</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>necrotic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Mr. Dory has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Water Dependency</name>
      <text>Mr. Dory takes 6 (1d12) acid damage at the end of every hour he goes without exposure to water.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Mr. Dory makes three attacks with his rapier.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Rapier</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (1d8 + 5) piercing damage and 7 (2d6) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Rapier|+9|1d8+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Eye of Corruption (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>Mr. Dory glares at a creature he can see within 30 feet of him. The target must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, it takes 27 (5d10) necrotic damage and 27 (5d10) poison damage and then gains vulnerability to both necrotic and poison damage for 1 minute. On a successful save, it takes half damage and does not gain the vulnerabilities.</text>
      <attack>Eye of Corruption (Recharge 5-6)||5d10</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Mr. Dory's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (save DC 15, +7 to hit with spell attacks). Mr. Dory can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: detect magic, detect thoughts, invisibility (self only)</text>
      <text>2/day each: fear, fireball, fly</text>
      <text>1/day each: cloudkill, etherealness</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>detect magic, detect thoughts, invisibility, fear, fireball, fly, cloudkill, etherealness</spells>
    <description>One of the four councillors who rule the Styes, Mr. Dory hides his cursed nature in plain sight. His rare, liquid-sensitive "skin condition" is actually a form of the same aboleth affliction that creates skum, though Dory's condition is not as severe, and he has managed to retain his free will.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 246</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Oceanus</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (elf)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Good</alignment>
    <ac>12 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>30 (4d8+12)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Con +5</save>
    <skill>Athletics +4, Perception +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Aquan, Elvish</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>Oceanus can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Friend of the Sea</name>
      <text>Using gestures and sounds, Oceanus can communicate simple ideas with any beast that has an innate swimming speed.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Trident</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage, or 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Trident|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Light Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 5 (1d8 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Light Crossbow|+3|1d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Before being captured, this sea elf had been tasked with investigating the Sea Ghost's movements in The Sinister Secret of Saltmarsh. Oceanus is a smart and resourceful elf who is more than willing to join adventurers who have brave hearts and good intentions.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 246</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Othokent</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (lizardfolk)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>78 (12d8+24)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>17</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Con +4, Wis +2</save>
    <skill>Perception +4, Stealth +5, Survival +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>frightened</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>Othokent can hold its breath for 15 minutes.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Skewer</name>
      <text>Once per turn, when Othokent makes a melee attack with its trident and hits, the target takes an extra 10 (3d6) damage, and Othokent gains temporary hit points equal to the extra damage dealt.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Othokent makes two attacks: one with its bite and one with its claws or trident or two melee attacks with its trident.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+5|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Trident</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage, or 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Trident|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 81</description>
    <environment>forest, swamp</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Pirate Bosun</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (studded leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +5, Intimidation +3</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Cargo Hauler</name>
      <text>The bosun has advantage on Strength checks.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sea Legs</name>
      <text>The bosun has advantage on ability checks and saving throws to resist being knocked prone.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Light Hammer</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Light Hammer|+5|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hook</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage, and the target is grappled (escape DC 13).</text>
      <attack>Hook|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>The bosun (or boatswain) is tasked with organizing the cargo and crew aboard a ship. Bosuns are capable fighters whose experience with hauling cargo and delivering beatings make them tough opponents. Foul Frithoff in The Sinister Secret of Saltmarsh is the bosun who protects the cargo aboard the smugglers' ship. Ever since a bad accident, he has worn a hook at the end of one arm in place of a hand.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 247</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Pirate Captain</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>14 (studded leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>45 (7d8+14)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +5, Intimidation +4</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Flourish</name>
      <text>The captain adds its Charisma modifier to the damage roll for its longsword attacks (included in the attack).</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sea Legs</name>
      <text>The captain has advantage on ability checks and saving throws to resist being knocked prone.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The captain makes two attacks: one with its hand crossbow and one with its longsword.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hand Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Hand Crossbow|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Longsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (1d8 + 5) slashing damage, or 10 (1d10 + 5) slashing damage if used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Longsword|+5|1d8+5</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Shape Up, Ye Dog (2/Day)</name>
      <text>Whenever a friendly creature within 30 feet of the captain that can hear it misses with an attack, the captain can yell perilous threats to allow that creature to reroll the attack roll.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>Pirate captains spend their lives at sea, earning and keeping command through blood and daring. A captain's impressive sword work and biting words inspire both confidence and fear in a ship's crew. Sigurd "Snake Eyes" is the pirate captain who leads a gang of smugglers in The Sinister Secret of Saltmarsh.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 247</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Pirate Deck Wizard</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>32 (5d8+10)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Arcana +5, Perception +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Sea Legs</name>
      <text>The deck wizard has advantage on ability checks and saving throws to resist being knocked prone.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Quarterstaff</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Quarterstaff|+2|1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The deck wizard is a 4th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). It has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): friends, mage hand, prestidigitation, ray of frost</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): disguise self, fog cloud, mage armor, witch bolt</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): gust of wind, Melf's acid arrow, misty step</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3</slots>
    <spells>friends, mage hand, prestidigitation, ray of frost, disguise self, fog cloud, mage armor, witch bolt, gust of wind, Melf's acid arrow, misty step</spells>
    <description>These salt-encrusted practitioners of magic are at once learned and superstitious. The crews of pirate ships generally give their deck wizards a wide berth, as they magically step from place to place and unleash their briny magic against attackers. The ship Sea Ghost in The Sinister Secret of Saltmarsh is home to a pirate deck wizard named Punketah.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 248</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Pirate First Mate</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>16 (chain mail)</ac>
    <hp>26 (4d8+8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +4, Intimidation +3</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Sea Legs</name>
      <text>The first mate has advantage on ability checks and saving throws to resist being knocked prone.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The first mate makes two attacks with its longsword.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Longsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) slashing damage, or 7 (1d10 + 2) slashing damage if used with two hands. If the target is a creature, the first mate can choose to deal no damage with the attack to disarm the target. The target must succeed on a DC 14 Strength saving throw or drop one item it is holding on the ground.</text>
      <attack>Longsword|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>These no-nonsense sailors are the trusted allies of a pirate ship's captain. Ex-soldiers and trained mercenaries often find employment as mates aboard pirate ships. In The Sinister Secret of Saltmarsh, Bloody Bjorn serves as the first mate aboard Sea Ghost.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 248</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Rip Tide Priest</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13 (chain shirt)</ac>
    <hp>52 (8d8+16)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +5, Religion +2, Stealth +2</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Aquan, Common</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Quarterstaff</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Quarterstaff|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The priest is a 5th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). It knows the following sorcerer spells:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): chill touch, mage hand, minor illusion, prestidigitation, ray of frost</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): expeditious retreat, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): blur, hold person</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (2 slots): sleet storm</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>chill touch, mage hand, minor illusion, prestidigitation, ray of frost, expeditious retreat, magic missile, shield, blur, hold person, sleet storm</spells>
    <description>Priests of the Rip Tide cult gather in secret cabals to perform dark rituals that glorify Olhydra, the elemental Princess of Evil Water, as the embodiment of water's destructiveness. They believe that using water to kill their enemies, such as through ritual drowning, earns them Olhydra's favor.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 248</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sahuagin Blademaster</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (sahuagin)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>20 (plate armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>97 (15d8+30)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Str +6, Con +5</save>
    <skill>Athletics +6, Intimidation +4</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Sahuagin</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Blood Frenzy</name>
      <text>The blademaster has advantage on melee attack rolls against any creature that doesn't have all its hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Limited Amphibiousness</name>
      <text>The blademaster can breathe air and water, but it needs to be submerged at least once every 4 hours to avoid suffocating.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Shark Telepathy</name>
      <text>The blademaster can magically command any shark within 120 feet of it, using a limited telepathy.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The blademaster makes three attacks with its wavecutter blade, or one attack with its bite and two with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Wavecutter Blade</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 12 (2d8 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Wavecutter Blade|+6|2d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (1d10 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+6|1d10+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+6|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>A cunning veteran of countless campaigns, the sahuagin blademaster decorates its armor with the bones of its defeated foes. As demonstrated in The Final Enemy, sahuagin blademasters often serve as officers in the sa huagin army.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 249, Essentials Kit: Sleeping Dragon's Wake, Locathah Rising</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sahuagin Champion</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (sahuagin)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>71 (13d8+13)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Sahuagin</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Blood Frenzy</name>
      <text>The champion has advantage on melee attack rolls against any creature that doesn't have all its hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Limited Amphibiousness</name>
      <text>The champion can breathe air and water, but it needs to be submerged at least once every 4 hours to avoid suffocating.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Shark Telepathy</name>
      <text>The champion can magically command any shark within 120 feet of it, using a limited telepathy.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The champion makes three attacks with its spear, or one attack with its bite and two with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage, or 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Spear|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+5|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Those sahuagin warriors who prove themselves through heroic acts are given both title and status. Sahuagin champions often serve as lieutenants in the sahuagin army, as they do in The Final Enemy.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 249</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sahuagin Coral Smasher</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (sahuagin)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>33 (6d8+6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Sahuagin</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Blood Frenzy</name>
      <text>The coral smasher has advantage on melee attack rolls against any creature that doesn't have all its hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Limited Amphibiousness</name>
      <text>The coral smasher can breathe air and water, but it needs to be submerged at least once every 4 hours to avoid suffocating.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Shark Telepathy</name>
      <text>The coral smasher can magically command any shark within 120 feet of it, using a limited telepathy.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The coral smasher deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The coral smasher makes two attacks with its warhammer, or one attack with its bite and one with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Warhammer</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Warhammer|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+5|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+5|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Employed as frontline brutes in The Final Enemy, coral smashers are drawn from the ranks of the strongest sahuagin warriors. Their physical strength overcomes the resistance of the water as they swing their hammers at structures and foes with equal zeal.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 249</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sahuagin Deep Diver</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (sahuagin)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>91 (14d8+28)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save>Con +4, Wis +3</save>
    <skill>Perception +5, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Sahuagin</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Blood Frenzy</name>
      <text>The deep diver has advantage on melee attack rolls against any creature that doesn't have all its hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Brine Lurker</name>
      <text>The deep diver has advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks made while submerged in water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Limited Amphibiousness</name>
      <text>The deep diver can breathe air and water, but it needs to be submerged at least once every 4 hours to avoid suffocating.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Lure</name>
      <text>The deep diver can cause its lure to light up or darken at will. While the lure is lit, the deep diver sheds bright light in a 30-foot radius centered on itself and dim light for an additional 20 feet.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Shark Telepathy</name>
      <text>The deep diver can magically command any shark within 120 feet of it, using a limited telepathy.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The deep diver makes two attacks with its glaive, or one attack with its bite and two with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Glaive</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 13 (2d10 + 2) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Glaive|+4|2d10+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d10 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+4|1d10+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Light of Sekolah</name>
      <text>The deep diver pulses magical light from its lure. Any creature within 30 feet of the deep diver that can see the light must succeed on a DC 11 Wisdom saving throw or be charmed until the end of its next turn. A creature charmed in this way is incapacitated as it stares at the light.</text>
      </action>
    <description>These mighty sahuagin, found in The Final Enemy, are transformed by the divine magic of Sekolah to enable them to better explore the darkest depths of the ocean. Out of the water, they cling to shadows and serve as hunters and assassins. A long, scaly lure that can be illuminated extends from a deep diver's forehead.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 250, Locathah Rising</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sahuagin Hatchling Swarm</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>swarm of Large beasts</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14</ac>
    <hp>52 (8d10+8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, prone, restrained, stunned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Blood Frenzy</name>
      <text>The swarm has advantage on melee attack rolls against any creature that doesn't have all its hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Seething</name>
      <text>Once it enters combat, the swarm deals 10 slashing damage to itself at the end of its turn if it did not make an attack on that turn. This damage ignores resistance, and it cannot reduce the swarm to 0 hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Swarm</name>
      <text>The swarm can occupy another creature's space and vice versa, and it can move through any opening large enough for a Tiny creature. The swarm can't regain hit points or gain temporary hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Water Breathing</name>
      <text>The swarm can breathe only underwater.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bites</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 0 ft., one creature in the swarm's space. 14 (4d6) piercing damage, or 7 (2d6) piercing damage if the swarm has half of its hit points or fewer.</text>
      <attack>Bites|+6|4d6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Roiling through the waters in The Final Enemy, these swarms of sahuagin hatchlings are dangerous to any creatures they encounter. Other sahuagin avoid the swarms, while the individual members devour one another until only the strongest hatchlings are left alive to grow to maturity.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 250, Locathah Rising</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sahuagin High Priestess</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (sahuagin)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>71 (11d8+22)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Insight +6, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Sahuagin</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Blood Frenzy</name>
      <text>The high priestess has advantage on melee attack rolls against any creature that doesn't have all its hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Limited Amphibiousness</name>
      <text>The high priestess can breathe air and water, but she needs to be submerged at least once every 4 hours to avoid suffocating.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Shark Telepathy</name>
      <text>The high priestess can magically command any shark within 120 feet of her, using a limited telepathy.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The high priestess makes two attacks with her toothsome staff, or one attack with her bite and one with her claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Toothsome Staff</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (2d8 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Toothsome Staff|+5|2d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The high priestess is a 7th-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks). She has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): guidance, mending, resistance, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): bless, detect magic, guiding bolt</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): hold person, spiritual weapon (trident)</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): bestow curse, fear, mass healing word, tongues</text>
      <text>• 4th level (1 slots): banishment</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>guidance, mending, resistance, thaumaturgy, bless, detect magic, guiding bolt, hold person, spiritual weapon, bestow curse, fear, mass healing word, tongues, banishment</spells>
    <description>A sahuagin high priestess is the most devout and ferocious of all Sekolah's worshipers. Armed with a staff studded with jagged shark's teeth, she can be seen leading dark rituals in The Final Enemy.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 251, Essentials Kit: Sleeping Dragon's Wake</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sahuagin Wave Shaper</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (sahuagin)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>60 (11d8+11)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Int +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, Intimidation +4, Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Sahuagin</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Blood Frenzy</name>
      <text>The wave shaper has advantage on melee attack rolls against any creature that doesn't have all its hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Limited Amphibiousness</name>
      <text>The wave shaper can breathe air and water, but it needs to be submerged at least once every 4 hours to avoid suffocating.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Shark Telepathy</name>
      <text>The wave shaper can magically command any shark within 120 feet of it, using a limited telepathy.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The wave shaper makes two attacks: one with its bite and one with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (2d8 + 1) piercing damage plus 13 (3d8) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+4|2d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (2d8 + 1) slashing damage plus 13 (3d8) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+4|2d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Whirlpool (1/Day)</name>
      <text>The wave shaper targets a body of water at least 50 feet square and 25 feet deep, causing a whirlpool to form in the center of the area. The whirlpool forms a vortex that is 5 feet wide at the base, up to 50 feet wide at the top, 25 feet tall, and lasts for 1 minute or until the wave shaper is incapacitated. Any creature or object in the water and within 25 feet of the vortex is pulled 10 feet toward it. A creature can swim away from the vortex by succeeding on a DC 14 Strength (Athletics) check.</text>
      <text>When a creature enters the vortex for the first time on a turn or starts its turn there, it must make a DC 14 Strength saving throw. On a failed save, the creature takes 9 (2d8) bludgeoning damage and is caught in the vortex until it ends. On a success, the creature takes half damage and isn't caught in the vortex. A creature caught in the vortex can use its action to try to swim away from the vortex as described above, but it has disadvantage on the Strength (Athletics) check to do so.</text>
      <attack>Whirlpool (1/Day)||2d8</attack>
      <text>The first time each turn that an object enters the vortex, the object takes 9 (2d8) bludgeoning damage. This damage occurs each round it remains in the vortex.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The wave shaper's spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks). It can cast the following spells, requiring only verbal components:</text>
      <text>At will: message</text>
      <text>1/day: comprehend languages</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>message, comprehend languages</spells>
    <description>These hunched and twisted sahuagin sacrifice their bodies to the mutating magic of Sekolah. Wave shapers add elemental magic to sahuagin armed forces (as seen in The Final Enemy) and delight in creating destructive whirlpools.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 251</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sanbalet</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>27 (6d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Arcana +5</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 3 (1d4 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+3|1d4+1</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Sanbalet is a 3rd-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). He has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): dancing lights, minor illusion, ray of frost</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): charm person, color spray, magic missile, silent image</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (2 slots): magic mouth, scorching ray</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 2</slots>
    <spells>dancing lights, minor illusion, ray of frost, charm person, color spray, magic missile, silent image, magic mouth, scorching ray</spells>
    <description>In The Sinister Secret of Saltmarsh, Sanbalet is the leader of the land-based half of a smuggling ring. He is a cunning narcissist with an interest in illusion and mind control. He defends the contraband stored in the caves under the haunted house.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 252</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sauriv</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (lizardfolk)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (breastplate)</ac>
    <hp>9 (2d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +5, Insight +4, Persuasion +5</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>any two languages, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; can hold their breath for up to 15 minutes at a time.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Rapier</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d8 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Rapier|+3|1d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Sauriv adds 2 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, Sauriv must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 79</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Shell Shark</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>18 (shell plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>32 (5d8+10)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save>Str +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +6</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Blood Frenzy</name>
      <text>The shark has advantage on melee attack rolls against any creature that doesn't have all its hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The shark has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Water Breathing</name>
      <text>The shark can breathe only underwater.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The shark makes two bite attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d10 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+4|2d10+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>These impressive creatures, swimming through the sahuagin stronghold in The Final Enemy, are chosen by priestesses of Sekolah to serve as protectors and messengers. The sharks are blessed in a ritual during which plates of shell and coral are permanently affixed to their bodies.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 252</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Skeletal Alchemist</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>32 (5d8+10)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Arcana +4</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands all languages it knew in life but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable>bludgeoning</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The skeletal alchemist has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The skeletal alchemist makes two Lob Acid attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft. one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Lob Acid</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. 5 (1d8 + 1) acid damage.</text>
      <attack>Lob Acid|+3|1d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>This undead retains enough of its former self to continue its alchemical work, often on behalf of necromancers or other sinister patrons. It toils in a dark laboratory (such as the one found in The Sinister Secret of Saltmarsh), often falling dormant for long periods of time.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 253</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Skeletal Juggernaut</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13 (armor scraps)</ac>
    <hp>142 (19d10+38)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>8</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable>bludgeoning</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Disassemble</name>
      <text>If the juggernaut is reduced to 0 hit points, twelve skeletons rise from its remains.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Falling Apart</name>
      <text>If the juggernaut does not have all of its hit points at the start of its turn, it loses 10 hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The juggernaut makes two claws attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 12 (2d8 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+6|2d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Avalanche of Bones (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The juggernaut collapses into a large heap before quickly reforming. Each creature within 10 feet of the juggernaut must make a DC 14 Dexterity saving throw, taking 18 (4d8) bludgeoning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. A creature that fails this saving throw is also knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Avalanche of Bones (Recharge 5-6)||4d8</attack>
      </action>
    <description>As seen lumbering across the beaches in Isle of the Abbey, a skeletal juggernaut is an oversized, bipedal assembly of bones that loses a portion of its mass with each step. These skeletal guardians hold together for only a short time before disassembling into a gang of individual undead.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 253, Infernal Machine Rebuild</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Skeletal Swarm</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>swarm of Large undeads</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13 (armor scraps)</ac>
    <hp>60 (8d10+16)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>8</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist>slashing, piercing</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable>bludgeoning</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone, restrained, stunned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Deafening Clatter</name>
      <text>Creatures are deafened while in the swarm's space.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Swarm</name>
      <text>The swarm can occupy another creature's space and vice versa, and the swarm can move through any opening large enough for a Small humanoid. The swarm can't regain hit points or gain temporary hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Slash</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 0 ft., one target in the swarm's space. 11 (2d8 + 2) slashing damage, or 6 (1d8 + 2) slashing damage if the swarm has half of its hit points or fewer.</text>
      <attack>Slash|+4|2d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>This swarm of bones found rising out of the sand in Isle of the Abbey is made from the remains of several animated skeletons. A skeletal swarm alternates its appearance between partially formed humanoid shapes and a chaotic, swirling mass.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 254, Essentials Kit: Divine Contention, Infernal Machine Rebuild</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Skum</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>93 (11d8+44)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>7</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common, Deep Speech, telepathy 60 ft.</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist>psychic</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Abolethic Vassal</name>
      <text>The skum is permanently charmed by its aboleth master.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The skum can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Psychic Conditioning</name>
      <text>The skum is immune to the frightened and charmed conditions unless they are from effects created by an aboleth.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Water Dependency</name>
      <text>The skum takes 6 (1d12) acid damage every 10 minutes it goes without exposure to water.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The skum makes three attacks: two with its trident and one with its Mind-Breaking Touch.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Trident</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Trident|+7|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Mind-Breaking Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 18 (4d8) psychic damage, and the target has disadvantage on Wisdom saving throws until the end of the skum's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Mind-Breaking Touch|+7|4d8</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Several poor souls around the Styes have succumbed to an aboleth's magic through its disease-bearing touch. Transformed into creatures called skum, they barely resemble their past forms, their skin turning slimy and translucent while their limbs warp to resemble those of deep-sea oddities. The change makes them dependent on water, which they must immerse themselves in regularly lest they experience painful-and potentially lethal-skin eruptions. Skum are bound to their aboleth master not just by their cursed state, but by a psychic bond that compels them to serve its every sinister whim.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 254</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Thousand Teeth</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>93 (11d10+33)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save>Str +7, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +7, Stealth +3</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hold Breath</name>
      <text>Thousand Teeth can hold its breath for 30 minutes.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (2/Day)</name>
      <text>If Thousand Teeth fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Thousand Teeth makes two attacks: one with its bite and one with its tail.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 15 (2d10 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+7|2d10+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 8 (1d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 15 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Tail|+7|1d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>Thousand can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Thousand regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Detect</name>
      <text>Thousand Teeth makes a Wisdom (Perception) check.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Lunge</name>
      <text>Thousand Teeth moves up to half its speed.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Bite (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Thousand Teeth makes a bite attack.</text>
      </legendary>
    <description>Thousand Teeth is an ancient crocodilian nightmare that has served as the apex predator in the swamps near Saltmarsh for as long as anyone can remember. This monster recently fought a number of lizardfolk and lost one of its teeth. Angered and hungry, it sulks in its lair, lost in primal dreams of rending and tearing. It is found in the deep marshes in Danger at Dunwater.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 256</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Vampiric Jade Statue</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>114 (12d10+48)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>lightning, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable>force</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The statue is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If the statue fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The statue makes three attacks: one with its bite and two with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (2d6 + 3) piercing damage. If the target is a creature, that creature becomes cursed by the statue. The curse lasts for 10 minutes. While the creature is cursed, the statue has advantage on all attacks against it.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+6|2d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (2d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+6|2d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>The construct can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The construct regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>The statue makes one bite attack.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Blood Reaper</name>
      <text>All creatures currently cursed by the statue and within 20 feet of it take 5 necrotic damage.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Move</name>
      <text>The statue moves up to its speed without provoking opportunity attacks.</text>
      </legendary>
    <description>A large, exquisitely carved jade statue of a vampire guards the tunnels in Isle of the Abbey, having been brought to life by dark magic. Its stone fangs draw blood that it then uses to work a curse on its victims.
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 256</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Yalaga Maladwyn</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (elf)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (scale mail)</ac>
    <hp>71 (13d8+13)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Con +4, Wis +6, Cha +7</save>
    <skill>Insight +6, Perception +6, Religion +4, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Elvish, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, Yalaga has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Yalaga makes two scourge attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Scourge</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage plus 17 (5d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Scourge|+5|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Drow Magic Armor and Weapons</name>
      <text>Drow often wear magic armor and carry magic weapons that lose their enhancement bonuses permanently if they are exposed to sunlight for 1 hour or longer.</text>
      <text>A drow priestess of lolth wearing +3 scale mail has AC 19.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Yalaga's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 15). She can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: dancing lights</text>
      <text>1/day each: darkness, faerie fire, levitate (self only)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Yalaga is a 10th-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Wisdom (save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks). Yalaga has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): guidance, poison spray, resistance, spare the dying, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): animal friendship, cure wounds, detect poison and disease, ray of sickness</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): lesser restoration, protection from poison, web</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): conjure animals (2 giant spiders), dispel magic</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): divination, freedom of movement</text>
      <text>• 5th level (2 slots): insect plague, mass cure wounds</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>dancing lights, darkness, faerie fire, levitate, guidance, poison spray, resistance, spare the dying, thaumaturgy, animal friendship, cure wounds, detect poison and disease, ray of sickness, lesser restoration, protection from poison, web, conjure animals, dispel magic, divination, freedom of movement, insect plague, mass cure wounds</spells>
    <description>
Source: Ghosts of Saltmarsh p. 226</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  </compendium>
