<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <monster>
      <name>Ahmaergo</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>143 (22d8+44)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Str +9, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +9, Intimidation +5, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
      <text>Ahmaergo has advantage on saving throws against being poisoned.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Indomitable (2/Day)</name>
      <text>Ahmaergo can reroll a saving throw that he fails. He must use the new roll.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Second Wind (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Ahmaergo can regain 20 hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Extra Damage</name>
      <text>If Ahmaergo has more than half his hit points remaining he deals an extra 7 (2d6) slashing damage on every hit.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Ahmaergo makes three attacks with his greataxe.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Greataxe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (1d12 + 5) slashing damage</text>
      <attack>Greataxe|+9|1d12+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Heavy Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 100/400 ft., one target. 7 (1d10 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Heavy Crossbow|+6|1d10+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Ahmaergo, Xanathar's majordomo, has a fascination with minotaurs. Although outwardly civil, the shield dwarf is as devious and corrupt as the worst devil, yet also unflinchingly loyal to his beholder master.
After the beholder, Ahmaergo is the most influential member of the Xanathar Guild.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 193</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Ammalia Cassalanter</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>45 (10d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Int +6, Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, History +6, Insight +4, Persuasion +5</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Elvish, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Quarterstaff</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d6 - 1) bludgeoning damage, or 3 (1d8 - 1) bludgeoning damage if used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Quarterstaff|+2|1d6-1</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Ammalia is a 9th-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks). She has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): friends, mage hand, mending, message</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): charm person, mage armor, magic missile</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): hold person, invisibility, suggestion</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): fireball, haste, tongues</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): confusion, stoneskin</text>
      <text>• 5th level (1 slots): hold monster</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>friends, mage hand, mending, message, charm person, mage armor, magic missile, hold person, invisibility, suggestion, fireball, haste, tongues, confusion, stoneskin, hold monster</spells>
    <description>The vainglorious lady of House Cassalanter is schooled in the arcane arts. Like her husband Victoro, she worships Asmodeus. When they were young, Ammalia and Victoro signed a contract with the archdevil, trading the souls of their children for power, good health, and long life. The soul of Osvaldo, their eldest son, was taken immediately, and he was transformed into a chain devil. The souls of the younger twins, Terenzio and Elzerina, will be taken when they turn nine years old.
A provision in the contract allows the Cassalanters to buy their way out of it, but doing so requires a tremendous amount of coin and a mass sacrifice of unfortunate people. While Victoro hunts for Dagult Neverember's lost cache of gold, Ammalia makes plans to host a poisoned feast in celebration of Founders' Day.
Ammalia is well mannered, well read, well traveled, and exceptionally shrewd. She is known for driving a hard bargain. Her hobby is lepidopterology, and her estate has the most beautiful butterfly garden. She allows her youngest children to play in the garden under her supervision.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 193</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Aurinax</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>dragon</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>256 (19d12+133)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft., fly 80 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>27</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>25</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>24</cha>
    <save>Dex +8, Con +13, Wis +8, Cha +13</save>
    <skill>Insight +8, Perception +14, Persuasion +13, Stealth +8</skill>
    <passive>24</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>17</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>fire</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft., darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>Aurinax can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If Aurinax fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Aurinax can use its Frightful Presence. It then makes three attacks: one with its bite and two with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 19 (2d10 + 8) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+14|2d10+8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 15 (2d6 + 8) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+14|2d6+8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 15 ft., one target. 17 (2d8 + 8) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Tail|+14|2d8+8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Frightful Presence</name>
      <text>Each creature of Aurinax's choice that is within 120 feet of Aurinax and aware of it must succeed on a DC 21 Wisdom saving throw or become frightened for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. If a creature's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the creature is immune to Aurinax's Frightful Presence for the next 24 hours.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Breath Weapons (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>Aurinax uses one of the following breath weapons.</text>
      <text>• Fire Breath. Aurinax exhales fire in a 60-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 21 Dexterity saving throw, taking 66 (12d10) fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Breath Weapons (Recharge 5-6)||12d10</attack>
      <text>• Weakening Breath. Aurinax exhales gas in a 60-foot cone. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 21 Strength saving throw or have disadvantage on Strength-based attack rolls, Strength checks, and Strength saving throws for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Change Shape</name>
      <text>Aurinax magically polymorphs into a humanoid or beast that has a challenge rating no higher than its own, or back into its true form. It reverts to its true form if it dies. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying is absorbed or borne by the new form (Aurinax's choice).</text>
      <text>In a new form, Aurinax retains its alignment, hit points, Hit Dice, ability to speak, proficiencies, Legendary Resistance, lair actions, and Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma scores, as well as this action. Its statistics and capabilities are otherwise replaced by those of the new form, except any class features or legendary actions of that form.</text>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>The dragon can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The dragon regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Detect</name>
      <text>Aurinax makes a Wisdom (Perception) check.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Tail Attack</name>
      <text>Aurinax makes a tail attack.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Wing Attack (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Aurinax beats its wings. Each creature within 10 feet of Aurinax must succeed on a DC 22 Dexterity saving throw or take 15 (2d6 + 8) bludgeoning damage and be knocked prone. Aurinax can then fly up to half its flying speed.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Lair Actions</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>On initiative count 20 (losing initiative ties), the dragon takes a lair action to cause one of the following effects; the dragon can't use the same effect two rounds in a row:</text>
      <text>• The dragon glimpses the future, so it has advantage on attack rolls, ability checks, and saving throws until initiative count 20 on the next round.</text>
      <text>• One creature the dragon can see within 120 feet of it must succeed on a DC 15 Charisma saving throw or be banished to a dream plane, a different plane of existence the dragon has imagined into being. To escape, the creature must use its action to make a Charisma check contested by the dragon's. If the creature wins, it escapes the dream plane. Otherwise, the effect ends on initiative count 20 on the next round. When the effect ends, the creature reappears in the space it left or in the nearest unoccupied space if that one is occupied.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Regional Effects</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>The region containing a legendary gold dragon's lair is warped by the dragon's magic, which creates one or more of the following effects:</text>
      <text>• Whenever a creature that can understand a language sleeps or enters a state of trance or reverie within 6 miles of the dragon's lair, the dragon can establish telepathic contact with that creature and converse with it in its dreams. The creature remembers its conversation with the dragon upon waking.</text>
      <text>• Banks of beautiful, opalescent mist manifest within 6 miles of the dragon's lair. The mist doesn't obscure anything. It assumes haunting forms when evil creatures are near the dragon or other non-evil creatures in the mist, warning such creatures of the danger.</text>
      <text>• Gems and pearls within 1 mile of the dragon's lair sparkle and gleam, shedding dim light in a 5-foot radius.</text>
      <text>If the dragon dies, these effects end immediately.</text>
      </legendary>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 194</description>
    <environment>grassland, forest</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Avi</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (chain shirt)</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Medicine +7, Persuasion +3, Religion +5</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>any two languages</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Control Water</name>
      <text>At will, Avi can control the flow and shape of water in a 5-foot cube, or cause the water to freeze for up to 1 hour.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Divine Eminence</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Avi can expend a spell slot to cause its melee weapon attacks to magically deal an extra 10 (3d6) radiant damage to a target on a hit. This benefit lasts until the end of the turn. If Avi expends a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the extra damage increases by 1d6 for each level above 1st.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Mace</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Mace|+2|1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Avi is a 5th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). Avi has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): cure wounds, guiding bolt, sanctuary</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): lesser restoration, spiritual weapon</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (2 slots): dispel magic, spirit guardians</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy, cure wounds, guiding bolt, sanctuary, lesser restoration, spiritual weapon, dispel magic, spirit guardians</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 32</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Awakened Rat</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>1 (1d4-1)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>2</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>9</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>4</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>The rat has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +0 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 1 piercing damage.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 102</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Barnibus Blastwind</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>10 (13 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>24 (7d8-7)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>9</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Int +5, Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Arcana +5, Insight +6, Investigation +7, Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Dwarvish, Halfling</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Barnibus carries a wand of magic detection. (spell included in spell list below but does not use a slot when cast from the wand)</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Barnibus is a 7th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks) He has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): blade ward, light, mage hand, message</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): comprehend languages, identify, detect magic, mage armor, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, suggestion</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): clairvoyance, sending</text>
      <text>• 4th level (1 slots): locate creature, Otiluke's resilient sphere</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>blade ward, light, mage hand, message, comprehend languages, identify, detect magic, mage armor, shield, detect thoughts, suggestion, clairvoyance, sending, locate creature, Otiluke's resilient sphere</spells>
    <description>Barnibus works for the Watchful Order of Magists and Protectors, investigating crimes that involve the use of magic. He comes across as prickly and secretive, confiding only in Saeth Cromley, a retired sergeant of the City Watch who assists in many of his investigations.
A lifelong bachelor, Barnibus has a small, tidy estate in the Sea Ward that he inherited from his grandmother. When not serving the Watchful Order, he spends his days reading and writing books in his library.
Barnibus uses spells that help him investigate crimes, pry secrets from the minds of suspects, and locate missing persons. He finds violence appalling and would never use his magic to inflict harm on others-even those who harm him.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 195</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Bepis Honeymaker</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (Stronghearthalfling)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>4 (1d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Halfling</languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Halfling Nimbleness</name>
      <text>Bepis can move through a space occupied by a creature of a size larger than him</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Brave</name>
      <text>Bepis has advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <description>Bepis Honeymaker is a honey merchant who was kidnapped from his Trades Ward home a month ago. The Xanathar Guild tried to ransom him back, but seemingly his relatives either couldn't pay or decided not to. (In truth, his rotten in-laws destroyed the ransom notes and told Bepis's wife and children that he ran away with another family.) Ahmaergo has put him to work as a cook but threatens to give him over to the mind flayer Nihiloor every so often.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 112</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Black Viper</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>16 (studded leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>84 (13d8+26)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Dex +7, Int +3</save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +7, Athletics +3, Perception +3, Sleight of hand +7, Stealth +7</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common, Thieves' cant</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Cunning Action</name>
      <text>On each of her turns, the Black Viper can use a bonus action to take the Dash, Disengage, or Hide action.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Evasion</name>
      <text>If the Black Viper is subjected to an effect that allows her to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, she instead takes no damage if she succeeds on the saving throw, and only half damage if she fails. She can't use this trait if she's incapacitated.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sneak Attack (1/Turn)</name>
      <text>The Black Viper deals an extra 14 (4d6) damage when she hits a target with a weapon attack and has advantage on the attack roll, or when the target is within 5 feet of an ally of the Black Viper that isn't incapacitated and the Black Viper doesn't have disadvantage on the attack roll.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The Black Viper makes three attacks with her rapier.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Rapier</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Rapier|+7|1d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hand Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Hand Crossbow|+7|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Uncanny Dodge</name>
      <text>The Black Viper halves the damage that she takes from an attack that hits her. She must be able to see the attacker.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>The Black Viper was a notorious burglar, pickpocket, mugger, and assassin who died a century ago, after a long and nefarious career. Esvele Rosznar, a brash young noble, has recently adopted the Black Viper's persona to lead a secret life of crime. Like many other nobles, Esvele gossips about the Black Viper's exploits to lend credence to the villain's mystique.
The Rosznar family was convicted of slave trading-highly illegal in Waterdeep-and banished over a hundred years ago, but has since returned. The Rosznars' inability to regain the respect they feel they deserve rankles them. The slave trade has continued in Amn and elsewhere, and it's not like other noble houses don't have skeletons in their closets. But just because of a little family squabble that went public, the Rosznar name has been said with a sneer for a century. As part of the family's constant effort to prove this conception wrong and win others' respect, Esvele has been brought up to be the most proper noble possible, partaking in lessons of etiquette, dance, and poise as befits someone of her station.
In her younger days, Esvele openly rebelled, but that behavior led to locked doors at night and house guards watching her every move during the day. So she taught herself how to pick locks, pluck keys from belts and pouches, clamber up walls, and sneak past guards-playing the perfect daughter by day while cutting loose at night. To hide her identity from those she met, she wore a hood and mask, exchanging her fine clothes for the kind of practical clothing her parents would never let her wear.
One of the things Esvele has learned is to embrace the legend of the Black Viper. When she throws back her cloak to reveal the costume she has put together, most folk toss their purses and flee. If that doesn't work, she usually needs only to draw her dagger. Of course, some of the nobles she targets are made of sterner stuff, so Esvele has learned how to fight as well. She knows she's playing a dangerous game, but is satisfied that at least one member of the Rosznar family is earning the respect of Waterdeep's nobility.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 196</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Blinded Troll</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>84 (8d10+40)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>7</int>
    <wis>9</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Giant</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Blinded</name>
      <text>The troll is wearing an eyeless helm, and is blinded.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>The troll has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Regeneration</name>
      <text>The troll regains 10 hit points at the start of its turn. If the troll takes acid or fire damage, this trait doesn't function at the start of the troll's next turn. The troll dies only if it starts its turn with 0 hit points and doesn't regenerate.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The troll makes three attacks: one with its bite and two with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+7|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+7|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Loathsome Limbs</name>
      <text>Whenever the troll takes at least 15 slashing damage at one time, roll a d20 to determine what else happens to it:</text>
      <text>• 1–10: Nothing else happens.</text>
      <text>• 11–14: One leg is severed from the troll if it has any legs left.</text>
      <text>• 15–18: One arm is severed from the troll if it has any arms left.</text>
      <text>• 19–20: The troll is decapitated, but the troll dies only if it can't regenerate. If it dies, so does the severed head.</text>
      <text>If the troll finishes a short or long rest without reattaching a severed limb or head, the part regrows. At that point, the severed part dies. Until then, a severed part acts on the troll's initiative and has its own action and movement. A severed part has AC 13, 10 hit points, and the troll's Regeneration trait.</text>
      <text>A severed leg is unable to attack and has a speed of 5 feet.</text>
      <text>A severed arm has a speed of 5 feet and can make one claw attack on its turn, with disadvantage on the attack roll unless the troll can see the arm and its target. Each time the troll loses an arm, it loses a claw attack.</text>
      <text>If its head is severed, the troll loses its bite attack and its body is blinded unless the head can see it. The severed head has a speed of 0 feet and the troll's Keen Smell trait. It can make a bite attack but only against a target in its space.</text>
      <text>The troll's speed is halved if it's missing a leg. If it loses both legs, it falls prone. If it has both arms, it can crawl. With only one arm, it can still crawl, but its speed is halved. With no arms or legs, its speed is 0, and it can't benefit from bonuses to speed.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 114</description>
    <environment>underdark, mountain, forest, swamp, hill, arctic</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Bonnie</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity (shapechanger)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>14</ac>
    <hp>52 (8d8+16)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +6, Insight +3</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>Bonnie can use its action to polymorph into a Small or Medium humanoid it has seen, or back into its true form. Its statistics, other than its size, are the same in each form. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying isn't transformed. It reverts to its true form if it dies.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Ambusher</name>
      <text>In the first round of a combat, Bonnie has advantage on attack rolls against any creature it surprised.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Surprise Attack</name>
      <text>If Bonnie surprises a creature and hits it with an attack during the first round of combat, the target takes an extra 10 (3d6) damage from the attack.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Bonnie makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+6|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Read Thoughts</name>
      <text>Bonnie magically reads the surface thoughts of one creature within 60 feet of it. The effect can penetrate barriers, but 3 feet of wood or dirt, 2 feet of stone, 2 inches of metal, or a thin sheet of lead blocks it. While the target is in range, Bonnie can continue reading its thoughts, as long as Bonnie's concentration isn't broken (as if concentrating on a spell). While reading the target's mind, Bonnie has advantage on Wisdom (Insight) and Charisma (Deception, Intimidation, and Persuasion) checks against the target.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 20</description>
    <environment>underdark, urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Davil Starsong</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (elf)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>15 (chain shirt)</ac>
    <hp>82 (15d8+15)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save>Dex +5, Cha +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, History +6, Insight +4, Perception +4, Performance +6</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Dwarvish, Elvish</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>Davil has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put him to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage. Or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Davil is a 12th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks) He has the following bard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): mage hand, mending, minor illusion, vicious mockery</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): cure wounds, disguise self, sleep</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): crown of madness, invisibility, suggestion</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): nondetection, sending, tongues</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): compulsion, freedom of movement, polymorph</text>
      <text>• 5th level (2 slots): dominate person, greater restoration</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): Otto's irresistible dance</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1</slots>
    <spells>mage hand, mending, minor illusion, vicious mockery, cure wounds, disguise self, sleep, crown of madness, invisibility, suggestion, nondetection, sending, tongues, compulsion, freedom of movement, polymorph, dominate person, greater restoration, Otto's irresistible dance</spells>
    <description>Within the Waterdeep division of the Black Network, Davil is accorded the title of Master of Opportunities and Negotiations because he's good at sniffing out lucrative business deals, and he makes friends easily.
Like many sun elves, Davil has an affinity for magic and is gifted with the kind of patience that comes with a long life span. Unlike most, he's not the least bit pretentious or aloof. He keeps a room at the Yawning Portal and does all his business in the establishment's taproom. He negotiates deals with grace and aplomb, even while drunk, and uses an elven lute as a spellcasting focus.
Davil can put the characters in contact with other leaders of the Black Network's Waterdeep division, namely Istrid Horn (if they need a loan), Skeemo Weirdbottle (if they need magic), Tashlyn Yafeera (if they need weapons or mercenaries), and Ziraj the Hunter (if they need a highly skilled assassin).
The Doom Raiders. The Doom Raiders were five unscrupulous adventurers who liked to plunder lich lairs (called "dooms" by some). They gave up adventuring to join the Black Network and came to Waterdeep three years ago with plans to establish a Zhentarim foothold in the city. In that time, they have forged alliances with various nobles and guilds and run afoul of others, all the while fending off Harper spies.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 199</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Diatryma</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>19 (3d10+3)</hp>
    <speed>walk 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Beak</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Beak|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 191</description>
    <environment>grassland, hill</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Dining Table Mimic</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity (shapechanger)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>12 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>75 (10d10+20)</hp>
    <speed>walk 15 ft.</speed>
    <str>17</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>5</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>acid</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>The mimic can use its action to polymorph into an object or back into its true, amorphous form. Its statistics are the same in each form. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying isn't transformed. It reverts to its true form if it dies.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Adhesive (Object Form Only)</name>
      <text>The mimic adheres to anything that touches it. A Huge or smaller creature adhered to the mimic is also grappled by it (escape DC 13). Ability checks made to escape this grapple have disadvantage.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>False Appearance (Object Form Only)</name>
      <text>While the mimic remains motionless, it is indistinguishable from an ordinary object.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Grappler</name>
      <text>The mimic has advantage on attack rolls against any creature grappled by it.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The mimic can make three attacks; two with its pseudopods and one with its bite</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Pseudopod</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) bludgeoning damage. If the mimic is in object form, the target is subjected to its Adhesive trait.</text>
      <attack>Pseudopod|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage plus 4 (1d8) acid damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 122</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Drow Gunslinger</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (elf)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>18 (studded leather armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>84 (13d8+26)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Dex +6, Con +4, Wis +3</save>
    <skill>Perception +3, Stealth +8</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Elvish, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>The drow has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put the drow to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Gunslinger</name>
      <text>Being within 5 feet of a hostile creature or attacking at long range doesn't impose disadvantage on the drow's ranged attack rolls with a pistol. In addition, the drow ignores half cover and three-quarters cover when making ranged attacks with a pistol.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, the drow has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The drow makes two shortsword attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+6|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Poisonous Pistol</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 30/90 ft., one target. 9 (1d10 + 4) piercing damage plus 11 (2d10) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Poisonous Pistol|+6|1d10+4</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The drow's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 12) It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: dancing lights</text>
      <text>1/day each: darkness, faerie fire, levitate (self only)</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>dancing lights, darkness, faerie fire, levitate</spells>
    <description>Firearms aren't widely available in the North, but some members of Bregan D'aerthe are equipped with Lantanese pistols, bullets, and packets of smokepowder. These drow gunslingers are expert pistoleers, as skilled with their guns as the best archers are with their bows.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 201</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Durnan</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>16 (elven chain)</ac>
    <hp>144 (17d8+68)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Str +8, Con +8</save>
    <skill>Athletics +8, Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Durnan wields a Greatsword of Sharpness called Grimvault. He wears boots of striding and springing, elven chain, and a ring of spell turning.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Indomitable (Recharges after a Long Rest)</name>
      <text>Durnan can reroll a saving throw that he fails. He must use the new roll.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Spell Turning</name>
      <text>While wearing his ring of spell turning, Durnan has advantage on saving throws against any spell that targets only him (not in an area of effect). If Durnan rolls a 20 for the save and the spell is 7th level or lower, the spell has no effect on him and instead targets the caster, using the slot level, spell save DC, attack bonus, and spellcasting ability of the caster.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Durnan makes four melee weapon attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Grimvault</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) slashing damage. If the target is an object, the hit instead deals 16 slashing damage. If the target is a creature and Durnan rolls a 20 on the d20 for the attack roll, the target takes an extra 14 slashing damage, and Durnan rolls another d20. On a roll of 20, he lops off one of the target's limbs, or some other part of its body if it is limbless.</text>
      <attack>Grimvault|+8|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Double Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 60/240 ft., one target. 13 (2d10 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Double Crossbow|+6|2d10+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Durnan is the owner and proprietor of the Yawning Portal. Although he looks like a middle-aged man whose best days are behind him, Durnan has a sharp mind and can still swing a sword when he must. He doesn't like talking about his past, and he won't reveal anything about his time as an adventurer.
If Durnan has any living family members, he doesn't speak of them. He rarely says two words when one will do. He has a dark sense of humor and spares no pity on those who take the risk of entering Undermountain.
He keeps Grimvault, his magic greatsword, within reach under the bar, and can chop tables in half with it if he so desires. He also can pull out a double crossbow (a heavy crossbow with reduced range that fires two bolts at the same target). Still, if he gets involved in a brawl, he prefers fighting with fists or a well-flung tankard.
Durnan doesn't often venture far from the Yawning Portal, using his employees to run errands for him as needed. If he's feeling charitable, he might gently discourage likable "nobodies" from venturing into Undermountain, if he thinks they wouldn't survive. He can also direct adventurers toward tavern regulars who might be able to help them or offer useful information.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 203</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Elzerina Cassalanter</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>1</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>1</text>
      </trait>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 115</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Embric</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any Non-Lawful Alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (studded leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>65 (10d8+20)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Str +4, Dex +5, Wis +2</save>
    <skill>Athletics +4, Deception +4</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>any two languages</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Embric makes three melee attacks: two with its scimitar and one with its dagger. Or Embric makes two ranged attacks with its daggers.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Scimitar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Scimitar|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Embric adds 2 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, Embric must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 32</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Emmek Frewn</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>4 (1d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Club</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Club|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 42</description>
    <environment>arctic, desert, coastal, grassland, hill, urban, forest</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Engineer</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (Rockgnome)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Good</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>7 (2d6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Arcana +4, History +4</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Gnomish</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Gnome Cunning</name>
      <text>The gnome has advantage on all Intelligence, Wisdom and Charisma saving throws against magic.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) piercing damage. Or Ranged Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+2|1d4</attack>
      <attack>Dagger|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The gnome is a 1st-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence. It has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, mending, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (2 slots): burning hands, disguise self, shield</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>2</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, mending, prestidigitation, burning hands, disguise self, shield</spells>
    <description>An engineer who maintains and operates the Scarlet Marpenoth, a submarine, currently attached below Jarlaxle's flagship the Eyecatcher
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 141</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Fala Lefaliir</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (Woodelf)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Good</alignment>
    <ac>11 (16 with barkskin)</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 35 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Medicine +4, Nature +3, Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Druidic, Common, Elvish</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>Fala has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put them to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Quarterstaff</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit or Melee Weapon Attack +4 to hit with shillelagh, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage, or 6 (1d8 + 2) bludgeoning damage with shillelagh or if wielded with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Quarterstaff|+2|1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Fala is a 4th-level spellcaster. Their spellcasting ability is Wisdom. They have the following druid spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): druidcraft, produce flame, shillelagh</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): entangle, longstrider, speak with animals, thunderwave</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): animal messenger, barkskin</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3</slots>
    <spells>druidcraft, produce flame, shillelagh, entangle, longstrider, speak with animals, thunderwave, animal messenger, barkskin</spells>
    <description>Fala Lefaliir is an outgoing wood elf with long, braided hair. Like the elven god Corellon Larethian, Fala is neither male nor female. If referred to as "he" or "she," Fala gently requests to be addressed by name or as "they." Fala is friends with a member of the Zhentarim named Ziraj, who saved Fala's life. He visits Fala from time to time, and Fala has set aside a room for him on the second floor. Fala runs Correllon's Crown, a herbalist shop in Trollskull Alley
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 32</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Falcon</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>1 (1d4-1)</hp>
    <speed>walk 10 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>5</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>8</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Sight</name>
      <text>The falcon has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Talons</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 1 slashing damage.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 53</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Fel'rekt Lafeen</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (elf)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>18 (studded leather armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>84 (13d8+26)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Dex +6, Con +4, Wis +3</save>
    <skill>Perception +3, Stealth +8</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Elvish, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>Fel'rekt has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put Fel'rekt to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Gunslinger</name>
      <text>Being within 5 feet of a hostile creature or attacking at long range doesn't impose disadvantage on Fel'rekt's ranged attack rolls with a pistol. In addition, Fel'rekt ignores half cover and three-quarters cover when making ranged attacks with a pistol.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, Fel'rekt has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Fel'rekt makes two shortsword attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+6|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Poisonous Pistol</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 30/90 ft., one target. 9 (1d10 + 4) piercing damage plus 11 (2d10) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Poisonous Pistol|+6|1d10+4</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Fel'rekt's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 12) It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: dancing lights</text>
      <text>1/day each: darkness, faerie fire, levitate (self only)</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>dancing lights, darkness, faerie fire, levitate</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 67</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Floon Blagmaar</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>4 (1d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Club</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Club|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 202</description>
    <environment>arctic, desert, coastal, grassland, hill, urban, forest</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Flying Staff</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>17 (5d6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>5</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save>Dex +4</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>7</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Antimagic Susceptibility</name>
      <text>The staff is incapacitated while in the area of an antimagic field. If targeted by dispel magic, the staff must succeed on a Constitution saving throw against the caster's spell save DC or fall unconscious for 1 minute.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>False Appearance</name>
      <text>While the staff remains motionless and isn't flying, it is indistinguishable from a normal staff.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Knife</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Knife|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 152</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Griffon Cavalry Rider</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>17 (half plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>58 (9d8+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Animal handling +3, Athletics +4, Perception +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Lance</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit (with disadvantage against a target within 5 ft.), reach 10 ft., one target. 8 (1d12 + 2) piercing damage, or 11 (1d12 + 5) piercing damage while mounted.</text>
      <attack>Lance|+4|1d12+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage. Or Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      <attack>Dagger|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Feather Fall</name>
      <text>The rider wears a magic ring with which it can cast the feather fall spell on itself once as a reaction to falling. After the spell is cast, the ring becomes nonmagical.</text>
      </action>
    <description>The City Guard is Waterdeep's army, charged with protecting the city's walls and gates, government buildings, harbor, and officials. The City Guard also patrols the roads to Amphail, Goldenfields, and Daggerford.
Ranks in the City Guard. Members of the City Guard have ranks. From lowest to highest, they are:
PrivateSergeant (armar)Lieutenant (civilar)Captain (senior civilar)Multiple command positions, some perennial (Seneschal of Castle Waterdeep, Defender of the Harbor, Master of the North Towers, Master of the South Towers, Master Armorer), others bestowed as needed in wartime (the Lords' Hand and the Lords' Champion)Warden of Waterdeep
The current Warden of Waterdeep is Elminster, who answers to the Open Lord, Laeral Silverhand.
The Griffon Cavalry is a special branch of the City Guard whose members are veteran soldiers trained to fly griffon mounts.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 197</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Grinda Garloth</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>40 (9d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Int +6, Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, History +6</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>any four languages</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Familiars</name>
      <text>Any spellcaster that can cast the find familiar spell (such as an archmage or mage) is likely to have a familiar. The familiar can be one of the creatures described in the spell (see the Player's Handbook) or some other Tiny monster, such as a crawling claw, imp, pseudodragon, or quasit.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Grinda is a 9th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks). Grinda has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): misty step, suggestion</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fireball, fly</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): greater invisibility, ice storm</text>
      <text>• 5th level (1 slots): cone of cold</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield, misty step, suggestion, counterspell, fireball, fly, greater invisibility, ice storm, cone of cold</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 65</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Grum'shar</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (half-orc)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>9 (2d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Arcana +4, History +4</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Orc</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Relentless Endurance</name>
      <text>When reduced to 0 hit points, Grum'shar drops to 1 hit point instead. He can only do this once per long rest.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) piercing damage. Or Ranged Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+2|1d4</attack>
      <attack>Dagger|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Grum'shar is a 1st-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Intelligence. He has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, mending, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (2 slots): burning hands, disguise self, shield</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>2</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, mending, prestidigitation, burning hands, disguise self, shield</spells>
    <description>Apprentice wizards are novice arcane spellcasters who serve more experienced wizards or attend school. They perform menial work, such as cooking and cleaning, in exchange for education in the ways of magic.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 29</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Hester Barch</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>9 (2d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Medicine +4, Religion +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Club</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Club|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Hester is a 1st-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 12, +4 to hit with spell attacks). Hester has following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (3 slots): bless, cure wounds, sanctuary</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>3</slots>
    <spells>light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy, bless, cure wounds, sanctuary</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 83</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Hlam</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>22 (Unarmored Defense)</ac>
    <hp>137 (25d8+25)</hp>
    <speed>walk 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>24</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>21</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Str +5, Dex +12</save>
    <skill>Athletics +5, Religion +7</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>all spoken languages</languages>
    <cr>16</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Evasion</name>
      <text>If Hlam is subjected to an effect that allows him to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, he instead takes no damage if he succeeds on the saving throw, and only half damage if he fails. He can't use this trait if he's incapacitated.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Attacks</name>
      <text>Hlam's unarmed strikes are magical.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unarmored Defense</name>
      <text>While Hlam is wearing no armor and wielding no shield, his AC includes his Wisdom modifier.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Hlam attacks three times using his unarmed strike, darts, or both.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Unarmed Strike</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 12 (1d10 + 7) bludgeoning, magic damage. If the target is a creature, Hlam can choose one of the following additional effects:</text>
      <attack>Unarmed Strike|+12|1d10+7</attack>
      <text>The target must succeed on a DC 18 Strength saving throw or drop one item it is holding (Hlam's choice).</text>
      <text>The target must succeed on a DC 18 Dexterity saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      <text>The target must succeed on a DC 18 Constitution saving throw or be stunned until the end of Hlam's next turn.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dart</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 9 (1d4 + 7) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dart|+12|1d4+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Quivering Palm (Recharge 6)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +12 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. The target must make a DC 18 Constitution saving throw. On a failed save, the target is reduced to 0 hit points. On a successful save, the target takes 55 (10d10) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Quivering Palm (Recharge 6)|+12|10d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Wholeness of Body (Recharges after a Long Rest)</name>
      <text>Hlam regains 60 hit points.</text>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Deflect Missile</name>
      <text>In response to being hit by a ranged weapon attack, Hlam deflects the missile. The damage he takes from the attack is reduced by 1d10 + 27. If the damage is reduced to 0, Hlam catches the missile if it's small enough to hold in one hand and he has a hand free.</text>
      </reaction>
    <reaction>
        <name>Slow Fall</name>
      <text>Hlam reduces the bludgeoning damage he takes from a fall by 100.</text>
      </reaction>
    <legendary>
        <text>Hlam can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Hlam regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Quick Step</name>
      <text>Hlam moves up to his speed without provoking opportunity attacks.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Unarmed Strike (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Hlam makes one unarmed strike.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Invisibility (Costs 3 Actions)</name>
      <text>Hlam becomes invisible until the end of his next turn. The effect ends if Hlam attacks or casts a spell.</text>
      </legendary>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Hlam is a 5th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 18, +10 to hit with spell attacks) He has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): guidance, light, sacred flame, spare the dying</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect evil and good, healing word, sanctuary, shield of faith</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): calm emotions, prayer of healing, silence</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (2 slots): protection from energy, remove curse, sending</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>guidance, light, sacred flame, spare the dying, detect evil and good, healing word, sanctuary, shield of faith, calm emotions, prayer of healing, silence, protection from energy, remove curse, sending</spells>
    <description>This venerable human monk lives in a cave halfway up the side of Mount Waterdeep. Hlam is the grand master of the Order of the Even-Handed, a small monastic group devoted to Tyr. Would-be students periodically visit him to learn the Way of the Sacred Fists, which combines cleric magic and monk training. They usually return to the city confused, bruised, and not inclined to visit again.
In times of great peril, Hlam can be called on to help. Sometimes he offers pearls of wisdom, and sometimes he descends from his cave to set things right with fisticuffs. He can show up at any point in the story as a helpful figure, and the characters can visit him in his cave if they need guidance or training. The Order of the Gauntlet considers him a staunch ally.
Hlam is immune to disease and doesn't require food or water. Although he ages, he suffers none of the frailty of old age.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 204</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Hrabbaz</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (half-orc)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>112 (15d8+45)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Str +8, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +8, Intimidation +4, Perception +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Common, Orc</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Indomitable (2/Day)</name>
      <text>Hrabbaz can reroll a saving throw that he fails. He must use the new roll.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Relentless Endurance (Recharges after a Long Rest)</name>
      <text>When Hrabbaz is reduced to 0 hit points but not killed outright, he drops to 1 hit point instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Extra Damage</name>
      <text>As long as Hrabbaz has more than half his hit points left he deals an extra 3 (1d6) damage on all hits.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Hrabbaz makes three attacks with his morningstar.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Morningstar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (1d8 + 5) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Morningstar|+8|1d8+5</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Hrabbaz is a muscle-bound half-orc with a cleft palate who serves the lord and lady of House Gralhund as a bodyguard. He is well mannered and dresses impeccably-a disarming appearance that belies a murderous heart. Though he has great respect for Lady Yalah Gralhund, he is less fond of her moody husband, and wouldn't be sad to see Orond knocked down a peg or two.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 205</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Istrid Horn</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>117 (18d8+36)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save>Con +5, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Intimidation +4, Religion +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
      <text>Istrid has advantage on saving throws against being poisoned.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Istrid makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Maul</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (2d6 + 1) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Maul|+4|2d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Treasure Sense (3/Day)</name>
      <text>Istrid magically pinpoints precious metals and stones, such as coins and gems, within 60 feet of her.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Istrid is a 9th-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks) She has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light, mending, sacred flame, spare the dying</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): divine favor, guiding bolt, healing word, shield of faith</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): lesser restoration, magic weapon, hold person, silence, spiritual weapon</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): beacon of hope, crusader's mantle, dispel magic, revivify, spirit guardians, water walk</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): banishment, freedom of movement, guardian of faith, stoneskin</text>
      <text>• 5th level (1 slots): flame strike, mass cure wounds, hold monster</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>light, mending, sacred flame, spare the dying, divine favor, guiding bolt, healing word, shield of faith, lesser restoration, magic weapon, hold person, silence, spiritual weapon, beacon of hope, crusader's mantle, dispel magic, revivify, spirit guardians, water walk, banishment, freedom of movement, guardian of faith, stoneskin, flame strike, mass cure wounds, hold monster</spells>
    <description>Istrid is regarded as the Black Network's Master of Trade and Coin in Waterdeep. The shield dwarf operates an illegal lending operation out of a heavily guarded warehouse in the Dock Ward, offering loans to those in need of coin. Her interest rates are comparable to those of her competitors (including noble families of bankers such as the Cassalanters and the Irlingstars), but the penalties for not paying back Istrid's loans are severe.
Istrid worships Vergadain, the dwarven god of wealth and luck. She likes having others indebted to her, and she employs thugs and enforcers to collect on her loans. If those resources prove inadequate, Istrid can call on her old adventuring companions for assistance.
The Doom Raiders. The Doom Raiders were five unscrupulous adventurers who liked to plunder lich lairs (called "dooms" by some). They gave up adventuring to join the Black Network and came to Waterdeep three years ago with plans to establish a Zhentarim foothold in the city. In that time, they have forged alliances with various nobles and guilds and run afoul of others, all the while fending off Harper spies.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 199</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Jalester Silvermane</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>18 (chain mail, Badge of the Watch)</ac>
    <hp>71 (13d8+13)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save>Str +4, Con +3</save>
    <skill>Athletics +4, Survival +4</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Elvish</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Jalester carries a badge of the Watch.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Second Wind (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Jalester can regain 16 (1d10 + 11) hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Jalester makes two weapon attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Longsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) slashing damage, or 7 (1d10 + 2) slashing damage when used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Longsword|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage. Or Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      <attack>Dagger|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Riposte</name>
      <text>When a creature that Jalester can see misses him with a melee attack, he can use his reaction to make a melee weapon attack against that creature. On a hit, the target takes an extra 4 damage from the weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>An earnest man in his mid-twenties, Jalester hails from the distant land of Cormyr, where he earned his spurs working for a mercenary company called the Steel Shadows. A few years ago, Jalester left the Dales and traveled to Waterdeep with several other members of the company, one of whom-Faerrel Dunblade-would become his best friend and lover.
The wizard Elminster befriended the two young men and brought them to the attention of Laeral Silverhand, who put them to work as deputies and spies. Jalester and Faerrel helped the Open Lord expose a plot to overthrow the government, but Faerrel was killed while helping bring the perpetrators to justice. Jalester remained in Waterdeep afterward, becoming one of Laeral's field operatives in the service of Waterdeep and the Lords' Alliance. He has been romantically unattached ever since Faerrel's death but longs again for love.
Treasure. Jalester carries a badge of the Watch (+2 bonus to AC if not using a shield). If the badge is lost or taken from him, it returns to Laeral Silverhand.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 205</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Jandar Chergoba</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (tiefling)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>33 (6d8+6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +4, Persuasion +4, Religion +2</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist>fire</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dark Devotion</name>
      <text>Jandar has advantage on saving throws against being charmed or frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Jandar makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage. Or Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one creature. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      <attack>Dagger|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Jandar's spellcasting ability is Charisma. He can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: thaumaturgy</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Jandar is a 4th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Wisdom. Jandar has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): command, inflict wounds, shield of faith</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): hold person, spiritual weapon</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3</slots>
    <spells>thaumaturgy, light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy, command, inflict wounds, shield of faith, hold person, spiritual weapon</spells>
    <description>As the head chef of Cassalanter Villa, Jandar determines each day's menu and oversees all activity in the kitchen.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 116</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Jarlaxle Baenre</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (elf)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>24 (+3 leather armor, Suave Defense)</ac>
    <hp>123 (19d8+38)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>22</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>19</cha>
    <save>Dex +11, Wis +8</save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +11, Athletics +6, Deception +14, Perception +8, Sleight of hand +11, Stealth +16</skill>
    <passive>18</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Draconic, Dwarvish, Elvish, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>15</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Jarlaxle wears +3 leather armor, a hat of disguise, a bracer of flying daggers, a cloak of invisibility, a knave's eye patch, and a ring of truth telling. He wields a +3 rapier and carries a portable hole and a wand of web. His hat is adorned with a feather of diatryma summoning.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Evasion</name>
      <text>If he is subjected to an effect that allows him to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, Jarlaxle instead takes no damage if he succeeds on the saving throw, and only half damage if he fails. He can't use this trait if he's incapacitated.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>Jarlaxle has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put him to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (1/Day)</name>
      <text>If Jarlaxle fails a saving throw, he can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Master Attuner</name>
      <text>Jarlaxle can attune to up to five magic items, and he can attune to magic items that normally require attunement by a sorcerer, warlock, or wizard.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sneak Attack (1/Turn)</name>
      <text>Jarlaxle deals an extra 24 (7d6) damage when he hits a target with a weapon attack and has advantage on the attack roll, or when the target is within 5 feet of an ally of Jarlaxle's that isn't incapacitated and Jarlaxle doesn't have disadvantage on the attack roll.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Suave Defense</name>
      <text>While Jarlaxle is wearing light or no armor and wielding no shield, his AC includes his Charisma modifier.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>When not wearing his knave's eye patch, Jarlaxle has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Jarlaxle makes three attacks with his +3 rapier or two attacks with daggers created by his bracer of flying daggers.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>+3 Rapier</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +14 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (1d8 + 9) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>+3 Rapier|+14|1d8+9</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Flying Dagger</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 8 (1d4 + 6) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Flying Dagger|+11|1d4+6</attack>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>Jarlaxle can take 2 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Jarlaxle regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Quick Step</name>
      <text>Jarlaxle moves up to his speed without provoking opportunity attacks.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Attack (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Jarlaxle makes one attack with his +3 rapier or two attacks with daggers created by his bracer of flying daggers.</text>
      </legendary>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Jarlaxle's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks) He can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: dancing lights</text>
      <text>1/day each: darkness, faerie fire, levitate (self only)</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>dancing lights, darkness, faerie fire, levitate</spells>
    <description>Jarlaxle is a flamboyant, swashbuckling drow iconoclast. He leads a renegade drow faction called Bregan D'aerthe, made up of disenfranchised male drow, most of them culled from destroyed or disgraced houses. Gifted with a sharp mind, a sense of humor, puissant skill with a blade, and a wealth of useful magic items, Jarlaxle infiltrated the city of Luskan, brought a kind of order to its lawlessness, and declared himself its secret lord.
Jarlaxle likes to weave a tangled web of schemes that leave his enemies baffled-the latest of which is a plan to legitimize Luskan by making it a member of the Lords' Alliance. The city's unsavory reputation has thwarted all previous efforts, and the current leaders of the Lords' Alliance have voiced their opposition to Luskan's admittance. A few have flatly declared that the city will never be welcome in the alliance. Nonetheless, Jarlaxle aims to persuade Laeral Silverhand, the Open Lord of Waterdeep, to champion Luskan's cause-even if that means losing other alliance members in the process. Tying Luskan's fortunes to those of Waterdeep would increase Jarlaxle's political and economic power on the Sword Coast.
Jarlaxle has come to Waterdeep in the guise of an Illuskan human named Zardoz Zord. "Captain Zord" is the master of the Sea Maidens Faire, a carnival that travels up and down the Sword Coast in three ships: the Eyecatcher, the Heartbreaker, and the Hellraiser (all words that describe Jarlaxle). He spends most of his time aboard the Eyecatcher, his personal ship. The other two vessels carry members of the carnival and their parade wagons.
Jarlaxle has forged an alliance with Lantan (an island to the south), and has armed his Bregan D'aerthe lieutenants with Lantanese firearms that rely on magical smokepowder to function. He has also acquired a Lantanese submarine called the Scarlet Marpenoth. This underwater vessel is mounted below the Eyecatcher and kept out of sight. Jarlaxle plans on using the submarine to flee Waterdeep if his scheme unravels.
Jarlaxle's loyalties are to himself first and foremost, and to Bregan D'aerthe secondarily.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 206</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Jenks</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>1</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>1</text>
      </trait>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 63</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Kaevja Cynavern</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (Mulanhuman)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>40 (9d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Int +6, Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, History +6</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Dwarvish, Elvish</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Kaevja carries a yellow elemental gem. As an action she can break the gem releasing an earth elemental under her command.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage. Or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Kaevja is a 9th-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Intelligence. Kaevja has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): misty step, suggestion</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fireball, sending</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): greater invisibility, ice storm</text>
      <text>• 5th level (1 slots): cone of cold</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield, misty step, suggestion, counterspell, fireball, sending, greater invisibility, ice storm, cone of cold</spells>
    <description>Previously a Red Wizard of Thay, this mage now studies magic under Manshoon.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 158</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Kalain</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (half-elf)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (chain shirt)</ac>
    <hp>44 (8d8+8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Dex +4, Wis +3</save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +4, Perception +5, Performance +6</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Common, Elvish</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>Kalain has advantage on saving throws against being charmed and magic can't put her to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Art Imitates Life (3/Day)</name>
      <text>Kalain touches one of her paintings and causes its subject to spring forth, becoming a creature of that kind provided its CR is 3 or lower. The creature appears in an unoccupied space within 5 feet of the painting, which becomes blank. The creature is friendly toward Kalain and hostile toward all others. It rolls initiative to determine when it acts. It disappears after 1 minute, when it is reduced to 0 hit points, or when Kalain dies or falls unconscious.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Taunt (2/Day)</name>
      <text>Kalain can use a bonus action on her turn to target one creature within 30 feet of it. If the target can hear Kalain, the target must succeed on a DC 12 Charisma saving throw or have disadvantage on ability checks, attack rolls, and saving throws until the start of Kalain's next turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Kalain is a 4th-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Charisma. She has the following bard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): friends, mage hand, vicious mockery</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): charm person, healing word, heroism, sleep, thunderwave</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): invisibility, shatter</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3</slots>
    <spells>friends, mage hand, vicious mockery, charm person, healing word, heroism, sleep, thunderwave, invisibility, shatter</spells>
    <description>Kalain, was once a famous Waterdavian painter, but now Kalain's spirit is broken, leading to the onset of madness. She locks herself away, content to let time erode the last of her conscience.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 89</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Krebbyg Masq'il'yr</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (elf)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>18 (studded leather armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>84 (13d8+26)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Dex +6, Con +4, Wis +3</save>
    <skill>Perception +3, Stealth +8</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Elvish, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>Krebbyg has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put Krebbyg to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Gunslinger</name>
      <text>Being within 5 feet of a hostile creature or attacking at long range doesn't impose disadvantage on Krebbyg's ranged attack rolls with a pistol. In addition, Krebbyg ignores half cover and three-quarters cover when making ranged attacks with a pistol.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, Krebbyg has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Krebbyg makes two shortsword attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+6|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Poisonous Pistol</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 30/90 ft., one target. 9 (1d10 + 4) piercing damage plus 11 (2d10) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Poisonous Pistol|+6|1d10+4</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Krebbyg's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 12) It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: dancing lights</text>
      <text>1/day each: darkness, faerie fire, levitate (self only)</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>dancing lights, darkness, faerie fire, levitate</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 67</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Lady Gondafrey</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>52 (7d8+21)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't adamantine</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>False Appearance</name>
      <text>While the gargoyle remains motionless, it is indistinguishable from an inanimate statue.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The gargoyle makes two attacks: one with its bite and one with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Lafy Gondafrey is the result of a magical experiment, a gargoyle that has been imbued with the personality of a human knight of Tyr (god of justice). Manshoon is amused by the creature so keeps it alive and locked in a cell.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 152</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Laeral Silverhand</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Good</alignment>
    <ac>18 (robe of the archmagi)</ac>
    <hp>228 (24d8+120)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>20</wis>
    <cha>19</cha>
    <save>Int +11, Wis +11</save>
    <skill>Arcana +17, History +17, Insight +11, Perception +11, Persuasion +10</skill>
    <passive>21</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Dwarvish, Elvish, Giant, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>17</cr>
    <resist>fire</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Laeral wears a white robe of the archmagi (accounted for in her statistics). She wields a flame tongue longsword.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>While wearing her robe of the archmagi, Laeral has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Laeral makes three attacks with her silver hair and flame tongue, in any combination. She can cast one of her cantrips or 1st-level spells before or after making these attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Silver Hair</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (2d6) force damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 19 Constitution saving throw or be paralyzed for 1 minute. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <attack>Silver Hair|+11|2d6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Flame Tongue</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d8 + 1) slashing damage plus 7 (2d6) fire damage, or 6 (1d10 + 1) slashing damage plus 7 (2d6) fire damage when used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Flame Tongue|+7|1d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spellfire (Recharges after a Long Rest)</name>
      <text>Magical, heatless, silver fire harmlessly erupts from Laeral and surrounds her until she is incapacitated or until she uses an action to quench it. She gains one of the following benefits of her choice, which lasts until the silver fire ends:</text>
      <text>• She can breathe underwater.</text>
      <text>• She can survive without food and water.</text>
      <text>• She is immune to magic that would ascertain her thoughts, truthfulness, alignment, or creature type.</text>
      <text>• She gains resistance to cold damage, and she is unharmed by temperatures as low as -50 degrees Fahrenheit.</text>
      <text>While the silver fire is present, she has the following additional action options:</text>
      <text>• Cast the cure wounds spell. The target regains 1d8 + 5 hit points. After Laeral takes this action, roll a d6. On a roll of 1, the silver fire disappears.</text>
      <text>• Cast the revivify spell without material components. After Laeral takes this action, roll a d6. On a roll of 1-2, the silver fire disappears.</text>
      <text>• Release a 60-foot line of silver fire that is 5 feet wide or a 30-foot cone of silver fire. Objects in the area that aren't being worn or carried take 26 (4d12) fire damage. Each creature in the area must succeed on a DC 21 Dexterity saving throw, taking 26 (4d12) fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. After Laeral takes this action, roll a d6. On a roll of 1-3, the silver fire disappears.</text>
      <attack>Spellfire (Recharges after a Long Rest)||4d12</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Laeral is a 19th-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 21, +13 to hit with spell attacks). Laeral has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light, mage hand, minor illusion, prestidigitation, ray of frost</text>
      <text>• 1st level (0 slots): detect magic, disguise self, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (0 slots): detect thoughts, invisibility, misty step</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fly, sending, tongues</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): banishment, greater invisibility, Otiluke's resilient sphere</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): cone of cold, geas, Rary's telepathic bond</text>
      <text>• 6th level (2 slots): globe of invulnerability, mass suggestion</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): prismatic spray, teleport</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): feeblemind, power word stun</text>
      <text>• 9th level (1 slots): time stop</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>0, 0, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>light, mage hand, minor illusion, prestidigitation, ray of frost, detect magic, disguise self, magic missile, shield, detect thoughts, invisibility, misty step, counterspell, fly, sending, tongues, banishment, greater invisibility, Otiluke's resilient sphere, cone of cold, geas, Rary's telepathic bond, globe of invulnerability, mass suggestion, prismatic spray, teleport, feeblemind, power word stun, time stop</spells>
    <description>Anamanué Laeral Silverhand was born in the Year of the Cowl (765 DR), the fifth of seven daughters of the goddess Mystra. Each of the Seven Sisters is a powerful and ageless beauty with a penchant for arcane magic.
Long ago, Laeral ruled a kingdom called Stornanter and held the title of Witch-Queen of the North. After that, she led a band of adventurers called the Nine. She met and married Khelben Arunsun, who would later become the Blackstaff, the Lord Mage of Waterdeep. After Khelben died, Laeral retired from public life. She resurfaced after the Spellplague and the Sundering, weakened by Mystra's death, rebirth, and withdrawal from the world.
Laeral's magic isn't as great as it once was, though she does her utmost to hide this fact. Only Elminster, her trusted friend and advisor, knows the extent of her decline. Despite her diminished abilities, Laeral remains a formidable, clear-headed wizard with plenty of magic at her disposal.
A few years ago, Dagult Neverember was ousted as Open Lord of Waterdeep. Laeral reluctantly stepped into the vacancy at the request of the Masked Lords, and has served as Waterdeep's Open Lord ever since. Initially overwhelmed by the demands of the nobles and guildmasters, she has settled nicely into her new role. She uses her magic sparingly and relies on trusted advisors and deputies. As time allows, she likes to venture outside the Palace of Waterdeep in disguise, just to clear her head or check up on old friends (and enemies).
Laeral's relationship with Vajra Safahr, the current Blackstaff, has its challenges. For one thing, Laeral is much older, much wiser, and much more powerful than Vajra, whom she views as an insecure child. In addition, Vajra wields the Blackstaff, which has Khelben Arunsun's soul and the souls of all the other Blackstaffs bound inside it. Laeral covets the staff, because it contains all that's left of her husband. Not surprisingly, the two mages avoid each other as much as possible.
In times of great need, Laeral can command Vajra to unleash Force Grey. Until that order is given, Force Grey isn't allowed to conduct operations in Waterdeep, though Laeral's spies tell her that Vajra has secretly activated members of the elite order and sent them on a number of unauthorized missions. Laeral is reluctant to confront Vajra on the matter, and rationalizes her inaction by framing it as a test of Vajra's competence.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 207</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Laiba "Nana" Rosse</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (tiefling)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>33 (6d8+6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +4, Persuasion +4, Religion +2</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist>fire</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dark Devotion</name>
      <text>Laiba has advantage on saving throws against being charmed or frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Laiba makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage. Or Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one creature. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      <attack>Dagger|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Laiba's spellcasting ability is Charisma. She can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: thaumaturgy</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Laiba is a 4th-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Wisdom. Laiba has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): command, inflict wounds, shield of faith</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): hold person, spiritual weapon</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3</slots>
    <spells>thaumaturgy, light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy, command, inflict wounds, shield of faith, hold person, spiritual weapon</spells>
    <description>Laiba Rosse, better known as "Nana," is the caretaker and private tutor for Terenzio and Elzerina, and she does her best to keep track of their every move. Even so, the two often sneak away from her watchful eye. Nana dresses in flowing red robes. She relaxes in the twins' playroom (area C17) when she's not with the children.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 116</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Losser Mirklav</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (Lightfoothalfling)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>31 (9d6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Int +6, Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, History +6</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common, Halfling</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Halfling Nimbleness</name>
      <text>Losser can move through the space of a creature that is a size bigger than him.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Brave</name>
      <text>Losser has advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage. Or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The mage is a 9th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence. The mage has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): misty step, suggestion</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): animate dead, fireball, fly</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): blight, ice storm</text>
      <text>• 5th level (1 slots): cone of cold</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield, misty step, suggestion, animate dead, fireball, fly, blight, ice storm, cone of cold</spells>
    <description>A halfling necromancer who is in possession of the Stone of Golorr. He lives in a cellar complex under a powdered wig shop in the Trades Ward.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 85</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Magister Umbero Zastro</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (half-elf)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>9 (2d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +5, Insight +4, Persuasion +5</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Elvish</languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>Umbero has advantage on saving throws against being charmed and magic can't put him to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Rapier</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d8 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Rapier|+3|1d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>The noble adds 2 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, the noble must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>A handsome, eloquent, and fair-minded half-elf in his thirties. He's known for his finely honed sense of poetic justice and for meting out unconventional punishments.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 82</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Manafret Cherryport</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (Lightfoothalfling)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>31 (9d6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Int +6, Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, History +6</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common, Halfling</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Halfling Nimbleness</name>
      <text>Manafret can move through a space of a Medium or larger creature.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Brave</name>
      <text>Manafret has advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage. Or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The mage is a 9th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence. The mage has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): misty step, suggestion</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fireball, fly</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): greater invisibility, ice storm</text>
      <text>• 5th level (1 slots): cone of cold</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield, misty step, suggestion, counterspell, fireball, fly, greater invisibility, ice storm, cone of cold</spells>
    <description>One of Manshoon's lieutenants
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 149</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Manshoon</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>19 (robe of the archmagi, staff of power)</ac>
    <hp>126 (23d8+23)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>23</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Str +2, Dex +4, Con +3, Int +13, Wis +9, Cha +5</save>
    <skill>Arcana +11, History +11</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Goblin, Infernal, Orc, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>13</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Manshoon wears a black robe of the archmagi and wields a staff of power (both accounted for in his statistics). Roll 2d10 to determine how many charges the staff has remaining.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>While wearing his robe of the archmagi, Manshoon has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Metal Fist</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Metal Fist|+6|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Staff of Power</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) bludgeoning damage, or 6 (1d8 + 2) bludgeoning damage when used with two hands. Manshoon can expend 1 of the staff's charges to deal an extra 3 (1d6) force damage on a hit.</text>
      <attack>Staff of Power|+7|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Manshoon is an 18th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 21, +15 to hit with spell attacks). He has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, lightning bolt, sending</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): fire shield, greater invisibility, polymorph</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): Bigby's hand, scrying, wall of force</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): flesh to stone, globe of invulnerability</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): finger of death, simulacrum</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): feeblemind, mind blank</text>
      <text>• 9th level (1 slots): imprisonment, power word kill</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp, detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield, detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step, counterspell, lightning bolt, sending, fire shield, greater invisibility, polymorph, Bigby's hand, scrying, wall of force, flesh to stone, globe of invulnerability, finger of death, simulacrum, feeblemind, mind blank, imprisonment, power word kill</spells>
    <description>Referred to in this adventure simply as "Manshoon," this clone of the ancient archwizard infiltrated Waterdeep years ago and has been hiding out in Kolat Towers ever since, in the city's Southern Ward.
The original Manshoon was one of the founders of the Zhentarim. Evil to the core, he made enemies all across Faerûn, including other powerful spellcasters such as Khelben Arunsun and Elminster. Fearing that he might be destroyed by his foes, Manshoon magically crafted several clones-but a mishap caused all of them to be awakened at once, whereupon they tried to destroy one another in a series of conflicts that came to be known as the Manshoon Wars.
Now the original Manshoon is dead, and it's widely believed that all his clones were destroyed as well. In fact, at least three are still alive. The one presently in Waterdeep escaped death by hiding out in Undermountain, where he eventually ran afoul of Halaster Blackcloak. After a brief spell duel, Halaster captured Manshoon and amputated his left arm at the elbow for reasons unknown. Manshoon escaped imprisonment and fled Undermountain, taking refuge in the city above. Attempts to magically regenerate his severed limb failed, forcing him to craft an artificial arm and hand for himself.
Manshoon took control of Kolat Towers, a crumbling residence in the Southern Ward that was abandoned years ago by the two wizards who built it. The edifice is surrounded by a magical barrier that has the properties of a wall of force. Manshoon rarely leaves the towers and uses a teleportation circle when he must do so, and thus is never seen entering or leaving.
Manshoon aims to rule Waterdeep and replace the City Watch with Black Network mercenaries that are loyal to him alone. By bribing and blackmailing the Masked Lords, he hopes to oust Laeral Silverhand as Open Lord and take her place, kill the Blackstaff, reduce the Masked Lords to mere vassals, and declare himself the Wizard-King of Waterdeep. Once the city is firmly in his clutches, Manshoon will then turn his attention toward Undermountain, destroy Halaster once and for all, and claim the dungeon's riches.
Manshoon Simulacrum. Manshoon uses the simulacrum spell to create a magical duplicate of himself as needed. He has customized the spell to increase his simulacrum's hit points at the expense of its spellcasting ability.
Manshoon can have only one simulacrum at any given time, and he uses it as a subordinate to command his Zhentarim minions in the field. If his simulacrum is destroyed, Manshoon creates another. Each simulacrum has the statistics of Manshoon, with these changes:
• The simulacrum has no special equipment. Consequently, it has AC 12 and lacks the Magic Resistance trait and the Staff of Power action option.
• It loses all spell slots of 6th level and higher.
• It has a challenge rating of 8 (3,900 XP).
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 209</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Manshoon Simulacrum</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>126 (23d8+23)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>23</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Str +3, Dex +5, Con +4, Int +12, Wis +8, Cha +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +12, History +12</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Goblin, Infernal, Orc, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <action>
        <name>Metal Fist</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Metal Fist|+6|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Manshoon is an 18th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 21, +15 to hit with spell attacks). He has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, lightning bolt, sending</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): fire shield, greater invisibility, polymorph</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): Bigby's hand, scrying, wall of force</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp, detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield, detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step, counterspell, lightning bolt, sending, fire shield, greater invisibility, polymorph, Bigby's hand, scrying, wall of force</spells>
    <description>Manshoon uses the simulacrum spell to create a magical duplicate of himself as needed. He has customized the spell to increase his simulacrum's hit points at the expense of its spellcasting ability.
Manshoon can have only one simulacrum at any given time, and he uses it as a subordinate to command his Zhentarim minions in the field. If his simulacrum is destroyed, Manshoon creates another. Each simulacrum has the statistics of Manshoon, with these changes:
• The simulacrum has no special equipment. Consequently, it has AC 12 and lacks the Magic Resistance trait and the Staff of Power action option.
• It loses all spell slots of 6th level and higher.
• It has a challenge rating of 8 (3,900 XP).
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 208</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Mattrim "Threestrings" Mereg</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (chain shirt)</ac>
    <hp>44 (8d8+8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Dex +4, Wis +3</save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +4, Perception +5, Performance +6</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>any two languages</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Song of Rest</name>
      <text>Mattrim can perform a song while taking a short rest. Any ally who hears the song regains an extra 1d6 hit points if it spends any Hit Dice to regain hit points at the end of that rest. Mattrim can confer this benefit on itself as well.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Taunt (2/Day)</name>
      <text>Mattrim can use a bonus action on its turn to target one creature within 30 feet of it. If the target can hear Mattrim, the target must succeed on a DC 12 Charisma saving throw or have disadvantage on ability checks, attack rolls, and saving throws until the start of Mattrim's next turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Mattrim is a 4th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 12, +4 to hit with spell attacks). It has the following bard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): friends, mage hand, vicious mockery</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): charm person, healing word, heroism, sleep, thunderwave</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): invisibility, shatter</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3</slots>
    <spells>friends, mage hand, vicious mockery, charm person, healing word, heroism, sleep, thunderwave, invisibility, shatter</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 20</description>
    <environment>urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Maxeene</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>19 (3d10+3)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Hooves</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (2d4 + 4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Hooves|+6|2d4+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Maxeene is a talking horse.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 37</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Mechanical Bird</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>1</hp>
    <speed>fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>1</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +0 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d3) piercing damage, and the bird is destroyed by the impact.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+0|1d3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 46</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Melannor Fellbranch</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (half-elf)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Good</alignment>
    <ac>11 (16 with barkskin)</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Medicine +4, Nature +3, Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common, Elvish</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>Melannor has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put him to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Quarterstaff</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit or Melee Weapon Attack +4 to hit with shillelagh, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage, or 6 (1d8 + 2) bludgeoning damage with shillelagh or if wielded with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Quarterstaff|+2|1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Melannor is a 4th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Wisdom. He has the following druid spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): druidcraft, produce flame, shillelagh</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): entangle, longstrider, speak with animals, thunderwave</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): animal messenger, barkskin</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3</slots>
    <spells>druidcraft, produce flame, shillelagh, entangle, longstrider, speak with animals, thunderwave, animal messenger, barkskin</spells>
    <description>Melannor Fellbranch, the friendly but humorless groundskeeper of Phaulkonmere, a compound located one block south of Kolat Towers, is the characters' main contact in the Emerald Enclave
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 36</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Meloon Wardragon</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>143 (22d8+44)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Str +9, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +9, Survival +6</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Deep Speech, telepathy 60 ft.</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Meloon wields Azuredge but can't attune to it, and thus gains none of its benefits.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Indomitable (2/Day)</name>
      <text>Meloon can reroll a saving throw that he fails. He must use the new roll.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Second Wind (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Meloon can regain 20 hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Meloon makes four attacks with Azuredge.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Azuredge</name>
      <text>Melee Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (1d12 + 5) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Azuredge|+9|1d12+5</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Meloon is a handsome, formidable warrior in his prime, who serves the goddess Tymora and loves a good fight. His friends-among them Renaer Neverember and Vajra Safahr-describe him as honest, optimistic, and extraordinarily lucky. Until recently, he was a member of Force Grey and reported directly to the Blackstaff. In recent months, Meloon has spent much of his time at the Yawning Portal.
Three months ago, out of boredom, Meloon accompanied a fledgling band of adventurers on an expedition to Undermountain. There, his luck ran out. While resting in the dungeon, the adventuring party was attacked by monsters unleashed by Xanathar-including a number of intellect devourers. One of the creatures succeeded in magically devouring and replacing Meloon's brain, turning the champion of Tymora into a puppet. After finishing off his unsuspecting companions, Meloon returned to Waterdeep as a Xanathar Guild spy.
The intellect devourer that inhabits Meloon's skull was bred by Nihiloor, a mind flayer in Xanathar's employ. It knows everything Meloon knew, and Meloon behaves much as he did before his descent into Undermountain. He hangs out at the Yawning Portal, tries to bond with adventurers, and offers a helping hand whenever doing so feels appropriate. The intellect devourer's primary goals are to steer adventurers away from Undermountain and get them to undertake quests that further the aims of Xanathar. Such quests usually involve the eradication of Xanathar's enemies, and Meloon is all too eager to fight alongside those who fall for his ruse.
Adjusted Game Statistics. If Meloon is killed and raised from the dead, his true self is restored and his statistics change as follows:
• Meloon is neutral good.
• He loses his telepathy, and his ability to speak and understand Deep Speech.
• He can attune to Azuredge (see appendix A).
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 210</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Mirt</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Good</alignment>
    <ac>16 (bracers of defense)</ac>
    <hp>153 (18d8+72)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Dex +8, Wis +5</save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +8, Athletics +8, Perception +5, Persuasion +6, Stealth +8</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Mirt wears bracers of defense and a ring of regeneration. He wields a +1 longsword and a +1 dagger.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Brute</name>
      <text>A melee weapon deals one extra die of its damage when Mirt hits with it (included in the attacks below).</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Evasion</name>
      <text>If he is subjected to an effect that allows him to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, Mirt instead takes no damage if he succeeds on the saving throw, and only half damage if he fails. He can't use this trait if he's incapacitated.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sneak Attack (1/Turn)</name>
      <text>Mirt deals an extra 14 (4d6) damage when he hits a target with a weapon attack and has advantage on the attack roll, or when the target is within 5 feet of an ally of Mirt's that isn't incapacitated and Mirt doesn't have disadvantage on the attack roll.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Mirt makes three attacks: two with his +1 longsword and one with his +1 dagger.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>+1 Longsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 14 (2d8 + 5) slashing damage, or 16 (2d10 + 5) slashing damage when used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>+1 Longsword|+9|2d8+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>+1 Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (2d4 + 5) piercing damage. Or Ranged Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 7 (1d4 + 5) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>+1 Dagger|+9|2d4+5</attack>
      <attack>+1 Dagger|+9|1d4+5</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Mirt adds 2 to his AC against one melee attack that would hit him. To do so, Mirt must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>Once known as Mirt the Merciless and the Old Wolf, Mirt made a fortune and carved out a reputation as an adventurer and philanderer. Today, an older and wiser Mirt serves as one of the Masked Lords, a Harper, and a close advisor to Laeral Silverhand. The years have not worn him down, and though he has grown soft in the flesh, he remains deceptively strong, vigorous, and clear of mind. Mirt has survived the passing of centuries by means of magic, and of all the Masked Lords, he is the least concerned with concealing his identity.
Despite his prodigious girth, Mirt can move with good speed when he must, and he hasn't let his adventuring skills wither. His wife, Asper, passed away several years ago, and his rambling mansion has seen better days. Mirt spends his days embroiled in politics and whiles away his nights in drink and debauchery.
Treasure. Mirt has access to magic items of all kinds, but keeps only a few on his person. He can equip himself with other magic items as the need arises.
In addition to his other magical gear, Mirt owns a Lord's ensemble (see appendix A). He dons the ensemble only when meeting with other Masked Lords in an official capacity.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 211</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Nar'l Xibrindas</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (elf)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>45 (10d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, Deception +5, Perception +4, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Elvish, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>7</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>Nar'l has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put Nar'l to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, Nar'l has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Nar'l carries a vial containing three doses of eyescratch, a contact poison. A creature that comes into contact with the poison must succeed on a DC 14 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned for 1 hour and blinded while poisoned in this way. A lesser restoration spell or similar magic ends the effect.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Staff</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d6 + 1) bludgeoning damage + 3 (1d6) poison damage, or 3 (1d8 + 1) bludgeoning damage + 3 (1d6) poison damage if used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Staff|+2|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Summon Demon (1/Day)</name>
      <text>Nar'l magically summons a quasit, or attempts to summon a shadow demon with a 50 percent chance of success. The summoned demon appears in an unoccupied space within 60 feet of its summoner, acts as an ally of its summoner, and can't summon other demons. It remains for 10 minutes, until it or its summoner dies, or until its summoner dismisses it as an action.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Nar'l's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma. He can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: dancing lights</text>
      <text>1/day each: darkness, faerie fire, levitate (self only)</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Nar'l is a 10th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Intelligence. Nar'l has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): mage hand, minor illusion, poison spray, ray of frost</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): mage armor, magic missile, shield, witch bolt</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): alter self, misty step, web</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): sending, lightning bolt</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): Evard's black tentacles, greater invisibility</text>
      <text>• 5th level (2 slots): cloudkill</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>dancing lights, darkness, faerie fire, levitate, mage hand, minor illusion, poison spray, ray of frost, mage armor, magic missile, shield, witch bolt, alter self, misty step, web, sending, lightning bolt, Evard's black tentacles, greater invisibility, cloudkill</spells>
    <description>Xanathar's advisor is a nervous and conniving male drow named Nar'l Xibrindas. Nar'l's house was wiped out long ago, but he and his elder brother Soluun survived and joined Bregan D'aerthe. A year ago, Nar'l was given the difficult task of infiltrating the Xanathar Guild and getting as close to the beholder as possible. Not only did he succeed, but in the course of gaining Xanathar's trust, he managed to convince the beholder to eliminate its other advisors. The beholder's paranoia will eventually cause Xanathar to question the drow's loyalty, though, and Nar'l has become increasingly worried about his future. If forced to decide between himself and Bregan D'aerthe, he'll choose the former and betray his drow allies to save his own skin.
Xanathar is aware that something is off with Nar'l, and recently assigned him a grell bodyguard. The grell has instructions to dispose of Nar'l at the first sign of disloyalty.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 211</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Nat</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>1</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>1</text>
      </trait>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 63</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Nihiloor</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (breastplate)</ac>
    <hp>71 (13d8+13)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>19</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save>Int +7, Wis +6, Cha +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +7, Deception +6, Insight +6, Perception +6, Persuasion +6, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Deep Speech, Undercommon, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>7</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Nihiloor has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Tentacles</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 15 (2d10 + 4) psychic damage. If the target is Medium or smaller, it is grappled (escape DC 15) and must succeed on a DC 15 Intelligence saving throw or be stunned until this grapple ends.</text>
      <attack>Tentacles|+7|2d10+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Extract Brain</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one incapacitated humanoid grappled by Nihiloor. The target takes 55 (10d10) piercing damage. If this damage reduces the target to 0 hit points, Nihiloor kills the target by extracting and devouring its brain.</text>
      <attack>Extract Brain|+7|10d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Mind Blast (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>Nihiloor magically emits psychic energy in a 60-foot cone. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 15 Intelligence saving throw or take 22 (4d8 + 4) psychic damage and be stunned for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <attack>Mind Blast (Recharge 5-6)||4d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting (Psionics)</name>
      <text>Nihiloor's innate spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 15). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no components:</text>
      <text>At will: detect thoughts, levitate</text>
      <text>1/day each: dominate monster, plane shift (self only)</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>detect thoughts, levitate, dominate monster, plane shift</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 212</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Nimblewright</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>45 (6d8+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>8</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save>Dex +6</save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +8, Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>understands one language known to its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, frightened, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The nimblewright has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Weapons</name>
      <text>The nimblewright's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Repairable</name>
      <text>As long as it has at least 1 hit point remaining, the nimblewright regains 1 hit point when a mending spell is cast on it.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sure-Footed</name>
      <text>The nimblewright has advantage on Strength and Dexterity saving throws made against effects that would knock it prone.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The nimblewright makes three attacks: two with its rapier and one with its dagger.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Rapier</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (1d8 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Rapier|+6|1d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d4 + 4) piercing damage. Or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 6 (1d4 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+6|1d4+4</attack>
      <attack>Dagger|+6|1d4+4</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>The nimblewright adds 2 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, the nimblewright must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>A nimblewright is a magical construct created to serve as a guard or assassin. Composed predominantly of lightweight wood and powered by magic, it can pass for humanoid while wearing clothing. Some nimblewrights wear plain clothing, while others are clad in flashier attire. A nimblewright is emotionless, its face frozen in whatever expression was given to it by its creator.
Duelist. A nimblewright moves like a dancer and fights like a swashbuckler, using dodges and parries to avoid damage while deftly skewering its foes.
Constructed Nature. A nimblewright doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep. Damage it takes can be repaired with mending spells, but a nimblewright reduced to 0 hit points is permanently destroyed.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 212</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Noska Ur'gray</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>11 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>32 (5d8+10)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Intimidation +2</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>Noska has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of Noska's allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
      <text>Noska has advantage on saving throws against poison and resistance to poison damage.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Difficult Climber</name>
      <text>Noska has disadvantage on Strength checks made to climb, due to his disability.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Noska makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Mace</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 5 (1d6 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Mace|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Heavy Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, range 100/400 ft., one target. 5 (1d10) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Heavy Crossbow|+2|1d10</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Noska is a ruthless enforcer in the Xanathar Guild. A green slime in Undermountain dissolved his left hand and forearm, and the lost appendage has been replaced with a heavy crossbow that attaches to the stump.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 213</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Obaya Uday</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (chain shirt)</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Medicine +7, Persuasion +3, Religion +5</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>any two languages</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Divine Eminence</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Obaya can expend a spell slot to cause its melee weapon attacks to magically deal an extra 10 (3d6) radiant damage to a target on a hit. This benefit lasts until the end of the turn. If Obaya expends a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the extra damage increases by 1d6 for each level above 1st.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Mace</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Mace|+2|1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Obaya is a 5th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). Obaya has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): cure wounds, guiding bolt, sanctuary</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): lesser restoration, spiritual weapon</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (2 slots): dispel magic, spirit guardians</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy, cure wounds, guiding bolt, sanctuary, lesser restoration, spiritual weapon, dispel magic, spirit guardians</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 20</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Obliteros</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>126 (11d12+55)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., swim 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Aquan</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Blood Frenzy</name>
      <text>Obliteros has advantage on melee attack rolls against any creature that doesn't have all its hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Water Breathing</name>
      <text>Obliteros can breathe only underwater.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 22 (3d10 + 6) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+9|3d10+6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>An awakened Giant Shark who inhabits the harbor around Mistshore.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 66</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Orond Gralhund</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (Tethyrianhuman)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (breastplate)</ac>
    <hp>9 (2d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +5, Insight +4, Persuasion +5</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Rapier</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d8 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Rapier|+3|1d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Orond adds 2 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, Orond must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>The Gralhunds are nobles who trade in arms and mercenaries, and whose family motto is "We see both sides." Orond is the patriarch, but he's not a quick-thinking or cultured sort-and deep down, he knows it. He leaves most of the plotting and socializing to his wife, Yalah, to whom he is devoted.
When several of the Masked Lords were assassinated in quick succession some years ago, Lord Gralhund had expected his wife to fill one of the vacancies. That never happened, though, despite many promises and bribes. After she was passed over, Orond became insanely angry, and he has remained that way ever since.
Less than a year ago, the Gralhunds were approached by agents of the Zhentarim loyal to Manshoon, and the nobles formed an alliance with them. House Gralhund gives the Zhents coin and allows them to use the family's noble villa as a refuge. In exchange, the house reaps all the benefits that the Black Network offers, including intelligence that its spies have gathered. So while the Zhents use House Gralhund as a shield, the Gralhunds are using the Zhents to ascertain the identities and weaknesses of the Masked Lords.
Orond doesn't fully grasp how entwined the Black Network and his family have become-it is now next to impossible to separate one from the other. It's no secret in Waterdeep that the Black Network has firmly rooted itself in House Gralhund. But what's not generally known is that the Zhents in House Gralhund are agents of Manshoon. Neither Orond nor any other member of his family knows about the wizard's clone. As far as Orond and his wife are concerned, the local leaders of the Black Network (with Urstul Floxin chief among them) reside with them in the family villa.
Orond is a short, stocky man who dresses well and is easy on the eyes. When he opens his mouth, his boorish nature, inflated sense of self-importance, fragile ego, and despicable opinions about "the common rabble" come to the fore, and his charm quickly dissipates. When not in his wife's company, he is prone to excessive boasting and temper tantrums. When he must speak to strangers, he keeps his half-orc bodyguard Hrabbaz close by, for fear that others might attack and rob him at any moment. While in Yalah's presence, Orond becomes an altogether different person: quiet, almost timid, and happy to let his wife have the spotlight.
Orond relies on Yalah to manage the Zhentarim. He spends his days watching mercenaries train, paying bills, and ranting about the cost of doing business in the city. Although he is human, Orond was born with a tiefling's tail. The tail was amputated when he was a young boy, but the scar on his backside remains.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 213</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Osvaldo Cassalanter</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>fiend (devil)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>85 (10d8+40)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Con +7, Wis +4, Cha +5</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>8</passive>
    <languages>Infernal, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist>cold; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't silvered</resist>
    <immune>fire, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Devil's Sight</name>
      <text>Magical darkness doesn't impede Osvaldo's darkvision.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Osvaldo has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Osvaldo makes two attacks with its chains.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Chain</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) slashing damage. The target is grappled (escape DC 14) if Osvaldo isn't already grappling a creature. Until this grapple ends, the target is restrained and takes 7 (2d6) piercing damage at the start of each of its turns.</text>
      <attack>Chain|+8|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Animate Chains (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>Up to four chains Osvaldo can see within 60 feet of it magically sprout razor-edged barbs and animate under Osvaldo's control, provided that the chains aren't being worn or carried.</text>
      <text>Each animated chain is an object with AC 20, 20 hit points, resistance to piercing damage, and immunity to psychic and thunder damage. When Osvaldo uses Multiattack on its turn, it can use each animated chain to make one additional chain attack. An animated chain can grapple one creature of its own but can't make attacks while grappling. An animated chain reverts to its inanimate state if reduced to 0 hit points or if Osvaldo is incapacitated or dies.</text>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Unnerving Mask</name>
      <text>When a creature Osvaldo can see starts its turn within 30 feet of Osvaldo, Osvaldo can create the illusion that it looks like one of the creature's departed loved ones or bitter enemies. If the creature can see Osvaldo, it must succeed on a DC 14 Wisdom saving throw or be frightened until the end of its turn.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 124</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Ott Steeltoes</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>9 (2d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +2, Religion +0</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
      <text>Ott has advantage on saving throws against poison and resistance to poison damage.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Dark Devotion</name>
      <text>The cultist has advantage on saving throws against being charmed or frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Scimitar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 4 (1d6 + 1) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Scimitar|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>The dwarf Ott Steeltoes has the nerve-wracking task of tending to Xanathar's pet fish, Sylgar. In his spare time, he worships Zuggtmoy, the demon queen of fungi, and cultivates mushrooms, spores, and molds. He wears a leather skullcap stitched with fake beholder eyestalks.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 214</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Panopticus Wizard</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>9 (2d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Arcana +4, History +4</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
      <text>The dwarf has advantage on saving throws against poison and resistance to poison damage.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) piercing damage. Or Ranged Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+2|1d4</attack>
      <attack>Dagger|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The Dwarf is a 1st-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence. It has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, mending, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (2 slots): burning hands, disguise self, shield</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>2</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, mending, prestidigitation, burning hands, disguise self, shield</spells>
    <description>This bald-headed and tattooed dwarf operates Xanathar's "panopticus" magical surveillance system.
Apprentice wizards are novice arcane spellcasters who serve more experienced wizards or attend school. They perform menial work, such as cooking and cleaning, in exchange for education in the ways of magic.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 106</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Remallia Haventree</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (elf)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Good</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>66 (12d8+12)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>18</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save>Int +8, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +8, Deception +7, History +8, Persuasion +7</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Dwarvish, Elvish, Halfling</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Remallia has a Figurine of Wondrous Power, Silver Raven.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>Remallia has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put her to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Arcane Ward</name>
      <text>Remallia has a magical ward that has 30 hit points. Whenever she takes damage, the ward takes the damage instead. If the ward is reduced to 0 hit points, Remallia takes any remaining damage. When Remallia casts an abjuration spell of 1st level or higher, the ward regains a number of hit points equal to twice the level of the spell. This applies to any of the following spells she casts: alarm. mage armor, shield, arcane lock, counterspell, dispel magic, banishment, stoneskin, globe of invulnerability and symbol</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+6|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Remallia is a 13th-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 16, +8 to hit with spell attacks). She has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): dancing lights, mage hand, mending, message, ray of frost</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): alarm, mage armor, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): arcane lock, invisibility</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, dispel magic, fireball</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): banishment, stoneskin</text>
      <text>• 5th level (2 slots): cone of cold, wall of force</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): flesh to stone, globe of invulnerability</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): symbol, teleport</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>dancing lights, mage hand, mending, message, ray of frost, alarm, mage armor, magic missile, shield, arcane lock, invisibility, counterspell, dispel magic, fireball, banishment, stoneskin, cone of cold, wall of force, flesh to stone, globe of invulnerability, symbol, teleport</spells>
    <description>Remallia (Remi to her friends) is the lady of House Ulbrinter and a guiding light for the Harpers in Waterdeep
She became an active force for good in the city after assassins killed her husband, Arthagast Ulbrinter, and destroyed his remains. A sun elf, she has two adult children (a half-elf son named Arthius, who is studying music in Silverymoon, and a half-elf daughter named Serenore, who lives on the Moonshae island of Alaron with her husband and daughter). Lady Haventree retains a handful of loyal servants and spies.
Remi holds secret Harper meetings in her villa, which is warded by all manner of spells. She uses a silver raven figurine of wondrous power to deliver messages to Harper spies scattered throughout the city.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 214</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Renaer Neverember</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (Illuskanhuman)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Good</alignment>
    <ac>17 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>66 (12d8+12)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +8, Athletics +5, Persuasion +6</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Lightfooted</name>
      <text>The swashbuckler can take the Dash or Disengage action as a bonus action on each of its turns.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Suave Defense</name>
      <text>While the swashbuckler is wearing light or no armor and wielding no shield, its AC includes its Charisma modifier.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The swashbuckler makes three attacks: one with a dagger and two with its rapier.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d4 + 4) piercing damage. Or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 6 (1d4 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+6|1d4+4</attack>
      <attack>Dagger|+6|1d4+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Rapier</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (1d8 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Rapier|+6|1d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Renaer is the estranged son of Dagult Neverember, the former Open Lord of Waterdeep and the current Lord of Neverwinter. Father and son detest one another, and Renaer is least happy when he finds himself forced to deal with some mess his father left behind. Qualities that both share include striking good looks, a love of drink, and a flair for diplomacy. What Renaer lacks is his father's belligerence, ill temper, and bad judgment.
Renaer lives off a sizable inheritance left to him by his mother. Approaching middle age, he has given up adventuring and settled down somewhat. As a Harper, he spends a lot of time defending Waterdavians against those who, like his father, would deprive them of their coin and rights. He owns Neverember House, a four-story residence in the Sea Ward. Renaer spends as little time there as possible, however, since it's constantly under surveillance by spies loyal to his father. His friends have an open invitation to use the house as they please, while Renaer spends most of his free time in taverns and festhalls.
Some believe that Renaer's estrangement from his father is nothing but an act, and that anyone who bears the Neverember name is an enemy of Waterdeep. Renaer just shakes his head at such accusations and gets on with his life. He has many powerful friends to watch his back.
Swashbuckler. Swashbucklers are charming ne'er-do-wells who live by their own codes of honor. They crave notoriety, often indulge in romantic trysts, and eke out livings as pirates and corsairs, rarely staying in one place for too long.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 215</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Rishaal the Page-Turner</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dragonborn)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>40 (9d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Int +6, Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, History +6</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Dwarvish, Elvish</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist>fire</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Breath Weapon</name>
      <text>Rishaal can use his action to exhale a 15-foot cone of fire (but can't do this again until he finishes a short or long rest); each creature in the cone must make a DC 10 Dexterity saving throw, taking 2d6 fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage. Or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Rishaal is a 9th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Intelligence. Rishaal has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): misty step, suggestion</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fireball, fly</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): greater invisibility, ice storm</text>
      <text>• 5th level (1 slots): cone of cold</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield, misty step, suggestion, counterspell, fireball, fly, greater invisibility, ice storm, cone of cold</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 33</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Saeth Cromley</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (Illuskanhuman)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>17 (splint armor)</ac>
    <hp>58 (9d8+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +5, Perception +2, Intimidation +4</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Saeth makes two longsword attacks. If he has a shortsword drawn, he can also make a shortsword attack.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Longsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) slashing damage, or 8 (1d10 + 3) slashing damage if used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Longsword|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Heavy Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, range 100/400 ft., one target. 6 (1d10 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Heavy Crossbow|+3|1d10+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Saeth Cromley is a retired sergeant of the City Watch, a likable fellow with a sharp, sarcastic wit. He occasionally comes out of retirement at the request of Barnibus Blastwind, and he assists the mage in investigating unusual crimes in the city. Cromley helps Barnibus relate to the common folk, and he is good at coaxing information out of them. Though Cromley was once a strict proponent of Watch regulations and dress codes, he has grown a bit lax in both matters now that he's officially retired.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 216</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Samara Strongbones</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (halfling)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>27 (6d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +5, Insight +4, Investigation +5, Perception +6, Persuasion +5, Sleight of hand +4, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>any two languages, Halfling</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Cunning Action</name>
      <text>On each of its turns, Samara can use a bonus action to take the Dash, Disengage, or Hide action.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sneak Attack (1/Turn)</name>
      <text>Samara deals an extra 7 (2d6) damage when it hits a target with a weapon attack and has advantage on the attack roll, or when the target is within 5 feet of an ally of Samara that isn't incapacitated and Samara doesn't have disadvantage on the attack roll.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Halfling Nimbleness</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; can move through a space of a Medium or larger creature.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Brave</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; has advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Samara makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hand Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Hand Crossbow|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 104</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sergeant</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>16 (chain shirt, shield)</ac>
    <hp>11 (2d8+2)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) piercing damage, or 5 (1d8 + 1) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Spear|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 197</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Shard Shunner</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (halfling, shapechanger)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>27 (6d6+6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +2, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Halfling, Thieves' cant</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't silvered</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft. (rat form only)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>The Shard Shunner can use their action to polymorph into a rat-humanoid hybrid or into a giant rat, or back into their true form, which is humanoid. Their statistics, other than their size, are the same in each form. Any equipment they are wearing or carrying isn't transformed. They revert to their true form if they die.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>The Shard Shunner has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Halfling Nimbleness</name>
      <text>The Shard Shunner can move through the space of creatures that is of a size larger than them.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Brave</name>
      <text>The Shard Shunner has advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>The Shard Shunner makes two attacks, only one of which can be a bite.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite (Rat or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage. If the target is a humanoid, it must succeed on a DC 11 Constitution saving throw or be cursed with wererat lycanthropy.</text>
      <attack>Bite (Rat or Hybrid Form Only)|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hand Crossbow (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Hand Crossbow (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description> Member of the Shard Shunner gang hired by Emmek Frewn to disrupt the characters' running of the Trollskull Manor
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 42</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Skeemo Weirdbottle</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (gnome)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>72 (16d6+16)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Int +6, Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, History +6, Perception +4, Performance +5</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Gnomish, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Gnome Cunning</name>
      <text>Skeemo has advantage on Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saving throws against magic.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage. Or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Skeemo is a 9th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks) He has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): misty step, suggestion</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fireball, fly</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): greater invisibility, ice storm</text>
      <text>• 5th level (1 slots): cone of cold</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield, misty step, suggestion, counterspell, fireball, fly, greater invisibility, ice storm, cone of cold</spells>
    <description>Skeemo became the Master of Magic for the Black Network in Waterdeep, setting up a cover in the Trades Ward in the form of a cramped little shop called Weirdbottle's Concoctions. Most of his potions and elixirs are nonmagical, but he crafts magical ones for his Zhent friends.
Skeemo can add "sellout" to his credentials, his services having been bought by House Gralhund and the Black Network operatives loyal to Manshoon. The rock gnome uses paper birds (see appendix A) to send messages both to his new friends and his old ones.
The Doom Raiders. The Doom Raiders were five unscrupulous adventurers who liked to plunder lich lairs (called "dooms" by some). They gave up adventuring to join the Black Network and came to Waterdeep three years ago with plans to establish a Zhentarim foothold in the city. In that time, they have forged alliances with various nobles and guilds and run afoul of others, all the while fending off Harper spies.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 200</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Soluun Xibrindas</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (elf)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>18 (studded leather armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>84 (13d8+26)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Dex +6, Con +4, Wis +3</save>
    <skill>Perception +3, Stealth +8</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Elvish, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>Soluun has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put Soluun to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Gunslinger</name>
      <text>Being within 5 feet of a hostile creature or attacking at long range doesn't impose disadvantage on Soluun's ranged attack rolls with a pistol. In addition, Soluun ignores half cover and three-quarters cover when making ranged attacks with a pistol.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, Soluun has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Equipment</name>
      <text>Four packets of smokepowder and a pouch containing 20 pistol bullets</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Boots of Elvenkind</name>
      <text>Whilst wearing these boots Soluun's steps make no sound and he has advantage on any Dexterity (Stealth) checks that rely on moving silently.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Soluun makes two scimitar attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Scimitar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Scimitar|+6|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Poisonous Pistol</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 30/90 ft., one target. 9 (1d10 + 4) piercing damage plus 11 (2d10) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Poisonous Pistol|+6|1d10+4</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Soluun's spellcasting ability is Charisma. It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: dancing lights</text>
      <text>1/day each: darkness, faerie fire, levitate (self only)</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>dancing lights, darkness, faerie fire, levitate</spells>
    <description>Soluun is a sadistic, fanatical bully who is fiercely loyal to Bregan D'aerthe, and to Jarlaxle in particular. His younger brother, Nar'l, has infiltrated the Xanathar Guild. Soluun considers Nar'l a weakling who turned to arcane magic by way of compensation, and he has never had much faith in his brother or his abilities.
Soluun has a burning hatred of surface elves and halfelves, having been taught from a young age to kill them as opportunity permits. When not engaged in a Bregan D'aerthe operation, Soluun spends his nights haunting the darkened streets and alleys of Waterdeep, looking for solitary elves or half-elves to pick off. He conceals his nighttime escapades as well as he can, but Jarlaxle, Fel'rekt, and Krebbyg know what he's up to.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 202</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Squiddly</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (tiefling)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>1</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>1</text>
      </trait>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 63</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Swarm of Books</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>swarm of Medium constructs</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>22 (5d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>5</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>4</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, prone, restrained, stunned, grappled</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Swarm</name>
      <text>The swarm can occupy another creature's space and vice versa, and the swarm can move through any opening large enough for a Tiny book. The swarm can't regain hit points or gain temporary hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 0 ft., one creature in the swarm's space. 5 (2d4) bludgeoning damage, or 2 (1d4) bludgeoning damage if the swarm has half of its hit points or fewer.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+4|2d4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Animated books which form a swarm when disturbed
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 156</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Swarm of Mechanical Spiders</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>swarm of Medium constructs</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>22 (5d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., climb 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>3</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>7</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>8</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable>lightning</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, charmed, frightened, grappled, paralyzed, petrified, prone, restrained, stunned, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 10 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Constructed Nature</name>
      <text>The swarm doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Swarm</name>
      <text>The swarm can occupy another creature's space and vice versa, and the swarm can move through any opening large enough for a Tiny insect. The swarm can't regain hit points or gain temporary hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Spider Climb</name>
      <text>The swarm can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without needing to make an ability check.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Web Sense</name>
      <text>While in contact with a web, the swarm knows the exact location of any other creature in contact with the same web.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Web Walker</name>
      <text>The swarm ignores movement restrictions caused by webbing.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bites</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 0 ft., one target in the swarm's space. 10 (4d4) piercing damage, or 5 (2d4) piercing damage if the swarm has half of its hit points or fewer.</text>
      <attack>Bites|+3|4d4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>A swarm of tiny constructed spiders which attack anyone messing with Jarlaxle's chest aboard the Scarlet Marpenoth
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 143</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sylgar</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>1 (1d4-1)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>2</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>9</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>7</wis>
    <cha>2</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>8</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Water Breathing</name>
      <text>Sylgar can breathe only underwater.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 1 piercing damage.</text>
      </action>
    <description>Xanathar's pet fish.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 220</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Talisolvanar "Tally" Fellbranch</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (half-elf)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Good</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>4 (1d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Elvish</languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>Tally has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put him to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Club</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Club|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>A male half-elf carpenter and woodcarver.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 32</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Tashlyn Yafeera</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>149 (23d8+46)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Str +8, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +8, Intimidation +5, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Indomitable (2/Day)</name>
      <text>Tashlyn can reroll a saving throw that she fails. She must use the new roll.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Second Wind (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Tashlyn can regain 20 hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Extra Damage</name>
      <text>Tashlyn deals an extra 7 (2d6) damage to every hit if she has more than half her hit points remaining.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Tashlyn makes three attacks with her greatsword or her shortbow.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Greatsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Greatsword|+8|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow|+6|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Tashlyn is Master of Arms and Mercenaries for the Waterdeep Zhentarim. In this role, she provides armor, weapons, and training to sellswords on the Black Network's payroll.
Tashlyn has established a useful cover by serving as a bodyguard to Vorondar Levelstone, a dwarf magister stationed at the South Gate. She likes the dwarf and has earned his confidence, allowing her to reach the rank of captain in the City Guard. In that position, she watches over traffic that passes through the gate-and ensures that her associates in the Black Network can come and go freely.
Born to a well-off family in Calimshan, Tashlyn has an unfettered sense of superiority. Quick to anger, she hates to back down from a fight. She respects anyone who can best her in melee combat.
The Doom Raiders. The Doom Raiders were five unscrupulous adventurers who liked to plunder lich lairs (called "dooms" by some). They gave up adventuring to join the Black Network and came to Waterdeep three years ago with plans to establish a Zhentarim foothold in the city. In that time, they have forged alliances with various nobles and guilds and run afoul of others, all the while fending off Harper spies.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 200</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Terenzio Cassalanter</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>1</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr></cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>1</text>
      </trait>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 115</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Thorvin Twinbeard</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>4 (1d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
      <text>Thorvin has advantage on saving throws against poison and resistance to poison damage.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Club</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Club|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Thorvin serves as Xanathar's chief engineer and trapsmith. He also serves the Harpers as a paid informant, keeping that faction apprised of Xanathar's plans as well as he can. Thorvin uses the ruse of maintenance inspections to cover up secret meetings he holds with Harper spies in Skullport and elsewhere.
Thorvin wears iron-rimmed spectacles and carries a large, heavy wrench that doubles as a club. He also carries mason's tools, smith's tools, and thieves' tools, and has proficiency with all three.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 216</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Thrakkus</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dragonborn)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>67 (9d8+27)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist>fire</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Reckless</name>
      <text>At the start of his turn, Thrakkus can gain advantage on all melee weapon attack rolls during that turn, but attack rolls against him have advantage until the start of his next turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Greataxe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (1d12 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Greataxe|+5|1d12+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Breath Weapon (1/Day)</name>
      <text>Thrakkus can use his action to exhale a 15-foot cone of fire. Each creature in the cone must make a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw, taking 6 (2d6) fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Breath Weapon (1/Day)||2d6</attack>
      </action>
    <description> A member of the Guild of Butchers, Thrakkus has a lucrative side business. Zhents loyal to Manshoon pay Thrakkus to chop up people they kill, and he sells the meat on the sly.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 89</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Tissina Khyret</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (tiefling)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>33 (6d8+6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +4, Persuasion +4, Religion +2</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist>fire</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dark Devotion</name>
      <text>Tissina has advantage on saving throws against being charmed or frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Tissina makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage. Or Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one creature. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      <attack>Dagger|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Tissina's spellcasting ability is Charisma. She can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: thaumaturgy</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Tissina is a 4th-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Wisdom. Tissina has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): command, inflict wounds, shield of faith</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): hold person, spiritual weapon</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3</slots>
    <spells>thaumaturgy, light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy, command, inflict wounds, shield of faith, hold person, spiritual weapon</spells>
    <description>Madame Khyret is the personal attendant to Ammalia Cassalanter and is the family's chief housemaid. Madame Khyret dresses in a long black gown and wears a headdress with black tassels. She is an aging tiefling and she spends most of her time in the master sitting room
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 116</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Urstul Floxin</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (Illuskanhuman)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (studded leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>78 (12d8+24)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Dex +6, Int +4</save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +6, Deception +3, Perception +3, Stealth +9</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common, Orc, Thieves' cant</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Assassinate</name>
      <text>During its first turn, Urstul has advantage on attack rolls against any creature that hasn't taken a turn. Any hit Urstul scores against a surprised creature is a critical hit.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Evasion</name>
      <text>If Urstul is subjected to an effect that allows him to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, Urstul instead takes no damage if he succeeds on the saving throw, and only half damage if it fails.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sneak Attack (1/Turn)</name>
      <text>Urstul deals an extra 14 (4d6) damage when he hits a target with a weapon attack and has advantage on the attack roll, or when the target is within 5 feet of an ally of Urstul that isn't incapacitated and Urstul doesn't have disadvantage on the attack roll.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Urstul makes two shortsword attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage, and the target must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw, taking 24 (7d6) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+6|1d6+3</attack>
      <attack>Shortsword||7d6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Light Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage, and the target must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw, taking 24 (7d6) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Light Crossbow|+6|1d8+3</attack>
      <attack>Light Crossbow||7d6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Urstul Floxin works for Manshoon, and he is the highest-ranking member of the Zhentarim squad stationed at House Gralhund. Urstul is a glorified thug with all the charm and breeding of a snake, but the Gralhunds tolerate him because he feeds them useful information culled from his spies throughout the city. Urstul takes his orders from Manshoon's current simulacrum, which comes and goes from House Gralhund by way of a teleportation circle (connected to the circle in Kolat Towers).
Urstul is a large, heavyset man in his forties. He storms about House Gralhund like he owns the place. He has a collection of black flying snakes that he uses as couriers to deliver messages to underlings throughout the city.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 216</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Vajra Safahr</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>14 (17 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>126 (23d8+23)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Str +2, Dex +4, Con +3, Int +12, Wis +7, Cha +5</save>
    <skill>Arcana +10, History +10</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish, Elvish, Giant, Halfling, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>13</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Vajra wields the Blackstaff, accounted for in her statistics. Roll 2d10 to determine how many charges the staff has remaining.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Vajra has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Staff Spells</name>
      <text>While holding the blackstaff, Vajra can use an action to expend 1 or more of its charges to cast one of the following spells from it, using her spell save DC and spell attack bonus: cone of cold (5 charges), fireball (5th-level version, 5 charges), globe of invulnerability (6 charges), hold monster (5 charges), levitate (2 charges), lightning bolt (5th-level version, 5 charges), magic missile (1 charge), ray of enfeeblement (1 charge), or wall of force (5 charges).</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Blackstaff</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) bludgeoning, magic damage, or 6 (1d8 + 2) bludgeoning, magic damage when used with two hands. Vajra can expend 1 of the staff's charges to deal an extra 3 (1d6) force damage on a hit.</text>
      <attack>Blackstaff|+7|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Vajra is an 18th-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 18, +12 to hit with spell attacks). She has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, message, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, identify, mage armor, thunderwave</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): invisibility, misty step, web</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fly, sending</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): banishment, fire shield, stoneskin</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): Bigby's hand, geas, telekinesis</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): chain lightning, globe of invulnerability</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): forcecage, prismatic spray</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): antimagic field, power word stun</text>
      <text>• 9th level (1 slots): imprisonment</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, light, mage hand, message, prestidigitation, detect magic, identify, mage armor, thunderwave, invisibility, misty step, web, counterspell, fly, sending, banishment, fire shield, stoneskin, Bigby's hand, geas, telekinesis, chain lightning, globe of invulnerability, forcecage, prismatic spray, antimagic field, power word stun, imprisonment</spells>
    <description>Vajra is a capable wizard in her mid-thirties, the youngest person ever to hold the position of Blackstaff. As the High Wizard of Waterdeep, she is charged with using all the magic and resources at her disposal to defend the city against threats. She was handpicked for the job by Khelben Arunsun, and wields the Blackstaff from which Khelben derived his name and the title of the office. Vajra isn't the city's most powerful wizard, but she can hold her own. Despite her many gifts, she still questions her ability to meet the demands of her role, and she rarely makes a decision without first soliciting the advice of the Blackstaff, which contains Khelben Arunsun's spirit as well as the spirits of all the other Blackstaffs who preceded her. She also gets intelligence from many other sources, both through her own network of spies and from Harper agents.
Vajra runs Blackstaff Academy, a school for mages, out of Blackstaff Tower in the Castle Ward. She is also in charge of Force Grey, an order of highly skilled adventurers who are called upon to defend the city in times of need. Vajra is always looking for new adventurers to fill the ranks of Force Grey, and she is particularly interested in those who can bring unique skills, abilities, or spells to the mix.
Several of the older and more seasoned wizards in Waterdeep consider Vajra an upstart, but they are smart enough not to challenge her. Only the Open Lord, currently Laeral Silverhand, can strip Vajra of her title.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 217</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Valetta</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dragonborn)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>13 (chain shirt)</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Medicine +7, Persuasion +3, Religion +5</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist>lightning</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Divine Eminence</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Valetta can expend a spell slot to cause her melee weapon attacks to magically deal an extra 10 (3d6) radiant damage to a target on a hit. This benefit lasts until the end of the turn. If Valetta expends a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the extra damage increases by 1d6 for each level above 1st.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Breathe Weapon</name>
      <text>Valetta can use her action to exhale a 5-foot-wide, 30-foot line of lightning (but can't do this again until she finishes a short or long rest); each creature in the line must make a DC 11 Dexterity saving throw, taking 2d6 lightning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Mace</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Mace|+2|1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Valetta is a 5th-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Wisdom. Valetta has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): cure wounds, guiding bolt, sanctuary</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): lesser restoration, spiritual weapon</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (2 slots): dispel magic, spirit guardians</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy, cure wounds, guiding bolt, sanctuary, lesser restoration, spiritual weapon, dispel magic, spirit guardians</spells>
    <description>A dragonborn priest of bronze dragon ancestry.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 47</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Victoro Cassalanter</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (half-elf)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (glamoured studded leather, ring of protection)</ac>
    <hp>97 (15d8+30)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Con +6, Wis +7</save>
    <skill>History +7, Insight +7, Persuasion +8, Religion +7</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Elvish, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Victoro wears a ring of protection and glamoured studded leather disguised to look like fine clothing. He carries a rod of rulership shaped like a ruby-tipped cane.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Fey Ancestry</name>
      <text>Victoro has advantage on saving throws against being charmed, and magic can't put him to sleep.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Rod of Rulership</name>
      <text>Victoro can use an action to present the rod and command obedience from each creature of his choice that he can see within 120 feet of him. Each target must succeed on a DC 15 Wisdom saving throw or be charmed for 8 hours by Victoro. While charmed in this way, the creature regards Victoro as its trusted leader. If harmed by Victoro or his companions, or commanded to do something contrary to its nature, a target ceases to be charmed in this way. The rod can't be used again until the next dawn.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Victoro makes two attacks with his rapier.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Rapier</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d8 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Rapier|+5|1d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Cloak of Shadows (2/Day)</name>
      <text>Victoro becomes invisible until the end of his next turn. He becomes visible early immediately after he attacks or casts a spell.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Summon Devil (Recharges after 9 Days)</name>
      <text>Victoro summons a barbed devil. The devil appears in an unoccupied space within 30 feet of Victoro, acts as Victoro's ally, and can't summon other devils. It remains for 1 minute, until it or Victoro dies, or until Victoro dismisses it as an action.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Victoro is a 15th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 15, +7 to hit with spell attacks). Victoro has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): guidance, light, mending, spare the dying, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): charm person, command, detect magic, disguise self, protection from evil and good, sanctuary</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): augury, lesser restoration, mirror image, pass without trace, spiritual weapon</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): blink, clairvoyance, dispel magic, magic circle, protection from energy</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): banishment, dimension door, divination, freedom of movement, polymorph</text>
      <text>• 5th level (2 slots): dominate person, flame strike, modify memory, insect plague</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): heal</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): divine word</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): earthquake</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>guidance, light, mending, spare the dying, thaumaturgy, charm person, command, detect magic, disguise self, protection from evil and good, sanctuary, augury, lesser restoration, mirror image, pass without trace, spiritual weapon, blink, clairvoyance, dispel magic, magic circle, protection from energy, banishment, dimension door, divination, freedom of movement, polymorph, dominate person, flame strike, modify memory, insect plague, heal, divine word, earthquake</spells>
    <description>The lord of House Cassalanter is a devilishly handsome half-elf who likes coin and power. He and his wife gained both by cutting a deal with Asmodeus-which involved trading away the souls of their three children.
Victoro is a priest of Asmodeus, though his devotion to the Lord of the Nine Hells is a secret known only to his wife and his closest friends. Most Waterdavians know him as a successful banker, philanthropist, and worshiper of Lathander. Some of his business profits go toward feeding and sheltering the poor. But behind this veneer of generosity, Victoro is a self-serving beast.
The soul of Victoro's eldest son, Osvaldo, is forever lost and can't be saved. To allay his guilt, Victoro has forged a plan to win back the souls of his young twins, Terenzio and Elzerina. Under the terms of the contract, their souls will be forfeit on their ninth birthdays, and that day is fast approaching. But Victoro can buy his way out of the obligation by providing, as the contract states, "one shy of a million gold coins and the sacrifice of one shy of a hundred unfortunate souls."
Victoro is well schooled, suave, slow to anger, and blessed with good health, long life, and immunity to disease. He dresses in the latest fashions and walks with a ruby-tipped cane, though not because he needs to. This cane has the magical properties of a rod of rulership.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 218</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Vincent Trench</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>fiend</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>16 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>110 (13d8+52)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>20</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +10, Insight +8</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>13</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</immune>
    <vulnerable>piercing from magic weapons wielded by good creatures</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Limited Magic Immunity</name>
      <text>Vincent can't be affected or detected by spells of 6th level or lower unless it wishes to be. It has advantage on saving throws against all other spells and magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Vincent makes two claw attacks</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (2d6 + 2) slashing damage, and the target is cursed if it is a creature. The magical curse takes effect whenever the target takes a short or long rest, filling the target's thoughts with horrible images and dreams. The cursed target gains no benefit from finishing a short or long rest. The curse lasts until it is lifted by a remove curse spell or similar magic.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+7|2d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Vincent's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 18, +10 to hit with spell attacks). Vincent can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: detect thoughts, disguise self, mage hand, minor illusion</text>
      <text>3/day each: charm person, detect magic, invisibility, major image, suggestion</text>
      <text>1/day each: dominate person, fly, plane shift, true seeing</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>detect thoughts, disguise self, mage hand, minor illusion, charm person, detect magic, invisibility, major image, suggestion, dominate person, fly, plane shift, true seeing</spells>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 32</description>
    <environment>urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Walking Statue of Waterdeep</name>
    <size>G</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>314 (17d20+136)</hp>
    <speed>walk 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>30</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>27</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save>Con +14</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>18</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>cold, fire, poison, psychic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks not made with adamantine weapons</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, stunned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Crumbling Colossus</name>
      <text>When the statue drops to 0 hit points, it crumbles and is destroyed. Any creature on the ground within 30 feet of the crumbling statue must make a DC 22 Dexterity saving throw, taking 22 (4d10) bludgeoning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The statue is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The statue has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The statue deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The statue makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +16 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 29 (3d12 + 10) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+16|3d12+10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hurled Stone</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +16 to hit, range 200/800 ft., one target. 43 (6d10 + 10) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Hurled Stone|+16|6d10+10</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Scattered throughout Waterdeep are eight enormous statues that can defend the city in times of great peril. Because they are so destructive, the walking statues are used only to fend off armies and seemingly insurmountable foes.
Each statue has a name and a unique appearance (see "The Walking Statues"), but in terms of statistics they are similar. The statue known as the Swordmaiden is too broken to be animated, and only the wielder of the Blackstaff (see appendix A) can animate the other seven.
Landmarks. Over the years, Waterdavians have built structures around and on top of several of the statues, believing them to be little more than landmarks at this point. In their inanimate state, the statues pose little danger-but any structures attached to a walking statue are destroyed the first time it animates.
Constructed Nature. A walking statue doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 219</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Willifort Crowelle</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity (shapechanger)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>14</ac>
    <hp>52 (8d8+16)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +6, Insight +3</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>Willifort can use its action to polymorph into a Small or Medium humanoid it has seen, or back into its true form. Its statistics, other than its size, are the same in each form. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying isn't transformed. It reverts to its true form if it dies.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Ambusher</name>
      <text>In the first round of a combat, Willifort has advantage on attack rolls against any creature it surprised.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Surprise Attack</name>
      <text>If Willifort surprises a creature and hits it with an attack during the first round of combat, the target takes an extra 10 (3d6) damage from the attack.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Willifort makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+6|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Read Thoughts</name>
      <text>Willifort magically reads the surface thoughts of one creature within 60 feet of it. The effect can penetrate barriers, but 3 feet of wood or dirt, 2 feet of stone, 2 inches of metal, or a thin sheet of lead blocks it. While the target is in range, Willifort can continue reading its thoughts, as long as Willifort's concentration isn't broken (as if concentrating on a spell). While reading the target's mind, Willifort has advantage on Wisdom (Insight) and Charisma (Deception, Intimidation, and Persuasion) checks against the target.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 62</description>
    <environment>underdark, urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Xanathar</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>aberration</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>18 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>180 (19d10+76)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>17</cha>
    <save>Int +8, Wis +7, Cha +8</save>
    <skill>Perception +12</skill>
    <passive>22</passive>
    <languages>Deep Speech, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>13</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Xanathar wears a ring of invisibility, a ring of mind shielding, and a ring of force resistance.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Antimagic Cone</name>
      <text>Xanathar's central eye creates an area of antimagic, as in the antimagic field spell, in a 150-foot cone. At the start of each of its turns, Xanathar decides which way the cone faces and whether the cone is active. The area works against Xanathar's own eye rays.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 14 (4d6) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+5|4d6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Eye Rays</name>
      <text>Xanathar shoots three of the following magical eye rays at random (reroll duplicates), choosing one to three targets it can see within 120 feet of it:</text>
      <text>1. Charm Ray. The targeted creature must succeed on a DC 16 Wisdom saving throw or be charmed by Xanathar for 1 hour, or until Xanathar harms the creature.</text>
      <text>2. Paralyzing Ray. The targeted creature must succeed on a DC 16 Constitution saving throw or be paralyzed for 1 minute. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <text>3. Fear Ray. The targeted creature must succeed on a DC 16 Wisdom saving throw or be frightened for 1 minute. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <text>4. Slowing Ray. The targeted creature must succeed on a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, the target's speed is halved for 1 minute. In addition, the creature can't take reactions, and it can take either an action or a bonus action on its turn, not both. The creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <text>5. Enervation Ray. The targeted creature must make a DC 16 Constitution saving throw, taking 36 (8d8) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Eye Rays||8d8</attack>
      <text>6. Telekinetic Ray. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 16 Strength saving throw or Xanathar moves it up to 30 feet in any direction. It is restrained by the ray's telekinetic grip until the start of Xanathar's next turn or until Xanathar is incapacitated.</text>
      <text>If the target is an object weighing 300 pounds or less that isn't being worn or carried, it is moved up to 30 feet in any direction. Xanathar can also exert fine control on objects with this ray, such as manipulating a simple tool or opening a door or a container.</text>
      <text>7. Sleep Ray. The targeted creature must succeed on a DC 16 Wisdom saving throw or fall asleep and remain unconscious for 1 minute. The target awakens if it takes damage or another creature takes an action to wake it. This ray has no effect on constructs and undead.</text>
      <text>8. Petrification Ray. The targeted creature must make a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, the creature begins to turn to stone and is restrained. It must repeat the saving throw at the end of its next turn. On a success, the effect ends. On a failure, the creature is petrified until freed by the  greater restoration spell or other magic.</text>
      <text>9. Disintegration Ray. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw or take 45 (10d8) force damage. If this damage reduces the creature to 0 hit points, its body becomes a pile of fine gray dust.</text>
      <attack>Eye Rays||10d8</attack>
      <text>If the target is a Large or smaller nonmagical object or creation of magical force, it is disintegrated without a saving throw. If the target is a Huge or larger object or creation of magical force, this ray disintegrates a 10-foot cube of it.</text>
      <text>10. Death Ray. The targeted creature must succeed on a DC 16 Dexterity saving throw or take 55 (10d10) necrotic damage. The target dies if the ray reduces it to 0 hit points.</text>
      <attack>Eye Rays||10d10</attack>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>Xanathar can take 3 legendary actions, using the Eye Ray option below. It can take only one legendary action at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Xanathar regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Eye Ray</name>
      <text>Xanathar uses one random eye ray.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Lair Actions</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>When fighting inside its lair, a beholder can invoke the ambient magic to take lair actions. On initiative count 20 (losing initiative ties), the beholder can take one lair action to cause one of the following effects:</text>
      <text>• A 50-foot-square area of ground within 120 feet of the beholder becomes slimy; that area is difficult terrain until initiative count 20 on the next round.</text>
      <text>• Walls within 120 feet of the beholder sprout grasping appendages until initiative count 20 on the round after next. Each creature of the beholder's choice that starts its turn within 10 feet of such a wall must succeed on a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw or be grappled. Escaping requires a successful DC 15 Strength (Athletics) or Dexterity (Acrobatics) check.</text>
      <text>• An eye opens on a solid surface within 60 feet of the beholder. One random eye ray of the beholder shoots from that eye at a target of the beholder's choice that it can see. The eye then closes and disappears.</text>
      <text>The beholder can't repeat an effect until they have all been used, and it can't use the same effect two rounds in a row.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Regional Effects</name>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <text>A region containing a beholder's lair is warped by the creature's unnatural presence, which creates one or more of the following effects:</text>
      <text>• Creatures within 1 mile of the beholder's lair sometimes feel as if they're being watched when they aren't.</text>
      <text>• When the beholder sleeps, minor warps in reality occur within 1 mile of its lair and then vanish 24 hours later. Marks on cave walls might change subtly, an eerie trinket might appear where none existed before, harmless slime might coat a statue, and so on. These effects apply only to natural surfaces and to nonmagical objects that aren't on anyone's person.</text>
      <text>If the beholder dies, these effects fade over the course of 1d10 days.</text>
      </legendary>
    <description>
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 220</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Yagra Stonefist</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (half-orc)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>11 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>32 (5d8+10)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Intimidation +2</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Orc</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Relentless Endurance</name>
      <text>When reduced to 0 hit points, Yagra drops to 1 hit point instead (but can't do this again until she finishes a long rest).</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>Yagra has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of her allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Savage Attacks</name>
      <text>When she scores a critical hit Yagra can roll one of the weapon's damage dice and add it to the extra damage of the critical hit.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Yagra makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Mace</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 5 (1d6 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Mace|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Heavy Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, range 100/400 ft., one target. 5 (1d10) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Heavy Crossbow|+2|1d10</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Yagra is a Black Network mercenary who gets paid to protect a Zhent negotiator named Davil Starsong (see appendix B for more information on him). Yagra finds the job boring and likes to pass the time by challenging adventurers to arm wrestle. (Resolve such contests using contested Strength checks.) If the characters express their opposition to the Xanathar Guild, Yagra might urge them to speak to Davil about joining forces with the Zhentarim to destroy the beholder crime lord.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 20</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Yalah Gralhund</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (Tethyrianhuman)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (breastplate)</ac>
    <hp>9 (2d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +5, Insight +5, Persuasion +5</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Rapier</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d8 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Rapier|+3|1d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Yalah adds 2 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, Yalah must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>The lady of House Gralhund is no fool. She has a keen mind and the wisdom to discern friend from foe. She also has a husband who worships her (see "Orond Gralhund"), and a house that has the resources of the Black Network at its disposal.
Yalah stays abreast of events in the city, keeps a tight rein on her children, and uses her station and her family's wealth to pry secrets from the lips of nobles, guildmasters, and commoners alike. Though her previous attempts to become a Masked Lord have been thwarted, she believes it's only a matter of time until that honor is bestowed on her. Once she knows the identities and secrets of enough Masked Lords, Yalah is confident that she can bribe, blackmail, or extort her way into their ranks. From there, she plans to effect changes in the government that will ensure House Gralhund's prosperity for generations to come.
Yalah shares the services of a half-orc bodyguard with her husband, although Hrabbaz (see "Hrabbaz") is more loyal to her than to him. She also uses the Zhentarim who are based in House Gralhund as her personal spy network, not realizing that the Zhents' true master is Manshoon. Most of her dealings are with the Zhent master assassin Urstul Floxin (see "Urstul Floxin"), whom she treats as an underling.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 220</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Yorn</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (half-orc)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>11 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>32 (5d8+10)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Intimidation +2</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common, Orc</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>The thug has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the thug's allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Relentless Endurance (1/Day)</name>
      <text>When reduced to 0 hit points Yorn drops to 1 hit point instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The thug makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Mace</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 5 (1d6 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Mace|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Heavy Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, range 100/400 ft., one target. 5 (1d10) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Heavy Crossbow|+2|1d10</attack>
      </action>
    <description>A burly half-orc Zhentarim in the employ of Manshoon
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 150</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Zhent Martial Arts Adept</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (Lightfoothalfling)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>16</ac>
    <hp>49 (11d6+11)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +5, Insight +5, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common, Halfling</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Halfling Nimbleness</name>
      <text>The adept can move through the space of a medium of larger creature.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Brave</name>
      <text>The adept has advantage on any saving throws against being frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Unarmored Defense</name>
      <text>While the adept is wearing no armor and wielding no shield, their AC includes their Wisdom modifier.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The adept makes three unarmed strikes or three dart attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Unarmed Strike</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a creature, the adept can choose one of the following additional effects:</text>
      <attack>Unarmed Strike|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      <text>• The target must succeed on a DC 13 Strength saving throw or drop one item it is holding (adept's choice).</text>
      <text>• The target must succeed on a DC 13 Dexterity saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      <text>• The target must succeed on a DC 13 Constitution saving throw or be stunned until the end of the adept's next turn.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dart</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 20/60 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dart|+5|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Deflect Missile</name>
      <text>In response to being hit by a ranged weapon attack, the adept deflects the missile. The damage it takes from the attack is reduced by 1d10 + 3. If the damage is reduced to 0, the adept catches the missile if it's small enough to hold in one hand and the adept has a hand free.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>The adepts believe that Manshoon should be the Zhantarim leader and serves him fearlessly
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 160</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Ziraj the Hunter</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (half-orc)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (+2 leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>153 (18d8+72)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>18</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Wis +5, Cha +5</save>
    <skill>Athletics +7, Intimidation +5, Stealth +7, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Orc</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Ziraj makes three attacks with his glaive or with his oversized longbow.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Glaive</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (1d10 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Glaive|+7|1d10+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Oversized Longbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, range 150/600 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Oversized Longbow|+7|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dreadful Aspect (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>Ziraj exudes magical menace. Each enemy within 30 feet of him must succeed on a DC 13 Wisdom saving throw or be frightened for 1 minute of Ziraj. If a frightened enemy ends its turn more than 30 feet away from Ziraj, the enemy can repeat the saving throw, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Ziraj is a 10th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Charisma. He has the following paladin spells prepared:</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): command, protection from evil and good, thunderous smite</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): branding smite, find steed</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (2 slots): blinding smite, dispel magic</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>command, protection from evil and good, thunderous smite, branding smite, find steed, blinding smite, dispel magic</spells>
    <description>Ziraj is a half-orc hunter who wields an oversized bow that shoots correspondingly large arrows. He is the Master of Assassination for the Black Network. If Ziraj sets out to kill someone, it's because one of his friends (Davil, Istrid, Skeemo, or Tashlyn) asked him to. The characters might become Ziraj's prey, or Ziraj might come to their aid to eliminate a common enemy. He's the strong, silent type.
The City Watch has received reports of a figure who haunts the rooftops of Waterdeep-a hulking shadow that glares from its perch, rains down death in the form of long black arrows, and slinks off without so much as a whisper. Where he comes from-if he even has a home-remains a mystery, as does the question of where he might show up next.
Treasure. Ziraj wears +2 leather armor and carries an oversized longbow. This unique weapon can be used only by a Medium or larger creature that has a Strength of 18 or higher. The bow shoots oversized arrows that deal piercing damage equal to 2d6 + the wielder's Strength modifier. Its range is the same as an ordinary longbow.
The Doom Raiders. The Doom Raiders were five unscrupulous adventurers who liked to plunder lich lairs (called "dooms" by some). They gave up adventuring to join the Black Network and came to Waterdeep three years ago with plans to establish a Zhentarim foothold in the city. In that time, they have forged alliances with various nobles and guilds and run afoul of others, all the while fending off Harper spies.
Source: Waterdeep: Dragon Heist p. 201</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  </compendium>
