<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Monk</name>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Monastic Tradition: Way of the Long Death</name>
        <text>Monks of the Way of the Long Death are obsessed with the meaning and mechanics of dying. They capture creatures and prepare elaborate experiments to capture, record, and understand the moments of their demise. They use this knowledge to guide their understanding of martial arts, yielding a deadly fighting style.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 130</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Long Death: Touch of Death</name>
        <text>Starting when you choose this tradition at 3rd level, your study of death allows you to extract vitality from another creature as it nears its demise. When you reduce a creature within 5 feet of you to 0 hit points, you gain temporary hit points equal to your Wisdom modifier + your monk level (minimum of 1 temporary hit point).</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 130</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Long Death: Hour of Reaping</name>
        <text>At 6th level, you gain the ability to unsettle or terrify those around you as an action, for your soul has been touched by the shadow of death. When you take this action, each creature within 30 feet of you that can see you must succeed on a Wisdom saving throw or be frightened of you until the end of your next turn.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 130</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="11">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Long Death: Mastery of Death</name>
        <text>Beginning at 11th level, you use your familiarity with death to escape its grasp. When you are reduced to 0 hit points, you can expend 1 ki point (no action required) to have 1 hit point instead.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 130</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Way of the Long Death: Touch of the Long Death</name>
        <text>Starting at 17th level, your touch can channel the energy of death into a creature. As an action, you touch one creature within 5 feet of you, and you expend 1 to 10 ki points. The target must make a Constitution saving throw, and it takes 2d10 necrotic damage per ki point spent on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 130</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
