<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Wizard</name>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Tradition: Bladesinging</name>
        <text>Bladesingers are elves who bravely defend their people and lands. They are elf wizards who master a school of sword fighting grounded in a tradition of arcane magic. In combat, a bladesinger uses a series of intricate, elegant maneuvers that fend off harm and allow the bladesinger to channel magic into devastating attacks and a cunning defense.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Bladesinging: Bladesinger Styles</name>
        <text>From its inception as a martial and magical art, Bladesinging has been tied to the sword, more specifically the longsword. Yet many generations of study gave rise to various styles of Bladesinging based on the melee weapon employed. The techniques of these styles are passed from master to students in small schools, some of which have a building dedicated to instruction. Even the newest styles are hundreds of years old, but are still taught by their original creators due to the long lives of elves. Most schools of Bladesinging are in Evermeet or Evereska. One was started in Myth Drannor, but the city's destruction has scattered those students who survived.</text>
        <text>Styles of Bladesinging are broadly categorized based on the type of weapon employed, and each is associated with a category of animal. Within that style are specializations named after specific animal types, based on the types of spells employed, the techniques of the master, and the particular weapon used. Bladesingers who apprentice to a master typically get a tattoo of their chosen style's animal. Some bladesingers learn multiple styles and bear many tattoos, wearing a warning on their skin of their deadly skills.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Cat</text>
        <text>   Styles that employ a sword belong to this family. The lion style, the eldest, trains practitioners in the use of the longsword and doesn't favor any particular type of spells. Leopard style focuses on the shortsword and spells of illusion and stealth. Red tiger, a style just three centuries old, has its bladesingers using the scimitar in a whirling dance of defense from which they launch into sudden leaps and attacks.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Bird</text>
        <text>   Styles that focus on the use of a hafted weapon, such as an axe or hammer, have been grouped together as bird styles, yet they vary wildly. All relatively new styles, they use weapons not typically favored by elves. Eagle-style bladesingers use small handaxes, and many maneuvers in the style focus on fluid ways to throw the weapon and draw a new one. Raven style uses a war pick, and spells associated with it grant the bladesinger more agility in combat.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Snake</text>
        <text>   Practitioners of these styles use a flail, chain, or whip. Viper style uses a whip, despite its inelegance as a weapon, and has almost as long a history as the lion style. Its masters punctuate their bladesong with a stunningly rapid rhythm of whip cracks, which can keep many foes at bay and allow the bladesinger space to cast the cruel spells of poison and disease favored by the style.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Bladesinging: Bladesong</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, you can invoke a secret elven magic called the Bladesong, provided you aren't wearing medium or heavy armor or using a shield. It graces you with supernatural speed, agility, and focus.</text>
        <text>You can use a bonus action to start the Bladesong, which lasts for 1 minute. It ends early if you are incapacitated, if you don medium or heavy armor or a shield, or if you use two hands to make an attack with a weapon. You can also dismiss Bladesong at any time you choose (no action required).</text>
        <text>While your bladesong is active, you gain the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• You gain a bonus to your AC equal to your Intelligence modifier (minimum of +1).</text>
        <text>• Your walking speed increases by 10 feet.</text>
        <text>• You have advantage on Dexterity (Acrobatics) checks.</text>
        <text>• You gain a bonus to any Constitution saving throws you make to maintain concentration on a spell. The bonus equals your Intelligence modifier (minimum of +1).</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses of it when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Bladesinging: Training in War and Song (Bladesinging)</name>
        <text>When you adopt this tradition at 2nd level, you gain proficiency with light armor, and you gain proficiency with one type of one-handed melee weapon of your choice.</text>
        <text>You also gain proficiency in the Performance skill if you don't already have it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Tradition: Order of Scribes</name>
        <text>Magic of the book-that's what many folk call wizardry. The name is apt, given how much time wizards spend poring over tomes and penning theories about the nature of magic. It's rare to see wizards traveling without books and scrolls sprouting from their bags, and a wizard would go to great lengths to plumb an archive of ancient knowledge.</text>
        <text>Among wizards, the Order of Scribes is the most bookish. It takes many forms in different worlds, but its primary mission is the same everywhere: recording magical discoveries so that wizardry can flourish. And while all wizards value spellbooks, a wizard in the Order of Scribes magically awakens their book, turning it into a trusted companion. All wizards study books, but a wizardly scribe talks to theirs!</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 77</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Order of Scribes: Awakened Spellbook</name>
        <text>2nd-level Order of Scribes feature</text>
        <text>Using specially prepared inks and ancient incantations passed down by your wizardly order, you have awakened an arcane sentience within your spellbook.</text>
        <text>While you are holding the book, it grants you the following benefits:</text>
        <text>• You can use the book as a spellcasting focus for your wizard spells.</text>
        <text>• When you cast a wizard spell with a spell slot, you can temporarily replace its damage type with a type that appears in another spell in your spellbook, which magically alters the spell's formula for this casting only. The latter spell must be of the same level as the spell slot you expend.</text>
        <text>• When you cast a wizard spell as a ritual, you can use the spell's normal casting time, rather than adding 10 minutes to it. Once you use this benefit, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>If necessary, you can replace the book over the course of a short rest by using your Wizardly Quill to write arcane sigils in a blank book or a magic spellbook to which you're attuned. At the end of the rest, your spellbook's consciousness is summoned into the new book, which the consciousness transforms into your spellbook, along with all its spells. If the previous book still existed somewhere, all the spells vanish from its pages.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 77</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Order of Scribes: Wizardly Quill</name>
        <text>2nd-level Order of Scribes feature</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, you can magically create a Tiny quill in your free hand. The magic quill has the following properties:</text>
        <text>• The quill doesn't require ink. When you write with it, it produces ink in a color of your choice on the writing surface.</text>
        <text>• The time you must spend to copy a spell into your spellbook equals 2 minutes per spell level if you use the quill for the transcription.</text>
        <text>• You can erase anything you write with the quill if you wave the feather over the text as a bonus action, provided the text is within 5 feet of you.</text>
        <text>This quill disappears if you create another one or if you die.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 77</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="3">
        <feature>
          <name>Cantrip Formulas</name>
        <text>3rd-level wizard optional class features</text>
        <text>You have scribed a set of arcane formulas in your spellbook that you can use to formulate a cantrip in your mind. Whenever you finish a long rest and consult those formulas in your spellbook, you can replace one wizard cantrip you know with another cantrip from the wizard spell list.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 75</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Bladesinging: Extra Attack</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, you can attack twice, instead of once, whenever you take the Attack action on your turn. Moreover, you can cast one of your cantrips in place of one of those attacks.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Order of Scribes: Manifest Mind</name>
        <text>6th-level Order of Scribes feature</text>
        <text>You can conjure forth the mind of your Awakened Spellbook. As a bonus action while the book is on your person, you can cause the mind to manifest as a Tiny spectral object, hovering in an unoccupied space of your choice within 60 feet of you. The spectral mind is intangible and doesn't occupy its space, and it sheds dim light in a 10-foot radius. It looks like a ghostly tome, a cascade of text, or a scholar from the past (your choice).</text>
        <text>While manifested, the spectral mind can hear and see, and it has darkvision with a range of 60 feet. The mind can telepathically share with you what it sees and hears (no action required).</text>
        <text>Whenever you cast a wizard spell on your turn, you can cast it as if you were in the spectral mind's space, instead of your own, using its senses. You can do so a number of times per day equal to your proficiency bonus, and you regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text>As a bonus action, you can cause the spectral mind to hover up to 30 feet to an unoccupied space that you or it can see. It can pass through creatures but not objects.</text>
        <text>The spectral mind stops manifesting if it is ever more than 300 feet away from you, if someone casts dispel magic on it, if the Awakened Spellbook is destroyed, if you die, or if you dismiss the spectral mind as a bonus action.</text>
        <text>Once you conjure the mind, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest, unless you expend a spell slot of any level to conjure it again.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 77</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Bladesinging: Song of Defense</name>
        <text>Beginning at 10th level, you can direct your magic to absorb damage while your bladesong is active. When you take damage, you can use your reaction to expend one spell slot and reduce that damage to you by an amount equal to five times the spell's slot level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Order of Scribes: Master Scrivener</name>
        <text>10th-level Order of Scribes feature</text>
        <text>Whenever you finish a long rest, you can create one magic scroll by touching your Wizardly Quill to a blank piece of paper or parchment and causing one spell from your Awakened Spellbook to be copied onto the scroll. The spellbook must be within 5 feet of you when you make the scroll.</text>
        <text>The chosen spell must be of 1st or 2nd level and must have a casting time of 1 action. Once in the scroll, the spell's power is enhanced, counting as one level higher than normal. You can cast the spell from the scroll by reading it as an action. The scroll is unintelligible to anyone else, and the spell vanishes from the scroll when you cast it or when you finish your next long rest.</text>
        <text>You are also adept at crafting spell scrolls, which are described in the treasure chapter of the Dungeon Master's Guide. The gold and time you must spend to make such a scroll are halved if you use your Wizardly Quill.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 77</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Bladesinging: Song of Victory</name>
        <text>Starting at 14th level, you add your Intelligence modifier (minimum of +1) to the damage of your melee weapon attacks while your Bladesong is active.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 76</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Order of Scribes: One with the Word</name>
        <text>14th-level Order of Scribes feature</text>
        <text>Your connection to your Awakened Spellbook has become so profound that your soul has become entwined with it. While the book is on your person, you have advantage on all Intelligence (Arcana) checks, as the spellbook helps you remember magical lore.</text>
        <text>Moreover, if you take damage while your spellbook's mind is manifested, you can prevent all of that damage to you by using your reaction to dismiss the spectral mind, using its magic to save yourself. Then roll 3d6. The spellbook temporarily loses spells of your choice that have a combined spell level equal to that roll or higher. For example, if the roll's total is 9, spells vanish from the book that have a combined level of at least 9, which could mean one 9th-level spell, three 3rd-level spells, or some other combination. If there aren't enough spells in the book to cover this cost, you drop to 0 hit points.</text>
        <text>Until you finish 1d6 long rests, you are incapable of casting the lost spells, even if you find them on a scroll or in another spellbook. After you finish the required number of rests, the spells reappear in the spellbook.</text>
        <text>Once you use this reaction, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Tasha's Cauldron of Everything p. 77</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
