<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <monster>
      <name>Acererak</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>21 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>285 (30d8+150)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>27</int>
    <wis>21</wis>
    <cha>20</cha>
    <save>Con +12, Int +15, Wis +12</save>
    <skill>Arcana +22, History +22, Insight +12, Perception +12</skill>
    <passive>22</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Draconic, Dwarvish, Elvish, Giant, Infernal, Primordial, Undercommon</languages>
    <cr>23</cr>
    <resist>cold, lightning</resist>
    <immune>necrotic, poison; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, stunned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Acererak carries the Staff of the Forgotten One. He wears a Talisman of the Sphere and has a Sphere of Annihilation under his control.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If Acererak fails a saving throw, he can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Rejuvenation</name>
      <text>Acererak's body turns to dust when he drops to 0 hit points, and his equipment is left behind. Acererak gains a new body after 1d10 days, regaining all his hit points and becoming active again. The new body appears within 5 feet of Acererak's phylactery, the location of which is hidden.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Turn Resistance</name>
      <text>Acererak has advantage on saving throws against any effect that turns undead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Paralyzing Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +15 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 10 (3d6) cold damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 20 Constitution saving throw or be paralyzed for 1 minute. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <attack>Paralyzing Touch|+15|3d6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Staff (+3 Quarterstaff)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +11 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) bludgeoning damage plus 10 (3d6) necrotic damage, or 8 (1d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage plus 10 (3d6) necrotic damage when used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Staff (+3 Quarterstaff)|+11|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Invoke Curse</name>
      <text>While holding the Staff of the Forgotten One, Acererak expends 1 charge from it and targets one creature he can see within 60 feet of him. The target must succeed on a DC 23 Constitution saving throw or be cursed. Until the curse is ended, the target can't regain hit points and has vulnerability to necrotic damage. Greater restoration, remove curse, or similar magic ends the curse on the target.</text>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>Acererak can take 5 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Acererak regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>At-Will Spell</name>
      <text>Acererak casts one of his at-will spells.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Melee Attack</name>
      <text>Acererak uses Paralyzing Touch or makes one melee attack with his staff.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Frightening Gaze (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Acererak fixes his gaze on one creature he can see within 10 feet of him. The target must succeed on a DC 20 Wisdom saving throw against this magic or become frightened for 1 minute. The frightened target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. If a target's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the target its immune to Acererak's gaze for the next 24 hours.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Talisman of the Sphere (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Acererak uses his Talisman of the Sphere to move the Sphere of Annihilation under his control up to 90 feet.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Disrupt Life (Costs 3 Actions)</name>
      <text>Each creature within 20 feet of Acererak must make a DC 20 Constitution saving throw against this magic, taking 42 (12d6) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      </legendary>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Acererak is a 20th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 23, +15 to hit with spell attacks). Acererak has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): mage hand, ray of frost, shocking grasp</text>
      <text>• 1st level (0 slots): ray of sickness, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (0 slots): arcane lock, knock</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (0 slots): animate dead, counterspell</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): blight, ice storm, phantasmal killer</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): cloudkill, hold monster, wall of force</text>
      <text>• 6th level (3 slots): chain lightning, circle of death, disintegrate</text>
      <text>• 7th level (3 slots): finger of death, plane shift, teleport</text>
      <text>• 8th level (2 slots): maze, mind blank</text>
      <text>• 9th level (2 slots): power word kill, time stop</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>0, 0, 0, 3, 3, 3, 3, 2, 2</slots>
    <spells>mage hand, ray of frost, shocking grasp, ray of sickness, shield, arcane lock, knock, animate dead, counterspell, blight, ice storm, phantasmal killer, cloudkill, hold monster, wall of force, chain lightning, circle of death, disintegrate, finger of death, plane shift, teleport, maze, mind blank, power word kill, time stop</spells>
    <description>Acererak is an archlich who travels between worlds and is known to take sick pleasure in devouring the souls of adventurers, whom he lures into trap-ridden dungeons where they suffer horrible deaths. One such dungeon lies under the lost city of Omu. This dungeon is called the Tomb of the Nine Gods, for Acererak slew nine false gods and sealed them within it. More recently, he built a necromantic device called the Soulmonger, then hid it in the heart of the tomb.
Acererak's Traits. Ideal. "Why be a god when I can be a creator of gods?"
Bond. "I build dungeons to trap and slay powerful adventurers. Their deaths and souls are my nourishment."
Flaw. "I underestimate the resolve of my enemies."
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 209</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Albino Dwarf Spirit Warrior</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>30 (4d8+12)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +4, Stealth +3, Survival +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
      <text>The dwarf has advantage on saving throws against poison.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Handaxe</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Handaxe|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The dwarf's innate spellcasting ability is Wisdom. It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>1/day each: hunter's mark, jump, pass without trace, speak with animals, speak with plants</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>hunter's mark, jump, pass without trace, speak with animals, speak with plants</spells>
    <description>The albino dwarves of Chult were driven from their subterranean homes by volcanic activity, and those who didn't seek refuge in Port Nyanzaru adapted to living in the jungle. They make armor out of dinosaur hide; shape weapons out of dinosaur bones, flint, and wood; and craft ornate jewelry out of bones, feathers, tusks, and stone beads. Albino dwarves haven't forgotten how to forge metal, but they seldom have the means to do so.
Albino Dwarf Spirit Warriors. An albino dwarf can become so attuned to the land of Chult that a benevolent nature spirit takes notice and bestows a powerful charm on the dwarf, granting it innate spellcasting abilities. These dwarf spirit warriors dedicate themselves to preserving the natural beauty of Chult and battling unnatural threats. An albino dwarf spirit warrior has the statistics of an albino dwarf warrior, except it has a challenge rating of 1 (200 XP) and gains an Innate Spellcasting feature.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 210</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Albino Dwarf Warrior</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>30 (4d8+12)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +4, Stealth +3, Survival +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
      <text>The dwarf has advantage on saving throws against poison.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Handaxe</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Handaxe|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>The albino dwarves of Chult were driven from their subterranean homes by volcanic activity, and those who didn't seek refuge in Port Nyanzaru adapted to living in the jungle. They make armor out of dinosaur hide; shape weapons out of dinosaur bones, flint, and wood; and craft ornate jewelry out of bones, feathers, tusks, and stone beads. Albino dwarves haven't forgotten how to forge metal, but they seldom have the means to do so.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 210</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Aldani (Lobsterfolk)</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>49 (9d8+9)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., swim 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>8</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +4, Survival +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The aldani can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The aldani makes two attacks with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d8 + 1) slashing damage, and the target is grappled (escape DC 11). The aldani has two claws, each of which can grapple only one target.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+3|1d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Many Chultan natives can recall childhood fables of the aldani, the eerie lobsterfolk that lived in the rivers and lakes of their homeland. As there have been no sightings of the aldani in years, it is widely believed that they were wiped out. In truth, many aldani survived and retreated to the lakes of the Aldani Basin in the heart of Chult.
An aldani looks like a giant lobster that walks upright. Its face is mostly encased in armor, looking almost humanoid except for its long eyestalks. Despite their frightful appearance, aldani avoid conflict. Reclusive and xenophobic, they hide in their lakes and rivers.
Aldani Bribes. If disturbed, aldani try to frighten intruders away without killing them. When confronted by creatures who aren't easily startled, they offer bribes in exchange for being left alone. These bribes take the form of treasures that the aldani collect from the bottoms of rivers and lakes.
Cursed by Ubtao.  The aldani are the monstrous descendants of Chultan humans belonging to the Aldani tribe. The fishers of the tribe trapped the lobsters of the rivers by the thousands, until no lobsters remained. Their greed made Ubtao angry, and he cursed the fishers by transforming them into lobsterfolk. The fishers accepted their punishment and embraced their new existence. However, they were scorned by other members of their tribe and forced to take refuge in the rivers they had once plundered. Although the Aldani tribe went extinct, the lobsterfolk remain to this day.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 210</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Almiraj</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>3 (1d6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>2</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +4, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Senses</name>
      <text>The almiraj has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing or sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Familiar</name>
      <text>With the DM's permission, the find familiar spell can summon an almiraj.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Horn</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Horn|+5|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>An almiraj (pronounced AWL-meer-ahj) is a large, timid rabbit with a 1-foot-long spiral horn emerging from its forehead, not unlike the horn of a unicorn. If driven to attack, it tries to spear enemies with its horn.
Almiraj were brought to Chult long ago by merchants of the distant land of Zakhara. Skilled at evading predators, these creatures have flourished throughout the tropical peninsula. They live in earthen burrows and can be captured and domesticated. With the DM's permission, the find familiar spell can summon an almiraj.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 211</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Ankylosaurus Zombie</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>68 (8d12+16)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>6</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>8</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Undead Fortitude</name>
      <text>If damage reduces the zombie to 0 hit points, it must make a Constitution saving throw with a DC of 5+the damage taken, unless the damage is radiant or from a critical hit. On a success, the zombie drops to 1 hit point instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target 18 (4d6 + 4) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 14 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Tail|+6|4d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Several new zombie variants are presented below. For more information on zombies, see the Monster Manual.
Ankylosaurus Zombie. This creature is slow and barely aware of its surroundings.
Girallon Zombie. Girallons are four-armed apes with white fur. Girallon zombies are slower than their non-undead counterparts but no less fierce. The necromantic energy empowering them fuels their murderous hearts and their hunger for living flesh.
Tyrannosaurus Zombie. A tyrannosaurus zombie has a gullet full of smaller zombies, which it can disgorge. These zombies aren't under the tyrannosaurus zombie's control.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 240</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Artus Cimber</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Good</alignment>
    <ac>14 (studded leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>82 (15d8+15)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Dex +5, Cha +7</save>
    <skill>Deception +7, History +9, Insight +6, Survival +9</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Dwarvish, Goblin</languages>
    <cr>7</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>While wearing the Ring of Winter: cold</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Artus wears the Ring of Winter. He and the ring can't be targeted by divination magic or perceived through magical scrying sensors. While attuned to and wearing the ring, Artus ceases to age and is immune to cold damage and the effects of extreme cold.</text>
      <text>Artus wields Bookmark a +3 dagger with additional magical properties. As a bonus action, Artus can activate any one of the following properties while attuned to the dagger, provided he has the weapon drawn:</text>
      <text>• Cause a blue gem set into the dagger's pommel to shed bright light in a 20-foot radius and dim light for an additional 20 feet, or make the gem go dark.</text>
      <text>• Turn the dagger into a compass that, while resting on your palm, points north.</text>
      <text>• Cast dimension door from the dagger. Once this property is used, it can't be used again until the next dawn.</text>
      <text>• Cast compulsion (save DC 15) from the dagger. The range of the spell increases to 90 feet but it targets only spiders that are beasts. Once this property is used, it can't be used again until the next dawn.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Artus makes three attacks with Bookmark or his longbow.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bookmark (+3 Dagger)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d4 + 5) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bookmark (+3 Dagger)|+8|1d4+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Longbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 150/600 ft., one target 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Longbow|+5|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Ring of Winter</name>
      <text>The Ring of Winter has 12 charges and regains all its expended charges daily at dawn. While attuned to and wearing the ring, Artus can expend the necessary number of charges to activate one of the following properties:</text>
      <text>• Artus can expend 1 charge and use the ring to lower the temperature in a 120-foot-radius sphere centered on a point he can see within 300 feet of him. The temperature in that area drops 20 degrees per minute, to a minimum of −30 degrees Fahrenheit. Frost and ice begin to form on surfaces once the temperature drops below 32 degrees. This effect is permanent unless Artus uses the ring to end the effect as an action, at which point the temperature in the area returns to normal at a rate of 10 degrees per minute.</text>
      <text>• Artus can cast one of the following spells from the ring (spell save DC 17) by expending the necessary number of charges: Bigby's hand (2 charges) the hand is made of ice, is immune to cold damage, and deals bludgeoning damage instead of force damage as a clenched fist, cone of cold (2 charges), flesh to stone (3 charges); as flesh to stone except that the target turns to solid ice with the density and durability of stone, ice storm (2 charges), Otiluke's freezing sphere (3 charges), sleet storm (1 charge), spike growth (1 charge) the spikes are made of ice, or wall of ice (2 charges).</text>
      <text>• Artus can expend the necessary number of charges and use the ring to create either an inanimate ice object (2 charges) or an animated ice creature (4 charges). The ice object can't have any moving parts, must be able to fit inside a 10-foot cube, and has the density and durability of metal or stone (Artus's choice). The ice creature must be modeled after a beast with a challenge rating of 2 or less. The ice creature has the same statistics as the beast it models, with the following changes: the creature is a construct with vulnerability to fire damage, immunity to cold and poison damage, and immunity to the following conditions: charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, and poisoned. The ice creature obeys only its creator's commands. The object or creature appears in an unoccupied space within 60 feet of Artus. It melts into a pool of normal water after 24 hours or when it drops to 0 hit points. In extreme heat, it loses 5 (1d10) hit points per minute as it melts. Use the guidelines in chapter 8 of the Dungeon Master's Guide to determine the hit points of an inanimate object if they become necessary.</text>
      </action>
    <description>A former member of the Harpers, Artus Cimber is the keeper of the Ring of Winter. He found the ring in the jungles of Chult, where he also met his wife, Alisanda. The ring halts its wearer's natural aging and has allowed Artus to survive well beyond his natural lifespan. The ring also defies magical attempts to divine its location and that of its wearer. On his fingers above the knuckles, Artus has tattooed the names of his dearly departed animal companions-a pair of talking wombats named Byrt and Lugg.
Artus has spent most of his life trying to keep the Ring of Winter out of evil hands, but his return to Chult is focused on reuniting with his beloved Alisanda, who disappeared along with the city of Mezro during the Spellplague. No longer content to wait for Alisanda and Mezro to return on their own, Artus has been seeking the means to bring them back. He believes that Saja N'baza, an ancient guardian naga, can help him. As such, his search has been focused on locating the ruins of Orolunga, where the naga is said to dwell. Fate has handed Artus a saurial traveling companion named Dragonbait, whom he met in Port Nyanzaru. The two are always on the move. Consequently, their location in the adventure is randomly determined.
Using Artus. Artus has never been to Omu, and he has no idea where the city is. However, he has a powerful artifact in his possession and a good heart. If the characters explain why they've come to Chult, Artus puts aside his personal quest and offers to help them find Omu and destroy the Soulmonger.
The first time a situation forces Artus to use the Ring of Winter, he warns the characters that evil forces are after the ring and that his presence in the party might put the characters in danger.
Artus Cimber's Traits. Ideal. "The preservation of knowledge and history is important to me."
Bond. "I long to be reunited with my wife, Alisanda."
Flaw. "I am slow to trust strangers-adventurers in particular."
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 212</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Asharra</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (aarakocra)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>31 (7d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., fly 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>17</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>History +4, Insight +5, Perception +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages>Auran, Common</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dive Attack</name>
      <text>If the aarakocra is flying and dives at least 30 feet straight toward a target and then hits it with a melee weapon attack, the attack deals an extra 3 (1d6) damage to the target.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Dance of the Seven Winds</name>
      <text>Asharra knows a ritual called the Dance of the Seven Winds, which temporarily grants magical flight to as many as ten nonflying creatures. The ritual, which takes 10 minutes to complete, can only be performed by an aarakocra elder and requires a black orchid as a material component.</text>
      <text>Asharra must grind the orchid to powder, inhale it, and dance in circles around the ritual's beneficiaries uninterrupted while seven other aarakocra chant prayers to the Wind Dukes of Aaqa. When the dance concludes, Asharra's wings disappear and she loses the ability to fly. The ritual's beneficiaries each gain a magical flying speed of 30 feet (allowing them to fly 4 miles per hour). This benefit lasts for 3 days, after which Asharra's wings reappear and she regains the ability to fly.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Talon</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Talon|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Javelin</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 30/120 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Javelin|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Summon Air Elemental</name>
      <text>Five aarakocra within 30 feet of each other can magically summon an air elemental. Each of the five must use its action and movement on three consecutive turns to perform an aerial dance and must maintain concentration while doing so (as if concentrating on a spell). When all five have finished their third turn of the dance, the elemental appears in an unoccupied space within 60 feet of them. It is friendly toward them and obeys their spoken commands. It remains for 1 hour, until it or all its summoners die, or until any of its summoners dismisses it as a bonus action. A summoner can't perform the dance again until it finishes a short rest. When the elemental returns to the Elemental Plane of Air, any aarakocra within 5 feet of it can return with it.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Asharra is a 5th-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). Asharra has the following druid spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): druidcraft, mending, produce flame</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, faerie fire, thunderwave</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): gust of wind, hold person, lesser restoration</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (2 slots): call lightning, wind wall</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>druidcraft, mending, produce flame, detect magic, faerie fire, thunderwave, gust of wind, hold person, lesser restoration, call lightning, wind wall</spells>
    <description>Aarakocra range the Howling Gyre, an endless storm of mighty winds and lashing rains that surrounds the tranquil realm of Aaqa in the Elemental Plane of Air. Making aerial patrols, these birdlike humanoids guard the windy borders of their home against invaders from the Elemental Plane of Earth, such as gargoyles, their sworn enemies.
Biography. The incredibly old leader of the community at Kir Sabal. The others refer to her as Teacher, and they revere her as a living saint. Asharra is intelligent, ambitious, and somewhat manipulative, but never cruel or insensitive.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 69</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Assassin Vine</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>plant</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>85 (10d10+30)</hp>
    <speed>walk 5 ft., climb 5 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist>cold, fire</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, deafened, exhaustion, prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>False Appearance</name>
      <text>While the assassin vine remains motionless, it is indistinguishable from a normal plant.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Constrict</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 20 ft., one creature. The target takes 11 (2d6 + 4) bludgeoning damage, and it is grappled (escape DC 14). Until this grapple ends, the target is restrained, and it takes 21 (6d6) poison damage at the start of each of its turns. The vine can constrict only one target at a time.</text>
      <attack>Constrict|+6|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Entangling Vines</name>
      <text>The assassin vine can animate normal vines and roots on the ground in a 15-foot square within 30 feet of it. These plants turn the ground in that area into difficult terrain. A creature in that area when the effect begins must succeed on a DC 13 Strength saving throw or be restrained by entangling vines and roots. A creature restrained by the plants can use its action to make a DC 13 Strength (Athletics) check, freeing itself on a successful check. The effect ends after 1 minute or when the assassin vine dies or uses Entangling Vines again.</text>
      </action>
    <description>An assassin vine is an ambulatory plant that collects its fertilizer by grabbing and crushing prey and depositing the carcasses near its roots. It usually stays put unless it needs to seek out prey. A mature plant consists of a main vine, about 20 feet long. Smaller vines up to 5 feet long branch from the main vine every 6 inches. In late summer, the secondary vines produce bunches of small fruits that resemble wild grapes. The fruit is tough and has a hearty but bitter flavor.
A subterranean variant grows near hot springs, volcanic vents, and other sources of heat. An assassin vine growing underground usually generates enough offal to support a thriving colony of mushrooms and other fungi, which spring up around the plant and help conceal it.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 213, Ghosts of Saltmarsh, Essentials Kit: Sleeping Dragon's Wake</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Atropal</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>undead (titan)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>7</ac>
    <hp>225 (18d12+108)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>5</dex>
    <con>22</con>
    <int>25</int>
    <wis>19</wis>
    <cha>24</cha>
    <save>Con +11, Wis +9</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>understands Celestial but utters only obscene nonsense</languages>
    <cr>13</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>cold, necrotic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</immune>
    <vulnerable>radiant</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft., truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The atropal has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Negative Energy Aura</name>
      <text>Creatures within 30 feet of the atropal can't regain hit points, and any creature that starts its turn within 30 feet of the atropal takes 10 (3d6) necrotic damage. If the atropal is struck by a vorpal sword, the wielder can cut the atropal's umbilical cord instead of dealing damage. If its umbilical cord is cut, the atropal loses this feature.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Turn Resistance Aura</name>
      <text>The atropal and any other undead creature within 30 feet of it has advantage on saving throws against any effect that turns undead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (3d6) necrotic damage.</text>
      <attack>Touch|+9|3d6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Ray of Cold</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +12 to hit, range 120 ft., one target. 21 (6d6) cold damage.</text>
      <attack>Ray of Cold|+12|6d6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Life Drain</name>
      <text>The atropal targets one creature it can see within 120 feet of it. The target must succeed on a DC 19 Constitution saving throw, taking 36 (8d8) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one. The atropal regains a number of hit points equal to half the amount of damage dealt.</text>
      <attack>Life Drain||8d8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Summon Wraith (Recharge 6)</name>
      <text>The atropal summons a wraith which materializes within 30 feet of it in an unoccupied space it can see. The wraith obeys its summoner's commands and can't be controlled by any other creature. The Wraith vanishes when it drops to 0 hit points or when its summoner dies.</text>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>The undead (titan) can take 3 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. The undead (titan) regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Touch</name>
      <text>The atropal makes a touch attack.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Ray of Cold (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>The atropal uses its Ray of Cold.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Wail (Costs 3 Actions)</name>
      <text>The atropal lets out a withering wail. Any creature within 120 feet of the atropal that can hear the wail must succeed on a DC 19 Constitution saving throw or gain 1 level of exhaustion.</text>
      </legendary>
    <description>An atropal is a ghastly, unfinished creation of an evil god, cast adrift and abandoned long ago. Since an atropal was never truly alive, it can't be raised from the dead or resurrected by any means. Even divine intervention can't breathe true life into this hateful, miserable horror.
An atropal is malformed and unfinished. Its wet, wrinkled, and bloated body is surmounted by a hairless, overlarge head set with glassy, vacant eyes. It constantly drools stinking ichor as it mouths obscenities. Its arms are too slender, with tiny hands ending in cruelly shaped nails. An atropal never walks but always floats, with its atrophied, dead legs hanging useless below it.
Negative Energy Connection. The shriveled umbilical cord of an atropal appears to trail off into nothingness, but in fact, it attaches to the Negative Plane. This connection gives the atropal power over death and undeath. The cord can be severed by a vorpal sword or other vorpal weapon, and doing so weakens the atropal's tie to the Negative Plane.
An atropal can summon vestiges of creatures that died in the Negative Plane, which manifest as wraiths. These servants can exist outside the Negative Plane only by the atropal's sheer force of will, and they quickly dissipate when the atropal is destroyed.
Undead Nature. An atropal doesn't require air, food, drink, or sleep.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 214</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Azaka Stormfang</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human, shapechanger)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>120 (16d8+48)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>17</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +5, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>Common (can't speak in tiger form)</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't silvered</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>The Azaka can use its action to polymorph into a tiger-humanoid hybrid or into a tiger, or back into its true form, which is humanoid. Its statistics, other than its size, are the same in each form. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying isn't transformed. It reverts to its true form if it dies.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Hearing and Smell</name>
      <text>The Azaka has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing or smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Pounce (Tiger or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>If the Azaka moves at least 15 feet straight toward a creature and then hits it with a claw attack on the same turn, that target must succeed on a DC 14 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone. If the target is prone, the Azaka can make one bite attack against it as a bonus action.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>In humanoid form, the Azaka makes two scimitar attacks or two longbow attacks. In hybrid form, it can attack like a humanoid or make two claw attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite (Tiger or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (1d10 + 3) piercing damage. If the target is a humanoid, it must succeed on a DC 13 Constitution saving throw or be cursed with Azaka lycanthropy.</text>
      <attack>Bite (Tiger or Hybrid Form Only)|+5|1d10+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw (Tiger or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw (Tiger or Hybrid Form Only)|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Scimitar (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Scimitar (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Longbow (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 150/600 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Longbow (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Nonhuman Lycanthropes</name>
      <text>The statistics presented in this section assume a base creature of human. However, you can also use the statistics to represent nonhuman lycanthropes, adding verisimilitude by allowing a nonhuman lycanthrope to retain one or more of its humanoid racial traits. For example, an elf werewolf might have the Fey Ancestry trait.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 33</description>
    <environment>grassland, forest, desert</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Bag of Nails</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (tabaxi)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>15 (studded leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>78 (12d8+24)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Dex +6, Int +4</save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +6, Deception +3, Perception +3, Stealth +9</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Thieves' cant, Common, Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Feline Agility</name>
      <text>When Bag of Nails moves on its turn in combat, he can double his speed until the end of the turn. Once he uses this trait, Bag of Nails can't use it again until he moves 0 feet on one of his turns.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Assassinate</name>
      <text>During his first turn, Bag of Nails has advantage on attack rolls against any creature that hasn't taken a turn. Any hit Bag of Nails scores against a surprised creature is a critical hit.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Evasion</name>
      <text>If Bag of Nails is subjected to an effect that allows him to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, Bag of Nails instead takes no damage if he succeeds on the saving throw, and only half damage if it fails.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sneak Attack (1/Turn)</name>
      <text>Bag of Nails deals an extra 14 (4d6) damage when he hits a target with a weapon attack and has advantage on the attack roll, or when the target is within 5 feet of an ally of his that isn't incapacitated and Bag of Nails doesn't have disadvantage on the attack roll.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Bag of Nails makes two shortsword attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+3|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage, and the target must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw, taking 24 (7d6) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+6|1d6+3</attack>
      <attack>Shortsword||7d6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Longbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 150/600 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage, and the target must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw, taking 24 (7d6) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Longbow|+6|1d8+3</attack>
      <attack>Longbow||7d6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Bag of Nails yearns for a hunter's death. Senility has taken hold, and now he sees all creatures as his prey.
He explains that he came to Omu to find a fabled treasure called the Navel of the Moon. He hoped to use its alleged powers to find his lost son, but he has long since given up hope of ever finding it.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 102</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Blind Artist</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>8</ac>
    <hp>22 (3d8+9)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>6</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>6</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save>Wis +0</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>8</passive>
    <languages>understands all languages it spoke in life but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Undead Fortitude</name>
      <text>If damage reduces the artist to 0 hit points, it must make a Constitution saving throw with a DC of 5 + the damage taken, unless the damage is radiant or from a critical hit. On a success, the artist drops to 1 hit point instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 164</description>
    <environment>urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Bosco Daggerhand</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any Non-Good Alignment</alignment>
    <ac>11 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>32 (5d8+10)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Intimidation +2</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Bosco wears a ring of animal influence.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>Bosco has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of Bosco's allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Bosco makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Mace</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 5 (1d6 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Mace|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Heavy Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, range 100/400 ft., one target. 5 (1d10) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Heavy Crossbow|+2|1d10</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 68</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Chwinga</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <hp>5 (2d4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft., climb 20 ft., swim 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>1</str>
    <dex>20</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +7, Perception +7, Stealth +7</skill>
    <passive>17</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Unusual Nature</name>
      <text>The chwinga doesn't require air, food, or drink. When it dies, it turns into a handful of flower petals, a cloud of pollen, a stone statuette resembling its former self, a tiny sphere of smooth stone, or a puddle of fresh water (your choice).</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Evasion</name>
      <text>When the chwinga is subjected to an effect that allows it to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, it instead takes no damage if it succeeds on the saving throw, and only half damage if it fails.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Magical Gift (1/Day)</name>
      <text>The chwinga targets a humanoid it can see within 5 feet of it. The target gains a supernatural charm of the DM's choice. See chapter 7 of the Dungeon Masters Guide for more information on supernatural charms.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Natural Shelter</name>
      <text>The chwinga magically takes shelter inside a rock, a living plant, or a natural source of fresh water in its space. The chwinga can't be targeted by any attack, spell, or other effect while inside this shelter, and the shelter doesn't impair the chwinga's blindsight. The chwinga can use it's action to emerge from a shelter. If its shelter is destroyed, the chwinga is forced out and appears in the shelter's space, but is otherwise unharmed.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The chwinga's innate spellcasting ability is Wisdom. It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material or verbal components:</text>
      <text>At will: druidcraft, guidance, pass without trace, resistance</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>druidcraft, guidance, pass without trace, resistance</spells>
    <description>A chwinga (pronounced cheh-WING-ah) is a tiny elemental spirit that lives in plants, rocks, and rivers far from civilization. Painfully shy, chwingas prefer to move about unseen.
If two or more chwingas live in the same area, each one will take shelter in a different plant, rock, or body of fresh water. Though no two chwingas look exactly alike, they resemble 6-inch-tall animated dolls with strange masks, spindly limbs, and wild hair. Their appearance is sometimes foreshadowed by cool breezes, the sweet smell of flowers, and dancing fireflies. Their mere presence makes a natural setting more lush and vibrant.
Humanoid Fascination. Chwingas shun most other creatures, but they find the trappings of civilization fascinating. They puzzle over creatures that wear armor, carry weapons, use tools, and cook food. When a chwinga encounters one or more humanoids, its curiosity sometimes gets the better of it, and it shadows those creatures for a short time to observe them. If it takes a liking to a particular humanoid, a chwinga might use its cantrips to aid it, or might bestow a magical gift before departing. The features that attract a chwinga to a particular humanoid can vary. In some cases, a chwinga might simply like the way a humanoid walks or the way it combs its hair. Other times, it might be smitten by a humanoid's ability to play music or to eat copious amounts of food.
Elemental Nature. Chwingas sleep but don't require air, food, or drink. They don't have names and have no ability to speak. When a chwinga dies, it turns into a handful of flower petals, a cloud of pollen, a stone statuette resembling its former self, a marble of smooth stone, or a puddle of fresh water.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 216</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Clay Gladiator</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>112 (15d8+45)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Str +7, Dex +5, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +10, Intimidation +5</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Climbing</name>
      <text>The gladiator can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without needing to make an ability check.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Steadfast</name>
      <text>The gladiator can't be disarmed, and cannot make ranged attacks.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Brute</name>
      <text>A melee weapon deals one extra die of its damage when the gladiator hits with it (included in the attack).</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The gladiator makes three melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) piercing damage, or 13 (2d8 + 4) piercing damage if used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Spear|+7|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shield Bash</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 9 (2d4 + 4) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Medium or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 15 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Shield Bash|+7|2d4+4</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>The gladiator adds 3 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, the gladiator must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>A clay gladiator fights if attacked or when called to the gladiatorial pit. If reduced to 0 hit points outside of the gladiatorial pit, the gladiator disappears along with its possessions, reappears in its cell at full health with spear and shield in hand, and returns to the gladiatorial pit if it can. If defeated in the gladiatorial pit, the gladiator leaves its spear behind before reforming in its cell
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 100</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Dragonbait</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (saurial)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>17 (breastplate, shield)</ac>
    <hp>120 (16d8+48)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Wis +6, Cha +7</save>
    <skill>Athletics +5, Medicine +6</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>understands Common but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Divine Health</name>
      <text>Dragonbait is immune to disease.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>While holding his holy avenger, Dragonbait creates an aura in a 10-foot radius around him. While this aura is active, Dragonbait and all creatures friendly to him in the aura have advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Dragonbait makes two melee weapon attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Holy Avenger (+3 Longsword)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (1d8 + 5) slashing damage, or 10 (1d10 + 5) slashing damage when used with two hands. If the target is a fiend or an undead it takes an extra 11 (2d10) radiant damage.</text>
      <attack>Holy Avenger (+3 Longsword)|+8|1d8+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Sense Alignment</name>
      <text>Dragonbait chooses one creature he can see within 60 feet of him and determines its alignment, as long as the creature isn't hidden from divination magic by a spell or other magical effect.</text>
      </action>
    <description>Dragonbait is a champion of good and a saurial-a race that originated on a distant world and whose members have long lives. Very few saurials dwell in the Forgotten Realms, and no saurial communities are believed to exist anywhere in the world.
The saurial's language is a combination of clicks and whistles beyond the human range of hearing, so Dragonbait tends to rely on scents to communicate emotions. To be understood by most speaking creatures, he must "shout" a scent. Dragonbait's known scents include: brimstone (confusion), roses (sadness), lemon (pleasure or joy), baked bread (anger), violets (danger or fear), honeysuckle (tenderness or concern), wood smoke (devotion or piety), tar (victory or celebration), and ham (nervousness or worry).
Dragonbait stands 4 feet 10 inches tall, weighs 150 pounds, and has a dry, wrinkled hide. He wields a holy avenger longsword and carries a blue, red, and white shield. Though he has traits in common with paladins, Dragonbait isn't a member of any class. Using an ability known as the Shen-state, he can determine the alignment of any creature within 60 feet of him.
An Unexpected Friendship. Dragonbait met Artus Cimber in Port Nyanzaru, and the two became fast friends. As Artus spoke of his quest to reunite with his wife, Alisanda, he was comforted by Dragonbait's quiet manner and unusual methods of communication. With a smile and a nod, Dragonbait agreed to help Artus. A frequent visitor to Chult, the saurial understood the dangers of the jungle all too well.
Using Dragonbait. Dragonbait has never been to Omu and doesn't know where the city is located. If the characters convince Artus Cimber to help them destroy the Soulmonger, Dragonbait wants to help as well.
Dragonbait's Traits. Ideal. Dragonbait emits a lemon scent while thinking about exploring the world, seeing its many wonders, and helping others along the way. (Translation: He has the heart of an explorer.)
Bond. Dragonbait gives off the scent of wood smoke while doing things to aid a friend's quest. (Translation: He would do anything for a friend.)
Flaw. Dragonbait "shouts" the scent of ham while going where others fear to tread. (Translation: He will hurl himself into danger no matter how frightening.)
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 218</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Drufi</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>giant</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (patchwork armor)</ac>
    <hp>138 (12d12+60)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>23</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>21</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Con +8, Wis +3, Cha +4</save>
    <skill>Athletics +9, Perception +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Giant</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>cold</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Drufi makes two greataxe attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Greataxe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 25 (3d12 + 6) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Greataxe|+9|3d12+6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Rock</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, range 60/240 ft., one target. 28 (4d10 + 6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Rock|+9|4d10+6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: New Giant Options</name>
      <text>Some adult frost giants are skilled hunters who construct and hurl nets weighted down with fragments of metal or bone. This ability is represented by the following action option.</text>
      <text>Weighted Net. Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, ranged 20/60 ft., one Small, Medium, or Large creature. The target is restrained until it escapes the net. Any creature can use its action to make a DC 17 Strength check to free itself or another creature in the net, ending the effect on a success. Dealing 15 slashing damage to the net (AC 12) destroys the net and frees the target.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 64</description>
    <environment>mountain, arctic</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Eblis</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>26 (4d10+4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Auran, Common</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The eblis attacks twice with its beak.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Beak</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Beak|+5|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The eblis's innate spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 11). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>1/day each: blur, hypnotic pattern, minor illusion</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>blur, hypnotic pattern, minor illusion</spells>
    <description>Eblis (pronounced EH-blee) are thought to be reincarnations of evil humans who were punished by gods for acts of larceny and kidnapping. These intelligent, evil cranes loom 8 feet tall and lay eggs as mundane birds do. They can manipulate objects with their beaks and feet.
Eblis try to sway other creatures into doing their bidding, and their plots are self-serving. They live to destroy creatures that offend them and delight in luring humanoids to an unexpected death. Eblis also like to collect treasure, which they sometimes use to reward those who serve them. They build crude huts and nests out of grass and reeds, wherein they hide their treasure.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 219</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Ekene-Afa</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>16 (studded leather armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>112 (15d8+45)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Str +7, Dex +5, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +10, Intimidation +5</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Brave</name>
      <text>Ekene-Afa has advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Brute</name>
      <text>A melee weapon deals one extra die of its damage when Ekene-Afa hits with it (included in the attack).</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Ekene-Afa makes three melee attacks or two ranged attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft. and range 20/60 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) piercing damage, or 13 (2d8 + 4) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Spear|+7|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shield Bash</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 9 (2d4 + 4) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Medium or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 15 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Shield Bash|+7|2d4+4</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Ekene-Afa adds 3 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, Ekene-Afa must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 25</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Eku</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>celestial</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>19 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>97 (13d8+39)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 90 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>20</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>18</int>
    <wis>20</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Con +5, Wis +7, Cha +6</save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>all, telepathy 120 ft.</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist>radiant</resist>
    <immune>psychic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Weapons</name>
      <text>Eku's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Shielded Mind</name>
      <text>Eku is immune to scrying and to any effect that would sense its emotions, read its thoughts, or detect its location.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 8 (1d6 + 5) piercing damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 13 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned for 24 hours. Until this poison ends, the target is unconscious. Another creature can use an action to shake the target awake.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+8|1d6+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Constrict</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 10 ft., one Medium or smaller creature. 10 (2d6 + 3) bludgeoning damage, and the target is grappled (escape DC 15). Until this grapple ends, the target is restrained, and Eku can't constrict another target.</text>
      <attack>Constrict|+6|2d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Change Shape</name>
      <text>Eku magically polymorphs into a humanoid or beast that has a challenge rating equal to or less than its own, or back into its true form. It reverts to its true form if it dies. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying is absorbed or borne by the new form (Eku's choice).</text>
      <text>In a new form, Eku retains its game statistics and ability to speak, but its AC, movement modes, Strength, Dexterity, and other actions are replaced by those of the new form, and it gains any statistics and capabilities (except class features, legendary actions, and lair actions) that the new form has but that it lacks. If the new form has a bite attack, Eku can use its bite in that form.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Eku's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 14). It can innately cast the following spells, requiring only verbal components:</text>
      <text>At will: detect evil and good, detect magic, detect thoughts</text>
      <text>3/day each: bless, create food and water, cure wounds, lesser restoration, protection from poison, sanctuary, shield</text>
      <text>1/day each: dream, greater restoration, scrying</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>detect evil and good, detect magic, detect thoughts, bless, create food and water, cure wounds, lesser restoration, protection from poison, sanctuary, shield, dream, greater restoration, scrying</spells>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 34</description>
    <environment>grassland, forest, urban, desert</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Elok Jaharwon</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human, shapechanger)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>10 (in humanoid form, 11 (natural armor) in boar or hybrid form)</ac>
    <hp>78 (12d8+24)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>17</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>8</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common (can't speak in boar form)</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't silvered</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>Elok can use its action to polymorph into a boar-humanoid hybrid or into a boar, or back into its true form, which is humanoid. Its statistics, other than its AC, are the same in each form. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying isn't transformed. It reverts to its true form if it dies.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Charge (Boar or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>If Elok moves at least 15 feet straight toward a target and then hits it with its tusks on the same turn, the target takes an extra 7 (2d6) slashing damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 13 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Relentless (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>If Elok takes 14 damage or less that would reduce it to 0 hit points, it is reduced to 1 hit point instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Elok makes two attacks, only one of which can be with its tusks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Maul (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (2d6 + 3) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Maul (Humanoid or Hybrid Form Only)|+5|2d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Tusks (Boar or Hybrid Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (2d6 + 3) slashing damage. If the target is a humanoid, it must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or be cursed with wereboar lycanthropy.</text>
      <attack>Tusks (Boar or Hybrid Form Only)|+5|2d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Nonhuman Lycanthropes</name>
      <text>The statistics presented in this section assume a base creature of human. However, you can also use the statistics to represent nonhuman lycanthropes, adding verisimilitude by allowing a nonhuman lycanthrope to retain one or more of its humanoid racial traits. For example, an elf werewolf might have the Fey Ancestry trait.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 67</description>
    <environment>grassland, forest, hill</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Faroul</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>16 (3d8+3)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Nature +4, Perception +5, Stealth +6, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Hearing and Sight</name>
      <text>Faroul has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing or sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Faroul makes two melee attacks or two ranged attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Longbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, ranged 150/600 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Longbow|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 34</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Fenthaza</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity (shapechanger, yuan-ti)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>71 (13d8+13)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Wis +3, Cha +5</save>
    <skill>Deception +5, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 120 ft. (penetrates magical darkness)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>Fenthaza can use its action to polymorph into a Medium snake or back into its true form. Its statistics are the same in each form. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying isn't transformed. If it dies, it stays in its current form.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Death Fangs (2/Day)</name>
      <text>The first time Fenthaza hits with a melee attack on its turn, it can deal an extra 16 (3d10) necrotic damage to the target.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Fenthaza has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack (Yuan-ti Form Only)</name>
      <text>Fenthaza makes one constrict attack and one scimitar attack.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Constrict</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 10 (2d6 + 3) bludgeoning damage, and the target is grappled (escape DC 14) if it is a Large or smaller creature. Until this grapple ends, the target is restrained, and Fenthaza can't constrict another target.</text>
      <attack>Constrict|+5|2d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Scimitar (Yuan-ti Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Scimitar (Yuan-ti Form Only)|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Invoke Nightmare (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>Fenthaza taps into the nightmares of a creature it can see within 60 feet of it and creates an illusory, immobile manifestation of the creature's deepest fears, visible only to that creature. The target must make a DC 13 Intelligence saving throw. On a failed save, the target takes 11 (2d10) psychic damage and is frightened of the manifestation, believing it to be real. Fenthaza must concentrate to maintain the illusion (as if concentrating on a spell), which lasts for up to 1 minute and can't be harmed. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the illusion on a success, or taking 11 (2d10) psychic damage on a failure.</text>
      <attack>Invoke Nightmare (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)||2d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Chameleon Skin</name>
      <text>Fenthaza has advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks made to hide.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Shed Skin (1/Day)</name>
      <text>Fenthaza can shed its skin as a bonus action to free itself from a grapple, shackles, or other restraints. If Fenthaza spends 1 minute eating its shed skin, it regains hit points equal to half its hit point maximum.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting (Yuan-ti Form Only)</name>
      <text>Fenthaza's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 13). Fenthaza can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: animal friendship (snakes only)</text>
      <text>3/day: suggestion</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting (Yuan-ti Form Only)</name>
      <text>Fenthaza is a 6th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). It regains its expended spell slots when it finishes a short or long rest. It knows the following warlock spells:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): chill touch, eldritch blast (range 300 ft., +3 bonus to each damage roll), mage hand, message, poison spray, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (2 slots): arms of Hadar, darkness, fear, hex, hold person, hunger of Hadar, witch bolt</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>2</slots>
    <spells>animal friendship, suggestion, chill touch, eldritch blast, mage hand, message, poison spray, prestidigitation, arms of Hadar, darkness, fear, hex, hold person, hunger of Hadar, witch bolt</spells>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 113</description>
    <environment>underdark, forest, desert</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Flask of Wine</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (tabaxi)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Good</alignment>
    <ac>14 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>40 (9d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +2, Perception +4, Stealth +5, Survival +6</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common plus any one language</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Feline Agility</name>
      <text>When Flask of Wine moves on its turn in combat, it can double its speed until the end of the turn. Once it uses this ability, Flask of Wine can't use it again until it moves 0 feet on one of its turns.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Flask of Wine makes two attacks with its claws, its shortsword, or its shortbow.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 35</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Flying Monkey</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>3 (1d6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 20 ft., fly 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>8</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>5</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>The flying monkey has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the monkey's allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Familiar</name>
      <text>With the DM's permission, the find familiar spell can summon a flying monkey.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +1 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target 1 (1d4 - 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+1|1d4-1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Flying monkeys are slightly more clever and curious than common monkeys, and they can be domesticated and taught to obey simple commands. They come in many colors and varieties, with feathered wings that have a span of about 5 feet. With the DM's permission, the find familiar spell can summon a flying monkey.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 220</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Giant Four-Armed Gargoyle</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>147 (14d10+70)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>20</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save>Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Terran</languages>
    <cr>10</cr>
    <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks not made with adamantine weapons</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>False Appearance</name>
      <text>While the gargoyle remains motionless, it is indistinguishable from an inanimate statue.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The gargoyle makes five attacks: one with its bite and four with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+8|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +8 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (2d4 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+8|2d4+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Only Acererak knows the secret of creating these creatures. A giant four-armed gargoyle stands 8 to 9 feet tall and weighs roughly five thousand pounds. It is typically employed as a tomb guardian, rending intruders with its fangs and deadly claws. For more information on gargoyles, see the Monster Manual.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 221</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Giant Snapping Turtle</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor, 12 while prone)</ac>
    <hp>75 (10d10+20)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., swim 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>The turtle can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Stable</name>
      <text>Whenever an effect knocks the turtle prone, it can make a DC 10 Constitution saving throw to avoid being knocked prone. A prone turtle is upside down. To stand up, it must succeed on a DC 10 Dexterity check on its turn and then use all its movement for that turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 18 (4d6 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+6|4d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Giant snapping turtles can grow to be 12 feet in diameter. Although they appear slow and ponderous, they are capable of startling bursts of speed and will aggressively attack smaller creatures that approach them. One snap of a giant turtle's jaws can cut a human in half, and these creatures aren't fussy about what they eat.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 222</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Girallon Zombie</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>11 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>59 (7d10+21)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>7</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>8</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Aggressive</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, the zombie can move up to its speed toward a hostile creature that it can see.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Undead Fortitude</name>
      <text>If damage reduces the zombie to 0 hit points, it must make a Constitution saving throw with a DC of 5+the damage taken, unless the damage is radiant or from a critical hit. On a success, the zombie drops to 1 hit point instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The zombie makes five attacks: one with its bite and four with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d6 + 4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+6|1d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d4 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+6|1d4+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Several new zombie variants are presented below. For more information on zombies, see the Monster Manual.
Ankylosaurus Zombie. This creature is slow and barely aware of its surroundings.
Girallon Zombie. Girallons are four-armed apes with white fur. Girallon zombies are slower than their non-undead counterparts but no less fierce. The necromantic energy empowering them fuels their murderous hearts and their hunger for living flesh.
Tyrannosaurus Zombie. A tyrannosaurus zombie has a gullet full of smaller zombies, which it can disgorge. These zombies aren't under the tyrannosaurus zombie's control.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 240</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Gondolo</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (halfling)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>13 (3d6+3)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Nature +4, Perception +5, Stealth +6, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common), Halfling</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Hearing and Sight</name>
      <text>Gondolo has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing or sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Halfling Nimbleness</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; can move through a space of a Medium or larger creature.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Brave</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; has advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Gondolo makes two melee attacks or two ranged attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Longbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, ranged 150/600 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Longbow|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 34</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Grabstab</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (goblinoid)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (chain shirt, shield)</ac>
    <hp>21 (6d6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>8</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Stealth +6</skill>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages>Common, Goblin</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Nimble Escape</name>
      <text>Grabstab can take the Disengage or Hide action as a bonus action on each of its turns.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Grabstab makes two attacks with its scimitar. The second attack has disadvantage.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Scimitar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Scimitar|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Javelin</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 30/120 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Javelin|+2|1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Redirect Attack</name>
      <text>When a creature Grabstab can see targets it with an attack, Grabstab chooses another goblin within 5 feet of it. The two goblins swap places, and the chosen goblin becomes the target instead.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 89</description>
    <environment>underdark, grassland, forest, hill</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Grandfather Zitembe</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (chain shirt)</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Medicine +7, Persuasion +3, Religion +5</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>any two languages</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Divine Eminence</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Zitembe can expend a spell slot to cause its melee weapon attacks to magically deal an extra 10 (3d6) radiant damage to a target on a hit. This benefit lasts until the end of the turn. If Zitembe expends a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the extra damage increases by 1d6 for each level above 1st.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Mace</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Mace|+2|1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Zitembe is a 5th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). Zitembe has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): cure wounds, guiding bolt, sanctuary</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): lesser restoration, spiritual weapon</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (2 slots): dispel magic, spirit guardians</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy, cure wounds, guiding bolt, sanctuary, lesser restoration, spiritual weapon, dispel magic, spirit guardians</spells>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 20</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Hew Hackinstone</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>13 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>67 (9d8+27)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Survival +4</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
      <text>Hew has resistance to poison damage and advantage on saving throws against being poisoned.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Reckless</name>
      <text>At the start of his turn, Hew can gain advantage on all melee weapon attack rolls during that turn, but attack rolls against him have advantage until the start of his next turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Battleaxe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Battleaxe|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Hailing from uncivilized lands, unpredictable berserkers come together in war parties and seek conflict wherever they can find it.
Biography. Three years ago, Hew was part of a dwarven expedition seeking to reopen Wyrmheart Mine. The expedition encountered Tinder the red dragon. Hew alone escaped, and only after the dragon bit off his left arm. Hew wants to return to the mine and slay the dragon, but he needs a band of stout-hearted adventurers to help him. If the characters hire him as a guide, Hew says he can lead them wherever they want, but he'll only take them to Wyrmheart Mine.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 33</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Ifan Talro'a</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (breastplate)</ac>
    <hp>9 (2d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +5, Insight +4, Persuasion +5</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>any two languages</languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Rapier</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d8 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Rapier|+3|1d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Ifan adds 2 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, Ifan must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 25</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Jaculi</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>14 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>16 (3d10)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>8</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +4, Perception +1, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Camouflage</name>
      <text>The jaculi has advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks made to hide.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>The jaculi has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 9 (2d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+4|2d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spring</name>
      <text>The jaculi springs up to 30 feet in a straight line and makes a bite attack against a target within its reach. This attack has advantage if the jaculi springs at least 10 feet. If the attack hits, the bite deals an extra 7 (2d6) piercing damage.</text>
      </action>
    <description>A jaculi (pronounced jah-KOO-lee) is a 15-foot-long snake that can alter the color and texture of its scales to camouflage itself. Altering its appearance to resemble wood or stone, it coils around pillars and tree trunks from which it launches itself like a javelin, striking with great force and accuracy.
Jaculis are found in damp climates, and their preferred habitats are rainforests and cool dungeons. The shed skin of the jaculi is coveted for use in crafting boots of striding and springing and cloaks of invisibility.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 225</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Jessamine</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any Non-Good Alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (studded leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>78 (12d8+24)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save>Dex +6, Int +4</save>
    <skill>Acrobatics +6, Deception +3, Perception +3, Stealth +9</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Thieves' cant plus any two languages</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Assassinate</name>
      <text>During its first turn, the assassin has advantage on attack rolls against any creature that hasn't taken a turn. Any hit the assassin scores against a surprised creature is a critical hit.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Evasion</name>
      <text>If the assassin is subjected to an effect that allows it to make a Dexterity saving throw to take only half damage, the assassin instead takes no damage if it succeeds on the saving throw, and only half damage if it fails.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sneak Attack (1/Turn)</name>
      <text>The assassin deals an extra 14 (4d6) damage when it hits a target with a weapon attack and has advantage on the attack roll, or when the target is within 5 feet of an ally of the assassin that isn't incapacitated and the assassin doesn't have disadvantage on the attack roll.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The assassin makes two shortsword attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage, and the target must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw, taking 24 (7d6) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+6|1d6+3</attack>
      <attack>Shortsword||7d6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Light Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) piercing damage, and the target must make a DC 15 Constitution saving throw, taking 24 (7d6) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Light Crossbow|+6|1d8+3</attack>
      <attack>Light Crossbow||7d6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 26</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Jobal</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>16 (3d8+3)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Nature +4, Perception +5, Stealth +6, Survival +5</skill>
    <passive>15</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Hearing and Sight</name>
      <text>Jobal has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing or sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Jobal makes two melee attacks or two ranged attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Longbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, ranged 150/600 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Longbow|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 26</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Kamadan</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>67 (9d10+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +4, Stealth +7</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Smell</name>
      <text>The kamadan has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Pounce</name>
      <text>If the kamadan moves at least 20 feet straight toward a creature and then hits it with a claw attack on the same turn that target must succeed on a DC 13 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone. If the target is knocked prone, the kamadan can make two attacks—one with its bite and one with its snakes—against it as a bonus action.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The kamadan makes two attacks: one with its bite or claw and one with its snakes.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Snakes</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage, and the target must make a DC 12 Constitution saving throw, taking 21 (6d6) poison damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Snakes|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      <attack>Snakes||6d6</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Sleep Breath (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>The kamadan exhales sleep gas in a 30-foot cone. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or fall unconscious for 10 minutes. This effect ends for a creature if it takes damage or someone uses an action to wake it.</text>
      </action>
    <description>A kamadan (pronounced KAM-ah-dan) is a feline predator that resembles a leopard with six snakes sprouting from its shoulders. Although it bears a passing resemblance to a displacer beast, the two creatures are unrelated (though some sages claim otherwise).
Kamadans typically hunt alone or in mated pairs. They can exhale clouds of sleep gas, which they typically do before entering melee combat. If a kamadan has both conscious and unconscious enemies within striking range, it tries to kill the conscious enemies first before finishing off any sleeping foes.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 225</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>King of Feathers</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>200 (19d12+52)</hp>
    <speed>walk 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>25</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>19</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Detect Invisibility</name>
      <text>The King of Feathers can see invisible creatures and objects as if they were visible.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If the King of Feathers fails a saving throw, it can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The King of Feathers makes two attacks: one with its bite and one with its tail. It can't make both attacks against the same target.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 33 (4d12 + 7) piercing damage. If the target is a Medium or smaller creature, it is grappled (escape DC 17). Until this grapple ends, the target is restrained, and the tyrannosaurus can't bite another target.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+10|4d12+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 20 (3d8 + 7) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Tail|+10|3d8+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Summon Swarm (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The King of Feathers exhales a swarm of insects (wasps) that forms in a space within 20 feet of it. The swarm acts as an ally of the King of Feathers and takes its turn immediately after it. The swarm disperses after 1 minute. It can't use the Summon Swarm action while it is grappling a creature with its jaws.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>The King of Feathers's innate spellcasting ability is Wisdom. It can innately cast the following spell, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: misty step</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>misty step</spells>
    <description>The monstrous tyrannosaurus known as the King of Feathers is the undisputed lord of Omu. Most other dwellers of the Forbidden City live in fear of its thunderous approach and steer well clear of the amphitheater, its lair.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 106</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Kupalué</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>plant</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>9 (2d6+2)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>7</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +2, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Vegepygmy</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist>lightning, piercing</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Plant Camouflage</name>
      <text>Kupalué has advantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks it makes in any terrain with ample obscuring plant life.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Regeneration</name>
      <text>Kupalué regains 3 hit points at the start of its turn. If it takes cold, fire, or necrotic damage, this trait doesn't function at the start of Kupalué's next turn. Kupalué dies only if it starts its turn with 0 hit points and doesn't regenerate.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Sling</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Sling|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 35</description>
    <environment>forest, swamp</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Kwayothé</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (chain shirt)</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Medicine +7, Persuasion +3, Religion +5</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>any two languages</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Divine Eminence</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Kwayothé can expend a spell slot to cause its melee weapon attacks to magically deal an extra 10 (3d6) radiant damage to a target on a hit. This benefit lasts until the end of the turn. If Kwayothé expends a spell slot of 2nd level or higher, the extra damage increases by 1d6 for each level above 1st.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Mace</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Mace|+2|1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Kwayothé is a 5th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). Kwayothé has the following cleric spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): cure wounds, guiding bolt, sanctuary</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): lesser restoration, spiritual weapon</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (2 slots): dispel magic, spirit guardians</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 2</slots>
    <spells>light, sacred flame, thaumaturgy, cure wounds, guiding bolt, sanctuary, lesser restoration, spiritual weapon, dispel magic, spirit guardians</spells>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 26</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Laskilar</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any Non-Lawful Alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (studded leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>65 (10d8+20)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Str +4, Dex +5, Wis +2</save>
    <skill>Athletics +4, Deception +4</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>any two languages</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Laskilar wears a cape of the mountebank.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Laskilar makes three melee attacks: two with its scimitar and one with its dagger. Or Laskilar makes two ranged attacks with its daggers.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Scimitar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Scimitar|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Laskilar adds 2 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, Laskilar must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 67</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Liara Portyr</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (studded leather armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>84 (13d8+26)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Con +4, Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Athletics +5, Deception +5, Insight +4, Intimidation +5</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Brave</name>
      <text>Liara has advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Flaming Fury</name>
      <text>Once per turn, when Liara hits a creature with a melee weapon, she can cause fire to magically erupt from her weapon and deal an extra 10 (3d6) fire damage to the target.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Liara makes three melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Battleaxe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) slashing damage, or 8 (1d10 + 3) slashing damage when used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Battleaxe|+5|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Heavy Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, range 100/400 ft., one target. 6 (1d10 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Heavy Crossbow|+3|1d10+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>As the commander of Fort Beluarian, Liara spends most of her time worrying about the security of her stronghold while cutting deals with pirates. In general, she has no problem with adventurers and will do her utmost to help them deal with the myriad threats lurking in the jungle.
Liara comes from an influential family in Baldur's Gate and has held her post for the past three years. To her, the assignment feels like a test of mettle, but to many of her subordinates, Fort Beluarian feels like banishment. Liara's spies in Port Nyanzaru furnish her with ship manifests and departure schedules that she passes along to the pirates of Jahaka Anchorage, in exchange for promises to never attack ships flying the flag of Baldur's Gate. Liara also receives a cut of the pirates' profits, some of which go toward keeping her garrison happy.
Liara Portyr's Traits. Ideal. "One must respect the chain of command. You follow my orders, or you die."
Bond. "I have sworn to hold and protect Fort Beluarian in the name of Grand Duke Ulder Ravengard of Baldur's Gate. The fort will not fall on my watch!"
Flaw. "It's a ghoul-eat-you world out here. I have no pity for those who can't defend themselves."
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 227, Baldur's Gate: Descent Into Avernus</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Mantrap</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>plant</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>45 (7d10+7)</hp>
    <speed>walk 5 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>2</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +4, Stealth +6</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, deafened, exhaustion, prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>tremorsense 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Attractive Pollen (1/Day)</name>
      <text>When the mantrap detects any creatures nearby, it can use its reaction to release pollen out to a radius of 30 feet. Any beast or humanoid within the area must succeed on a DC 11 Wisdom saving throw or be forced to use all its movement on its turns to get as close to the the mantrap as possible. An affected target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>False Appearance</name>
      <text>While the mantrap remains motionless, it is indistinguishable from an ordinary tropical plant.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Engulf</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one Medium or smaller creature. The target is trapped inside the mantrap's leafy jaws. While trapped in this way, the target is blinded and restrained, has total cover from an attacks and other effects outside the mantrap, and takes 14 (4d6) acid damage at the start of each of the target's turns. If the mantrap dies, the creature inside it is no longer restrained by it. A mantrap can engulf only one creature at a time.</text>
      <attack>Engulf|+4|4d6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>A mantrap is a giant carnivorous plant that resembles an oversized flytrap. To attract prey, the mantrap releases a pollen that magically draws creatures to it. Though it will snap its leafy jaws shut around any warm-blooded creature that strays within its reach, it prefers humanoid prey.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 227</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Mister Threadneedle</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>36 (8d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>13</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist>bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable>fire</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>False Appearance</name>
      <text>While Mister Threadneedle remains motionless, it is indistinguishable from an ordinary, inanimate scarecrow.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Mister Threadneedle makes two claw attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (2d4 + 1) slashing damage. If the target is a creature, it must succeed on a DC 11 Wisdom saving throw or be frightened until the end of Mister Threadneedle's next turn.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+3|2d4+1</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Terrifying Glare</name>
      <text>Mister Threadneedle targets one creature it can see within 30 feet of it. If the target can see Mister Threadneedle, the target must succeed on a DC 11 Wisdom saving throw or be magically frightened until the end of Mister Threadneedle's next turn. The frightened target is paralyzed.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 183</description>
    <environment>grassland</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Musharib</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (dwarf)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>13 (hide armor)</ac>
    <hp>30 (4d8+12)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +4, Stealth +3, Survival +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist>poison</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dwarven Resilience</name>
      <text>Musharib has advantage on saving throws against poison.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Handaxe</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Handaxe|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Musharib's innate spellcasting ability is Wisdom. It can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>1/day each: hunter's mark, jump, pass without trace, speak with animals, speak with plants</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>hunter's mark, jump, pass without trace, speak with animals, speak with plants</spells>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 34</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Mwaxanaré</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>13 (3d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>6</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +5, Nature +3, Persuasion +5, Religion +3</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Auran, Common, telepathy 30 ft.</languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +2 to hit. reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Mwaxanaré is a 2nd-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). She regains her expended spell slots when she finishes a short or long rest. She knows the following warlock spells:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): eldritch blast, mage hand</text>
      <text>• 1st level (2 slots): charm person, protection from evil and good, unseen servant</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>2</slots>
    <spells>eldritch blast, mage hand, charm person, protection from evil and good, unseen servant</spells>
    <description>At the tender age of seventeen, Princess Mwaxanaré ("Naré" for short) is the oldest living descendant of the royal families of Omu and the natural inheritor of their fallen kingdom. She and her six-year-old brother, Na, are guests of the aarakocra in Kir Sabal. The aarakocra aim to protect the young royals until such time as the evil in Omu has been vanquished.
Mwaxanaré is too headstrong for her own good. She longs to claim her throne and will eagerly use adventurers to make that happen. Her tone is almost always condescending, and she doesn't take kindly to backtalk.
After forging a pact with the Wind Dukes of Aaqa, ancient beings of the Outer Planes, the princess has become a fledgling warlock. Her hatred of physical labor allows her to put her mage hand and unseen servant spells to good use. Through her pact, she has also gained telepathy.
The young Prince Na is a noncombatant with AC 10 and 3 hit points. Having lived among the aarakocra for most of his life, Na considers himself one of them. He dresses like an aarakocra and prefers to speak Auran rather than Common.
Mwaxanaré's Traits. Ideal. "One day, I shall rule Chult as queen."
Bond. "I have forged a pact with the Wind Dukes of Aaqa and will use their power to protect my brother and the aarakocra who watch over us."
Flaw. "I am a princess and must be addressed with the proper respect. I don't follow orders; I give them."
Na's Traits. Ideal. "I want to become an aarakocra and learn how to fly like a bird!"
Bond. "I love my sister and the aarakocra. They mean everything to me."
Flaw. "I know nothing of the world."
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 228</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Na</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>3 (1d6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 228</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Nanny Pu'pu</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>fey</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>82 (11d8+33)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Arcana +3, Deception +4, Perception +4, Stealth +3</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Sylvan</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>Pu'pu can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Mimicry</name>
      <text>Pu'pu can mimic animal sounds and humanoid voices. A creature that hears the sounds can tell they are imitations with a successful DC 14 Wisdom (Insight) check.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hag Coven</name>
      <text>When hags must work together, they form covens, in spite of their selfish natures. A coven is made up of hags of any type, all of whom are equals within the group. However, each of Pu'pus continues to desire more personal power.</text>
      <text>A coven consists of three hags so that any arguments between two hags can be settled by the third. If more than three hags ever come together, as might happen if two covens come into conflict, the result is usually chaos.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Hag Eye (Coven Only)</name>
      <text>A hag coven can craft a magic item called a hag eye, which is made from a real eye coated in varnish and often fitted to a pendant or other wearable item. Pu'pu eye is usually entrusted to a minion for safekeeping and transport. A hag in the coven can take an action to see what Pu'pu eye sees if Pu'pu eye is on the same plane of existence. A hag eye has AC 10, 1 hit point, and darkvision with a radius of 60 feet. If it is destroyed, each coven member takes 3d10 psychic damage and is blinded for 24 hours.</text>
      <text>A hag coven can have only one hag eye at a time, and creating a new one requires all three members of the coven to perform a ritual. The ritual takes 1 hour, and Pu'pus can't perform it while blinded. During the ritual, if Pu'pus take any action other than performing the ritual, they must start over.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d8 + 4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+6|2d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Illusory Appearance</name>
      <text>Pu'pu covers herself and anything she is wearing or carrying with a magical illusion that makes her look like another creature of her general size and humanoid shape. The illusion ends if Pu'pu takes a bonus action to end it or if she dies.</text>
      <text>The changes wrought by this effect fail to hold up to physical inspection. For example, Pu'pu could appear to have smooth skin, but someone touching her would feel her rough flesh. Otherwise, a creature must take an action to visually inspect the illusion and succeed on a DC 20 Intelligence (Investigation) check to discern that Pu'pu is disguised.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Invisible Passage</name>
      <text>Pu'pu magically turns invisible until she attacks or casts a spell, or until her concentration ends (as if concentrating on a spell). While invisible, she leaves no physical evidence of her passage, so she can be tracked only by magic. Any equipment she wears or carries is invisible with her.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Pu'pu's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 12). She can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: dancing lights, minor illusion, vicious mockery</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Shared Spellcasting (Coven Only)</name>
      <text>While all three members of a hag coven are within 30 feet of one another, they can each cast the following spells from the wizard's spell list but must share the spell slots among themselves:</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): identify, ray of sickness</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): hold person, locate object</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): bestow curse, counterspell, lightning bolt</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): phantasmal killer, polymorph</text>
      <text>• 5th level (2 slots): contact other plane, scrying</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): eyebite</text>
      <text>For casting these spells, each hag is a 12th-level spellcaster that uses Intelligence as her spellcasting ability. The spell save DC is 12 + Pu'pu's Intelligence modifier, and the spell attack bonus is 4 + Pu'pu's Intelligence modifier.</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1</slots>
    <spells>dancing lights, minor illusion, vicious mockery, identify, ray of sickness, hold person, locate object, bestow curse, counterspell, lightning bolt, phantasmal killer, polymorph, contact other plane, scrying, eyebite</spells>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 72</description>
    <environment>forest, swamp, hill</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Nepartak</name>
    <size>T</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>40 (9d4+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., fly 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>1</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Arcana +5, Perception +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist>lightning, necrotic, piercing</resist>
    <immune>cold, fire, poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned, prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Illumination</name>
      <text>Nepartak sheds either dim light in a 15-foot radius, or bright light in a 15-foot radius and dim light for an additional 15 feet. It can switch between the options as an action.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Nepartak has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Rejuvenation</name>
      <text>If Nepartak is destroyed, it regains all its hit points in 1 hour unless holy water is sprinkled on its remains or a dispel magic or remove curse spell is cast on them.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Nepartak uses Fire Ray twice.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Fire Ray</name>
      <text>Ranged Spell Attack: +5 to hit, range 30 ft., one target. 10 (3d6) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Fire Ray|+5|3d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Nepartak is a 5th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). It requires no somatic or material components to cast its spells. Nepartak has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): mage hand</text>
      <text>• 1st level (3 slots): magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (2 slots): blur, flaming sphere</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (1 slots): fireball</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>3, 2, 1</slots>
    <spells>mage hand, magic missile, shield, blur, flaming sphere, fireball</spells>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 137</description>
    <environment>underdark</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Niles Breakbone</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (breastplate)</ac>
    <hp>9 (2d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +5, Insight +4, Persuasion +5</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>any two languages</languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Rapier</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d8 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Rapier|+3|1d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Niles adds 2 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, Niles must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 47</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Ortimay Swift and Dark</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (gnome)</type>
    <alignment>Any Non-Lawful Alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (studded leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>65 (10d8+20)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Str +4, Dex +5, Wis +2</save>
    <skill>Athletics +4, Deception +4</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>any two languages, Gnomish</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Gnome Cunning</name>
      <text>&lt;$title_short_name$&gt; has advantage on all Intelligence, Wisdom, and Charisma saving throws against magic.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Ortimay makes three melee attacks: two with its scimitar and one with its dagger. Or Ortimay makes two ranged attacks with its daggers.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Scimitar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Scimitar|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Ortimay adds 2 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, Ortimay must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 21</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Orvex Ocrammas</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>27 (6d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +5, Insight +4, Investigation +5, Perception +6, Persuasion +5, Sleight of hand +4, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>any two languages</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Cunning Action</name>
      <text>On each of its turns, Orvex can use a bonus action to take the Dash, Disengage, or Hide action.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sneak Attack (1/Turn)</name>
      <text>Orvex deals an extra 7 (2d6) damage when it hits a target with a weapon attack and has advantage on the attack roll, or when the target is within 5 feet of an ally of Orvex that isn't incapacitated and Orvex doesn't have disadvantage on the attack roll.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Orvex makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Hand Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 30/120 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Hand Crossbow|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 96</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Pterafolk</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>26 (4d10+4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., fly 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>13</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +2, Survival +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Terror Dive</name>
      <text>If the pterafolk is flying and dives at least 30 feet straight toward a target, and then hits that target with a melee weapon attack, the target is frightened until the end of its next turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The pterafolk makes three attacks: one with its bite and two with its claws. Alternatively, it makes two melee attacks with its javelin.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (2d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+4|2d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claw</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claw|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Javelin</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 30/120 ft., one target. 9 (2d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Javelin|+4|2d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Pterafolk (pronounced TAIR-eh-folk) are 10-foot-tall, winged, reptilian bipeds native to Chult. Malevolent isolationists, they regard most other creatures as their enemies. In Chultan culture, pterafolk are often referred to as "terror folk" for their habit of swooping down from the sky to snatch whatever and whomever they can, then transporting treasure and food back to their roosts.
Pterafolk have 20-foot wingspans and give birth to live young. Ancient rituals once bestowed upon pterafolk the ability to assume the forms of pteranodons and wingless lizardfolk, but those rituals have long been forgotten.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 229</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Qawasha</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>11 (16 with barkskin)</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Medicine +4, Nature +3, Perception +4</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Druidic plus any two languages</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Quarterstaff</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit (+4 to hit with shillelagh), reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage, or 6 (1d8 + 2) bludgeoning damage with shillelagh or if wielded with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Quarterstaff|+2|1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Qawasha is a 4th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Wisdom (spell save DC 12, +4 to hit with spell attacks). It has the following druid spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): druidcraft, produce flame, shillelagh</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): entangle, longstrider, speak with animals, thunderwave</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): animal messenger, barkskin</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3</slots>
    <spells>druidcraft, produce flame, shillelagh, entangle, longstrider, speak with animals, thunderwave, animal messenger, barkskin</spells>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 35</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Ras Nsi</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity (shapechanger, yuan-ti)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (bracers of defense)</ac>
    <hp>127 (17d8+51)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>17</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>17</con>
    <int>18</int>
    <wis>18</wis>
    <cha>21</cha>
    <save>Con +6, Wis +7</save>
    <skill>Deception +8, Persuasion +5, Religion +7, Stealth +6</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>7</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Hit Points</name>
      <text>127 (17d8+51) reduced to 107; subtract 1 for each day that passes during the adventure</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Ras Nsi wears bracers of defense, wields a flame tongue longsword, and carries a sending stones matched to the one carried by the guide Salida (see chapter 1).</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>Ras Nsi can use his action to polymorph into a Medium snake or back into his yuan-ti form. His statistics are the same in each form. Any equipment he is wearing or carrying isn't transformed. He doesn't change form if he dies.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Ras Nsi has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Ras Nsi makes three melee attacks, but can use Constrict only once.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite (Snake Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage plus 7 (2d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite (Snake Form Only)|+6|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Constrict</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 10 (2d6 + 3) bludgeoning damage, and the target is grappled (escape DC 14). Until this grapple ends, the target is restrained, and Ras Nsi can't constrict another target.</text>
      <attack>Constrict|+6|2d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Flame Tongue Longsword (Yuan-ti Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (1d8 + 3) slashing damage, or 8 (1d10 + 3) slashing damage when used with two hands, plus 7 (2d6) fire damage.</text>
      <attack>Flame Tongue Longsword (Yuan-ti Form Only)|+6|1d8+3</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Ras Nsi's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 16). He can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: animal friendship (snakes only)</text>
      <text>3/day: suggestion</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Ras Nsi is an 11th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 15, +7 to hit with spell attacks).</text>
      <text>Ras Nsi has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): chill touch, fire bolt, mage hand, mending, poison spray</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): expeditious retreat, false life, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): blindness/deafness, hold person, misty step</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): animate dead, counterspell, fireball</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): blight, polymorph</text>
      <text>• 5th level (2 slots): contact other plane, geas</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): create undead</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 2, 1</slots>
    <spells>animal friendship, suggestion, chill touch, fire bolt, mage hand, mending, poison spray, expeditious retreat, false life, magic missile, shield, blindness/deafness, hold person, misty step, animate dead, counterspell, fireball, blight, polymorph, contact other plane, geas, create undead</spells>
    <description>The word "ras" is a noble title akin to "duke." Ras Nsi was once a Chultan paladin, a Chosen of Ubtao and sworn protector of the city of Mezro. He betrayed his oaths and was banished from the city. Becoming a vengeful warlord, Ras Nsi attempted to conquer Mezro with an undead army but was defeated. Rather than seek redemption, he sought revenge and was stripped of his god-given powers. The undead horde, no longer under his control, spread throughout the jungles of Chult.
Withdrawing to Omu, Nsi clung to his noble title, joined forces with the yuan-ti living there, and underwent a horrible ritual to become a powerful yuan-ti malison-retaining his human head and torso and gaining a serpentine lower body. With Ubtao gone from the world, Ras Nsi and his new yuan-ti followers began searching for a way to bring forth Dendar the Night Serpent. Acererak has promised to help this effort, in exchange for Ras Nsi's pledge to defend the Tomb of the Nine Gods. In truth, Acererak has no intention of honoring his bargain, and Ras Nsi is beginning to suspect as much.
Strange Collection. Ras Nsi has a sizable collection of apparel and accouterments from distant lands, most of which were taken from dead explorers. The collection includes a fine Cormyrean cloak, a Sembian wine flask, and a bejeweled Amnian doublet and matching money pouch. He also bears a flame tongue longsword.
Slow Death. Ras Nsi has died and been brought back from the dead more than once. Consequently, he is suffering from the effects of the Soulmonger's death curse. His hit point maximum has been reduced, and leprous wounds cover his flesh. In a fitting irony, Ras Nsi is unaware that Acererak is the cause of the curse, for neither he nor the yuan-ti are aware of what lies within the Tomb of the Nine Gods, other than the dead gods for which it is named. If the characters can make him understand that their efforts will help him, Ras Nsi might be tempted not to stand in their way.
Ras Nsi's Traits. Ideal. "I seek to bring about the end of this world and rule the next one."
Bond. "The yuan-ti of Chult are mine to command. They will help me rule an empire."
Flaw. "I will do anything and betray anyone to save myself."
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 230</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>River Mist</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (tabaxi)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Good</alignment>
    <ac>14 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>40 (9d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +2, Perception +4, Stealth +5, Survival +6</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common plus any one language</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Feline Agility</name>
      <text>When River Mist moves on its turn in combat, it can double its speed until the end of the turn. Once it uses this ability, River Mist can't use it again until it moves 0 feet on one of its turns.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>River Mist makes two attacks with its claws, its shortsword, or its shortbow.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 35</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Salida</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (yuan-ti)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>40 (9d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +6, Perception +3, Stealth +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Salida has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Salida makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Scimitar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Scimitar|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 4 (1d6 + 1) piercing damage plus 7 (2d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow|+3|1d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Salida's spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 12). Salida can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: animal friendship (snakes only)</text>
      <text>3/day each: poison spray, suggestion</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>animal friendship, poison spray, suggestion</spells>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 35</description>
    <environment>forest, swamp, urban, desert</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Sekelok</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>18 (plate armor)</ac>
    <hp>143 (22d8+44)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>20</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Str +9, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +9, Intimidation +5, Perception +6</skill>
    <passive>16</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>9</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Sekelok has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Indomitable (2/Day)</name>
      <text>Sekelok rerolls a failed saving throw.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Second Wind (Recharges after a Short or Long Rest)</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Sekelok can regain 20 hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Sekelok makes three attacks with its greatsword or its shortbow.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Greatsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +9 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 12 (2d6 + 5) slashing damage, plus 7 (2d6) slashing damage if Sekelok has more than half of its total hit points remaining.</text>
      <attack>Greatsword|+9|2d6+5</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage, plus 7 (2d6) piercing damage if Sekelok has more than half of its total hit points remaining.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow|+6|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 120</description>
    <environment>desert, urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Shago</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>16 (studded leather armor, shield)</ac>
    <hp>112 (15d8+45)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>18</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save>Str +7, Dex +5, Con +6</save>
    <skill>Athletics +10, Intimidation +5</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>any one language (usually Common)</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Brave</name>
      <text>Shago has advantage on saving throws against being frightened.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Brute</name>
      <text>A melee weapon deals one extra die of its damage when Shago hits with it (included in the attack).</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Shago makes three melee attacks or two ranged attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spear</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft. and range 20/60 ft., one target. 11 (2d6 + 4) piercing damage, or 13 (2d8 + 4) piercing damage if used with two hands to make a melee attack.</text>
      <attack>Spear|+7|2d6+4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shield Bash</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 9 (2d4 + 4) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Medium or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 15 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Shield Bash|+7|2d4+4</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Shago adds 3 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, Shago must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 35</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Skeleton Key</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13 (armor scraps)</ac>
    <hp>13 (2d8+4)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>8</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>9</passive>
    <languages>understands all languages it spoke in life but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable>bludgeoning</vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Spider Climb</name>
      <text>The skeleton can climb difficult surfaces, including upside down on ceilings, without needing to make an ability check.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 126</description>
    <environment>urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Spiked Tomb Guardian</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>17</ac>
    <hp>93 (11d8+44)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>lightning, poison; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't adamantine</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Berserk</name>
      <text>Whenever the tomb guardian starts its turn with 40 hit points or fewer, roll a d6. On a 6, the tomb guardian goes berserk. On each of its turns while berserk, the tomb guardian attacks the nearest creature it can see. If no creature is near enough to move to and attack, the tomb guardian attacks an object, with preference for an object smaller than itself. Once the tomb guardian goes berserk, it continues to do so until it is destroyed or regains all its hit points. The golem's creator, if within 60 feet of the berserk tomb guardian, can try to calm it by speaking firmly and persuasively. The tomb guardian must be able to hear its creator, who must take an action to make a DC 15 Charisma (Persuasion) check. If the check succeeds, the tomb guardian ceases being berserk. If it takes damage while still at 40 hit points or fewer, the tomb guardian might go berserk again.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Aversion of Fire</name>
      <text>If the tomb guardian takes fire damage, it has disadvantage on attack rolls and ability checks until the end of its next turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The tomb guardian is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Lightning Absorption</name>
      <text>Whenever the tomb guardian is subjected to lightning damage, it takes no damage and instead regains a number of hit points equal to the lightning damage dealt.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The tomb guardian has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Weapons</name>
      <text>The golem's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Chained</name>
      <text>This trait applies when two guardians are chained together.</text>
      <text>A magical spiked chain that binds a pair of guardians together prevents them from moving more than 15 feet apart. Additionally, as long as the chain is intact, damage dealt to either guardian is divided evenly between them. The spiked chain can be attacked separately and has AC 18, a damage threshold of 10, 5 hit points, and immunity to poison and psychic damage. If the chain breaks, both tomb guardians instantly go berserk.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The tomb guardian makes two spiked gauntlet attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Spiked Gauntlet</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage plus 9 (2d6) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Spiked Gauntlet|+7|2d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Adventurers who have perished inside the tomb are stitched together by tomb dwarves and bolted into suits of armor. Once complete, these shambling golems are released into the tomb to hunt intruders.
A tomb guardian is a flesh golem clad in plate armor, giving it AC 17
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 154</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Stone Juggernaut</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>157 (15d10+75)</hp>
    <speed>walk 50 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks not made with adamantine weapons</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned, prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Devastating Roll</name>
      <text>The juggernaut can move through the space of a prone creature. A creature whose space the juggernaut enters for the first time on a turn must make a DC 17 Dexterity saving throw, taking 55 (10d10) bludgeoning damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The juggernaut is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Regeneration</name>
      <text>As long as it has 1 hit point left, the juggernaut magically regains all its hit points daily at dawn. The juggernaut is destroyed and doesn't regenerate if it drops to 0 hit points.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Siege Monster</name>
      <text>The juggernaut deals double damage to objects and structures.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 25 (3d12 + 6) bludgeoning damage. If the target is a Large or smaller creature, it must succeed on a DC 17 Strength saving throw or be knocked prone.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+10|3d12+6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>A stone juggernaut is a rolling construct imbued with enough awareness to avoid obvious dangers such as open pits and chasms. It trundles across open battlefields or rolls down dungeon corridors, crushing anyone in its path. Every stone juggernaut has a unique shape and appearance. One might resemble an elephant with bejeweled tusks, while another might look like a scowling demon with flaming eyes and obsidian teeth.
A stone juggernaut is fast, but it lacks maneuverability and can move in only one direction on its turn. It poses little danger to creatures it can't crush beneath its rollers. Its best tactic is to slam into a creature, knock it prone, and then roll over it.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 231</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Su-monster</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>27 (5d8+5)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +6, Perception +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The su-monster makes two attacks: one with its bite and one with its claws.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 7 (2d4 + 2) slashing damage, or 12 (4d4 + 2) slashing damage if the su-monster is hanging by its tail and all four of its limbs are free.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+4|2d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Psychic Crush (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>The su-monster targets one creature it can see within 30 feet of it. The target must succeed on a DC 11 Wisdom saving throw or take 17 (5d6) psychic damage and be stunned for 1 minute. The stunned target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <attack>Psychic Crush (Recharge 5-6)||5d6</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Su-monsters are cunning, wicked primates that inhabit forsaken wilderness areas and caves. Adults stand 5 feet tall and have long prehensile tails. Although they can grasp tools and weapons with their tails or clawed feet, su-monsters prefer to rend prey with their claws. Adult su-monsters can also project blasts of psionic energy that leave enemies stunned and unable to flee or defend themselves.
A su-monster sleeps while hanging upside down by its tail. While awake, it can also unleash a devastating attack from that position, rending with all four of its claws.
Su-monsters communicate silently by using their prehensile tails to make gestures. They typically kill more than they can eat, burying the leftovers and marking their location with the victim's possessions.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 232</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Syndra Silvane</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>99 (18d8+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Int +9, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +13, History +13</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>any six languages</languages>
    <cr>12</cr>
    <resist>damage from spells; nonmagical bludgeoning, piercing, slashing (from stoneskin)</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>Syndra has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +6 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+6|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Familiars</name>
      <text>Any spellcaster that can cast the find familiar spell (such as an archmage or mage) is likely to have a familiar. The familiar can be one of the creatures described in the spell (see the Player's Handbook) or some other Tiny monster, such as a crawling claw, imp, pseudodragon, or quasit.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Syndra is an 18th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 17, +9 to hit with spell attacks). Syndra can cast disguise self and invisibility at will and has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>At will: disguise self, invisibility</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, identify, mage armor*, magic missile</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fly, lightning bolt</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): banishment, fire shield, stoneskin*</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): cone of cold, scrying, wall of force</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): globe of invulnerability</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): teleport</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): mind blank*</text>
      <text>• 9th level (1 slots): time stop</text>
      <text>*Syndra casts these spells on itself before combat.</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>disguise self, invisibility, fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, shocking grasp, detect magic, identify, mage armor, magic missile, detect thoughts, mirror image, misty step, counterspell, fly, lightning bolt, banishment, fire shield, stoneskin, cone of cold, scrying, wall of force, globe of invulnerability, teleport, mind blank, time stop</spells>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 8</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Tabaxi Hunter</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (tabaxi)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Good</alignment>
    <ac>14 (leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>40 (9d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>17</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>13</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +2, Perception +4, Stealth +5, Survival +6</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common plus any one language</languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Feline Agility</name>
      <text>When the tabaxi moves on its turn in combat, it can double its speed until the end of the turn. Once it uses this ability, the tabaxi can't use it again until it moves 0 feet on one of its turns.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The tabaxi makes two attacks with its claws, its shortsword, or its shortbow.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Tabaxi are catfolk who hail from the land of Maztica. The ultimate wanderers, Tabaxi rarely stay in one place for long. They love to collect interesting artifacts, gather tales, and lay eyes on all the world's wonders. This curiosity pushes them to leave no secrets uncovered, and no treasures or legends lost. They revere a fickle deity called the Cat Lord, who is said to wander the world.
Tabaxi hunters are trained to survive in the wild, making them excellent guides. Tabaxi minstrels gather in small troupes and make themselves at home in any settlement, earning coin through music and storytelling.
Names. A tabaxi typically has a single name, determined by his or her clan and based on a complex formula involving astrology, prophecy, clan history, and other factors. Male and female tabaxi use the same names, and most use nicknames derived from or inspired by their full names. Tabaxi clan names are usually based on a geographical feature located in or near a clan's territory. Sample tabaxi names include Nest of Eggs ("Eggs"), Dead Leaf ("Leaf"), Eyes of Onyx ("Onyx"), Lost Spear ("Lost"), and Daylight Moon ("Moon"). Clan names include Distant Rain, Hundred Feathers, Sleeping Creek, Bright Cliffs, and Snoring Mountain.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 232</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Tabaxi Minstrel</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (tabaxi)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Good</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>22 (5d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +3, Performance +7, Persuasion +5, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common plus any two languages</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Feline Agility</name>
      <text>When the tabaxi moves on its turn in combat, it can double its speed until the end of the turn. Once it uses this ability, the tabaxi can't use it again until it moves 0 feet on one of its turns.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Inspire (1/Day)</name>
      <text>While taking a short rest, the tabaxi can spend 1 minute singing, playing an instrument, telling a story, or reciting a poem to soothe and inspire creatures other than itself. Up to five creatures of the tabaxi's choice that can see and hear its performance gain 8 temporary hit points at the end of the tabaxi's short rest.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The tabaxi makes two claws attacks or two dart attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 2 (1d4) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Claws|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dart</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 20/ 60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dart|+4|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Tabaxi are catfolk who hail from the land of Maztica. The ultimate wanderers, Tabaxi rarely stay in one place for long. They love to collect interesting artifacts, gather tales, and lay eyes on all the world's wonders. This curiosity pushes them to leave no secrets uncovered, and no treasures or legends lost. They revere a fickle deity called the Cat Lord, who is said to wander the world.
Tabaxi hunters are trained to survive in the wild, making them excellent guides. Tabaxi minstrels gather in small troupes and make themselves at home in any settlement, earning coin through music and storytelling.
Names. A tabaxi typically has a single name, determined by his or her clan and based on a complex formula involving astrology, prophecy, clan history, and other factors. Male and female tabaxi use the same names, and most use nicknames derived from or inspired by their full names. Tabaxi clan names are usually based on a geographical feature located in or near a clan's territory. Sample tabaxi names include Nest of Eggs ("Eggs"), Dead Leaf ("Leaf"), Eyes of Onyx ("Onyx"), Lost Spear ("Lost"), and Daylight Moon ("Moon"). Clan names include Distant Rain, Hundred Feathers, Sleeping Creek, Bright Cliffs, and Snoring Mountain.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 233</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Terracotta Warrior</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>18 (natural terracotta warrior)</ac>
    <hp>33 (6d8+6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>3</wis>
    <cha>1</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>6</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison, psychic</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, charmed, deafened, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 60 ft. (blind beyond this radius)</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Fragile</name>
      <text>If a critical hit is scored against the terracotta warrior, it shatters and is destroyed.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Antimagic Susceptibility</name>
      <text>The terracotta warrior is incapacitated while in the area of an antimagic field. If targeted by dispel magic, the terracotta warrior must succeed on a Constitution saving throw against the caster's spell save DC or fall unconscious for 1 minute.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>False Appearance</name>
      <text>While the terracotta warrior remains motionless, it is indistinguishable from a terracotta statue.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The terracotta warrior makes two melee attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 161</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Tomb Dwarf</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (studded leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>45 (6d8+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +3, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>the languages it knew in life</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist>necrotic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't silvered</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, the tomb dwarf has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The tomb dwarf makes two longsword attacks or two crossbow attacks. It can use its Life Drain in place of one longsword attack.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Life Drain</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 5 (1d6 + 2) necrotic damage. The target must succeed on a DC 13 Constitution saving throw or its hit point maximum is reduced by an amount equal to the damage taken. This reduction lasts until the target finishes a long rest. The target dies if this effect reduces its hit point maximum to 0.A humanoid slain by this attack rises 24 hours later as a zombie under the tomb dwarf's control, unless the humanoid is restored to life or its body is destroyed. The tomb dwarf can have no more than twelve zombies under its control at one time.</text>
      <attack>Life Drain|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Battleaxe</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) slashing damage, or 7 (1d10 + 2) slashing damage if used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Battleaxe|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Light Crossbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Light Crossbow|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Acererak abducted dwarf miners and transformed them into wights to exploit their expertise at underground construction.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 135</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Tomb Guardian</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>construct</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>17</ac>
    <hp>93 (11d8+44)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>19</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>18</con>
    <int>6</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands the languages of its creator but can't speak</languages>
    <cr>5</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>lightning, poison; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't adamantine</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, petrified, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Berserk</name>
      <text>Whenever the tomb guardian starts its turn with 40 hit points or fewer, roll a d6. On a 6, the tomb guardian goes berserk. On each of its turns while berserk, the tomb guardian attacks the nearest creature it can see. If no creature is near enough to move to and attack, the tomb guardian attacks an object, with preference for an object smaller than itself. Once the tomb guardian goes berserk, it continues to do so until it is destroyed or regains all its hit points. The golem's creator, if within 60 feet of the berserk tomb guardian, can try to calm it by speaking firmly and persuasively. The tomb guardian must be able to hear its creator, who must take an action to make a DC 15 Charisma (Persuasion) check. If the check succeeds, the tomb guardian ceases being berserk. If it takes damage while still at 40 hit points or fewer, the tomb guardian might go berserk again.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Aversion of Fire</name>
      <text>If the tomb guardian takes fire damage, it has disadvantage on attack rolls and ability checks until the end of its next turn.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Immutable Form</name>
      <text>The tomb guardian is immune to any spell or effect that would alter its form.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Lightning Absorption</name>
      <text>Whenever the tomb guardian is subjected to lightning damage, it takes no damage and instead regains a number of hit points equal to the lightning damage dealt.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The tomb guardian has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Weapons</name>
      <text>The golem's weapon attacks are magical.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The tomb guardian makes two slam attacks.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +7 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 13 (2d8 + 4) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+7|2d8+4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Adventurers who have perished inside the tomb are stitched together by tomb dwarves and bolted into suits of armor. Once complete, these shambling golems are released into the tomb to hunt intruders.
A tomb guardian is a flesh golem clad in plate armor, giving it AC 17
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 127</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Tri-flower Frond</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>plant</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>11 (2d8+2)</hp>
    <speed>walk 5 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>9</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>9</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, deafened, exhaustion, prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 30 ft.</senses>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The tri-flower frond uses its orange blossom, then its yellow blossom, and then its red blossom.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Orange Blossom</name>
      <text>The tri-flower frond chooses one creature it can see within 5 feet of it. The target must succeed on a DC 11 Constitution saving throw or be poisoned for 1 hour. While poisoned in this way, the target is unconscious. At the end of each minute, the poisoned target can repeat the saving throw, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Yellow Blossom</name>
      <text>The tri-flower frond chooses one creature it can see within 5 feet of it. The target must succeed on a DC 11 Dexterity saving throw, or it is covered with corrosive sap and takes 5 acid damage at the start of each of its turns. Dousing the target with water reduces the acid damage by 1 point per pint or flask of water used.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Red Blossom</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +2 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 2 (1d4) piercing damage, and the target is grappled (escape DC 11). Until this grapple ends, the target takes 5 (2d4) poison damage at the start of each of its turns. The red blossom can grapple only one target at a time. Another creature within reach of the tri-flower frond can use its action to end the grapple on the target.</text>
      <attack>Red Blossom|+2|1d4</attack>
      </action>
    <description>When fully grown, a tri-flower frond stands 6 to 7 feet tall. It has three bright, trumpet-shaped flowers, each as large as a human head and each one a different color: intense red, vivid orange, and bright yellow. Each flower can harm a creature in a different terrible way.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 234</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Tyrannosaurus Zombie</name>
    <size>H</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>11 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>136 (13d12+52)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>25</str>
    <dex>6</dex>
    <con>19</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>3</wis>
    <cha>5</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>6</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Disgorge Zombie</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, the tyrannosaurus zombie can disgorge a normal zombie, which appears in an unoccupied space within 10 feet of it. The disgorged zombie acts on its own initiative count. After a zombie is disgorged, roll a d6. On a roll of 1, the tyrannosaurus zombie runs out of zombies to disgorge and loses this trait. If the tyrannosaurus zombie still has this trait when it dies, 1d4 normal zombies erupt from its corpse at the start of its next turn. These zombies act on their own initiative count.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Undead Fortitude</name>
      <text>If damage reduces the tyrannosaurus zombie to 0 hit points, it must make a Constitution saving throw with a DC of 5+the damage taken, unless the damage is radiant or from a critical hit. On a success, the zombie drops to 1 hit point instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>The tyrannosaurus zombie makes two attacks: one with its bite and one with its tail. It can't make both attacks against the same target.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 33 (4d12 + 7) piercing damage. If the target is a Medium or smaller creature, it is grappled (escape DC 17). Until this grapple ends, the target is restrained and the tyrannosaurus zombie can't bite another target or disgorge zombies.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+10|4d12+7</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Tail</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +10 to hit, reach 10 ft., one target. 20 (3d8 + 7) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Tail|+10|3d8+7</attack>
      </action>
    <description>Several new zombie variants are presented below. For more information on zombies, see the Monster Manual.
Ankylosaurus Zombie. This creature is slow and barely aware of its surroundings.
Girallon Zombie. Girallons are four-armed apes with white fur. Girallon zombies are slower than their non-undead counterparts but no less fierce. The necromantic energy empowering them fuels their murderous hearts and their hunger for living flesh.
Tyrannosaurus Zombie. A tyrannosaurus zombie has a gullet full of smaller zombies, which it can disgorge. These zombies aren't under the tyrannosaurus zombie's control.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 241</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Valindra Shadowmantle</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>17 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>135 (18d8+54)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>20</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Con +10, Int +12, Wis +9</save>
    <skill>Arcana +19, History +12, Insight +9, Perception +9</skill>
    <passive>19</passive>
    <languages>Common, Abyssal, Draconic, Dwarvish, Elvish, Infernal</languages>
    <cr>21</cr>
    <resist>cold, lightning, necrotic</resist>
    <immune>poison; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion, frightened, paralyzed, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>truesight 120 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Mask</name>
      <text>As a bonus action, Valindra can mask her shriveled flesh and appear to be a living elf. This magical illusion lasts until she ends it as a bonus action or until she uses her Frightening Gaze legendary action. The effect also ends if Valindra drops to 30 hit points or fewer, or if dispel magic is cast on her.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Preparation</name>
      <text>When preparing her spells, Valindra can swap out any spell on her list of prepared spells for another wizard spell of the same level.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Legendary Resistance (3/Day)</name>
      <text>If Valindra fails a saving throw, she can choose to succeed instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Rejuvenation</name>
      <text>If destroyed Valindra gains a new body in 1d10 days, regaining all her hit points and becoming active again. The new body appears within 5 feet of the phylactery.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Turn Resistance</name>
      <text>Valindra has advantage on saving throws against any effect that turns undead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Paralyzing Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Spell Attack: +12 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 10 (3d6) cold damage. The target must succeed on a DC 18 Constitution saving throw or be paralyzed for 1 minute. The target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      <attack>Paralyzing Touch|+12|3d6</attack>
      </action>
    <legendary>
        <text>Valindra can take 4 legendary actions, choosing from the options below. Only one legendary action can be used at a time and only at the end of another creature's turn. Valindra regains spent legendary actions at the start of its turn.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Cantrip</name>
      <text>Valindra casts a cantrip.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Paralyzing Touch (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Valindra uses her Paralyzing Touch.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Frightening Gaze (Costs 2 Actions)</name>
      <text>Valindra fixes her gaze on one creature she can see within 10 feet of her. The target must succeed on a DC 18 Wisdom saving throw against this magic or become frightened for 1 minute. The frightened target can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success. If a target's saving throw is successful or the effect ends for it, the target is immune to the Valindra's gaze for the next 24 hours.</text>
      </legendary>
    <legendary>
        <name>Disrupt Life (Costs 3 Actions)</name>
      <text>Each non-undead creature within 20 feet of Valindra must make a DC 18 Constitution saving throw against this magic, taking 21 (6d6) necrotic damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      </legendary>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Valindra is an 18th-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 20, +12 to hit with spell attacks). Valindra has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): mage hand, prestidigitation, ray of frost</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, magic missile, shield, thunderwave</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): detect thoughts, invisibility, Melf's acid arrow, mirror image</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): animate dead, counterspell, dispel magic, fireball</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): blight, dimension door</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): cloudkill, scrying</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): disintegrate, globe of invulnerability</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): finger of death, plane shift</text>
      <text>• 8th level (1 slots): dominate monster, power word stun</text>
      <text>• 9th level (1 slots): power word kill</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>mage hand, prestidigitation, ray of frost, detect magic, magic missile, shield, thunderwave, detect thoughts, invisibility, Melf's acid arrow, mirror image, animate dead, counterspell, dispel magic, fireball, blight, dimension door, cloudkill, scrying, disintegrate, globe of invulnerability, finger of death, plane shift, dominate monster, power word stun, power word kill</spells>
    <description>Liches are the remains of great wizards who embrace undeath as a means of preserving themselves. They further their own power at any cost, having no interest in the affairs of the living except where those affairs interfere with their own. Scheming and insane, they hunger for long-forgotten knowledge and the most terrible secrets. Because the shadow of death doesn't hang over them, they can conceive plans that take years, decades, or centuries to come to fruition.
A lich is a gaunt and skeletal humanoid with withered flesh stretched tight across its bones. Its eyes succumbed to decay long ago, but points of light burn in its empty sockets. It is often garbed in the moldering remains of fine clothing and jewelry worn and dulled by the passage of time.
Biography. Valindra Shadowmantle works for Szass Tam, the most powerful lich among the Red Wizards of Thay, though she is not a Red Wizard herself. She found the heart and converted it into a base to use while her minions search for the Soulmonger. Her orders from Szass Tam are to seize control of the Soulmonger, if possible, or destroy it otherwise. Valindra created a teleportation circle inside the heart that she uses to travel instantly to and from Thay (where her phylactery is safely stored), to deliver reports to Szass Tam and pick up new instructions.
Characters who explore the Heart of Ubtao are certain to meet Valindra. She's considered the possibility that adventurers might cross her path, and she won't necessarily be hostile toward them. Her mission is to seize the Soulmonger by any means; if adventurers can help her achieve that, she'll use them.
With her ability to appear as a living elf, Valindra can easily conceal her lichdom and her association to Thay. She presents herself as a scholarly wizard who wants to "imprison" the Soulmonger; that way, its unique magic can be studied while it's safely quarantined from the world. She argues that destroying it should be a last resort.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 58</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Volothamp "Volo" Geddarm</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (human)</type>
    <alignment>Chaotic Good</alignment>
    <ac>11</ac>
    <hp>31 (7d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>10</con>
    <int>15</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save>Con +2, Wis +2</save>
    <skill>Animal handling +4, Arcana +4, Deception +5, History +4, Insight +2, Investigation +4, Perception +2, Performance +7, Persuasion +7, Sleight of hand +3, Survival +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Dwarvish, Elvish</languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 3 (1d4 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+3|1d4+1</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Volo is a 1st-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 12, +4 to hit with spell attacks). He has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): friends, mending, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (2 slots): comprehend languages, detect magic, disguise self</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>2</slots>
    <spells>friends, mending, prestidigitation, comprehend languages, detect magic, disguise self</spells>
    <description>The bombastic world traveler Volothamp Geddarmn has come to Chult to deliver signed copies of his latest book, Volo's Guide to Monsters. In addition to setting up audiences with the seven merchant princes of Port Nyanzaru (whom he knows well), Volo is visiting local taverns to promote his work, and the characters might meet him at some point in the city. Volo is a font of information (not all of it accurate), but he won't join the party under any circumstances. He might, however, allow the characters to tag along while he visits each merchant prince in turn.
The personable Volo is more than willing to share 1d4 + 1 rumors from the Jungle Rumors table at the end of chapter 1, which he's overheard since arriving in Port Nyanzaru.
Volo's Traits. Ideal. "I have no wish to explore jungles, lost cities, and dungeons. Friendly taverns and bawdy festhalls are more my style."
Bond. "Planning an expedition? You really should buy a copy of my latest book, Volo's Guide to Monsters!"
Flaw. "My penchant for indulgence and my propensity for mockery have earned me a few enemies. I tend to wear out my welcome."
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 235, Waterdeep: Dragon Heist</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Wakanga O'tamu</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>12 (15 with mage armor)</ac>
    <hp>40 (9d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>9</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>17</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>11</cha>
    <save>Int +6, Wis +4</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, History +6</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>any four languages</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Familiars</name>
      <text>Any spellcaster that can cast the find familiar spell (such as an archmage or mage) is likely to have a familiar. The familiar can be one of the creatures described in the spell (see the Player's Handbook) or some other Tiny monster, such as a crawling claw, imp, pseudodragon, or quasit.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Wakanga is a 9th-level spellcaster. Its spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 14, +6 to hit with spell attacks). Wakanga has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (3 slots): misty step, suggestion</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): counterspell, fireball, fly</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): greater invisibility, ice storm</text>
      <text>• 5th level (1 slots): cone of cold</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 3, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, light, mage hand, prestidigitation, detect magic, mage armor, magic missile, shield, misty step, suggestion, counterspell, fireball, fly, greater invisibility, ice storm, cone of cold</spells>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 27</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Wild Dog</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>3 (1d6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 40 ft.</speed>
    <str>8</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>6</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +3</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>0</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Keen Hearing and Smell</name>
      <text>The dog has advantage on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on hearing or smell.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Pack Tactics</name>
      <text>The dog has advantage on an attack roll against a creature if at least one of the dog's allies is within 5 feet of the creature and the ally isn't incapacitated.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Bite</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +1 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 1 (1d4 - 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite|+1|1d4-1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 96</description>
    <environment>grassland, desert</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Wine Weird</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>elemental</type>
    <alignment>Neutral</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>58 (9d10+9)</hp>
    <speed>walk 0 ft., swim 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>17</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>11</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>10</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>understands Aquan but doesn't speak</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist>fire; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, grappled, paralyzed, poisoned, restrained, prone, unconscious</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Invisible in Water</name>
      <text>The wine weird is invisible while fully immersed in water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Water Bound</name>
      <text>The wine weird dies if it leaves the water to which it is bound or if that water is destroyed.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Constrict</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 10 ft., one creature. 13 (3d6 + 3) bludgeoning damage. If the target is Medium or smaller, it is grappled (escape DC 13) and pulled 5 feet toward the wine weird. Until this grapple ends, the target is restrained, the wine weird tries to drown it, and the wine weird can't constrict another target.</text>
      <attack>Constrict|+5|3d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 141</description>
    <environment>underdark, urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Withers</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>14 (studded leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>45 (6d8+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Perception +3, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>the languages he knew in life</languages>
    <cr>4</cr>
    <resist>necrotic; bludgeoning, piercing, slashing from nonmagical attacks that aren't silvered</resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>exhaustion, poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Special Equipment</name>
      <text>Withers carries the amulet of the black skull.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Sunlight Sensitivity</name>
      <text>While in sunlight, Withers has disadvantage on attack rolls, as well as on Wisdom (Perception) checks that rely on sight.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Withers makes two longsword attacks. He can use his Life Drain in place of one longsword attack.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Life Drain</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 5 (1d6 + 2) necrotic damage. The target must succeed on a DC 13 Constitution saving throw or its hit point maximum is reduced by an amount equal to the damage taken. This reduction lasts until the target finishes a long rest. The target dies if this effect reduces its hit point maximum to 0.</text>
      <attack>Life Drain|+4|1d6+2</attack>
      <text>A humanoid slain by this attack rises 24 hours later as a zombie under the Withers's control, unless the humanoid is restored to life or its body is destroyed. Withers can have no more than twelve zombies under its control at one time.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Longsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +4 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) slashing damage, or 7 (1d10 + 2) slashing damage if used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Longsword|+4|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Withers is a 9th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Intelligence (spell save DC 13, +5 to hit with spell attacks). Withers has the following wizard spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): acid splash, mage hand, minor illusion, prestidigitation</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): detect magic, expeditious retreat, feather fall, thunderwave</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (4 slots): darkness, hold person, rope trick</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): dispel magic, lightning bolt</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): blight, wall of fire</text>
      <text>• 5th level (1 slots): telekinesis</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 4, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>acid splash, mage hand, minor illusion, prestidigitation, detect magic, expeditious retreat, feather fall, thunderwave, darkness, hold person, rope trick, dispel magic, lightning bolt, blight, wall of fire, telekinesis</spells>
    <description>Before he was turned into an undead creature, Withers was an Omuan engineer named Gorra. Like all of Omu's citizens, Gorra was enslaved and put to work constructing the tomb. When Acererak sacrificed his workers to their own dungeon, Gorra's traps performed the best.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 145</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Xandala</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (half-elf)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>71 (11d8+22)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>18</int>
    <wis>16</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Int +7, Wis +6</save>
    <skill>Arcana +7, Deception +10, History +7, Insight +6, Survival +6</skill>
    <passive>13</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Dwarvish, Elvish, Halfling</languages>
    <cr>7</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Quickened Spell (3/Day)</name>
      <text>When she casts a spell that has a casting time of 1 action, Xandala changes the casting time to 1 bonus action for that casting.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Quarterstaff</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 3 (1d6) bludgeoning damage, or 4 (1d8) bludgeoning damage when used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Quarterstaff|+3|1d6</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Xandala is a 9th-level spellcaster. Her spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 15, +7 to hit with spell attacks). Xandala has the following sorcerer spells prepared:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): acid splash, fire bolt, light, mage hand, ray of frost</text>
      <text>• 1st level (4 slots): chromatic orb, feather fall, shield</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (4 slots): invisibility, misty step</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): fireball, fly</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): ice storm, polymorph</text>
      <text>• 5th level (1 slots): dominate person</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>4, 4, 3, 3, 1</slots>
    <spells>acid splash, fire bolt, light, mage hand, ray of frost, chromatic orb, feather fall, shield, invisibility, misty step, fireball, fly, ice storm, polymorph, dominate person</spells>
    <description>The half-elf sorcerer Xandala has come to Chult in search of the Ring of Winter, an artifact in Artus Cimber's possession. Xandala knows that the ring has kept Artus alive for over a century, and she craves its power. If she meets the characters, Xandala pretends to be Artus's daughter and tries to convince them to help her find him. Her plan is to cast dominate person on Artus and force him to give her the ring, then escape using her fly spell.
Xandala's magic traces back to a draconic bloodline, and parts of her skin are covered by a thin sheen of protective scales. She has befriended a pseudodragon named Summerwise, who thinks that Xandala's quest for the ring is dangerous but has given up trying to talk the sorcerer out of it. Summerwise can be turned against Xandala by good-aligned characters.
Xandala's Traits. Ideal. "I have the blood of dragons flowing through my veins. I am destined for greatness."
Bond. "The Ring of Winter will bring me power and immortality."
Flaw. "I'm surrounded by fools."
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 236</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Yellow Musk Creeper</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>plant</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>6</ac>
    <hp>60 (11d8+11)</hp>
    <speed>walk 5 ft., climb 5 ft.</speed>
    <str>12</str>
    <dex>3</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>10</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>blinded, deafened, exhaustion, prone</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>False Appearance</name>
      <text>While the creeper remains motionless, it is indistinguishable from an ordinary flowering vine.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Regeneration</name>
      <text>The creeper regains 10 hit points at the start of its turn. If the creeper takes fire, necrotic, or radiant damage, this trait doesn't function at the start of its next turn. The creeper dies only if it starts its turn with 0 hit points and doesn't regenerate.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Touch</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 13 (3d8) psychic damage. If the target is a humanoid that drops to 0 hit points as a result of this damage, it dies and is implanted with a yellow musk creeper bulb. Unless the bulb is destroyed, the corpse animates as a yellow musk zombie after being dead for 24 hours. The bulb is destroyed if the creature is raised from the dead before it can transform into a yellow musk zombie, or if the corpse is targeted by a remove curse spell or similar magic before it animates.</text>
      <attack>Touch|+3|3d8</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Yellow Musk (3/Day)</name>
      <text>The creeper's flowers release a strong musk that targets all humanoids within 30 feet of it. Each target must succeed on a DC 11 Wisdom saving throw or be charmed by the creeper for 1 minute. A creature charmed in this way does nothing on its turn except move as close as it can to the creeper. A creature charmed by the creeper can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      </action>
    <description>A yellow musk creeper is an unholy vine whose flowers resemble an orchid's. Bright yellow with splashes of purple, these flowers expel a musk that attracts prey. A yellow musk creeper clings to walls, pillars, gravestones, door frames, or statuary in shadowy locations, remaining motionless until it strikes.
Humanoid Hosts. A yellow musk creeper destroys the minds of humanoids, then implants bulbs in those it kills. Twenty-four hours after being implanted, a bulb sprouts a creeper vine that magically animates the host corpse, turning it into a yellow musk zombie under the young vine's control. In addition to protecting the defenseless plant, the zombie acts as fertilizer for the young creeper vine, which grows to full size in seven days. Once it is fully grown, the new yellow musk creeper becomes mobile and bursts from its zombie host, whereupon the zombie collapses into a mound of dead offal. If the zombie is destroyed before the creeper emerges, the creeper withers and dies.
Small Yellow Musk Zombies. A Medium humanoid transformed into a yellow musk zombie uses the stat block presented in this section. A Small humanoid transformed into a yellow musk zombie becomes a Small undead with 27 (6d6 + 6) hit points, but otherwise has the same statistics.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 237</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Yellow Musk Zombie</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>undead</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>9</ac>
    <hp>33 (6d8+6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 20 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>9</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>1</int>
    <wis>6</wis>
    <cha>3</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>8</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>charmed, exhaustion</conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 30 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Undead Fortitude</name>
      <text>If damage reduces the zombie to 0 hit points, it must make a Constitution saving throw with a DC of 5 +the damage taken, unless the damage is fire or from a critical hit. On a success, the zombie drops to 1 hit point instead.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Slam</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d8 + 1) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Slam|+3|1d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>A yellow musk creeper is an unholy vine whose flowers resemble an orchid's. Bright yellow with splashes of purple, these flowers expel a musk that attracts prey. A yellow musk creeper clings to walls, pillars, gravestones, door frames, or statuary in shadowy locations, remaining motionless until it strikes.
Humanoid Hosts. A yellow musk creeper destroys the minds of humanoids, then implants bulbs in those it kills. Twenty-four hours after being implanted, a bulb sprouts a creeper vine that magically animates the host corpse, turning it into a yellow musk zombie under the young vine's control. In addition to protecting the defenseless plant, the zombie acts as fertilizer for the young creeper vine, which grows to full size in seven days. Once it is fully grown, the new yellow musk creeper becomes mobile and bursts from its zombie host, whereupon the zombie collapses into a mound of dead offal. If the zombie is destroyed before the creeper emerges, the creeper withers and dies.
Small Yellow Musk Zombies. A Medium humanoid transformed into a yellow musk zombie uses the stat block presented in this section. A Small humanoid transformed into a yellow musk zombie becomes a Small undead with 27 (6d6 + 6) hit points, but otherwise has the same statistics.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 237</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Yorb</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>humanoid (grung)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>13</ac>
    <hp>49 (9d6+18)</hp>
    <speed>walk 25 ft., climb 25 ft.</speed>
    <str>7</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>15</con>
    <int>10</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>12</cha>
    <save>Dex +5</save>
    <skill>Athletics +2, Perception +2, Stealth +5, Survival +2</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Grung</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Amphibious</name>
      <text>Yorb can breathe air and water.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Poisonous Skin</name>
      <text>Any creature that grapples Yorb or otherwise comes into direct contact with Yorb's skin must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or become poisoned for 1 minute. A poisoned creature no longer in direct contact with Yorb can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Standing Leap</name>
      <text>Yorb's long jump is up to 25 feet and its high jump is up to 15 feet, with or without a running start.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or take 5 (2d4) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+3</attack>
      <attack>Dagger||2d4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 80/320 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) piercing damage, and the target must succeed on a DC 12 Constitution saving throw or take 5 (2d4) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortbow|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      <attack>Shortbow||2d4</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Mesmerizing Chirr (Recharge 6)</name>
      <text>Yorb makes a chirring noise to which grungs are immune. Each humanoid or beast that is within 15 feet of Yorb and able to hear it must succeed on a DC 12 Wisdom saving throw or be stunned until the end of Yorb's next turn.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Variant: Grung Poison</name>
      <text>Grung poison loses its potency 1 minute after being removed from a grung. A similar breakdown occurs if Yorb dies. A creature poisoned by a grung can suffer an additional effect that varies depending on Yorb's skin color. This effect lasts until the creature is no longer poisoned by Yorb.</text>
      <text>Green. The poisoned creature can't move except to climb or make standing jumps. If the creature is flying, it can't take any actions or reactions unless it lands.</text>
      <text>Blue. The poisoned creature must shout loudly or otherwise make a loud noise at the start and end of its turn.</text>
      <text>Purple. The poisoned creature feels a desperate need to soak itself in liquid or mud. It can't take actions or move except to do so or to reach a body of liquid or mud.</text>
      <text>Red. The poisoned creature must use its action to eat if food is within reach.</text>
      <text>Orange. The poisoned creature is frightened of its allies.</text>
      <text>Gold. The poisoned creature is charmed and can speak Grung.</text>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 108</description>
    <environment>forest</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Yuan-ti Priest</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity (shapechanger, yuan-ti)</type>
    <alignment>Neutral Evil</alignment>
    <ac>12</ac>
    <hp>66 (12d8+12)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>14</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +5, Stealth +4</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages>Abyssal, Common, Draconic</languages>
    <cr>3</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune>poison</immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune>poisoned</conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Shapechanger</name>
      <text>The yuan-ti can use its action to polymorph into a Medium snake, or back into its true form. Its statistics are the same in each form. Any equipment it is wearing or carrying isn't transformed. It doesn't change form if it dies.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The yuan-ti has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Malison Type</name>
      <text>The yuan-ti has one of the following types:</text>
      <text>• Type 1: Human body with snake head</text>
      <text>• Type 2: Human head and body with snakes for arms</text>
      <text>• Type 3: Human head and upper body with a serpentine lower body instead of legs</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack (Yuan-ti Form Only)</name>
      <text>The yuan-ti makes two ranged attacks or two melee attacks, but can constrict only once.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Bite (Snake Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage plus 7 (2d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Bite (Snake Form Only)|+5|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Constrict</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 10 (2d6 + 3) bludgeoning damage, and the target is grappled (escape DC 13). Until this grapple ends, the target is restrained, and the yuan-ti can't constrict another target.</text>
      <attack>Constrict|+5|2d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Scimitar (Yuan-ti Form Only)</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Scimitar (Yuan-ti Form Only)|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Innate Spellcasting (Yuan-ti Form Only)</name>
      <text>The yuan-ti's innate spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 13). The yuan-ti can innately cast the following spells, requiring no material components:</text>
      <text>At will: animal friendship (snakes only)</text>
      <text>3/day: suggestion</text>
      </trait>
    <spells>animal friendship, suggestion</spells>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 118</description>
    <environment>forest, swamp, desert</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Zalkoré</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Evil</alignment>
    <ac>15 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>127 (17d8+51)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>10</str>
    <dex>15</dex>
    <con>16</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>13</wis>
    <cha>15</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +5, Insight +4, Perception +4, Stealth +5</skill>
    <passive>14</passive>
    <languages>Common</languages>
    <cr>6</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Petrifying Gaze</name>
      <text>When a creature that can see Zalkoré's eyes starts its turn within 30 feet of Zalkoré, Zalkoré can force it to make a DC 14 Constitution saving throw if Zalkoré isn't incapacitated and can see the creature. If the saving throw fails by 5 or more, the creature is instantly petrified. Otherwise, a creature that fails the save begins to turn to stone and is restrained. The restrained creature must repeat the saving throw at the end of its next turn, becoming petrified on a failure or ending the effect on a success. The petrification lasts until the creature is freed by the  greater restoration spell or other magic.</text>
      <text>Unless surprised, a creature can avert its eyes to avoid the saving throw at the start of its turn. If the creature does so, it can't see Zalkoré until the start of its next turn, when it can avert its eyes again. If the creature looks at Zalkoré in the meantime, it must immediately make the save.</text>
      <text>If Zalkoré sees itself reflected on a polished surface within 30 feet of it and in an area of bright light, Zalkoré is, due to its curse, affected by its own gaze.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Zalkoré makes either three melee attacks—one with its snake hair and two with its shortsword—or two ranged attacks with its longbow.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Snake Hair</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one creature. 4 (1d4 + 2) piercing damage plus 14 (4d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Snake Hair|+5|1d4+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Shortsword</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Shortsword|+5|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Longbow</name>
      <text>Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, range 150/600 ft., one target. 6 (1d8 + 2) piercing damage plus 7 (2d6) poison damage.</text>
      <attack>Longbow|+5|1d8+2</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 79</description>
    <environment>desert</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Zaroum Al-Saryak</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any Non-Lawful Alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (studded leather armor)</ac>
    <hp>65 (10d8+20)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>15</str>
    <dex>16</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>14</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>14</cha>
    <save>Str +4, Dex +5, Wis +2</save>
    <skill>Athletics +4, Deception +4</skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages>any two languages</languages>
    <cr>2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Multiattack</name>
      <text>Zaroum makes three melee attacks: two with its scimitar and one with its dagger. Or Zaroum makes two ranged attacks with its daggers.</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Scimitar</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 6 (1d6 + 3) slashing damage.</text>
      <attack>Scimitar|+5|1d6+3</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Dagger</name>
      <text>Melee or Ranged Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft. or range 20/60 ft., one target. 5 (1d4 + 3) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Dagger|+5|1d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Zaroum adds 2 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, Zaroum must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 67</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Zebra</name>
    <size>L</size>
    <type>beast</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>10</ac>
    <hp>13 (2d10+2)</hp>
    <speed>walk 60 ft.</speed>
    <str>16</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>12</con>
    <int>2</int>
    <wis>11</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill></skill>
    <passive>10</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/4</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Hooves</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (2d4 + 3) bludgeoning damage.</text>
      <attack>Hooves|+5|2d4+3</attack>
      </action>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 106</description>
    <environment>grassland, urban</environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Zhanthi</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (any race)</type>
    <alignment>Any alignment</alignment>
    <ac>15 (breastplate)</ac>
    <hp>9 (2d8)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>11</str>
    <dex>12</dex>
    <con>11</con>
    <int>12</int>
    <wis>14</wis>
    <cha>16</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Deception +5, Insight +4, Persuasion +5</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>any two languages</languages>
    <cr>1/8</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <action>
        <name>Rapier</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d8 + 1) piercing damage.</text>
      <attack>Rapier|+3|1d8+1</attack>
      </action>
    <reaction>
        <name>Parry</name>
      <text>Zhanthi adds 2 to its AC against one melee attack that would hit it. To do so, Zhanthi must see the attacker and be wielding a melee weapon.</text>
      </reaction>
    <description>
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 27</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Zindar</name>
    <size>M</size>
    <type>humanoid (half-dragon)</type>
    <alignment>Lawful Good</alignment>
    <ac>13 (natural armor)</ac>
    <hp>110 (17d8+34)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>14</str>
    <dex>10</dex>
    <con>14</con>
    <int>16</int>
    <wis>15</wis>
    <cha>18</cha>
    <save>Con +5, Wis +5</save>
    <skill>Arcana +6, History +9, Insight +5, Investigation +9</skill>
    <passive>12</passive>
    <languages>Common, Draconic, Dwarvish, Primordial</languages>
    <cr>8</cr>
    <resist>fire</resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses>blindsight 10 ft., darkvision 60 ft.</senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Dragon Wings</name>
      <text>As a bonus action on his turn, Zindar can sprout a pair of dragon wings from his back, gaining a flying speed of 30 feet until he dismisses them as a bonus action.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Quarterstaff</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +5 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 5 (1d6 + 2) bludgeoning damage, or 6 (1d8 + 2) bludgeoning damage when used with two hands.</text>
      <attack>Quarterstaff|+5|1d6+2</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Breath Weapon (Recharge 5-6)</name>
      <text>Zindar uses one of the following options:</text>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Fire Breath</name>
      <text>Zindar exhales fire in a 15-foot cone. Each creature in that area must make a DC 15 Dexterity saving throw, taking 22 (4d10) fire damage on a failed save, or half as much damage on a successful one.</text>
      <attack>Fire Breath||4d10</attack>
      </action>
    <action>
        <name>Weakening Breath</name>
      <text>Zindar exhales gas in a 15-foot cone. Each creature in that area must succeed on a DC 15 Strength saving throw or have disadvantage on Strength-based attack rolls, Strength checks, and Strength saving throws for 1 minute. A creature can repeat the saving throw at the end of each of its turns, ending the effect on itself on a success.</text>
      </action>
    <trait>
        <name>Spellcasting</name>
      <text>Zindar is a 14th-level spellcaster. His spellcasting ability is Charisma (spell save DC 15, +7 to hit with spell attacks). Zindar knows the following sorcerer spells:</text>
      <text>Cantrips (at will): fire bolt, friends, light, mage hand, mending, message</text>
      <text>• 1st level (6 slots): magic missile, shield, sleep</text>
      <text>• 2nd level (4 slots): detect thoughts, knock</text>
      <text>• 3rd level (3 slots): clairvoyance, tongues</text>
      <text>• 4th level (3 slots): dominate beast, stoneskin</text>
      <text>• 5th level (3 slots): hold monster, telekinesis</text>
      <text>• 6th level (1 slots): true seeing</text>
      <text>• 7th level (1 slots): fire storm</text>
      </trait>
    <slots>6, 4, 3, 3, 3, 1, 1</slots>
    <spells>fire bolt, friends, light, mage hand, mending, message, magic missile, shield, sleep, detect thoughts, knock, clairvoyance, tongues, dominate beast, stoneskin, hold monster, telekinesis, true seeing, fire storm</spells>
    <description>This half-gold dragon runs Port Nyanzaru's docks and keeps track of ship manifests. A sorcerer of impressive ability, Zindar is well paid by the merchant princes for his work. He is also a key member of the Ytepka Society and a great source of information about the city. Zindar has a soft spot for adventurers, but he knows the dangers of Chult well enough to understand that most of those who embark on expeditions to explore the jungle never return.
Zindar makes extensive use of spells in his day-today work, casting message to deliver missives to dock workers, detect thoughts for reading ship captains' minds, knock for unsealing containers for inspection, clairvoyance for peering into ship holds, dominate beast to pacify nervous animals, and so forth.
Zindar's Traits. Ideal. "I take pride in my work, and I like to keep all my business dealings honest."
Bond. "Port Nyanzaru is my home. I take a dim view of those who would bring harm to the city and its inhabitants."
Flaw. "I don't get mad. I get even."
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 239</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  <monster>
      <name>Zorbo</name>
    <size>S</size>
    <type>monstrosity</type>
    <alignment>Unaligned</alignment>
    <ac>10 (see Natural Armor feature)</ac>
    <hp>27 (6d6+6)</hp>
    <speed>walk 30 ft., climb 30 ft.</speed>
    <str>13</str>
    <dex>11</dex>
    <con>13</con>
    <int>3</int>
    <wis>12</wis>
    <cha>7</cha>
    <save></save>
    <skill>Athletics +3</skill>
    <passive>11</passive>
    <languages></languages>
    <cr>1/2</cr>
    <resist></resist>
    <immune></immune>
    <vulnerable></vulnerable>
    <conditionImmune></conditionImmune>
    <senses></senses>
    <trait>
        <name>Magic Resistance</name>
      <text>The zorbo has advantage on saving throws against spells and other magical effects.</text>
      </trait>
    <trait>
        <name>Natural Armor</name>
      <text>The zorbo magically absorbs the natural strength of its surroundings, adjusting its Armor Class based on the material it is standing or climbing on: AC 15 for wood or bone, AC 17 for earth or stone, or AC 19 for metal. If the zorbo isn't in contact with any of these substances, its AC is 10.</text>
      </trait>
    <action>
        <name>Destructive Claws</name>
      <text>Melee Weapon Attack: +3 to hit, reach 5 ft., one target. 8 (2d6 + 1) slashing damage, and if the target is a creature wearing armor, carrying a shield, or in possession of a magic item that improves its AC, it must make a DC 11 Dexterity saving throw. On a failed save, one such item worn or carried by the creature (the target's choice) magically deteriorates, taking a permanent and cumulative −1 penalty to the AC it offers, and the zorbo gains a +1 bonus to AC until the start of its next turn. Armor reduced to an AC of 10 or a shield or magic item that drops to a 0 AC increase is destroyed.</text>
      <attack>Destructive Claws|+3|2d6+1</attack>
      </action>
    <description>A zorbo (pronounced ZOR-boh) is a ferocious omnivore similar in size and appearance to a koala. Living in trees and caves, it has long claws, a dour disposition, and a fondness for humanoid flesh. A zorbo alters its natural armor to match its surroundings, and it can weaken and destroy armor, shields, and protective magic items with its sharp claws.
Source: Tomb of Annihilation p. 241</description>
    <environment></environment>
    </monster>
  </compendium>
