<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <item>
      <name>Birdpipes</name>
    <detail>Instrument</detail>
    <type>G</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>Pan pipes or satyr pipes, also known as the shalm, these are sacred to Lliira and popular with wood elf and wild elf bards.
Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 124</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Glaur</name>
    <detail>Instrument</detail>
    <type>G</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>Short, curved horns like a cornucopia. Played with valves, glaur sound like trumpets, while those without valves, known as gloon, have a more mournful sound.
Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 124</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Hand Drum</name>
    <detail>Instrument</detail>
    <type>G</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>A double-headed skin drum fitted with handles along its side.
Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 124</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Longhorn</name>
    <detail>Instrument</detail>
    <type>G</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>A Faerûnian flute of sophisticated make, found only in areas with skilled artisans, as in great cities or elven enclaves.
Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 124</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Shawm</name>
    <detail>Instrument</detail>
    <type>G</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>A double-reed instrument similar to an oboe or a bassoon, popular with gnomes, who have developed some bellows-powered versions.
Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 124</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Songhorn</name>
    <detail>Instrument</detail>
    <type>G</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>A recorder, a simple type of flute, usually carved from wood.
Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 124</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Tantan</name>
    <detail>Instrument</detail>
    <type>G</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>A tambourine, a popular instrument with halflings and humans south of the Dalelands.
Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 124</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Thelarr</name>
    <detail>Instrument</detail>
    <type>G</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>Also known as a whistlecane, a simple and easy-to-make wind instrument cut from a reed. They are so simple, in fact, that skilled bards frequently make and give them away to children—to the parents' delight or regret.
Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 124</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Tocken</name>
    <detail>Instrument</detail>
    <type>G</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>A hanging set of carved oval bells, usually played with a pair of light wooden hammers (or open handed). They are most common in underground cultures, where the resonant tones can carry.
Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 124</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Wargong</name>
    <detail>Instrument</detail>
    <type>G</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>A metal gong, traditionally made from a shield, particularly the shield of an enemy. Both goblins and dwarves make and play wargongs, their sound echoing through tunnels in the Underdark.
Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 124</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Yarting</name>
    <detail>Instrument</detail>
    <type>G</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>A southern instrument from Amn and Calimshan that is a Faerûnian analog to the guitar. Numerous variations have spread across the continent.
Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 124</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Zulkoon</name>
    <detail>Instrument</detail>
    <type>G</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>A complex pump organ that originated with the zulkirs of Thay, who use it in the casting of their spells. It is considered to have a dramatic, but sinister, sound.
Source: Sword Coast Adventurer's Guide p. 124</text>
    </item>
  </compendium>
