<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <item>
      <name>Akmon, Hammer of Purphoros</name>
    <detail>martial Weapon, Melee Weapon</detail>
    <type>M</type>
    <weight>2</weight>
    <property>V,M</property>
    <dmg1>1d8</dmg1>
    <dmg2>1d10</dmg2>
    <dmgType>B</dmgType>
    <text>Purphoros's hammer works wonders and disasters, the god of the forge using it to craft ground-breaking marvels and dangerous inventions in equal measure. Purphoros rarely bestows Akmon on mortals but occasionally leaves it unattended at his forge in Mount Velus. When Purphoros does permit a mortal to use the hammer, it's usually so they might bring an important work into being, wreck a force of destruction, or forge something remarkable somewhere the god isn't welcome.
Hammer of the Forge: This magic warhammer grants a +3 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with it. When you hit with an attack using it, the target takes an extra 3d10 fire damage.
Blessing of the Forge: If you are a worshiper of Purphoros, you gain all the following benefits for which you have the required piety:
• Piety 10+.: The hammer has 1 randomly determined minor beneficial property.
• Piety 25+.: The hammer has 1 randomly determined major beneficial property.
• Piety 50+.: The hammer has 1 additional randomly determined major beneficial property.
If you aren't a worshiper of Purphoros, the hammer has 2 randomly determined minor detrimental properties.
See "Artifacts" in chapter 7 of the Dungeon Master's Guide for details on randomly determined properties.
Reforged: While holding the hammer, you have resistance to fire damage and are immune to exhaustion. Additionally, you have proficiency with smith's tools and have advantage on all ability checks made using them.
Spells: While the hammer is on your person, you can use an action to cast one of the following spells (save DC 18): animate objects, heat metal, fabricate, magic weapon, mending, shatter. Once you use the hammer to cast a spell, the spell can't be cast again from it until the next dusk.
Destroying the Hammer: To destroy the hammer, it must be taken to the realm of Tizerus, in the Underworld. There it must be coated in clay from the Mire of Punishment. The heat of the hammer hardens the clay, which fuses to it after one month. Once fully hardened, the clay-covered hammer must be swallowed and digested by a kraken.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 198</text>
    <roll>3d10</roll>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Dekella, Bident of Thassa</name>
    <detail>martial Weapon, Melee Weapon</detail>
    <type>M</type>
    <weight>4</weight>
    <property>T,V,M</property>
    <dmg1>1d6</dmg1>
    <dmg2>1d8</dmg2>
    <dmgType>P</dmgType>
    <range>20/60</range>
    <text>Thassa wields Dekella, a two-pronged weapon gifted to her by Purphoros. When the god of the sea bestows her weapon on a mortal, it's often so they might work her will far from the ocean, right some wrong affecting those she'd prefer not to harm, or give a mortal a glimpse of her terrible responsibilities.
Bident of the Deep: Thassa's signature weapon thrums with the icy currents of the deep ocean. This weapon functions as a trident that grants a +3 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with it. When you hit with an attack using the bident, the target takes an extra 2d10 cold damage.
Blessing of the Deep: If you are a worshiper of Thassa, you gain all the following benefits for which you have the required piety:
• Piety 10+.: You can breathe underwater, and you gain a swimming speed of 60 feet.
• Piety 25+.: The bident has 1 randomly determined minor beneficial property.
• Piety 50+.: The bident has 1 randomly determined major beneficial property.
If you aren't a worshiper of Thassa, the bident has 1 minor detrimental property and 1 major detrimental property, both randomly determined.
See "Artifacts" in chapter 7 of the Dungeon Master's Guide for details on randomly determined properties.
Command the Deep: The bident holds the power to command the waves and its creatures. As an action, you can change the condition of the sea within 1 mile of you, creating strong winds and heavy rain that cause violent waves (see "Weather at Sea" in chapter 5 of the Dungeon Master's Guide) or calming a storm. In either case, the unnatural weather lasts for 1 hour before returning to normal. Once used, this property of the bident can't be used again until the next dusk.
Additionally, you can cast the dominate monster spell (save DC 18) from the bident, but only on beasts and monstrosities that have an innate swimming speed. Once used, this property of the bident can't be used again until the next dusk.
Aquatic Metamorphosis: You can cast the true polymorph spell (save DC 18) from the bident, but you must cast it on a creature to turn it into a kind of creature that has an innate swimming speed. Once used, this property of the bident can't be used again until the next dusk.
Destroying the Bident: To destroy the bident, it must be heated by the breath of an ancient red dragon and then, while still hot, immersed in the Tartyx River.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 199</text>
    <roll>2d10</roll>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Ephixis, Bow of Nylea</name>
    <detail>simple Weapon, Ranged Weapon</detail>
    <type>R</type>
    <weight>2</weight>
    <property>A,2H</property>
    <dmg1>1d6</dmg1>
    <dmgType>P</dmgType>
    <range>80/320</range>
    <text>Nylea wields the shortbow Ephixis, the bow whose arrows herald the turning of the seasons. Nylea is quick to let her favored followers borrow her bow, particularly when they intend to use it to perform great deeds, put an end to foul creatures, or cast down the arrogant.
Bow of the Wild: This divine weapon includes a shortbow and a quiver with four arrows, each tied to one of the four seasons. You gain a +3 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with this bow, and you suffer no disadvantage when attacking at the weapon's long range. Additionally, Ephixis scores a critical hit on a d20 roll of 19 or 20.
Blessing of the Wild: If you are a worshiper of Nylea, you gain all the following benefits for which you have the required piety:
• Piety 10+.: The bow has 1 randomly determined minor beneficial property.
• Piety 25+.: The bow has 1 randomly determined major beneficial property.
If you aren't a worshiper of Nylea, the bow has 1 randomly determined major detrimental property.
See "Artifacts" in chapter 7 of the Dungeon Master's Guide for details on randomly determined properties.
Arrows of the Seasons: The four arrows—each associated with a season—that accompany this bow can be fired only from it. Each arrow disappears immediately after it's used, and it reappears in the quiver at the next dusk. The save DC against spells cast with the arrows is 18. Each arrow has a unique property:
Spring: As an action, you can fire this arrow, targeting a beast or a plant creature you can see within 320 feet of you. On a hit, the arrow deals no damage, and the target gains the benefits of the awaken spell for 8 hours.
Summer: As an action, you can fire this arrow at an unoccupied space on the ground that you can see within 320 feet of you, no attack roll required. A Nyxborn lynx is summoned in that space (use the stat block for a tiger with the Nyxborn traits from chapter 6). The lynx understands your verbal commands and obeys them as best it can, and it takes its turns immediately after yours. The emissary remains for 1 hour before fading away.
Autumn: As an action, you can fire this arrow at a space on the ground that you can see within 320 feet of you, no attack roll required, casting the wall of thorns spell there.
Winter: As an action, you can fire this arrow at a space that you can see within 320 feet of you, no attack roll required, casting the ice storm spell there.
Destroying the Bow: The bow can't be destroyed without first destroying all its arrows. The winter arrow must be fed to a cerberus on the winter solstice. The spring arrow must be planted at the base of a Black Oak of Asphodel on the spring equinox. The summer arrow must be broken by a sea giant on the summer solstice. Then the autumn arrow must be shot into the carcass of a hydra on the autumnal equinox. When all four arrows are destroyed, the bow and quiver dissolve into dust.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 200</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Flying Chariot</name>
    <detail>Wondrous item</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>1</magic>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>The chariot's riders and creatures pulling the chariot gain a +1 bonus to their AC.
If this magic chariot is pulled by one or more flying creatures, it too can fly.
Chariots: Chariots and the creatures pulling them work like controlled mounts, as described in the mounted combat rules in the Player's Handbook, but with the following differences:
• Mounting or dismounting a chariot costs you 5 feet of movement, rather than a number of feet equal to half your speed.
• Being mounted on a chariot grants you half cover.
• A chariot's speed is equal to the speed of the slowest creature pulling it.
• If multiple creatures are pulling the chariot, they all act on the same initiative, and they must take the same action on their turn.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 196</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Helm of the Gods</name>
    <detail>Wondrous item</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>1</magic>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>While wearing this helm, you know whether there is a celestial or fiend within 30 feet of you, as well as where the creature is located, provided the creature isn't behind total cover.
Whenever you finish a long rest while wearing the helm, you can pray to one of the gods listed on the Helm of the Gods table and store the listed spell in the helm, replacing any spell that is already stored there. The save DC for the spell is 13.
The helm has 3 charges. To cast a spell from the helm, you must expend 1 charge, and the helm regains 1d3 charges daily at dawn.
God | Spell
Athreos | protection from evil and good
Ephara | sanctuary
Erebos | inflict wounds
Heliod | guiding bolt
Iroas | heroism
Karametra | goodberry
Keranos | thunderous smite
Klothys | entangle
Kruphix | dissonant whispers
Mogis | hellish rebuke
Nylea | faerie fire
Pharika | lesser restoration
Phenax | charm person
Purphoros | searing smite
Thassa | identify
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 196</text>
    <roll>1d3</roll>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Khrusor, Spear of Heliod</name>
    <detail>simple Weapon, Melee Weapon</detail>
    <type>M</type>
    <weight>3</weight>
    <property>T,V</property>
    <dmg1>1d6</dmg1>
    <dmg2>1d8</dmg2>
    <dmgType>P</dmgType>
    <range>20/60</range>
    <text>Heliod wields Khrusor, a spear blessed with the power of the sun. In his hands, it can be pitched from Nyx to any point on Theros. When Heliod lends his weapon to a mortal, it's typically so they can perform some great work in his name or as a test of their worthiness.
Spear of the Sun: This spear grants a +3 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with it. When you hit with an attack using this spear, the target takes an extra 2d8 radiant damage.
Blessing of the Sun: If you are a worshiper of Heliod, you gain all the following benefits for which you have the required piety:
• Piety 3+.: You gain 15 temporary hit points each dawn.
• Piety 10+.: The spear has 1 randomly determined minor beneficial property.
• Piety 25+.: The spear has 1 additional randomly determined minor beneficial property.
• Piety 50+.: The spear has 1 randomly determined major beneficial property.
If you aren't a worshiper of Heliod, the spear has 2 randomly determined major detrimental properties.
See "Artifacts" in chapter 7 of the Dungeon Master's Guide for details on randomly determined properties.
Luminous: The spear sheds bright light in a 30-foot radius and dim light for an additional 30 feet. The light is sunlight.
Sun's Retaliation: When you take damage from a creature within 5 feet of you, you can use your reaction to make a melee attack with the spear against that creature. On a hit, the spear deals damage as normal, and the creature is blinded until the start of its next turn. This property of the spear can't be used again until the next dawn.
Spells: The spear has 10 charges. While holding it, you can use an action to expend 1 or more of its charges to cast one of the following spells (save DC 18) from it: guiding bolt (1 charge), daylight (3 charges, targeting the tip of the spear only), sunbeam (6 charges). The spear regains 1d6 + 4 expended charges daily at dawn.
Destroying the Spear: If taken to Erebos's palace in Tizerus, and used to sacrifice a champion of Heliod to Erebos, Khrusor is either destroyed or fundamentally twisted to Erebos's service.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 200</text>
    <roll>2d8</roll>
    <roll>1d6+4</roll>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Mastix, Whip of Erebos</name>
    <detail>martial Weapon, Melee Weapon</detail>
    <type>M</type>
    <weight>3</weight>
    <property>F,R,M</property>
    <dmg1>1d4</dmg1>
    <dmgType>S</dmgType>
    <text>Erebos wields Mastix, a whip capable of extending like an impossibly long shadow. In the hands of the god of the dead, the whip snares the reluctant dead and drags them into his realm. When Erebos grants his weapon to a mortal follower, it's typically to reclaim a powerful soul or to humiliate Heliod.
Whip of the Dead: Erebos's whip seethes with the enervating energy of the Underworld. This magic whip grants a +3 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with it. When you hit with an attack using this whip, the target takes an extra 2d8 necrotic damage and you regain hit points equal to half the amount of necrotic damage dealt.
Additionally, when you make an attack with the whip on your turn, you can increase the range of the attack to 300 feet. This property of the weapon can't be used again until the next dusk.
Blessing of the Dead: If you are a worshiper of Erebos, you gain all the following benefits for which you have the required piety:
• Piety 1+.: The whip has 1 randomly determined minor detrimental property—a burden Erebos imposes to test his faithful.
• Piety 25+.: The whip has 1 randomly determined major beneficial property.
• Piety 50+.: The whip has 1 additional randomly determined major beneficial property.
If you aren't a worshiper of Erebos, the whip has 2 randomly determined major detrimental properties.
See "Artifacts" in chapter 7 of the Dungeon Master's Guide for details on randomly determined properties.
Erebos's Claim: While carrying the whip, you can use an action to cast either circle of death or dominate monster (targeting only undead) from the whip. The save DC for these spells is 18. Once you use the whip to cast a spell, that spell can't be cast from it again until the next dusk.
Destroying the Whip: To destroy the whip, it must be taken to the heights of Mount Hiastos in Nyx, unraveled by a Returned, and left to bask in continual daylight for one month.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 201</text>
    <roll>2d8</roll>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Molten Bronze Skin (Breastplate)</name>
    <detail>Medium Armor</detail>
    <type>MA</type>
    <weight>20</weight>
    <property></property>
    <ac>14</ac>
    <text>This magical armor appears as a jug of molten bronze. When you attune to it, the bronze adheres and contours to your skin. The armor can be worn under normal clothes, but it doesn't impede bodily functions. Once you put it on, it can't be removed unless you choose to do so.
While wearing the armor, you have resistance to fire damage. The armor also doesn't impose disadvantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Molten Bronze Skin (Half Plate)</name>
    <detail>Medium Armor</detail>
    <type>MA</type>
    <weight>40</weight>
    <property></property>
    <ac>15</ac>
    <text>This magical armor appears as a jug of molten bronze. When you attune to it, the bronze adheres and contours to your skin. The armor can be worn under normal clothes, but it doesn't impede bodily functions. Once you put it on, it can't be removed unless you choose to do so.
While wearing the armor, you have resistance to fire damage. The armor also doesn't impose disadvantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Molten Bronze Skin (Plate)</name>
    <detail>Heavy Armor</detail>
    <type>HA</type>
    <weight>65</weight>
    <property></property>
    <ac>18</ac>
    <strength>15</strength>
    <text>This magical armor appears as a jug of molten bronze. When you attune to it, the bronze adheres and contours to your skin. The armor can be worn under normal clothes, but it doesn't impede bodily functions. Once you put it on, it can't be removed unless you choose to do so.
While wearing the armor, you have resistance to fire damage. The armor also doesn't impose disadvantage on Dexterity (Stealth) checks.
If the wearer has a Strength score lower than 15, their speed is reduced by 10 feet.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Potion of Aqueous Form</name>
    <detail></detail>
    <type>P</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>When you drink this potion, you transform into a pool of water. You return to your true form after 10 minutes or if you are incapacitated or die.
You're under the following effects while in this form:
• Liquid Movement.: You have a swimming speed of 30 feet. You can move over or through other liquids. You can enter and occupy the space of another creature. You can rise up to your normal height, and you can pass through even Tiny openings. You extinguish nonmagical flames in any space you enter.
• Watery Resilience.: You have resistance to nonmagical damage. You also have advantage on Strength, Dexterity, and Constitution saving throws.
• Limitations.: You can't talk, attack, cast spells, or activate magic items. Any objects you were carrying or wearing meld into your new form and are inaccessible, though you continue to be affected by anything you're wearing, such as armor.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Pyxis of Pandemonium</name>
    <detail>Wondrous item, Cursed item</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>1</magic>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>A creature that touches this ornate wooden vessel for 1 minute gains the benefits of a short rest. That creature also gains the effects of the bless spell until the creature finishes a short or long rest. The creature can't gain these benefits again until it finishes a long rest.
If the vessel is opened, roll on the Pyxis of Pandemonium table to determine what happens. Any spells cast by the vessel have a spell save DC of 17. One minute after the vessel is opened, it disappears. It reappears, sealed, in a random location on the same plane of existence 24 hours later.
Curse: Any creature that gains the benefit of a short rest from the vessel hears cloying telepathic whispers emanating from it. That creature must make a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw. On a failed save, the creature is charmed by the vessel for 1 hour. The charmed creature does everything it can to open the vessel as soon as possible. On a successful save, the creature is immune to the vessel's whispers for 24 hours.
d8 | Calamity
1 | Androphagia. Each creature within 60 feet of the vessel must succeed on a DC 17 Wisdom saving throw or go berserk for 1 minute. The berserk creature must begin its turn using the Attack action to make one melee or ranged attack (its choice) against the creature nearest to it. The berserk creature can repeat the save at the end of its turn, ending the effect on itself on a success.
2 | Bile Blight. The vessel casts the harm spell on each creature within 30 feet of it.
3 | Flood. The vessel casts the tsunami spell at a point of the DM's choice within 120 feet of it.
4 | Medusa's Gaze. The vessel casts the flesh to stone spell on each creature within 30 feet of it.
5 | Labyrinth. The vessel casts the maze spell on each creature within 30 feet of it.
6 | Nightmare. Tendrils of shadow seep from the vessel and form into 1d4 shadow demon (see the Monster Manual for their stat block), which appear in unoccupied spaces within 30 feet of it and are hostile.
7 | Swarming Insects. The vessel casts the insect plague spell, centered on itself and with a radius of 30 feet.
8 | Unbridled Revel. The vessel casts the Otto's irresistible dance spell on each creature within 30 feet of it.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
    <roll>1d4</roll>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Siren Song Lyre</name>
    <detail>Wondrous item</detail>
    <type>W</type>
    <magic>1</magic>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>You can use an action to play this lyre and cast one of the following spells from it: animal friendship, charm person, enthrall, suggestion. If the spell requires a saving throw, the spell save DC is 13.
Once the instrument has been used to cast a spell, it can't be used to cast that spell again until the next dawn.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 198</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Sling Bullets of Althemone</name>
    <detail>Ammunition</detail>
    <type>A</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>The sling bullets come in a pouch, which contains 1d4 + 4 bullets. Roll on the Magic Sling Bullets table for each bullet to determine its magical property.
You have a +2 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with each of these bullets. If a bullet misses its target, the bullet teleports back into the pouch. Once a bullet hits a target, the bullet loses its magic.
Magic Sling Bullets
d4 | Bullet
1 | Banishment. A creature that takes damage from this bullet must succeed on a DC 15 Charisma saving throw or be banished as though affected by the banishment spell.
2 | Fulguration. On a hit, this bullet deals an extra 2d8 lightning damage to its target. All other creatures within 10 feet of the target must each succeed on a DC 15 Constitution saving throw or take 1d8 thunder damage.
3 | Stunning. On a hit, this bullet deals an extra 1d10 force damage, and the target is stunned until the end of your next turn.
4 | Tracking. A creature that takes damage from this bullet is marked with a glowing rune where the bullet hit. The mark lasts 24 hours. While the creature is marked, you always know the direction to it.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 198</text>
    <roll>1d4+4</roll>
    <roll>2d8</roll>
    <roll>1d8</roll>
    <roll>1d10</roll>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Two-Birds Sling</name>
    <detail>simple Weapon, Ranged Weapon</detail>
    <type>R</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <value>0.1</value>
    <property>A</property>
    <dmg1>1d4</dmg1>
    <dmgType>B</dmgType>
    <range>30/120</range>
    <text>You have a +1 bonus to attack and damage rolls made with this weapon.
When you make a ranged attack with this sling and hit a target, you can cause the ammunition to ricochet toward a second target within 10 feet of the first, and then make a ranged attack against the second target.
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 198</text>
    </item>
  <item>
      <name>Molten Bronze Skin</name>
    <detail>Generic Variant</detail>
    <type>G</type>
    <weight></weight>
    <property></property>
    <text>Molten Bronze Skin (Breastplate)
Molten Bronze Skin (Half Plate)
Molten Bronze Skin (Plate)
Source: Mythic Odysseys of Theros p. 197</text>
    </item>
  </compendium>
