<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Cleric</name>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Divine Domain: Death Domain</name>
        <text>The Death domain is concerned with the forces that cause death, as well as the negative energy that gives rise to undead creatures. Deities such as Chemosh, Myrkul, and WeeJas are patrons of necromancers, death knights, liches, mummy lords, and vampires. Gods of the Death domain also embody murder (Anubis, Bhaal, and Pyremius), pain (Iuz or Loviatar), disease or poison (Incabulos, Talona, or Morgion), and the underworld (Hades and Hel).</text>
        <text>At each indicated cleric level, add the listed spells to your spells prepared. They do not count towards your limit.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Death Domain Spells</text>
        <text>Cleric Level | Spells</text>
        <text>1st | false life, ray of sickness</text>
        <text>3rd | blindness/deafness, ray of enfeeblement</text>
        <text>5th | animate dead, vampiric touch</text>
        <text>7th | blight, death ward</text>
        <text>9th | antilife shell, cloudkill</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Dungeon Master's Guide p. 96</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Death Domain: Bonus Proficiency</name>
        <text>When the cleric chooses this domain at 1st level, he or she gains proficiency with martial weapons.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Dungeon Master's Guide p. 96</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="1">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Death Domain: Reaper</name>
        <text>At 1st level, the cleric learns one necromancy cantrip of his or her choice from any spell list. When the cleric casts a necromancy cantrip that normally targets only one creature, the spell can instead target two creatures within range and within 5 feet of each other.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Dungeon Master's Guide p. 96</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Death Domain: Channel Divinity: Touch of Death</name>
        <text>Starting at 2nd level, the cleric can use Channel Divinity to destroy another creature's life force by touch.</text>
        <text>When the cleric hits a creature with a melee attack, the cleric can use Channel Divinity to deal extra necrotic damage to the target. The damage equals 5 + twice his or her cleric level.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Dungeon Master's Guide p. 96</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Death Domain: Inescapable Destruction</name>
        <text>Starting at 6th level, the cleric's ability to channel negative energy becomes more potent. Necrotic damage dealt by the character's cleric spells and Channel Divinity options ignores resistance to necrotic damage.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Dungeon Master's Guide p. 96</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="8">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Death Domain: Divine Strike</name>
        <text>At 8th level, the cleric gains the ability to infuse his or her weapon strikes with necrotic energy. Once on each of the cleric's turns when he or she hits a creature with a weapon attack, the cleric can cause the attack to deal an extra 1d8 necrotic damage to the target. When the cleric reaches 14th level, the extra damage increases to 2d8.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Dungeon Master's Guide p. 96</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="17">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Death Domain: Improved Reaper</name>
        <text>Starting at 17th level, when the cleric casts a Necromancy spell of 1st through 5th-level that targets only one creature, the spell can instead target two creatures within range and within 5 feet of each other. If the spell consumes its material components, the cleric must provide them for each target.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Dungeon Master's Guide p. 96</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
