<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <spell>
      <name>Enter Mindscape</name>
    <classes>Psion</classes>
    <level>0</level>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 bonus action</time>
    <range>Self</range>
    <components></components>
    <duration>Concentration, up to 10 minutes</duration>
    <text>By shutting down your normal senses, you extend your mind into the psionics landscape around you. For the duration you can use a bonus action to sense the presence of creatures within a 60-foot cone. You learn the number of creatures within the cone and their creature type. You cannot detect undead or constructs with this spell.
This spell is blocked by 1 foot of stone, 1 inch of common metal, a thin sheet of lead,or 3 feet of wood or dirt.
This spell's duration cannot be ended due to damage.
Source: Livestream</text>
    </spell>
  <spell>
      <name>Mind Fist</name>
    <classes>Psion</classes>
    <level>0</level>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>60 feet</range>
    <components></components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <text>You point at one creature you can see within range and project a focused beam of telekinetic power at it. The target must succeed on a Strength saving throw or take 1d6 bludgeoning damage and be pushed up to 15 feet away from you.
This spell's damage increases by one die when you reach 5th level (2d6), 11th level (3d6), and 17th level (4d6).
Source: Livestream</text>
    <roll>1d6</roll>
    <roll>2d6</roll>
    <roll>3d6</roll>
    <roll>4d6</roll>
    </spell>
  <spell>
      <name>Mind Strike</name>
    <classes>Psion</classes>
    <level>0</level>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>60 feet</range>
    <components></components>
    <duration>Instantaneous</duration>
    <text>You point at one creature you can see within range, and a psychic bolt pierces its mind. The target must succeed on an Intelligence saving throw or take 1d10 psychic damage.
This spell's damage increases by one die when you reach 5th level (2d10), 11th level (3d10), and 17th level (4d10).
Source: Livestream</text>
    <roll>1d10</roll>
    <roll>2d10</roll>
    <roll>3d10</roll>
    <roll>4d10</roll>
    </spell>
  <spell>
      <name>Psychic Step</name>
    <classes>Psion</classes>
    <level>0</level>
    <ritual>NO</ritual>
    <time>1 action</time>
    <range>60 feet</range>
    <components></components>
    <duration>1 round</duration>
    <text>You alter the composition of your body in a subtle manner, allowing you to take seemingly impossible steps.
Until the end of your turn, you speed increases by 10 feet and you can walk across vertical surfaces without falling. If you end your turn on such a surface, you immediately fall.
Source: Livestream</text>
    </spell>
  </compendium>
