<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<compendium version="5" auto_indent="NO">
    <class>
      <name>Wizard</name>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Tradition: Chronurgy Magic</name>
        <text>Focusing on the manipulation of time, those who follow the Chronurgy tradition learn to alter the pace of reality to their liking. Using the ramping of anticipatory dunamis energy, these mages can bend the flow of time as adroitly as a skilled musician plays an instrument, lending themselves and their allies an advantage in the blink of an eye.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 184</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Chronurgy Magic: Chronal Shift</name>
        <text>2nd-level Chronurgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>You can magically exert limited control over the flow of time around a creature. As a reaction, after you or a creature you can see within 30 feet of you makes an attack roll, an ability check, or a saving throw, you can force the creature to reroll. You make this decision after you see whether the roll succeeds or fails. The target must use the result of the second roll.</text>
        <text>You can use this ability twice, and you regain any expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 184</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Chronurgy Magic: Temporal Awareness</name>
        <text>2nd-level Chronurgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>You can add your Intelligence modifier to your initiative rolls.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 184</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Arcane Tradition: Graviturgy Magic</name>
        <text>Understanding and mastering the forces that draw bodies of matter together or drive them apart, the students of the Graviturgy arcane tradition learn to further bend and manipulate the violent energy of gravity to their benefit, and the terrible detriment of their enemies.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 185</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="2">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Graviturgy Magic: Adjust Density</name>
        <text>2nd-level Graviturgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>As an action, you can magically alter the weight of one object or creature you can see within 30 feet of you. The object or creature must be Large or smaller. The target's weight is halved or doubled for up to 1 minute or until your concentration ends (as if you were concentrating on a spell).</text>
        <text>While the weight of a creature is halved by this effect, the creature's speed increases by 10 feet, it can jump twice as far as normal, and it has disadvantage on Strength checks and Strength saving throws. While the weight of a creature is doubled by this effect, the creature's speed is reduced by 10 feet, and it has advantage on Strength checks and Strength saving throws.</text>
        <text>Upon reaching 10th level in this class, you can target an object or a creature that is Huge or smaller.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 185</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Chronurgy Magic: Momentary Stasis</name>
        <text>6th-level Chronurgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>As an action, you can magically force a Large or smaller creature you can see within 60 feet of you to make a Constitution saving throw against your spell save DC. Unless the saving throw is a success, the creature is encased in a field of magical energy until the end of your next turn or until the creature takes any damage. While encased in this way, the creature is incapacitated and has a speed of 0.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Intelligence modifier (a minimum of once). You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 184</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="6">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Graviturgy Magic: Gravity Well</name>
        <text>6th-level Graviturgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>You've learned how to manipulate gravity around a living being: whenever you cast a spell on a creature, you can move the target 5 feet to an unoccupied space of your choice if the target is willing to move, the spell hits it with an attack, or it fails a saving throw against the spell.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 185</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Chronurgy Magic: Arcane Abeyance</name>
        <text>10th-level Chronurgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>When you cast a spell using a spell slot of 4th level or lower, you can condense the spell's magic into a mote. The spell is frozen in time at the moment of casting and held within a gray bead for 1 hour. This bead is a Tiny object with AC 15 and 1 hit point, and it is immune to poison and psychic damage. When the duration ends, or if the bead is destroyed, it vanishes in a flash of light, and the spell is lost.</text>
        <text>A creature holding the bead can use its action to release the spell within, whereupon the bead disappears. The spell uses your spell attack bonus and save DC, and the spell treats the creature who released it as the caster for all other purposes.</text>
        <text>Once you create a bead with this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a short or long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 184</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="10">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Graviturgy Magic: Violent Attraction</name>
        <text>10th-level Graviturgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>When another creature that you can see within 60 feet of you hits with a weapon attack, you can use your reaction to increase the attack's velocity, causing the attack's target to take an extra 1d10 damage of the weapon's type.</text>
        <text>Alternatively, if a creature within 60 feet of you takes damage from a fall, you can use your reaction to increase the fall's damage by 2d10.</text>
        <text>You can use this feature a number of times equal to your Intelligence modifier (a minimum of once). You regain all expended uses when you finish a long rest.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 185</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Chronurgy Magic: Convergent Future</name>
        <text>14th-level Chronurgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>You can peer through possible futures and magically pull one of them into events around you, ensuring a particular outcome. When you or a creature you can see within 60 feet of you makes an attack roll, an ability check, or a saving throw, you can use your reaction to ignore the die roll and decide whether the number rolled is the minimum needed to succeed or one less than that number (your choice).</text>
        <text>When you use this feature, you gain one level of exhaustion. Only by finishing a long rest can you remove a level of exhaustion gained in this way.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 184</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    <autolevel level="14">
        <feature optional="YES">
          <name>Graviturgy Magic: Event Horizon</name>
        <text>14th-level Graviturgy Magic feature</text>
        <text>As an action, you can magically emit a powerful field of gravitational energy that tugs at other creatures for up to 1 minute or until your concentration ends (as if you were concentrating on a spell). For the duration, whenever a creature hostile to you starts its turn within 30 feet of you, it must make a Strength saving throw against your spell save DC. On a failed save, it takes 2d10 force damage, and its speed is reduced to 0 until the start of its next turn. On a successful save, it takes half as much damage, and every foot it moves this turn costs 2 extra feet of movement.</text>
        <text>Once you use this feature, you can't do so again until you finish a long rest or until you expend a spell slot of 3rd level or higher on it.</text>
        <text></text>
        <text>Source: Explorer's Guide to Wildemount p. 185</text>
        </feature>
      </autolevel>
    </class>
  </compendium>
